<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37408565</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">10319274</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">399644</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S399644</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>The Relationship Between Cognitive Impairments and Sleep Quality Measures in Persistent Insomnia Disorder</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Künstler et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Künstler et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6007-5114</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Künstler</surname>
            <given-names>Erika C S</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bublak</surname>
            <given-names>Peter</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8546-7141</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Finke</surname>
            <given-names>Kathrin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Koranyi</surname>
            <given-names>Nicolas</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Meinhard</surname>
            <given-names>Marie</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Schwab</surname>
            <given-names>Matthias</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rupprecht</surname>
            <given-names>Sven</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Neurology, Jena University Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Jena</addr-line>, <country>Germany</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Interdisciplinary Centre for Sleep and Ventilatory Medicine, Jena University Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Jena</addr-line>, <country>Germany</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Erika CS Künstler, <institution>Department of Neurology, Jena University Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Am Klinikum 1</addr-line>, <addr-line>Jena</addr-line>, <addr-line>07747</addr-line>, <country>Germany</country>, <phone>Tel +49 3641 9323525</phone>, Email Erika.Kuenstler@med.uni-jena.de</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2023</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>15</volume>
      <fpage>491</fpage>
      <lpage>498</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>30</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2023 Künstler et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Künstler et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Study Objectives</title>
          <p>Persistent insomnia disorder (pID) is linked to neurocognitive decline and increased risk of Alzheimer’s Disease (AD) in later life. However, research in this field often utilizes self-reported sleep quality data - which may be biased by sleep misperception - or uses extensive neurocognitive test batteries - which are often not feasible in clinical settings. This study therefore aims to assess whether a simple screening tool could uncover a specific pattern of cognitive changes in pID patients, and whether these relate to objective aspect(s) of sleep quality.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>Neurocognitive performance (Montreal Cognitive Assessment; MoCA), anxiety/depression severity, and subjective sleep quality (Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index: PSQI; Insomnia Severity Index: ISI) data were collected from 22 middle-aged pID patients and 22 good-sleepers. Patients underwent overnight polysomnography.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>Compared to good-sleepers, patients had lower overall cognitive performance (average: 24.6 versus 26.3 points, Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic> = 136.5, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = &lt;0.006), with deficits in clock drawing and verbal abstraction. In patients, poorer overall cognitive performance correlated with reduced subjective sleep quality (PSQI: <italic toggle="yes">r</italic>(42) = −0.47, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.001; and ISI: <italic toggle="yes">r</italic>(42) = −0.43, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.004), reduced objective sleep quality (lower sleep efficiency: <italic toggle="yes">r</italic>(20) = 0.59, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.004 and less REM-sleep: <italic toggle="yes">r</italic>(20) = 0.52, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.013; and increased sleep latency: <italic toggle="yes">r</italic>(20) = −0.57, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.005 and time awake: <italic toggle="yes">r</italic>(20) = −0.59, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.004). Cognitive performance was not related to anxiety/depression scores.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>Using a simple neurocognitive screening tool, we found that pID patients showed cognitive deficiencies that related to both subjective/self-reported and objective/polysomnographic measures of sleep quality. Furthermore, these cognitive changes resembled those seen in preclinical non-amnestic AD, and thus could indicate incumbent neurodegenerative processes in pID. Interestingly, increased REM-sleep was correlated with better cognitive performance. However, whether REM-sleep is protective against neurodegeneration requires further investigation.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>insomnia</kwd>
        <kwd>sleep</kwd>
        <kwd>neurodegeneration</kwd>
        <kwd>Alzheimer’s disease</kwd>
        <kwd>polysomnography</kwd>
        <kwd>cognitive screening</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>German Research Foundation (Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft, DFG)</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>Research was funded by: German Research Foundation (Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft, DFG) Grant Number: SPP 1772 BU1327/4-1.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="2"/>
        <table-count count="2"/>
        <ref-count count="41"/>
        <page-count count="8"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s0001">
      <title>Plain Language Summary</title>
      <p>Neurodegeneration and sleep quality influence one another. Consequently, patients with neurodegenerative/dementing diseases often have poor sleep. Conversely, sleep disorders - like insomnia - increase a patient’s risk of developing dementias, making early identification of at-risk patients vital. We compared the performance of patients with insomnia to that of healthy peers using a simple screening tool. Patients not only had a lower overall cognitive status, but had particular difficulties in abstract thinking and clock drawing. When we compared the patients’ performance to their objective sleep quality, we found that patients who fell asleep faster, spent less of the night awake, and spent longer in “dream sleep” showed better performance on the cognitive screening test. These results are interesting for two reasons. Firstly, the cognitive difficulties faced by patients with insomnia are similar to those seen in mild cognitive impairment, a pre-stage of Alzheimer’s. This supports the idea that poor sleep quality, if left untreated, can cause similar cognitive difficulties as those found in dementing diseases. Secondly, dream sleep may be protective, possibly slowing down the rate of cognitive decline. Taken together, insomnia patients - and particularly those with reduced dream sleep - may benefit greatly from preventative intervention strategies.
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Correlation between overall MoCA score and sleep latency (<bold>A</bold>); wake after sleep onset (<bold>B</bold>); REM sleep (<bold>C</bold>); and sleep efficiency (<bold>D</bold>) in patients with pID.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-491-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviation</bold>: TIB, Time in Bed.</attrib></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0002">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Changes in sleep patterns are closely linked to neurodegenerative processes,<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> and are a common comorbidity in patients with dementing illnesses like Alzheimer’s disease (AD).<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> This relationship between sleep quality and neurodegeneration is bi-directional,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> and several brain regions involved in regulating the sleep-wake cycle are important for cognitive functions.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Consequently, poor sleep quality increases cognitive decline and dementia risk,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> making early identification of at-risk patients vital. One such risk state is insomnia, affecting 6–10% of adults.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Indeed, meta-analyses indicate that patients with persistent insomnia disorder (pID) have a 1.5-fold higher risk of developing AD in later life.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6–8</xref> Furthermore, extensive neuropsychological testing shows that patients with pID show decline in similar cognitive domains<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> to those in patients with amnestic mild cognitive impairment (aMCI), a transitional stage between normative aging and AD.</p>
      <p>Using short screening tools, rather than extensive test batteries, to identify at-risk patients would be ideal in clinical settings. However, it remains unclear whether these are sensitive enough in this context. Previous studies utilizing screening tools to test for cognitive impairments in insomnia patients either did not directly examine how cognitive deficits related to polysomnographic data,<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> or used self-reported measures of sleep quality to assess this relationship.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Such self-reported questionnaires may yield unreliable sleep quality estimates due to sleep misperception (a frequently seen discrepancy between subjective estimates and objective measurements of sleep duration).<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Thus, objective polysomnographic data is vital in examining whether potential cognitive alterations observed through screening tools relate to sleep quality in patients with pID.</p>
      <p>In summary, despite the importance of early identification of at-risk patients, research examining the relationship between early cognitive alterations in patients with pID, measured through screening tools, and specific aspect(s) of sleep quality, measured via polysomnography, is lacking. The aims of this study are therefore twofold. Firstly, we assessed whether a cognitive screening test could identify specific subdomains that were especially vulnerable in patients. For this, we utilized the Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA),<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> a short screening which measures of seven cognitive domains, and which is sensitive enough to detect relatively mild cognitive deficits, for example in aMCI.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Secondly, we evaluated the relationship between patients’ cognitive performance and their objective sleep quality, obtained by polysomnography.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Demographic Data</title>
        <p>We recruited 22 patients with pID and 22 matched healthy controls. The patients were diagnosed according to DSM V criteria,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> and had a disease duration of &gt;1 year. Patients with comorbid insomnia, occurring in the presence of other medical/mental disorders, were excluded. Exclusion criteria in both groups included comorbid sleep disorders, inadequate sleep hygiene, alcohol/substance abuse, a history of neurological/psychiatric diseases, and intake of sleep-altering medication (stimulants/anti-depressants/sedatives). Eligibility was assessed through questionnaires and structured interviews.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Study Protocol</title>
        <p>All participants completed the MoCA, obtaining an extra point if they had ≤12 years of education, as per guidelines.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> The Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS-A/D)<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> was used to quantify anxiety/depression symptoms. Premorbid intellectual functioning estimates were obtained using the German “Mehrfachwahl Wortschatz Intelligenz Test-B”.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Sleep Quality</title>
        <p>The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> and the Insomnia Severity Index (ISI)<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> were used to assess self-reported sleep quality. All patients underwent one night of polysomnography (SOMNOmedics),<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> sleeping ad libitum, at least one week prior to neuropsychological testing, ensuring that sleeping in a laboratory environment did not adversely impact test performance. An experienced staff member, who was blind to the study, scored the polysomnographic data according to the American Academy of Sleep Medicine Scoring Manual guidelines.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>Means and standard deviations are given for normally distributed data, and medians and interquartile ranges for non-normally distributed data. The difference in overall cognitive performance was calculated with a one-tailed <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test, with an alpha of 0.05. Due to low variance in each subdomain, resulting in non-parametric data, intergroup differences for each subdomains were calculated with one-tailed Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-tests. Multiple comparisons were controlled for using the Benjamini-Hochberg method, as this controls for false discoveries whilst avoiding being overly conservative.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> A false positive rate of 5% was used to calculate the critical values (<italic toggle="yes">q</italic>). Both objective and subjective sleep data were correlated to cognitive performance data, again corrected for multiple comparisons. To ensure psychological well-being did not confound cognitive performance in the patient group, the overall MoCA score was correlated to anxiety/depression scores using Pearson’s correlation coefficients. Confidence intervals were reported for all correlations. No data was missing or excluded from analysis, outlier analysis revealed no outliers, and all analyses were run with IBM SPSS, version 26.0.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>There were no significant group differences in age, gender, education, and estimated intelligence (see <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). As expected, patients had worse subjective sleep quality (PSQI: <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>(42) = −10.53, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = &lt;0.001) and insomnia severity (ISI: <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>(42) = −10.83, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = &lt;0.001). Additionally, patients reported significantly higher anxiety (<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>(42) = −4.32, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = &lt;0.001) and depression (<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>(42) = −3.80, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = &lt;0.001) symptoms.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic and Sleep Quality Data of Patients with pID and Healthy Controls</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">pID Patients</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy Controls</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sociodemographics:</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.1 (12.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.3 (10.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Gender (n. male/ female)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 / 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 / 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.13</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Education (n. low/medium/high)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 / 12 / 7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 / 15 / 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Estimated intelligence quotient (MWTB)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">112.6 (12.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">118.4 (14.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Self-</bold><bold>assessment</bold>
<bold>of anxiety and depression:</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HADS Anxiety (max. 21 points)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9 (5.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = &lt;0.01*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HADS Depression (max. 21 points)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5 (4.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3 (2.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = &lt;0.01*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Subjective sleep quality:</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> PSQI (max. 21 points)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.3 (3.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8 (2.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = &lt;0.01*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ISI (max. 28 points)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5 (4.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0 (4.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = &lt;0.01*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Objective polysomnographic sleep quality:</bold></td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sleep Efficiency (%)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">58.9 (17.8); CI: 50.97, 66.73</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sleep-onset latency (minutes)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">52.2 [86.3]; CI:41.57, 96.11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Wake after sleep onset (minutes)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">132.4 (52.0); CI:109.33, 155.41</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sleep-stage transition index (/hour)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">14.5 [6.6]; CI: 13.8, 20.22</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Arousal index (/hour)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">18.9 [14.9]; CI: 15.5, 25.13</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Apnea/Hypopnea index (/hour)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">2.4 [4.3]; CI: 1.17, 8.29</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Periodic Limb Movement index (/hour)</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">2.4 [6.1] CI: 2.21, 7.23</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep stage distribution (% of Time In Bed):</bold></td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Time Awake</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">41.2 (17.8); CI:33.24, 49.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Light sleep</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">34.2 (14.6); CI:27.76, 40.64</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Deep sleep</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">13.9 (7.4); CI:10.60, 17.18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> REM sleep</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">10.4 (5.6); CI:7.98, 12.90</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Mean and standard deviation (in parentheses) given for normally distributed data. Medians and interquartile ranges (in square brackets) and are presented for non-normally distributed data. CI: 95% Confidence Intervals are given for polysomnographic data. Gender and education expressed as number of participants. An asterisk marks significant differences.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: n., number of; pID, persistent Insomnia Disorder; MWTB, Mehrfachwahl Wortschatz Intelligenz Test B; PSQ, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index; ISI, Insomnia Severity Index; HADS, Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale; REM, Rapid Eye Movement.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <sec id="s0004-s2001">
        <title>Neurocognitive Performance</title>
        <p>MoCA performance is presented in <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. In total, five participants from each group qualified for an additional point. Using a cut-off of ≤23 points, which has better specificity for detecting MCI than the previously used ≤26,<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> we identified two good sleepers and seven patients with scores indicative of MCI.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>MoCA Scores of Patients with pID and Good Sleepers</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients with pID</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good Sleepers</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">q</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall score (Max 30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.6/2.2/20–28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.3/2.4/20–30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = &lt;0.006*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Subdomains:</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Visuospatial/executive (Max 5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (1.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.006*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Abstraction (Max 2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.009*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Attention (Max 6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (1.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (1.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.123</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Recall (Max 5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (2.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (2.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.309</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Naming (Max 3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.401</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Language (Max 3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.413</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.044</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Orientation (Max 6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.496</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.050</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Mean, standard deviation, and range of overall scores, and median and interquartile range (in parentheses) for each subdomain, as well as the maximum number of points possible on each subsection of the MoCA for both the healthy control group as well as for patients with pID. An asterisk marks significant differences. q values represent the significance threshold established using the Benjamini-Hochberg correction for multiple comparison.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <p>Patients had worse overall cognitive performance (Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic> = 136.5, <italic toggle="yes">n1</italic> = 22, <italic toggle="yes">n2</italic> = 22, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = &lt;0.006, <italic toggle="yes">q</italic> = 0.006), and showed specific deficits in verbal abstraction (Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic> = 141.5, <italic toggle="yes">n1</italic> = 22, <italic toggle="yes">n2</italic> = 22, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.009, <italic toggle="yes">q</italic> = 0.019) and visuospatial/executive function (Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic> = 134.5, <italic toggle="yes">n1</italic> = 22, <italic toggle="yes">n2</italic> = 22, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.006, <italic toggle="yes">q</italic> = 0.013), mainly related to clock drawing. Naming, attention, language, memory, and orientation subdomains showed no intergroup differences. Patients’ overall cognitive performance was not related to their anxiety (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>(20) = <italic toggle="yes">0</italic>.07, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.38, 95% C.I. [−0.36, 0.48], <italic toggle="yes">q</italic> = 0.03) or depression (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>(20) = −0.13, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.28, 95% C.I. [−0.52, 0.31], <italic toggle="yes">q</italic> = 0.05) scores.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2002">
        <title>Sleep Quality</title>
        <p>To assess whether cognitive performance related to sleep quality, overall MoCA scores were correlated to patients’ sleep quality measures. Poorer MoCA scores were linked to worse objective polysomnographic measures, namely with lower sleep efficiency (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>(20) = 0.59, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.004, 95% C.I. [0.22, 0.81], <italic toggle="yes">q</italic> = 0.007), higher amounts of wake (% of time in bed) (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>(20) = −0.59, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.004, 95% C.I. [−0.81, −0.22]; <italic toggle="yes">q</italic> = 0.014), higher sleep latency (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>(20) = −0.57, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.005, 95% C.I. [−0.80, −0.20]; <italic toggle="yes">q</italic> = 0.021), and lower amounts of REM-sleep (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>(20) = 0.52, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.013, 95% C.I. [0.13, 0.77]; <italic toggle="yes">q</italic> = 0.029; see <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). However, overall MoCA score did not correlate with the remaining polysomnographic parameters (see <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=399644.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Materials</ext-link></underline> and <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=399644.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 1</ext-link></underline>). Due to low sub-score variability, correlations between MoCA sub-scores and sleep parameters were not calculated.</p>
        <p>Finally, worse overall MoCA performance was linked to poorer subjective sleep quality (PSQI: <italic toggle="yes">r</italic>(42) = −0.47, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.001, 95% C.I. [−0.66, −0.18], <italic toggle="yes">q</italic> = 0.025 and ISI: <italic toggle="yes">r</italic>(42) = −0.43, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.004, 95% C.I. [−0.66, −0.18], <italic toggle="yes">q</italic> = 0.050), where higher PSQI and ISI scores reflect poorer sleep quality; see <xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>.
<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Distribution of overall MoCA scores relative to scores on subjective, self-reported sleep quality measures. (<bold>A</bold>) PSQI: Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Inventory; (<bold>B</bold>) ISI: Insomnia Severity Index. Note that due to overlapping scores, some points in the scatterplot represent multiple data points.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-491-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Using a screening tool, we found lower cognitive performance in pID patients compared to good sleepers, which was mainly attributable to deficiencies in verbal abstraction and clock drawing. These cognitive changes were significantly related to polysomnographic indices of insomnia severity and amount of REM-sleep in patients with pID.</p>
      <p>Lower cognitive status in patients with insomnia, assessed via screenings, has been reported in some,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> but not in all studies.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> The overall MoCA score has been found to be significantly lower in pID patients, although differences in sub-scores were not assessed.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> Studies addressing domain-specific cognitive constraints have used extensive neuropsychological test batteries,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> although have failed to find a consistent pattern of results, likely due to the diversity of tests used. Nevertheless, given that insomnia patients are at higher risk for Alzheimer’s disease, the finding of specific deficiencies in clock drawing and verbal abstraction in this study seem noteworthy. Clock drawing, a singular screening test in its own right, can detect patients with an elevated risk of dementia.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> Moreover, in a 22-year prospective study, verbal abstract reasoning was one of the strongest predictors for the development of Alzheimer’s disease in the pre-clinical phase.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> Thus, this specific pattern of deficits observed here could be indicative of an incipient neurodegenerative process.</p>
      <p>Lower cognitive performance has been linked to poorer subjective sleep.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6–8</xref> However, our results go beyond this by demonstrating that cognitive performance was also linked to objective polysomnographic sleep measures in patients with pID. Several different aspects sleep disturbances could account for this cognitive decline. For example, sleep fragmentation leads to an accelerated deposition of amyloid β.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Conversely, animal models suggests that reduced slow-wave sleep lowers glymphatic system activity, leading to a build-up of amyloid β.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> Concurrently, elderly subjects with less slow-wave sleep showed increased brain atrophy at autopsy.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> Conversely, data on healthy older adults implicates REM-sleep duration as being predictive of cognitive decline.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> Consequently, different aspects of sleep quality reduction could lead to pathological cerebral processes, which may predispose people to neurocognitive decline.</p>
      <p>However, we found no evidence linking cognitive performance and both deep (slow-wave) sleep, and arousal/sleep-stage transition indices (reflective of sleep fragmentation). Instead, increased REM-sleep was related to better cognitive performance, suggesting a protective role against cognitive decline. This supports similar findings in healthy older adults,<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> with REM-sleep amount being predictive of cognitive outcome at a three-year follow-up.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> Nevertheless, our study is the first - to the best of our knowledge - to show this in pID patients. Given that our patients had no objective memory deficits, and that REM-sleep is vital for the integrity of episodic memory function,<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> then it seems possible that some patients may be at a “pre-amnestic-MCI” neurodegenerative stage. Although speculative, longitudinal studies assessing whether the pattern of deficits observed in patients with pID later develops into one resembling aMCI are needed.</p>
      <p>One alternative explanation for our results could be that cognitive difficulties resulted from chronic sleep deprivation. However, neither chronic nor acute sleep deprivation studies have shown negative effects on abstraction, executive functions, and visuospatial capabilities.<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38–40</xref> Thus, our results are not explainable through mere reduction of sleep quantity. Nevertheless, experimental studies may not completely reflect sleep deprivation experienced in chronic disorders like insomnia. However, reduced sleep quantity could not explain why the amount of REM-sleep, but not slow-wave-sleep, is related to cognitive performance.</p>
      <p>One limitation is that polysomnographic data were not collected from controls, and thus, intergroup differences in sleep quality could not be quantified. However, given group differences in cognition, and the correlations of these cognitive deficits with not only subjective but also objective measures of sleep quality in the patient group, the results of the current study support the conclusion that impaired sleep quality is related to a decline in cognitive abilities. Furthermore, patients did not have an acclimatization night, and may have experienced poorer sleep due to the “first-night-effect”. Another potential confound is the patients’ higher anxiety/depression scores, commonly seen in patients with pID.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> However, in our study, these scores did not correlate with cognitive performance, suggesting that psychological distress was not linked to cognitive deficits. Nevertheless, an indirect, mediating role is possible.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> Finally, the sensitivity and specificity of the MoCA in the context of insomnia needs further elucidation.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Taken together, neurocognitive deficits can be identified in patients with pID using a simple screening tool. Furthermore, insomnia severity and the amount of REM-sleep are closely related to these deficits. Whilst these results demonstrate that a screening tool may be sufficient in identifying patients at risk, this would nevertheless need verification through a longitudinal study.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <p>AD, Alzheimer’s disease; aMCI, amnestic mild cognitive impairment; PID, persistent insomnia disorder; DSM V, Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders, 5th edition; HADS-A/D, Hospital anxiety and depression scale, Anxiety/Depression; ISI, Insomnia severity index; MCI, mild cognitive impairment; MoCA, Montreal cognitive assessment tool; PSQI, Pittsburgh sleep quality index; TIB, Time in bed; REM, rapid eye movement.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0008">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p>As much of the data pertains to patient information, the data will not be made publicly available. However, the data that support the findings of this study are available upon reasonable request from the corresponding author.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0009">
      <title>Ethics Approval and Informed Consent</title>
      <p>Ethical approval for this observational study was obtained from the Ethics Center at Friedrich-Schiller University (№ 4810-05/16), and written informed consent was given by each participant prior to participation. The study complies with the Declaration of Helsinki.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0010">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation, or in all these areas; took part in drafting, revising or critically reviewing the article; gave final approval of the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0011">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yaffe</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Falvey</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoang</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Connections between sleep and cognition in older adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1017</fpage>–<lpage>1028</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(14)70172-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25231524</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Iranzo</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Santamaria</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <part-title>Sleep in neurodegenerative diseases</part-title>. In: <string-name><surname>Chokroverty</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Billiard</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, editors. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>; <year>2015</year>:<fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>283</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shamim</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Warriach</surname>
<given-names>ZI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tariq</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia: risk factor for neurodegenerative diseases</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cureus</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e6004</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.6004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31807391</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Minakawa</surname>
<given-names>EN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wada</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nagai</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disturbance as a potential modifiable risk factor for Alzheimer’s disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Mol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>803</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms20040803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30781802</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Roth</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia: definition, prevalence, etiology, and consequences</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>S7</fpage>–<lpage>S10</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.26929</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17824495</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>MY</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep disturbances increase the risk of dementia: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>4</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2017.06.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28890168</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>de Almondes</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Costa</surname>
<given-names>MV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malloy-Diniz</surname>
<given-names>LF</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia and risk of dementia in older adults: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychiatr Res</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>115</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2016.02.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27017287</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bubu</surname>
<given-names>OM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brannick</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mortimer</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep, cognitive impairment, and Alzheimer’s disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>zsw032</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsw032</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Joo</surname>
<given-names>EY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suh</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Hippocampal substructural vulnerability to sleep disturbance and cognitive impairment in patients with chronic primary insomnia: magnetic resonance imaging morphometry</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1189</fpage>–<lpage>1198</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.3836</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25061247</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sexton</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sykara</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Karageorgiou</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Connections between insomnia and cognitive aging</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurosci Bull</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12264-019-00401-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31222500</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tan</surname>
<given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>GH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Patients with chronic insomnia disorder have increased serum levels of neurofilaments, neuron-specific enolase and S100B: does organic brain damage exist?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>171</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2017.12.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29957487</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cricco</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simonsick</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Foley</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The impact of insomnia on cognitive functioning in older adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Geriatr Soc</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1185</fpage>–<lpage>1189</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1532-5415.2001.49235.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11559377</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ding</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Changes in cognitive function in patients with primary insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Shanghai Arch Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>137</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11919/j.issn.1002-0829.216097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28904508</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fernandez-Mendoza</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Calhoun</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bixler</surname>
<given-names>EO</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep misperception and chronic insomnia in the general population: the role of objective sleep duration and psychological profiles</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychosom Med</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>73</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>88</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PSY.0b013e3181fe365a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20978224</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nasreddine</surname>
<given-names>ZS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Phillips</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bédirian</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The Montreal Cognitive Assessment, MoCA: a brief screening tool for mild cognitive impairment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Geriatr Soc</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>695</fpage>–<lpage>699</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1532-5415.2005.53221.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15817019</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pinto</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Machado</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bulgacov</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Is the Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) screening superior to the Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) in the detection of mild cognitive impairment (MCI) and Alzheimer’s Disease (AD) in the elderly?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Int Psychogeriatr</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>491</fpage>–<lpage>504</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1041610218001370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30426911</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zigmond</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Snaith</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Psychiatr Scand</italic></source>. <year>1983</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>361</fpage>–<lpage>370</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0447.1983.tb09716.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6880820</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Lehrl</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mehrfachwahl-Wortschatz-Intelligenztest, B-Version</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Straube</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Erlangen</publisher-name>; <year>1977</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>CF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monk</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0165-1781(89)90047-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2748771</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bastien</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vallieres</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morin</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Validation of the Insomnia Severity Index as an outcome measure for insomnia research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>307</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1389-9457(00)00065-4</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><string-name><surname>DOMINO Ver. 2.9.0</surname></string-name>, <source>SOMNOmedics, Randersacker, Germany</source>
<year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Berry</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brooks</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gamaldo</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, et al. <source><italic toggle="yes">The American Academy of Sleep Medicine Manual for the Scoring of Sleep and Associated Events: Rules, Terminology and Technical Specifications, Version 2.5</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Darien, Illinois</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</publisher-name>; <year>2018</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>VS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>LV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tukey</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Controlling error in multiple comparisons, with examples from state-to-state differences in educational achievement</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Educ Behav Stat</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>42</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3102/10769986024001042</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>IBM Corp</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows, Version 26.0</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Armonk, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>IBM Corp</publisher-name>; <year>2019</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Carson</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leach</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Murphy</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A re‐examination of Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) cutoff scores</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Geriatr Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>379</fpage>–<lpage>388</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/gps.4756</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28731508</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fortier-Brochu</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morin</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cognitive impairment in individuals with insomnia: clinical significance and correlates</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1787</fpage>–<lpage>1798</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.4172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25364074</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Potvin</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lorrain</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Forget</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep quality and 1-year incident cognitive impairment in community-dwelling older adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>491</fpage>–<lpage>499</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.1732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22467987</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Brain iron deposition in primary insomnia — an in vivo susceptibility‐weighted imaging study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Behav</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e01138</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/brb3.1138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30548431</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jeong</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seomun</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The clock drawing test: a systematic review and meta‐analysis of diagnostic accuracy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Adv Nurs</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>74</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2742</fpage>–<lpage>2754</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jan.13810</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30047147</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Elias</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beiser</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wolf</surname>
<given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The preclinical phase of Alzheimer disease: a 22-year prospective study of the Framingham Cohort</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>808</fpage>–<lpage>813</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archneur.57.6.808</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10867777</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rasmussen</surname>
<given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mestre</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nedergaard</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The glymphatic pathway in neurological disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1016</fpage>–<lpage>1024</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30353860</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gelber</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Redline</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ross</surname>
<given-names>GW</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Associations of brain lesions at autopsy with polysomnography features before death</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>84</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>296</fpage>–<lpage>303</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000001163</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Scullin</surname>
<given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bliwise</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Is cognitive aging associated with levels of REM sleep or slow wave sleep?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>336</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.4482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25669196</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blackwell</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yaffe</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Relationships between sleep stages and changes in cognitive function in older men: the MrOS Sleep Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>411</fpage>–<lpage>421</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.4500</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25325465</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Khazaie</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tahmasian</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghadami</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The effects of chronic partial sleep deprivation on cognitive functions of medical residents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Iranian J Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>74</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lafortune</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gagnon</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep spindles and rapID eye movement sleep as predictors of next morning cognitive performance in healthy middle‐aged and older participants</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24245769</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Olaithe</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bucks</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hillman</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cognitive deficits in obstructive sleep apnea: insights from a meta-review and comparison with deficits observed in COPD, insomnia, and sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2017.03.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28760549</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rauchs</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bertran</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guillery-Girard</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Consolidation of strictly episodic memories mainly requires rapID eye movement sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>395</fpage>–<lpage>401</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/27.3.395</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15164890</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Siegel</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>REM sleep: a biological and psychological paradox</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2011.01.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21482156</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wusk</surname>
<given-names>GC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nasrini</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of six weeks of chronic sleep restriction with weekend recovery on cognitive performance and wellbeing in high-performing adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>zsab051</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsab051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33630069</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tan</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zou</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep problems and risk of all-cause cognitive decline or dementia: an updated systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cog Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>236</fpage>–<lpage>244</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
