<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38213412</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">10778138</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">436824</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S436824</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Associations Between Sleep Spindle Metrics, Age, Education and Executive Function in Young Adult and Middle-Aged Patients with Obstructive Sleep Apnea</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Sui et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Sui et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sui</surname><given-names>Rongcui</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Jie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Yunhan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Shizhen</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Huijun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Jianhong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Xiang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Demin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Yanru</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Xingjun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Otorhinolaryngology Head and Neck Surgery, Beijing Tongren Hospital, Capital Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Obstructive Sleep Apnea-Hypopnea Syndrome Clinical Diagnosis and Therapy and Research Centre, Capital Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Key Laboratory of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Ministry of Education, Capital Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Electronic Engineering, Tsinghua Shenzhen International Graduate School, Tsinghua University</institution>, <addr-line>Shenzhen</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Demin Han; Yanru Li, <institution>Beijing Tongren Hospital, Capital Medical University, 1 Dongjiaominxiang</institution>, <addr-line>Dongcheng District</addr-line>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, Email deminhan_ent@hotmail.com; liyanruru@aliyun.com</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>9</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Sui et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sui et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Purpose</title><p>This study aimed to investigate the association between sleep spindle metrics and executive function in individuals with obstructive sleep apnea (OSA). Furthermore, we examined the association of age and education on executive function.</p></sec><sec><title>Patients and Methods</title><p>A total of 230 (40.90 ± 8.83 years, F/M = 45/185) participants were enrolled. Overnight electroencephalogram (C3-M2) recording detected sleep spindles by a novel U-Net-type neural network that integrates temporal information with time-frequency images. Sleep spindle metrics, including frequency (Hz), overall density (events/min), fast density (events/min), slow density (events/min), duration (sec) and amplitude (µV), were measured. Executive function was assessed using standardized neuropsychological tests. Associations between sleep spindle metrics, executive function, and demographic factors were analyzed using multivariate linear regression.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>In fully adjusted linear regression models, higher overall sleep spindle density (TMT-A, B=−1.279, p=0.009; TMT-B, B=−1.813, p=0.008), fast sleep spindle density (TMT-A, B=−1.542, p=0.048; TMT-B, B=−2.187, p=0.036) and slow sleep spindle density (TMT-A, B=−1.731, p=0.037; TMT-B, B=−2.449, p=0.034) were associated with better executive function. And the sleep spindle duration both during N2 sleep time (TMT-A, B=−13.932, p=0.027; TMT-B, B=−19.001, p=0.034) and N3 sleep time (TMT-B, B=−29.916, p=0.009; Stroop-incongruous, B=−21.303, p=0.035) was independently associated with better executive function in this population. Additionally, age and education were found to be highly associated with executive function.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Specific sleep spindle metrics, higher overall density, fast density and slow density during N2 sleep time, and longer duration during N2 and N3 sleep time, are independent and sensitive indicators of better executive function in young adult and middle-aged patients with OSA. Further research is needed to explore the underlying mechanisms and clinical implications of these findings.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>sleep spindle metrics</kwd><kwd>executive function</kwd><kwd>obstructive sleep apnea</kwd><kwd>young adults</kwd><kwd>middle-aged adults</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>funded by the National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This research was funded by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (81970866) and Beijing Dongcheng District Outstanding Talent Funding Project (2023-dchrcpyzz-10).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="8"/><ref-count count="50"/><page-count count="15"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) has emerged as a global concern due to its high prevalence and the various systemic complications it entails.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> OSA is characterized by recurrent episodes of complete or partial collapse of the upper airway during sleep, often accompanied by snoring and frequent arousal. These occurrences lead to hypoxia, sleep fragmentation, and subsequent physiological damage. Epidemiological studies have revealed significant independent associations between OSA and conditions such as hypertension, coronary artery disease, heart failure, and cognitive impairment.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3–5</xref></p>
      <p>Epidemiology shows that OSA co-morbid with cognitive impairment can be observed in children, adolescents, and adults. In a sleep clinic cohort, the prevalence of cognitive impairment was 47.9% in the entire patient population, rising to more than 55.3% in patients with moderate-to-severe OSA.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> In middle-aged adults, OSA is commonly associated with cognitive impairment in terms of attention, memory, and executive functioning.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Nemeth et al concluded that patients with OSA are selectively susceptible to higher-order cognitive functions (eg, executive function) compared to general skill learning and sequence-specific learning.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Furthermore, meta-analyses confirmed that executive function was a vulnerable cognitive domain in adults with OSA.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></p>
      <p>Executive function is an important domain of cognition in which higher cognitive processes modulate lower cognitive processes, including sustained attention, working memory, and inhibition control. It is supported by a distributed set of brain regions that include the prefrontal cortex (PFC) and the thalamus, particularly the dorsomedial nucleus (MD), which interconnects with the PFC.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Neuroimaging studies have shown that the MD is a key subcortical node in the prefrontal-parietal “executive control” network that supports working memory, cognitive flexibility, and inhibition control.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Damage to the thalamic-prefrontal circuit leads to deficits in executive function. Recent studies have reported that executive dysfunction coexists with abnormalities in thalamic-frontal connections in several psychiatric disorders, including schizophrenia.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></p>
      <p>Sleep spindles, which signal as 11–16 Hz bursts in the electroencephalogram (EEG) of the mammalian brain, represent electrical surface associations of thalamic neuron oscillations. They are a highly inherited feature of the sleep EEG and generated by the thalamic reticular nucleus (TRN) in conjunction with specific thalamic nuclei and are modulated by thalamo-cortical circuit.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> It has been shown that the presence of abnormal sleep spindle activity and deficits in individuals with chronic or early schizophrenia is associated with abnormal thalamo-cortical connectivity compared to healthy individuals.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Study showed that moderate OSA patients exhibit a lower percentage of slow spindles (11–13 Hz) with deceleration in frontal and parietal regions, in comparison to mild and non-OSA patients.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> Research has demonstrated that older adults with OSA show deficits in fast sleep spindles (14–16 Hz) but exhibit preserved overnight declarative memory consolidation.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Similarly, in children with obstructive sleep-disordered breathing (SDB), reduced sleep spindle density and intensity has been linked to poorer visual/executive function.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></p>
      <p>Abnormalities in thalamo-cortical circuit connectivity are commonly manifested as executive dysfunction and sleep spindle abnormalities. The strength and plasticity of thalamo-cortical circuits, as reflected by the spindle, may underlie an individual’s cognition, especially executive function. The metric of spindle and slow oscillation morphology has been identified as predicted cognitive performance in older adults.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> In healthy middle-aged and older adults (50–91 years old) without sleep disorders, higher spindle density predicted better performance in verbal learning, visual attention, and verbal fluency.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> In children, slow sleep spindle density reflects the developing brain’s ability to acquire and improve executive function learning abilities, such as integrated planning and problem-solving skills.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Although no direct neuroimaging studies have demonstrated impaired thalamo-cortical connectivity in patients with OSA, thinned prefrontal cortex and reduced thalamic tissue integrity were observed.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> This provides a neuroanatomical basis for executive dysfunction and sleep spindle deficits. Recent studies in middle-aged and older adults showed sleep spindle abnormalities were independently associated with OSA severity measures.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Furthermore, the associations between sleep spindle metrics and functional outcomes was explored in large population-based sample of aging men, and results showed that higher fast spindle density during N3 sleep time was associated with worse executive performance.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> These observations supported the utility of sleep spindle metrics as useful executive function markers in older OSA. Cognitive impairment in OSA patients presents at a younger age; however, our understanding of how this relationship may manifest in the younger OSA patient population is limited.</p>
      <p>In this study, we aimed to investigate the association between sleep spindle metrics and executive function in young adult and middle-aged patients with OSA.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <p>The study protocol was conducted according to the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki and was approved by the appropriate Institutional Review Board of Beijing Tongren Hospital, Capital Medical University (TREC2022-KY059). The participants signed written informed consent forms before the study for inclusion in the study and for the use of executive function test data and medical records.</p>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p>A total of 180 patients with obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) and 50 primary snorers, who underwent polysomnography (PSG) at Beijing Tongren Hospital, were included in this study (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Overnight PSG data were collected from all participants. Inclusion criteria for enrollment were as follows: 1) age between 18 and 59 years; 2) apnea-hypopnea index (AHI) &gt;5 events/h for OSA patients; 3) no reliance on sleep medication for falling asleep; 4) abstention from sleep medication on the night of PSG; 5) absence of active cardiovascular or cerebrovascular disease, uncontrolled diabetes or hypertension, or degenerative diseases (eg, Parkinson’s disease or Alzheimer’s disease); 6) no history of psychiatric disorders; and 7) no history of craniosurgery. All participants underwent comprehensive interviews and evaluations conducted by medical professionals.
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>A flow diagram for participants.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Overnight Polysomnography</title>
        <p>All participants underwent in-laboratory nocturnal PSG recording. Eight electroencephalogram (EEG) electrodes were positioned according to the standard 10–20 system configuration (F3, F4, C3, C4, O1, O2, M1 and M2). Electrocardiogram (ECG) electrodes were used for heart rate monitoring. Two chin electromyography (EMG) electrodes and a submental EMG were employed to measure chin muscle activity, while two electrooculogram (EOG) electrodes were used to detect eye movements. Respiratory data, including finger pulse oximetry, airflow, chest and abdominal respiratory effort, were collected using a thermistor flow sensor and nasal airflow sensors. Compumedics systems (Compumedics Medics Corporation, Australia) were used for PSG recording and experienced sleep technicians manually scored all PSG measures according to 2017 American Academy of Sleep Medicine (AASM). The AHI, representing the sum of apneic and hypopneic events per hour of sleep, was calculated. OSA was identified by an AHI ≥ 5/h and further categorized as mild (5–15/h), moderate (15–30/h), or severe (≥30/h). Additionally, participants completed the Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS) to assess their subjective sleep quality, with global scores &gt;10 indicating excessive daytime sleepiness (EDS).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Executive Function</title>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3001">
          <title>Trail Making Test A and B (TMT)</title>
          <p>The Trail Making Test (TMT) consists of two parts: TMT-A and TMT-B. TMT-A is primarily used to assess psychomotor functions and processing speed requiring participants to connect encircled numbers (1–25) in sequence.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> TMT-B is more complex and measures executive functions such as cognitive flexibility, divided attention, response monitoring, and task switching. In view of the wide variation in the mastery of the letters among Chinese, a revised version of the TMT-B in Chinese was used. It includes circles with numbers from 1 to 13 and boxes with numbers from 1 to 12. Participants are required to connect the numbers in ascending order, starting with the circles and then the boxes. Prior to the test, participants receive practice trials to ensure understanding of the tasks. During the practice test, if participants make errors during the test, the examiner points them out and guides the participants to complete the task correctly. Performance on the test is measured by the time taken to complete TMT-A and TMT-B. To provide a more specific assessment of executive function, the TMT difference (TMT-D) is calculated by subtracting the performance time in TMT Part A from Part B.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3002">
          <title>Stroop Color-Word Test (SCWT)</title>
          <p>The Stroop Color-Word Test (SCWT) is used to evaluate working memory and inhibitory control and is measured by completion times.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Participants are instructed to respond as quickly and accurately as possible. The test has congruous and incongruous conditions. In the congruous condition, participants read the word in black ink (eg, the word “GREEN” written in black ink) or identify the color of the ink (eg, the word “XX” written in red ink). In the incongruous condition, participants read the color of the ink in which the words are written (eg, the word “GREEN” written in red ink).<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Each test consists of 50 words, and the completion time for identifying all 50 words is measured using a stopwatch.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3003">
          <title>Spindle Detection</title>
          <p>All PSG data were exported to standardized European Data Format from which overnight C3-M2 EEG recordings underwent automated artifact detection using a previously validated algorithm.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> In this study, a new U-Net type neural network<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> integrating temporal information with time-frequency images was constructed to enhance spindle detection in N2/N3 sleep. To obtain time-frequency images, we employ the technique of Continuous Wavelet Transform (CWT), and the Morlet wavelet was chosen as the basis wavelet function. With the information from both the time domain and the time-frequency domain, a multi-modal fusion approach using a U-Net architecture was trained for sleep spindle detection (11–16 Hz, ≥0.5 and ≤3 s) (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=436824.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Figure S1</ext-link></underline>.). Fast sleep spindles (13–16 Hz) and slow sleep spindles (11–13 Hz) were detected. The training dataset used in this study was collected from the Beijing Tongren Hospital, and the dataset were partitioned into three splits ie the training set, validation and test set. The model hyperparameters and evaluation metrics were set to be consistent with the previous work SUMO.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> The validated model achieved an F1 score of 83% on the test set, surpassing the performance of existing state-of-the-art methods and reaching the level of expert recognition (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=436824.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Table S1</ext-link></underline>).</p>
          <p>As the model provides the start and end time points of each spindle, we can calculate the duration of a spindle by subtracting the start time from the end time. The amplitude is obtained by subtracting the minimum value from the maximum value of the signal within that time period, and the frequency is calculated as the average frequency of the signal during that time period.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3004">
          <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
          <p>Data analysis was conducted using IBM SPSS statistical software (version 24.0). Descriptive statistics are presented as mean ± standard deviation (SD) for normal distribution data, and median (IQR) was presented for non-normal distribution data. Differences in population characteristics and sleep spindle metrics were determined by one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) for normal distribution variables and the Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test for non-normal distribution variables.</p>
          <p>Univariate and multivariate linear regression models including Bonferroni correction were used to examine the relationships between sleep spindle metrics during N2/N3 sleep, age/education, and executive function. The models were adjusted for covariates such as age, AHI, total sleep time (TST), body mass index (BMI), minimum oxygen saturation (min SpO2), education, gender, and arousal index (AI). Unstandardized beta (B) coefficients with 95% confidence intervals (CI) are reported. Variance inflation factor values for all covariates were close to 1, indicating the absence of multicollinearity. As the oxygen desaturation index (ODI) was highly correlated with AHI, min SpO2 was used to assess sleep hypoxemia. The p &lt; 0.05 was statistically different, p &lt; 0.01 was statistically significant, and p &lt; 0.001 was extremely statistically significant.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Characteristics of Participants</title>
        <p>The study included a total of 230 participants. OSA prevalence (AHI ≥ 5/h) was 78.3% (n=180, F/M = 20/160), and 34.8% have severe OSA (AHI ≥ 30/h) (n=80, F/M = 7/73). <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> displays the participants characteristics, revealing no significant differences in age, education, body mass index (BMI), neck circumference (NC) in patients with OSA. Participants with severe OSA showed more pronounced hypoxia, as reflected by higher AHI, longer apnea/hypopnea duration, lower minimum oxygen saturation (min-SpO2), and increased sleep fragmentation, as indicated by the arousal index.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of Participants</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI&lt;5/h (n=50)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&lt; AHI &lt;30/h (n=100)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI≥30/h (n=80)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Demographic</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender (F/M)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25/25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13/87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/73</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (year)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.19 ± 10.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.68 ± 9.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.50 (11)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education (year)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.51 ± 3.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.15 (3.77)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.54 ± 3.10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC(cm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.64 ± 4.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.25 (4.38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.21 ± 3.25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSG parameter (events/hour)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.03 ± 1.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.25 (11.38)*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.63 ± 17.33*<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM - AHI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15 (4.53)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.30 (23.60)*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.84 ± 16.85*<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NREM - AHI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30 (2.23)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.75 (12.73)*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.39 ± 20.85*<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arousal index</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.70 (8.02)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.75 (9.68)*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.25 (24.20)*<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM - arousal index</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.05 (6.35)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.35 (7.93)*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.35 (29.53)*<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NREM - arousal index</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.45 (7.67)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.45 (11.47)*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.39 ± 20.85*<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Apnea/hypopnea time (sec)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean - apnea</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.50 (19.35)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (10.30)*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.12 ± 7.85*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max - apnea</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (22.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (24.13)*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.19 ± 23.51*<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean - hypopnea</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.90 (8.87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (18)*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.81 ± 10.46*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max - hypopnea</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.98 ± 16.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.75 (18.25)*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.25 (25.12)*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep structure</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NREM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08 ± 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08 (0.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11 (0.14)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 ± 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65 ± 0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67 (0.14)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 (0.14)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 (0.11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.04)*<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21 ± 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20 (0.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19 ± 0.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TST (min)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">412.00 ± 71.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">416.00 ± 66.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">444.73 ± 77.87</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N2 sleep time (min)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">255.38 ± 52.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">264.22 ± 66.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">282.47 ± 65.93</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Min-Spo2 (%)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93 (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (7)*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (15.75)*<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ESS</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.09 ± 3.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.79 ± 3.79</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>:* p &lt; 0.05 compared with AHI &lt; 5/h. <sup>#</sup> p &lt; 0.05 compared with 5&lt; AHI &lt;30/h.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: BMI, body mass index; NC, neck circumference; AHI, apnea hypopnea index; REM - AHI, apnea/hypopnea index during rapid eye movement; NREM - AHI, apnea/hypopnea index during non-rapid eye movement; REM - arousal index, arousal index during rapid eye movement; NREM - arousal index, arousal index during non-rapid eye movement; Max - apnea, maximum apnea time; Max - hypopnea, maximum hypopnea time; ODI, oxygen desaturation index; NREM, non- rapid eye movement; N1, non-rapid eye movement stage 1; N2, non-rapid eye movement stage 2; N3, non-rapid eye movement stage 3; REM, rapid eye movement; TST, total sleep time; SpO2, oxygen saturation; ESS, Epworth sleep score.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Spindle Metrics</title>
        <p>The study found significant differences in various metrics related to sleep spindles during N2 sleep between mild/moderate OSA (n=100, 40.68 ± 9.30 years), severe OSA (n=80, 40.5 (11) years) and primary snorers (n=50, 36.19 ± 10.07 years) (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Specifically, decreased overall spindle density, fast spindle density, and slow spindle density were observed in the mild/moderate OSA patients compared to simple snorers. A similar difference in spindle density was observed in patients with severe OSA compared to mild/moderate OSA. Additionally, the severe OSA patients exhibited a significant decrease in these sleep spindle metrics compared to the mild/moderate OSA patients (0.67 (2.16) vs 1.49 (2.51); 0.30 (1.22) vs 0.78 (1.10); 0.26 (0.88) vs 0.54 (1.07), respectively, p&lt;0.05). Moreover, the duration of sleep spindles showed a decreasing trend with the severity of OSA in comparison to primary snorers, although this difference was not statistically different. During N3 sleep time, decreased overall spindle density, fast spindle density, and slow spindle density were also observed in the mild/moderate OSA and severe OSA patients compared to simple snorers. The severe OSA patients also exhibited a significant decreased sleep spindle metrics compared to the mild/moderate OSA patients (0.29 (0.81) vs 0.77 (0.99); 0.14 (0.41) vs 0.43 (0.59); 0.10 (0.36) vs 0.32 (0.34), respectively, p&lt;0.05).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Sleep Spindle Metrics in OSA Patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI&lt;5/h (n=50)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&lt; AHI &lt;30/h (n=100)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI≥30/h (n=80)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N2 sleep spindle metrics</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency (Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.15 ± 0.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.10 (0.45)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.15 ± 0.41</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amplitude (µV)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.76 ± 15.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.63 (16.23)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.95 (11.12)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration (sec)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 ± 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 (0.04)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 (0.04)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall density (11–16 Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.73 (3.16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49 (2.51)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67 (2.16)*<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fast density (13–16 Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 (1.44)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 (1.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30 (1.22)*<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slow density (11–13 Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 (1.64)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 (1.07)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26 (0.88)*<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N3 sleep spindle metrics</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency (Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.05 ± 0.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.07 ± 0.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.05 ± 0.25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amplitude (µV)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.04 ± 20.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.67 (13.32)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.25 ± 11.41</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration (sec)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 ± 0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 (0.11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07±0.13</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall density (11–16 Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (1.04)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77 (0.99)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29 (0.81)*<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fast density (13–16 Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 (0.61)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43 (0.59)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 (0.41)*<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slow density (11–13 Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40 (0.30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32 (0.34)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10 (0.36)*<sup>#</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: *p &lt; 0.05 compared with AHI &lt; 5/h. <sup>#</sup>p &lt; 0.05 compared with 5&lt; AHI &lt;30/h.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Executive Function Performance</title>
        <p>The performance of executive function was assessed by Trail Making Test A and B (TMT) and Stroop Color-Word Test (SCWT) (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Specially, patients with OSA took longer to complete both in the TMT and SCWT tests compared to primary snorers. The completion time of TMT showed a significant increase in mild/moderate OSA (TMT-A, 30.80 ± 9.45 vs 26.49± 8.73, p&lt;0.05; TMT-B, 47.39 ± 17.64 vs 39.13 ± 9.20, p&lt;0.05; TMT-D, 16.34 (8.48) vs 11.80 ± 9.17, p&lt;0.05) and severe OSA patients (TMT-A, 28.48 (12.12) vs 26.4 9± 8.73, p&lt;0.05; TMT-B, 46.05 (17.35) vs 39.13 ± 9.20, p&lt;0.05; TMT-D, 17.64 (12.33) vs 11.80 ± 9.17, p&lt;0.05) compared to primary snorers. The completion time of the Stroop-word test (23.09 ± 5.15 vs 20.21 (5.22), p&lt;0.05) and Stroop-colour test (27.25 (7.67) vs 24.83 (5.21), p&lt;0.05) showed a significant increase in severe OSA patients compared to mild/moderate OSA.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Executive Function Assessment</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI&lt;5/h (n=50)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&lt; AHI&lt;30/h (n=100)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI≥30/h (n=80)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Trail Making Test A and B (TMT)(sec)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMT-A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.49 ± 8.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.80 ± 9.45*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.48 (12.12)*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMT-B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.13 ± 9.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.39 ± 17.64*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.05 (17.35)*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMT-D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.80 ± 9.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.34 (8.48)*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.64 (12.33)*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Stroop Color-Word Test (SCWT)(sec)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stroop-word</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.84 (4.70)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.21 (5.22)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.09 ± 5.15*<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stroop-colour</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.19 (8.35)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.83 (5.21)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.25 (7.67)*<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stroop-incongruous</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.65 (12.55)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.09 (14.11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.28 (13.70)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: *p &lt; 0.05 compared with AHI &lt; 5/h. <sup>#</sup>p &lt; 0.05 compared with 5&lt; AHI &lt;30/h.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Abbreviation</bold>: TMT-A, Trail Making Test A; TMT-B, Trail Making Test B; TMT-D, subtracting the performance time in TMT-A from TMT-B; Stroop-word, Stroop Word Test; Stroop-colour, Stroop Colour Test; Stroop-incongruous, Stroop Incongruous Test.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Associations of Age and Executive Function</title>
        <p>The associations between age and performance on the TMT and SCWT tests are presented in <xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. In the adjusted model, a decline in executive function was observed with increasing age in young adult and middle-aged patients with OSA. In young adult and middle-aged OSA patients, there was a significant increase in completion times for TMT-A (B=0.359, p&lt;0.001), TMT-B (B=0.661, p&lt;0.001), and TMT-D (B=0.283, p=0.002) as age increased. Similarly, the completion times for Stroop-word (B=0.197, p&lt;0.001), Stroop-colour (B=0.233, p&lt;0.001), and Stroop-incongruous tasks (B=0.494, p&lt;0.001) also increased with age. In primary snorers, completion time of TMT-B (B=0.316, p=0.048) and Stroop-colour test (B=0.296, p=0.021) also increased with age.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>The Association Between Age and Executive Function</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">OSA Cohort</th><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Primary snorers</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Unadjusted Model</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Adjusted Model</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Unadjusted Model</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Adjusted Model</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Β (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Β (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Β (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Β (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TMT</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMT-A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.165(0.079,0.251)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.359(0.211,0.508)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.322(0.095,0.548)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.007</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.228(−0.045,0.502)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.099</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMT-B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.304(0.178,0.431)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.661(0.450,0.872)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.505(0.243,0.767)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.316(0.003,0.630)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.048</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMT-D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.134(0.036,0.232)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.008</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.283(0.104,0.462)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.002</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.143(−0.074,0.357)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.192</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.212(−0.574,0.151)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.243</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SCWT</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stroop-word</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.121(0.075,0.166)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.197(0.115,0.278)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.175(0.064,0.286)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.003</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.097(−0.073,0.263)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.252</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stroop-colour</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.118(0.060,0.176)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.233(0.121,0.325)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.323(0.100,0.546)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.006</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.296(0.047,0.545)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.021</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stroop-incongruous</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.209(0.094,0.325)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.494(0.299,0.689)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.445(0.169,0.722)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.331(−0.079,0.740)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.110</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0006"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Coefficients: unstandardized beta (B) coefficients (95% CI) from univariable and multivariable linear regression models are reported. Estimates: represent the change in spindle metrics corresponding to a one-unit increase in AHI/h. Statistical adjustment: multivariable linear regression models were adjusted for AHI, arousal index, gender, education, BMI, total sleep time and min-SpO2. The p value &lt; 0.05 is highlighted in bold.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0007"><p><bold>Abbreviation</bold>: TMT, Trail Making Test A and B; TMT-A, Trail Making Test A; TMT-B, Trail Making Test B; TMT-D, subtracting the performance time in TMT-A from TMT-B; SCWT, Stroop Color-Word Test; Stroop-word, Stroop Word Test; Stroop-colour, Stroop Colour Test; Stroop-incongruous, Stroop Incongruous Test; CI, confidence interval.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2005">
        <title>Associations of Education and Executive Function</title>
        <p>The associations between education and performance on the TMT and SCWT in OSA patients and primary snorers were presented in <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>. In patients with OSA, higher levels of education were associated with better executive function performance. Specifically, individuals with higher education levels demonstrated shorter completion times on both TMT tests (TMT-A, B=−1.125, p&lt;0.001; TMT-B, B=−1.932, p&lt;0.001; TMT-D, B=−0.777, p=0.025) and SCWT tests (Stroop-word, B=−0.518, p=0.002; Stroop-color, B=−0.714 p=0.001; Stroop-incongruous, B=−1.601, p&lt;0.001). However, in primary snorers, completion time on the TMT tests and SCWT tests appeared to be independent of education.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>The Association Between Education and Executive Function.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1"/><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">OSA Cohort</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Primary snorers</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Unadjusted Model</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Adjusted Model</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Unadjusted Model</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Adjusted Model</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Β (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Β (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Β (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Β (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMT-A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.218(−1.799,-0.636)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.125(−1.690,-0.560)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.850(−2.692,0.993)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.357</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.580(−2.352,1.191)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.510</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMT-B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.110(−2.971,-1.249)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.932(−2.734,-1.131)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.030(−2.017,1.958)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.976</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.107(−1.727,1.940)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.906</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMT-D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.871(−1.541,-0.202)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.011</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.777(−1.457,-0.097)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.025</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.104(−2.386,2.177)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.927</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.374(−2.691,1.943)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.745</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCWT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stroop-word</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.663(−0.993,-0.334)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.518(−0.838,-0.199)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.002</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.667(−1.731,0.378)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.201</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.693(−1.750,0.450)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.238</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stroop-colour</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.849(−1.255,-0.443)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.714(−1.116,-0.312)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.778(−2.471,0.916)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.359</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.661(−2.303,0.917)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.387</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stroop-incongrous</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.908(−2.691,-1.125)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.095</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.601(−2.360,-0.843)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.170(−3.715,1.376)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.359</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.756(−3.405,1.892)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.565</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0008"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: TMT, Trail Making Test A and B; TMT-A, Trail Making Test A; TMT-B, Trail Making Test B; TMT-D, subtracting the performance time in TMT-A from TMT-B; SCWT, Stroop Color-Word Test; Stroop-word, Stroop Word Test; Stroop-colour, Stroop Colour Test; Stroop-incongruous, Stroop Incongruous Test; CI, confidence interval. Coefficients: unstandardized beta (B) coefficients (95% CI) from univariable and multivariable linear regression models are reported. Estimates: represent the change in spindle metrics corresponding to a one-unit increase in AHI/h. Statistical adjustment: multivariable linear regression models were adjusted for AHI, arousal index, gender, age, BMI, total sleep time and min-SpO2. The p value &lt; 0.05 is highlighted in bold.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2006">
        <title>Associations of Sleep Spindle Metrics and Executive Function</title>
        <p>The associations between sleep spindle metrics and executive function in both young adult and middle-aged patients with OSA and primary snorers are presented in <xref rid="t0006 t0007 t0008" ref-type="table">Tables 6–8</xref>. In the adjusted model, higher overall, fast and slow sleep spindle density and longer sleep spindle duration during N2 sleep time were associated with reduced completion time on the TMT-A test (B=−1.279, p=0.009; B=−1.542, p=0.048; B=−1.731, p=0.037; B=−13.932, p=0.027, respectively) and TMT-B test (B=−1.813, p=0.008; B=−2.187, p=0.036; B=−2.449, p=0.034; B=−19.001, p=0.034, respectively) in young adult and middle-aged patients with OSA. Similarly, in the adjusted model, longer duration of sleep spindle during N3 sleep time was associated with reduced completion time on the TMT-B test and Stroop-incongruous test (B=−29.916, p=0.009; B=−21.303, p=0.035, respectively) in young adult and middle-aged patients with OSA. In the unadjusted model, higher overall, fast and slow sleep spindle density and longer sleep spindle duration during N2 sleep time were associated with better performance in Stroop-incongruous test (B=−2.183, p&lt;0.001; B=−3.165, p&lt;0.001; B=−2.382, p=0.039; B=−17.664, p=0.002; respectively). However, in the adjusted model, the association was diminished. Moreover, executive function was found to be independent of sleep spindle metrics in primary snorers. No other adjusted associations of N2/N3 sleep spindle metrics with completion times of the TMT-D, Stroop-word, and Stroop-colour tests were found in young adult and middle-aged patients with OSA and primary snorers.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0006" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>The Association Between Sleep Spindle Metrics and TMT-A Test</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1"/><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">OSA Cohort</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Primary Snorers</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Unadjusted Model</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Adjusted Model</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Unadjusted Model</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Adjusted Model</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Β (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Β (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Β (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Β (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N2 sleep spindle metrics</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency (Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.663(−5.227,1.952)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.356</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.832(−4.218,2.533)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.628</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.141(−8.182,3.899)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.477</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.281(−12.228,3.666)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.279</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amplitude (µV)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004(−0.056,0.065)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.884</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.001(−0.057,0.055)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.964</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.066(−0.233,0.101)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.429</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.023(−0.227,0.082)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.821</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration (sec)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−15.248(−27.863,-2.633)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.018</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−13.932(−26.247,-1.616)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.027</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−14.197(−43.063,14.669)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.325</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−13.642(−50.269,22.985)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.451</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall density (11–16 Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.626(−2.333, −0.467)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.003</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.279(−2.240,-0.039)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.009</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.059(−1.427,1.544)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.937</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.199(−1.503,1.901)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.812</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fast density (13–16 Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.994(−3.397,-0.591)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.006</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.542(−3.015,-0.070)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.048</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.250(−2.843,2.343)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.846</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.696(−3.781,2.385)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.647</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slow density (11–13 Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.650(−3.344,0.044)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.174</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.731(−3.359,-1.102)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.037</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.323(−1.926,2.572)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.773</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.006(−1.633,3.644)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.441</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N3 sleep spindle metrics</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency (Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.108(−1.097,1.061)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.626</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.108(−1.097,1.061)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.626</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.484(−9.594,6.626)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.711</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.069(−12.241,12.103)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.991</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amplitude (µV)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.378(−0.495,1.251)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.391</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.418(−1.245,0.410)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.318</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.017(−0.086,0.053)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.629</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.030(−0.242,0.182)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.771</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration (sec)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.474(−43.684,-7.264)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.007</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−14.874(−31.566, 1.818)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.080</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−20.832(−50.846,0.183)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.167</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−13.690(−52.950,25.571)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.478</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall density (11–16 Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.093(−0.498,0.311)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.648</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.104(−0.460,0.253)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.565</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.477(−0.864,1.818)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.474</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061(−1.484,1.606)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.936</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fast density (13–16 Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.151(−1.253,0.951)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.786</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.214(−1.188,0.761)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.664</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.414(−3.381,0.544)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.778</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.291(−4.954,2.372)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.473</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slow density (11–13 Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.150(−0.729,0.430)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.609</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.155(−0.667,0.357)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.549</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.288(−0.702,1.277)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.196</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.604(−1.629,2.836)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.581</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0009"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Coefficients: unstandardized beta (B) coefficients (95% CI) from univariable and multivariable linear regression models are reported. Estimates: represent the change in TMT-A completion time corresponding to a one-unit increase in spindle metrics. Statistical adjustment: multivariable linear regression models were adjusted for age, AHI, arousal index, gender, education, BMI, total sleep time and min-SpO2. The p value &lt; 0.05 is highlighted in bold.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0010"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: TMT-A, Trail Making Test A; CI, confidence interval.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0007" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>The Association Between Sleep Spindle Metrics and TMT-B Test</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1"/><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">OSA Cohort</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Primary Snorers</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Unadjusted Model</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Adjusted Model</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Unadjusted Model</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Adjusted Model</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Β (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Β (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Β (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Β (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N2 sleep spindle metrics</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency (Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.328(−8.767,2.111)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.229</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.452(−6.266,3.362)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.552</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.435(−10.802,3.932)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.350</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.213(−11.097,2.670)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.219</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amplitude (µV)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007(−0.084,0.099)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.874</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007(−0.072,0.086)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.861</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.015(−0.224,0.194)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.888</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047(−0.132,0.227)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.591</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration (sec)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.040(−43.999,-6.080)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.010</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−19.001(−36.541,-1.462)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.034</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−21.709(−57.103,13.685)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.221</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.136(−27.463,47.735)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.582</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall density (11–16 Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.512(−3.198, −1.122)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.813(−3.143,-0.483)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.008</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.116(−1.552,1.785)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.888</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.189(−0.515,2.893)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.163</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fast density (13–16 Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.666(−5.800,-1.533)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.187(−4.226,-0.148)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.036</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.729(−4.928,3.471)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.726</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.449(−2.705,3.604)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.772</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slow density (11–13 Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.866(−5.833,-0.345)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.026</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.449(−4.705,-0.194)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.034</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.322(−1.918,2.563)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.772</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.241(−0.182,4.665)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.068</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N3 sleep spindle metrics</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency (Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.648(−10.784,16.152)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.693</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.605 (−4.520,19.730)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.215</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.485(−10.587,9.618)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.992</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.206(−16.363,9.951)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.617</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amplitude (µV)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.095(−0.057,2.247)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.062</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.162(−0.994,1.318)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.781</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.073(−0.133,0.280)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.472</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.058(−0.312,0.196)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.637</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration (sec)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−37.399(−61.304,-13.495)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.003</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−29.916(−52.001,-7.832)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.009</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−11.980(−22.623,-1.296)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−18.111(−69.627,13.305)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.172</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall density (11–16 Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.509(−1.917,0.898)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.474</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.645(−2.370,1.079)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.458</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.773(−0.752,2.298)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.308</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.248(−1.464,1.960)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.766</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fast density (13–16 Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.411(−3.540,0.718)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.191</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.489(−3.689,0.712)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.182</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.386(−3.321,-0.019)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.403</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.163(−4.263,3.937)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.935</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slow density (11–13 Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.120(−5.821,1.581)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.258</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.619(−5.463,2.224)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.404</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.092(−1.212,3.397)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.339</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.568(−1.878,3.014)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.633</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0011"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Coefficients: unstandardized beta (B) coefficients (95% CI) from univariable and multivariable linear regression models are reported. Estimates: represent the change in TMT-B completion time corresponding to a one-unit increase in spindle metrics. Statistical adjustment: multivariable linear regression models were adjusted for age, AHI, arousal index, gender, education, BMI, total sleep time and min-SpO2. The p value &lt; 0.05 is highlighted in bold.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0012"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: TMT-B, Trail Making Test B; CI, confidence interval.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0008" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 8</label><caption><p>The Association Between Sleep Spindle Metrics and Stroop-Incongruous Test</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1"/><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">OSA Cohort</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Primary Snorers</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Unadjusted model</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Adjusted Model</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Unadjusted Model</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Adjusted Model</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Β (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Β (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Β (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Β (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N2 sleep spindle metrics</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency (Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.078(−7.125,2.970)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.417</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.891(−7.351,1.534)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.199</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.985(−10.393,4.422)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.420</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.533(−18.684,3.579)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.176</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amplitude (µV)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.002(−0.080,0.077)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.965</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.030(−0.102,0.043)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.420</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016(−0.203,0.234)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.885</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.118(−0.404,0.168)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.404</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration (sec)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−17.664(−44.156,-10.531)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.002</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10.554(−26.966,5.895)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.206</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.272(−41.820,25.275)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.620</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.558(−51.348,54.465)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.952</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall density (11–16 Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.183(−3.348,-1.018)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.855(−2.140,0.429)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.190</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.391(−1.392,2.174)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.659</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.749(−1.621,3.119)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.522</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fast density (13–16 Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.165(−4.853,-1.477)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.115(−3.176,0.846)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.263</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.155(−2.975,3.284)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.921</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.016(−4.351,4.320)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.994</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slow density (11–13 Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.382(−4.639,-0.125)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.039</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.086(−3.276,1.103)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.328</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.687(−1.977,3.352)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.604</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.848(−1.820,5.516)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.311</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N3 sleep spindle metrics</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency (Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.782(−20.160,4.595)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.214</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.736(−12.417,8.944)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.505</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.836(−7.787,0.456)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.505</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.907(−17.231,21.044)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.839</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amplitude (µV)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.289(−3.749,6.327)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.611</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.273(−3.543,7.889)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.450</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.255(0.007,0.503)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.045</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.295(−0.061,0.652)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration (sec)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−29.887(−51.176,-8.599)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.007</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−21.303(−41.016,-1.589)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.035</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24.869(−68.561,18.823)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.254</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.145(−69.548,55.259)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.815</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall density (11–16 Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.135(−0.359,0.630)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.587</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.184(−0.229,0.598)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.337</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.254(−0.638,3.146)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.186</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.919(−1.480,3.319)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.463</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fast density (13–16 Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.249(−1.234,1.731)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.739</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.335(−0.909,1.580)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.593</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.820(−3.450,5.090)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.698</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.307(−6.136,5.522)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.914</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slow density (11–13 Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.217(−0.485,0.920)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.540</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.296(−0.290,0.882)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.317</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.481(−0.319,3.281)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.080</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.958(−1.366,5.282)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.226</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0013"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Stroop-incongruous, Stroop-incongruous Test; CI, confidence interval. Coefficients: unstandardized beta (B) coefficients (95% CI) from univariable and multivariable linear regression models are reported. Estimates: represent the change in Stroop-incongruous completion time corresponding to a one-unit increase in spindle metrics. Statistical adjustment: multivariable linear regression models were adjusted for age; AHI, arousal index, gender, education; BMI, total sleep time and min-SpO2. The p value &lt; 0.05 is highlighted in bold.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>This study represents a pioneering investigation into the connections between sleep spindle metrics and executive function in young adult and middle-aged patients with OSA and primary snorers while diligently considering potential confounding factors. Remarkably, young adult and middle-aged patients with OSA exhibited a significant correlation between impaired executive function, as assessed through the TMT and SCWT tests, and deficits of specific sleep spindle metrics. Moreover, advanced age and lower educational attainment demonstrated associations with impaired executive function in young adult and middle-aged patients with OSA. Intriguingly, no apparent association was observed between sleep spindle metrics and executive function in primary snorers.</p>
      <p>It is widely acknowledged that OSA presents a significant risk for cognitive impairment.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> Extensive research has demonstrated that individuals with OSA often exhibit cognitive impairments, including deficits in attention, memory, executive function, psychomotor function, and language abilities.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Our findings reveal that individuals with OSA experience difficulties in executive function when compared to primary snorers. This aligns with previous research, demonstrating that individuals with OSA who experience pronounced hypoxia (as indicated by AHI and min-SpO2) and frequent sleep fragmentation (as measured by the arousal index) are particularly susceptible to executive dysfunction.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></p>
      <p>In our study, patients with severe OSA had significantly decreased total sleep spindle density, fast sleep spindle density, and slow sleep spindle density. This result was partially consistent with a large community-based cohort study on OSA and sleep spindles, in which slow sleep spindle density decreased with increasing OSA severity.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Furthermore, our findings suggested that impaired executive performance in young and middle-aged OSA patients is associated with reduced overall, fast and slow sleep spindle density during N2 sleep time. Moreover, it has been shown that CPAP treatment for six months could reverse cognitive function and quantitative sleep EEG changes in OSA patients.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> These results strongly support previous findings in the field that altered sleep spindle morphology (lower spindle frequency, higher amplitude and density) could predict cognitive performance.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> In addition, our study makes a novel contribution by identifying the duration of the sleep spindle both during N2 and N3 sleep times as a significant marker of executive function.</p>
      <p>In our study, we found a negative association between age and executive performance in both young adult and middle-aged patients with OSA and primary snorers. Imbalances in thalamo-cortical circuits are part of the natural aging process. In particular, executive functions that depend on cognitive functions in the medial temporal and prefrontal cortex show significant age-related declines.<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> Consistent with previous research, we identified a decline in psychomotor functions, processing speed, and higher-order executive functions such as cognitive flexibility, divided attention, response monitoring, and task switching with increasing age.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> Supporting previous findings, our study also revealed a decline in inhibitory control, specifically, the ability to refrain from incorrect responses, with aging in both young adult and middle-aged patients with OSA and primary snorers.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></p>
      <p>We found that education plays an important role in preserving executive functions in young adult and middle-aged patients with OSA. Illiteracy and low level of educational attainment increase the incidence of cognitive impairment,<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> on the contrary, high level of education as one of the indicators of cognitive reserve (CR) delays cognitive decline.<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> Recent studies have shown that CR contributes to the enhancement of thalamo-cortical functional connectivity in young adults and stabilizes cognitive variability in middle-aged adults.<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> In young adult and middle-aged patients with OSA, we discovered that greater CR (as measured by years of education) was associated with improved executive function. This suggests that CR acts protectively against executive dysfunction in young adult and middle-aged patients with OSA. A recent regression study conducted with elderly individuals also highlighted the association between CR and attention, executive function, verbal memory, and working memory, partially supporting our findings in young adult and middle-aged OSA patients.<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></p>
      <p>Our study suggested that the sleep spindle metrics serve as independent and sensitive indicators of executive function in young adult and middle-aged patients with OSA. In our study, we initially observed that young adult and middle-aged OSA patients with higher overall, fast and slow sleep spindle density, as well as longer duration of sleep spindles during N2 sleep time, exhibited reduced psychomotor functions and processing speed. We also found similar results of sleep spindle metrics during N2 sleep time in executive functions, including cognitive flexibility, divided attention, response monitoring, and task switching. Moreover, our study revealed a positive association between longer spindle duration during N3 sleep time and improvements in executive function, as well as working memory and inhibitory control, respectively. The sleep spindle oscillation is generated by the TRN in combination with the dorsal thalamus and is then transmitted to the cortex. In the cortex, the sleep spindles are synchronized and amplified, while thalamic-cortical connections maintain and regulate the duration of the sleep spindle oscillation.<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> Therefore, individual characteristics of spindles, such as amplitude, density, and duration, reflect the integrity of the underlying thalamo-cortical network. Deficits in these parameters indicate dysfunctions in complementary thalamo-cortical neuronal circuits in psychiatric disorders.<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> Although there is no direct evidence of impaired thalamo-cortical functional connectivity in patients with OSA, our findings supported the utility of sleep spindle metrics as useful executive function markers in this population. Consistent with previous studies in healthy sedentary middle-aged and older adults, we confirmed that higher overall and fast sleep spindle density were associated with better executive function and less cognitive decline.<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> Additionally, in our study, we observed that a higher density of slow sleep spindles was significantly associated with better performance in the TMT-A and TMT-B test among patients. In contrast to a community-based cohort study in middle-aged and older adults,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> we did not observed an association between fast sleep spindle density and TMT-B test during N3 sleep time; instead, we observed that longer sleep spindle duration was significantly associated with better TMT-B performance in this period.</p>
      <p>We conducted a comprehensive investigation of the relationship between sleep spindle metrics and executive functioning in young adult and middle-aged patients with OSA, and age and education were not negligible as important associations on cognition. The study utilized a novel U-Net-type neural network to detect sleep spindles from electroencephalogram (EEG) recordings. The main strength of our study was that we first focused on young and middle-aged adults with objectively measured sleep spindles and multiple standardized and validated cognitive tests. Sleep spindle metrics could be used to monitor the effectiveness of OSA interventions. Improvements in specific sleep spindle characteristics might serve as objective EEG indicators of OSA treatment. However, it is worth noting that our study design was cross-sectional, which limited our ability to determine causality. In addition, due to practical constraints, we performed only one night of PSG, although multiple nights of sleep testing would be desirable. Although our study focused on the link between executive function and sleep spindles in patients with OSA, cognitive deficits were observed in multiple domains. We need to further investigate the relationship between sleep spindles and other important cognitive functions.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>In conclusion, our study investigated the associations between sleep spindle metrics and executive function and confirmed that sleep spindle metrics serve as independent sensitive indicators of executive function, although age and education play an irreplaceable role. We found that sleep spindle metrics, particularly higher overall density, fast density and slow density during N2 sleep time, and longer duration during N2 and N3 sleep time, were associated with better executive function. These findings highlight the importance of considering sleep spindle metrics and their impact on executive function in clinical practice and research. Future research should focus on investigating the underlying mechanisms linking sleep spindle metrics and executive function.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>The authors appreciate the contribution of the study participants, otolaryngologists, neurologists and technologists at the Department of Otolaryngology Head and Neck Surgery, Beijing Tongren Hospital.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <p>OSA, obstructive sleep apnea; PFC, prefrontal cortex; MD, dorsomedial nucleus;</p>
      <p>EEG, electroencephalogram; TRN, thalamic reticular nucleus; SDB, sleep-disordered</p>
      <p>breathing; PSG, polysomnography; AHI, apnea-hypopnea index; ECG, electrocardiogram;</p>
      <p>EMG, electromyography; EOG, electrooculogram; AASM, American Academy of Sleep</p>
      <p>Medicine; ESS, Epworth Sleepiness Scale; EDS, excessive daytime sleepiness; TMT,</p>
      <p>Trail Making Test A and B; SCWT, Stroop Color-Word Test; CWT, Continuous Wavelet</p>
      <p>Transform; min-SpO2, minimum oxygen saturation; AI, arousal index; ODI, oxygen</p>
      <p>desaturation index; BMI, body mass index; NC, neck circumference; CR, cognitive reserve.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p>The data underlying this article cannot be shared publicly for the privacy of individuals that participated in the study. The data will be shared on reasonable request to the corresponding authors.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0008">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Senaratna</surname>
<given-names>CV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perret</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lodge</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence of obstructive sleep apnea in the general population: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>70</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2016.07.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27568340</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cunningham</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hunter</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Budgeon</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The prevalence and comorbidities of obstructive sleep apnea in middle-aged men and women: the Busselton healthy ageing study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2029</fpage>–<lpage>2039</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.9378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34606440</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Torres</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sánchez-de-la-torre</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barbé</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Relationship between osa and hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>148</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>824</fpage>–<lpage>832</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.15-0136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25879807</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bradley</surname>
<given-names>TD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Floras</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea and its cardiovascular consequences</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>373</volume>(<issue>9657</issue>):<fpage>82</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(08)61622-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19101028</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bubu</surname>
<given-names>OM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Andrade</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Umasabor-Bubu</surname>
<given-names>OQ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea, cognition and alzheimer’s disease: a systematic review integrating three decades of multidisciplinary research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>101250</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2019.101250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31881487</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Beaudin</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raneri</surname>
<given-names>JK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ayas</surname>
<given-names>NT</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cognitive function in a sleep clinic cohort of patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Am Thorac Soc</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>865</fpage>–<lpage>875</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1513/AnnalsATS.202004-313OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33147067</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nemeth</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Csábi</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Janacsek</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Várszegi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mari</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Intact implicit probabilistic sequence learning in obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>396</fpage>–<lpage>401</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.2011.00983.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22340304</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stranks</surname>
<given-names>EK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crowe</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The cognitive effects of obstructive sleep apnea: an updated meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Clin Neuropsychol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>186</fpage>–<lpage>193</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26743325</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bucks</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olaithe</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eastwood</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Neurocognitive function in obstructive sleep apnoea: a meta-review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Respirology</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1843.2012.02255.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22913604</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Parnaudeau</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bolkan</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kellendonk</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The mediodorsal thalamus: an essential partner of the prefrontal cortex for cognition</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biol Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>83</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>648</fpage>–<lpage>656</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2017.11.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29275841</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Halassa</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sherman</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Thalamocortical circuit motifs: a general framework</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuron</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>103</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>762</fpage>–<lpage>770</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2019.06.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31487527</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Giraldo-Chica</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rogers</surname>
<given-names>BP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Damon</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Landman</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Woodward</surname>
<given-names>ND</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prefrontal-thalamic anatomical connectivity and executive cognitive function in schizophrenia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biol Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>83</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>509</fpage>–<lpage>517</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2017.09.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29113642</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fernandez</surname>
<given-names>LMJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lüthi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep spindles: mechanisms and functions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiol Rev</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>100</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>805</fpage>–<lpage>868</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physrev.00042.2018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31804897</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baran</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Karahanoğlu</surname>
<given-names>FI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mylonas</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Increased thalamocortical connectivity in schizophrenia correlates with sleep spindle deficits: evidence for a common pathophysiology</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biol Psychiatry Cogn Neurosci Neuroimaging</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>706</fpage>–<lpage>714</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpsc.2019.04.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31262708</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Carvalho</surname>
<given-names>DZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gerhardt</surname>
<given-names>GJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dellagustin</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Loss of sleep spindle frequency deceleration in obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Neurophysiol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>125</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>306</fpage>–<lpage>312</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinph.2013.07.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23899859</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Teh</surname>
<given-names>JZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grummitt</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haroutonian</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Overnight declarative memory consolidation and NREM sleep EEG oscillations in older adults with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>zsad087</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsad087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37052122</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shetty</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perera</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kadar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The effects of sleep-disordered breathing on sleep spindle activity in children and the relationship with sleep, behavior, and neurocognition</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>468</fpage>–<lpage>477</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2022.11.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36521367</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Djonlagic</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mariani</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Macro and micro sleep architecture and cognitive performance in older adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Hum Behav</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>123</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41562-020-00964-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33199858</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lafortune</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gagnon</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep spindles and rapid eye movement sleep as predictors of next morning cognitive performance in healthy middle-aged and older participants</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24245769</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vermeulen</surname>
<given-names>MCM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van der Heijden</surname>
<given-names>KB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Swaab</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Someren</surname>
<given-names>EJW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep spindle characteristics and sleep architecture are associated with learning of executive functions in school-age children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e12779</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30338601</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Joo</surname>
<given-names>EY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jeon</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>ST</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hong</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Localized cortical thinning in patients with obstructive sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1153</fpage>–<lpage>1162</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.2876</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23904675</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Roy</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sahib</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kang</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aysola</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Brain tissue integrity mapping in adults with obstructive sleep apnea using T1-weighted and T2-weighted images</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ther Adv Neurol Disord</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>17562864221137505</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/17562864221137505</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36419869</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Parker</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Melaku</surname>
<given-names>YA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>D’Rozario</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The association between obstructive sleep apnea and sleep spindles in middle-aged and older men: a community-based cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>zsab282</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsab282</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34850237</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Parker</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Appleton</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adams</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The association between sleep spindles and cognitive function in middle-aged and older men from a community-based cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Health</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>774</fpage>–<lpage>785</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleh.2023.03.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37268483</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yeager</surname>
<given-names>BE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bruss</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duffau</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Central precuneus lesions are associated with impaired executive function</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Struct Funct</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>227</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>3099</fpage>–<lpage>3108</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00429-022-02556-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36087124</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Furst</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Massaro</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>BT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>LaMacchia</surname>
<given-names>ZM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Horvath</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>β-alanine supplementation increased physical performance and improved executive function following endurance exercise in middle aged individuals</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Int Soc Sports Nutr</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>32</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12970-018-0238-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29996843</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hwang</surname>
<given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Stroop task-related brain activity in patients with insomnia: changes after cognitive-behavioral therapy for insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>621</fpage>–<lpage>633</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15402002.2018.1435546</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29451994</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>D’Rozario</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dungan</surname>
<given-names>GC</given-names> 2nd</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Banks</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>An automated algorithm to identify and reject artefacts for quantitative EEG analysis during sleep in patients with sleep-disordered breathing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>607</fpage>–<lpage>615</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-014-1056-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25225154</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Ronneberger</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fischer</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brox</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <part-title>U-net: convolutional networks for biomedical image segmentation</part-title>. In: <string-name><surname>Navab</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hornegger</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wells</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frangi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, editors. <source><italic toggle="yes">Medical Image Computing and Computer-Assisted Intervention – MICCAI 2015. Lecture Notes in Computer Science</italic></source>. <volume>9351</volume>. <publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>; <year>2015</year>. <fpage>234</fpage>–<lpage>241</lpage>—.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kaulen</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schwabedal</surname>
<given-names>JTC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schneider</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ritter</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bialonski</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Advanced sleep spindle identification with neural networks</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>7686</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-11210-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35538137</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yaffe</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laffan</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harrison</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep-disordered breathing, hypoxia, and risk of mild cognitive impairment and dementia in older women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>306</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>613</fpage>–<lpage>619</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2011.1115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21828324</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shieu</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dunietz</surname>
<given-names>GL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paulson</surname>
<given-names>HL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chervin</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Braley</surname>
<given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The association between obstructive sleep apnea risk and cognitive disorders: a population-based study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1177</fpage>–<lpage>1185</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.9832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34913866</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Olaithe</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bucks</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hillman</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eastwood</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cognitive deficits in obstructive sleep apnea: insights from a meta-review and comparison with deficits observed in COPD, insomnia, and sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2017.03.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28760549</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Crawford-Achour</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dauphinot</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Protective effect of long-term CPAP therapy on cognitive performance in elderly patients with severe osa: the proof study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>519</fpage>–<lpage>524</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.4694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25700873</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>D’Rozario</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoyos</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>KKH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Improvements in cognitive function and quantitative sleep electroencephalogram in obstructive sleep apnea after six months of continuous positive airway pressure treatment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>zsac013</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsac013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35029691</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Taillard</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sagaspe</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berthomier</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Non-REM sleep characteristics predict early cognitive impairment in an aging population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>197</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fneur.2019.00197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30918496</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dunietz</surname>
<given-names>GL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chervin</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burke</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Conceicao</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Braley</surname>
<given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea treatment and dementia risk in older adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>zsab076</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsab076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33769542</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Owens</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sands</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The effect of donepezil on arousal threshold and apnea-hypopnea index. a randomized, double-blind, cross-over study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Am Thorac Soc</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2012</fpage>–<lpage>2018</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1513/AnnalsATS.201605-384OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27442715</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Borghesani</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Madhyastha</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aylward</surname>
<given-names>EH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The association between higher order abilities, processing speed, and age are variably mediated by white matter integrity during typical aging</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropsychologia</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1435</fpage>–<lpage>1444</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2013.03.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23507612</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hadar</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trope</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ben-David</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Aging impairs inhibitory control over incidental cues: a construal-level perspective</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1442</fpage>–<lpage>1451</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0956797621998316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34383576</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jia</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The prevalence of dementia in urban and rural areas of China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Alzheimers Dement</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jalz.2013.01.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23871765</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jia</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cao</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Subjective cognitive decline, cognitive reserve indicators, and the incidence of dementia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Med Dir Assoc</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1449</fpage>–<lpage>1455</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jamda.2020.08.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32967819</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Olaithe</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pushpanathan</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hillman</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cognitive profiles in obstructive sleep apnea: a cluster analysis in sleep clinic and community samples</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1493</fpage>–<lpage>1505</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.8564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32400387</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stern</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Habeck</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moeller</surname>
<given-names>J, S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Brain networks associated with cognitive reserve in healthy young and old adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cereb Cortex</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>394</fpage>–<lpage>402</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/bhh142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15749983</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ferreira</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Machado</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Molina</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cognitive variability during middle-age: possible association with neurodegeneration and cognitive reserve</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Aging Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>188</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnagi.2017.00188</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28649200</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lavrencic</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Richardson</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harrison</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Is there a link between cognitive reserve and cognitive function in the oldest-old?</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Gerontol a Biol Sci Med Sci</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>73</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>499</fpage>–<lpage>505</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gerona/glx140</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28977420</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bonjean</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baker</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lemieux</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Timofeev</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sejnowski</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bazhenov</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Corticothalamic feedback controls sleep spindle duration in vivo</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>25</issue>):<fpage>9124</fpage>–<lpage>9134</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0077-11.2011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21697364</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pratt</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morris</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The thalamic reticular nucleus: a functional hub for thalamocortical network dysfunction in schizophrenia and a target for drug discovery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychopharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>137</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0269881114565805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25586397</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ferrarelli</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tononi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Reduced sleep spindle activity point to a TRN-MD thalamus-PFC circuit dysfunction in schizophrenia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Schizophr Res</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>180</volume>:<fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.schres.2016.05.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27269670</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Guadagni</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Byles</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Av</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of sleep spindle characteristics with executive functioning in healthy sedentary middle-aged and older adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e13037</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.13037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32281182</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
