<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38482468</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">10933526</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">435201</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S435201</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Dreaming Characteristics in Non-Rapid Eye Movement Parasomnia and Idiopathic Rapid Eye Movement Sleep Behaviour Disorder: Similarities and Differences</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">See et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">See et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>See</surname><given-names>Qi Rui</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Raheel</surname><given-names>Kausar</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>Iain</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0009-0003-8432-1310</contrib-id><name><surname>Biabani</surname><given-names>Nazanin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Di Giulio</surname><given-names>Irene</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4505-2600</contrib-id><name><surname>Romigi</surname><given-names>Andrea</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>Veena</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3809-022X</contrib-id><name><surname>O’Regan</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cairney</surname><given-names>Scott</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0006" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Urso</surname><given-names>Daniele</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0007" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0008" ref-type="aff">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2815-0505</contrib-id><name><surname>Chaudhuri</surname><given-names>K Ray</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0008" ref-type="aff">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gnoni</surname><given-names>Valentina</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0007" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Drakatos</surname><given-names>Panagis</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Rosenzweig</surname><given-names>Ivana</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Sleep and Brain Plasticity Centre, Department of Neuroimaging, Institute of Psychiatry, Psychology and Neuroscience (IoPPN), King’s College London</institution>, <addr-line>London</addr-line>, <country>U.K</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>School of Basic and Medical Biosciences, Faculty of Life Science and Medicine, King’s College London</institution>, <addr-line>London</addr-line>, <country>U.K</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>IRCCS Neuromed Istituto Neurologico Mediterraneo Pozzilli (IS)</institution>, <addr-line>Pozzilli</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Centre for Cognitive Neuroscience, College of Health, Medicine and Life Sciences, Brunel University London</institution>, <addr-line>Uxbridge</addr-line>, <country>U.K</country></aff><aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label><institution>Sleep Disorders Centre, Guy’s and St Thomas’ NHS Foundation Trust</institution>, <addr-line>London</addr-line>, <country>U.K</country></aff><aff id="aff0006"><label>6</label><institution>Department of Psychology, University of York and York Biomedical Research Institute, University of York</institution>, <addr-line>York</addr-line>, <country>U.K</country></aff><aff id="aff0007"><label>7</label><institution>Center for Neurodegenerative Diseases and the Aging Brain, Department of Clinical Research in Neurology, University of Bari ‘Aldo Moro’, “Pia Fondazione Cardinale G. Panico”</institution>, <addr-line>Tricase</addr-line>, <addr-line>Lecce</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><aff id="aff0008"><label>8</label><institution>Movement Disorders Unit, King’s College Hospital and Department of Clinical and Basic Neurosciences, Institute of Psychiatry, Psychology &amp; Neuroscience and Parkinson Foundation Centre of Excellence, King’s College London</institution>, <addr-line>London</addr-line>, <country>U.K</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Ivana Rosenzweig, <institution>Sleep and Brain Plasticity Centre, Department of Neuroimaging, Box 089, Institute of Psychiatry, Psychology and Neuroscience, King’s College London, De Crespigny Park</institution>, <addr-line>London</addr-line>, <addr-line>SE5 8AF</addr-line>, <country>UK</country>, Email ivana.1.rosenzweig@kcl.ac.uk</corresp><fn id="ft0001"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>08</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>277</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>9</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 See et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>See et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published by Dove Medical Press Limited, and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution License. The full terms of the License are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The license permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Speech graph analysis (SGA) of dreams has recently shown promise as an objective and language-invariant diagnostic tool that can aid neuropsychiatric diagnosis. Whilst the notion that dreaming mentations reflect distinct physiologic processes is not new, such studies in patients with sleep disorders remain exceptionally scarce. Here, using SGA and other dream content analyses, we set to investigate structural and thematic differences in morning dream recalls of patients diagnosed with Non-Rapid Eye Movement Parasomnia (NREMP) and Idiopathic REM Sleep Behavior Disorder (iRBD).</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>A retrospective cross-sectional study of morning dream recalls of iRBD and NREMP patients was undertaken. Traditional dream content analyses, such as Orlinsky and Hall and Van de Castle analyses, were initially conducted. Subsequently, SGA was performed in order to objectively quantify structural speech differences between the dream recalls of the two patient groups.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Comparable rate of morning recall of dreams in the sleep laboratory was recorded; 25% of iRBD and 18.35% of NREMP patients. Aggression in dreams was recorded by 28.57% iRBD versus 20.00% in NREMP group. iRBD patients were more likely to recall dreams (iRBD vs NREMP; P = 0.007), but they also had more white dreams, ie having a feeling of having dreamt, but with no memory of it. Visual and quantitative graph speech analyses of iRBD dreams suggested stable sequential structure, reflecting the linearity of the chronological narrative. Conversely, NREMP dream reports displayed more recursive, less stable systems, with significantly higher scores of graph connectivity measures.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The findings of our exploratory study suggest that iRBD and NREMP patients may not only differ on what is recalled in their dreams but also, perhaps more strikingly, on how dreams are recalled. It is hoped that future SGA-led dream investigations of larger groups of patients will help discern distinct mechanistic underpinnings and any associated clinical implications.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>dreams</kwd><kwd>speech graph analysis</kwd><kwd>NREM parasomnia</kwd><kwd>REM behavior sleep disorder</kwd><kwd>dream content analysis</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="4"/><ref-count count="57"/><page-count count="15"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Dreams have been argued to present a state of consciousness that arises during sleep from an internally generated cognitive, sensory and emotional experiences.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Commonalities between dreams and other stimulus-independent perceptions, such as hallucinations and mental imagery, comprise the internal mono- or poly sensory representation of an image within one’s mind.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2–4</xref> Unsurprisingly, some authors have argued that these perceptual phenomena may lie on a continuum, and that they may also utilize similar brain areas and pathways.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Historically, dream reports linked with awakening from rapid eye movement (REM) sleep have been described as containing most complex, vibrant and intense experiences, whilst existence of dreams arising from non-REM (NREM) sleep has been negated or considered controversial.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> This has recently been disputed, and it has been shown that dreams arising from NREM sleep, albeit less frequently, may feature complex narratives and structured dreams.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></p>
      <p>Moreover, recent evidence suggests that limited dreaming arising from NREM sleep may occur because of interfering phasic bursts or REM-like sleep microstructure.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7–11</xref> These phasic events have been linked to series of metabolically demanding physiologic events including contractions of the middle ear muscles, rapid eye movements, myoclonic twitches of skeletal muscles, sawtooth waves, irregularities in cardiorespiratory activity, and ponto-geniculo-occipital waves.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Thus, phasic REM sleep likely plays a distinct role in dreaming. However, its function remains unclear with some linking it to the reactivation of vivid visuospatial mental pictures of specific emotional valence or to the reprocessing of emotional memories during sleep.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Moreover, a body of work suggests that during sleep, an active systems’ consolidation process, embedded in global synaptic downscaling, may present the mechanistic platform for the formation of long-term memory.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> For instance, it has been proposed that during NREM slow-wave sleep, recurrent hippocampal neuronal-replays lead to the gradual transformation and integration of representations in neocortical networks.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></p>
      <p>In this context, parasomnias have historically attracted the interest of sleep experts due to distinct sleep behaviors associated with dream mentation, and specific perceptual and sensory experiences.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> More specifically, sleep parasomnias, such as NREM parasomnia (NREMP)<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> and (idiopathic) REM sleep Behavior Disorder (iRBD),<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> exemplify a rare opportunity to gain a direct insight into dream activity and mentation.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></p>
      <p>Parasomnias are associated with distinct sleep states/stages, but they can also occur during sleep wake transitions.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> RBD, characterized by loss of typical REM-like atonia and abnormal behaviors during REM sleep, may indicate an early stage of neurodegeneration linked with alpha-synucleinopathies.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Most of abnormal motor events likely arise during phasic REM, which in RBD can vacillate from elementary movements to vivid dream enactments.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Historically, RBD was predominantly linked with male sex,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24–27</xref> but that has been increasingly disputed with recognition that women tend to have a significantly later age of onset of RBD<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> and that they less frequently report dream-enacting behaviours.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29–31</xref> Fernández-Arcos et al reported significantly more aggressive behavior in male RBD, and less so in women, who dreamt more about children in life-threatening contexts.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> Thus, prevalence of female RBD might be grossly underestimated in the community. Here, the lack of specific questionnaires that would in equal measure also account for differential female RBD behaviours may also play a part.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> Conversely, NREM parasomnias, marked by significant physical action and autonomic activation, appear to be common at all ages, with slightly higher incidence in children and younger adults.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Patients can injure themselves during acted out NREM events, and they can endanger themselves and others.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11–13</xref> Excessive daytime sleepiness is frequently reported by NREM parasomnia sufferers, as well as lower threshold for pain and poorer quality of life.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></p>
      <p>Understanding how basic physiological components of sleep may contribute to the genesis of dreams will be pivotal for future translational clinical purposes.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> However, it is widely accepted that oneiric research is significantly limited by an inaccessible nature of dreams, where any insight on intrinsic dream activity depends on retrospective recall by dreamers.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> These, as of yet non-circumvented, methodological problems effectively mean that oneiric research commonly incorporates data that has unknown quantity of distortions in recall, along with omissions caused by reprocessing of memory for the event.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> Thus, perhaps unsurprisingly, dream research remains in its infancy, and to date only one another study has formally investigated putative differences between dream contents that arise from NREM parasomnia or RBD events.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> This study found that dreams of RBD patients were more complex and had a higher incidence of aggression. In particular, authors reported that NREMP events may predominantly translate into a “flight” defensive response to any perceived threat, whereas RBD patients were shown to engage in violence and counterattack more commonly when assaulted. In this background, we set to investigate the dream contents of patients with idiopathic RBD (iRBD) and NREMP, all of whom had a verified parasomnic event via video polysomnography (PSG). To define any putative distinct cognitive biomarkers, patients’ recalls of dreams upon awakening that they believed to be associated with the parasomnic event were collected, analyzed and compared according to their thematic contents, complexity, and content differences. Moreover, in order to objectively explore iRBD and NREMP dream report structure, a speech graph analysis (SGA) was subsequently undertaken.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <p>An exploratory study was conducted between May 2018 and January 2020, during which period all clinically diagnosed iRBD and NREM parasomnia patients who underwent video-polysomnography (VPSG) at the Sleep Disorders Center (Guy’s Hospital, London, United Kingdom) were identified.</p>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Research Design</title>
        <p>Patients diagnosed with iRBD (n = 37) and NREM parasomnia (n = 138) according to the American Academy of Sleep Medicine (AASM) criteria, as previously published<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> (also please refer to <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>), were initially identified. Of those initially identified, only seven iRBD and 20 NREMP patients had fulfilled required inclusion criteria for speech graph analysis (Orlinsky score of 2 or above), and thus subsequently their dream reports and sleep macrostructures were analyzed; none were receiving any psychotropic medication at the time of the VPSG investigation. The study was approved by the Guy’s and St Thomas’ Hospital Clinic Research Ethics Committee (Project-No-9585 and Project-No-11,378, GSTT NHS, UK), which did not require informed patients’ consent for retrospectively ascertained anonymized data where the study protocol was judged to abide by the strictest patients’ data confidentiality and when it complied with the EU General Data Protection Regulation and with the Declaration of Helsinki.
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Flowchart of the studied cohort of patients with iRBD and NREM parasomnia.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-263-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: n, total number of patients; NREMP, non-REM (NREM) parasomnia; iRBD, idiopathic rapid eye movement (REM) sleep behaviour disorder.</attrib></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Clinical Review and Morning Dream Questionnaire</title>
        <p>Systematic review of patients’ medical records, VPSG recordings, and post-VPSG morning questionnaires was undertaken, as previously described.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> As a part of an established clinical routine at the Sleep Disorders Centre, patients were asked to fill the post-VPSG morning questionnaires upon awaking, in order to record any oneiric mentation linked with their diagnostic VPSG-recorded motor events. The morning questionnaires were semi-structured, self-administered, and contained open-ended questions with elements of both the Orlinsky scale<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> and the Hall and Van de Castle dream coding system.<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> For instance, participants were asked whether they were able to remember dreams related to their parasomnic event, the emotions and people associated with them, and how they felt after dreaming.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Methods of Analysis</title>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3001">
          <title>Orlinsky Score Analysis</title>
          <p>Based on the participants’ responses to the morning dream questionnaire, their mental content was scored using the Orlinsky scale<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> (further details are provided in <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=435201.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link></underline>). The dreams were rated from 0 to 7 (0 = no dream recall; 1 = feeling of having dreamt but no memory of it; 2 = specific topic in isolation; 3 = disconnected thoughts, scenes, or actions; 4 = short but coherent dream; 5 = detailed dream sequence with two stages; 6 = long, detailed dream sequence with three or four stages; and 7 = detailed dream sequence of five or more).<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> For instance, for this analysis, if a patient reported not having remembered dreaming, it was scored as 0.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> Positive responses to questions related to dreaming were scored as 1. Conversely, if a patient reported dreaming and was able to describe the dream, it was scored as 2 or above depending on its content.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> A detailed explanation of the Orlinsky scoring system is provided in the <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=435201.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link></underline>. The terms coherent/incoherent here suggest faulty articulation of a consistent dream narrative, either in relation to the dream mentation, chronology of events, or both.</p>
          <p>According to the patients’ Orlinsky scores, they were further divided into two subgroups: (a) those with Orlinsky scores of 0 or 1 and (b) those with Orlinsky scores of 2 or above. Only those in subgroup (b) had dream reports, which were further evaluated using Hall and Van de Castle<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> dream analysis and speech graph analysis.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3002">
          <title>Hall and Van de Castle Dream Content Analysis</title>
          <p>Dream reports of patients who scored 2 or above 2 on the Orlinsky scale (ie, seven iRBD and 20 NREMP patients) were subsequently analyzed using the Hall and Van de Castle method.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> The Hall and Van de Castle method is considered as one of the most comprehensive systems for studying dream content.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> It comprises ten general categories, most of which are further divided into two or more subcategories. In this study, based on an initial pilot analysis of the patients’ dream content, nominal categories, and more specifically, categories for characters, emotions, and social interactions, including aggression, were used to qualify the dream contents. No dream records consisted of content that would be classified under the categories of friendliness, sexuality, fortune and misfortunes; thus, these categories were excluded from further analysis.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3003">
          <title>Speech Graph Attributes (SGA) Analysis</title>
          <p>In order to investigate the structural organization of the iRBD and NREMP dream reports, we used speech graph attributes (SGA) Analysis.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> Specifically, 14 graph-theoretical attributes were derived and evaluated in the context of the total report length (word count).</p>
          <p>SGA analysis has already shown significant promise as a non-invasive, affordable, and language-invariant tool for psychiatric diagnosis.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> SGA analysis enables identification of most promising behavioral biomarkers that can subsequently guide a bottom-up search for more objective neuroanatomical and neurophysiological biomarkers (also refer to).<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></p>
          <p>Speechgraphs, free Java software (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="http://neuro.ufrn.br/softwares/speechgraphs" ext-link-type="uri">http://neuro.ufrn.br/softwares/speechgraphs</ext-link></underline>), were used to transcribe the dream reports into non-semantic word graphs for our speech graph attribute analysis. To investigate the structural organization of iRBD and NREMP dream reports, each dream report was represented as a word graph, where nodes represent the words used and edges correspond to semantic and grammatical relationships.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> A number of graph measures were derived, as previously published. We concentrated on measures of recurrence and global, general and connectivity graph attributes (see <xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref> and <xref rid="f0003a" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) as complementary tools to specifically investigate the non-semantic structural organization of RBD and NREMP dream reports.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> Here, for example, in cases of two hypothetical separate reports, one with high recursiveness and higher interconnectivity, compared to the other, more linear report, with minimal recursiveness in a speech structure, one would expect higher scores for the difference between two connectivity parameters, namely the largest strongly connected component (LSC) and the largest connected component (LCC). In a purely linear graph, these attributes are the same, but marked differences between them arise from interconnectivity and recursiveness.</p>
          <p>In previous work, a number of graph theoretical measures, such as graph connectedness and graph random likeness, were found to be useful predictors of organizational changes in psychiatric disorders such as schizophrenia.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>
<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Representative speech graph transcribed from the dream reports of one iRBD and one NREMP patient. Adapted from Mota NB, Vasconcelos NA, Lemos N, et al. Speech graphs provide a quantitative measure of thought disorder in psychosis. <italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic>. 2012;7(4):e34928. Creative Commons.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-263-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: NREMP, non-rapid eye movement parasomnia; iRBD, idiopathic rapid eye movement sleep disorder.</attrib></fig>
<fig position="float" id="f0003a" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Continued.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-263-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig>
<fig position="float" id="f0003b" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Speech graph attributes (SGA) and their definitions adapted from Mota NB, Vasconcelos NA, Lemos N, et al. Speech graphs provide a quantitative measure of thought disorder in psychosis. <italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic>. 2012;7(4):e34928. Creative Commons.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-263-g0004" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>IBM SPSS Statistics (version 28.0.0.0) was used to analyze the data. All categorical data were reported as frequencies and percentages. Owing to the small sample size, Fisher’s exact test was used to compute the <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value for the differences between the two groups of patients. The test was two-tailed, and a <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value of 0.05, was considered significant. For polysomnographic variables and demographic group comparisons, we used one-way ANOVAs for parametric variables, Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-tests for non-parametric variables, and Pearson’s χ<sup>2</sup> tests for categorical variables.</p>
        <p>For graph speech analysis, 14 speech graph attributes were normalised by the number of nodes, tested for Gaussian distribution (Kolmogorov–Smirnov test of normality). Speech graphs were subsequently visually inspected, following which comparisons of graph speech attributes between the two groups were performed using either parametric (one-way ANOVA) or non-parametric statistics (Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>The rate of morning recall of dreams in the sleep laboratory was similar in the iRBD and NREMP groups (7/28 in iRBD <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> 20/109 in NREMP, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.432).</p>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p>Sociodemographic and polysomnographic descriptive statistics of all iRBD and NREMP patients who scored above two on the Orlinsky scale are shown in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Socio-Demographic and Sleep Parameters for iRBD and NREM Parasomnia Patients with Dream Recollection</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Total Number of Patients</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">iRBD</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">NREMP</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Statistics</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">7</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">20</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.714</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.406</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.6**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.04**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.561</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>n</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>%</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>n</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>%</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>χ<sup>2</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender (female)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.306</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.580</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Median</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>IQR</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Median</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>IQR</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>U</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep Macrostructure</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TST (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">360</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">378</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.407</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WASO (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.868</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.782</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM L (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">113</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">145</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">116.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.890</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NREM1 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.056</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NREM2 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.580</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NREM3 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.912</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.488</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLMI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.077</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>n</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>%</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>n</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>%</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>χ<sup>2</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Other Sleep Disorders</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RLS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.963</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypnopompic Hallucination</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.652</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.419</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bruxism</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.181</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.545</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep paralysis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.181</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.545</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.756</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insomnia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.756</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLMD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.363</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypnagogic Hallucination</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.363</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: *Denotes statistically significant differences (P &lt; 0.05). **Denotes that one of the iRBD patients was excluded in this calculation because their BMI was not accessible during the study. Group comparisons were performed using one-way ANOVAs for parametric variables, Mann–Whitney U-tests for non-parametric variables, and Pearson’s χ<sup>2</sup> tests for categorical variables.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: AHI, apnea–hypopnea index; AI, arousal index; BMI, body mass index kg/m<sup>2</sup>; F, one-way ANOVA; IQR, interquartile range; n, number; NREM, non-rapid eye movement; OSA, Obstructive Sleep Apnea; p, p-value; PLMD, Periodic Leg Movement Disorder; REM, rapid eye movement; REM, rapid eye movement latency; RLS, Restless Leg Syndrome; SL, sleep latency; SD, standard deviation; TST, total sleep time; U, Mann–Whitney U statistics; WASO, wake after sleep onset.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <p>Dream reports of seven iRBD patients (42.9% male) and 20 NREMP patients (45% male) were further evaluated. The participants were age-matched and their ages ranged between 20 and 59 years, with a mean age of 32.0 (SD) = 7.37) and 35.3 (SD = 9.32) years for the iRBD and NREMP groups, respectively (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.406). The BMI of iRBD patients was significantly higher than that of NREMP patients (29.6 ± 4.04 versus 25.2 ± 4.00 kg/m<sup>2</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.027). However, sleep- and non-sleep-related comorbidities did not differ between sleep and non-sleep related comorbidities (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Orlinsky Score</title>
        <p>Twenty-one iRBD and 89 NREM patients did not report any dreams and thus scored below 2 on the Orlinsky score (see <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> for further details). Patients with iRBD were more likely to report having a feeling of having a dreamt, but with no memory of it (white dream), in comparison to patients with NREMP (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.007).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Orlinsky Scores of iRBD and NREMP Patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">iRBD</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">NREMP</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">f</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">%</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">f</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">%</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total no. of patients</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0. No dream recall</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.007*</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1. Feeling of having dreamt but no memory of it</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.007*</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2. Specific topic in isolation or fragments</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.652</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3. Several disconnected thoughts, scenes or actions</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4. Short but coherent dream</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.269</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5. Detailed dream sequence, 2 events or stages occur</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6. Long detailed dream sequences, 3 or 4 distinct stages</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7. Extremely long sequence of 5 or more stages</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: *(in bold) denotes statistically significant differences (p &lt; 0.05). iRBD, idiopathic rapid eye movement sleep disorder; group comparisons were conducted using Fisher’s exact test.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: %, percentage; <italic toggle="yes">f</italic>, frequency; NREMP, non-rapid eye movement parasomnia; p, p-value.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Sleep Macrostructure</title>
        <p>Several differences were observed in the gross sleep macrostructure between the two patient groups. For instance, while duration of sleep was similar in the two patient groups (TST: 360 ± 35.5 versus 378 ± 68.5 minutes respectively, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.407), the percentage of time spent in stage N3 was recorded significantly longer for iRBD patients (n = 7; 25.1 ± 19.7 versus n = 20 NREMP patients, 19.7 ± 7.55%, respectively, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.017). Conversely, the arousal index was significantly higher in NREMP patients (17.7 ± 7.7 versus 13.4 ± 4.9, respectively, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.046).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Hall &amp; Van de Castle Dream Content Analysis</title>
        <sec id="s0003-s2004-s3001">
          <title>Characters</title>
          <p>The proportions of animals and humans reported by both groups were similar. NREMP patients (66.67%) frequently reported dreaming of indefinite characters (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>), eg, those whose sex or gender was unidentifiable from the dream content. Common terms used in dream reports include “someone”, “a person”, and “a tall figure”.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Characters Frequency and Percentage According to the Hall &amp; Van de Castle Dream Content Analysis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">iRBD</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">NREMP</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">f</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">%</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">f</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">%</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Characters</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Animals</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Creatures</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group human</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.262</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single human</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.262</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indefinite</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.063</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.523</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.523</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Familiar</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.184</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unfamiliar</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.184</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.184</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Explanation of terms used in this Table: characters, animals, creatures, and humans refer to the total number of characters, animals, creatures, and humans dreamt, respectively; Group human refers to the total number of characters that consist of two or more individuals who are not individually identified; Single human refers to the total number of characters that are described as individuals; Indefinite refers to the total number of characters whose genders are unidentifiable; Male and Female are the total number of male and female characters, respectively, and percentages are relative to the total number of definite human characters; Familiar refers to the total number of characters that are in one of the following four identity subclasses: family, relatives, Known, and Prominent; Unfamiliar refers to the total number of characters that are in the following identity subclasses: Occupational, Ethnic, Uncertain, and Stranger; Family is the total number of characters coded as family members or relatives. The male/female percentage was calculated by dividing the number of male characters by the total number of male and female characters; Familiarity percentage was calculated by dividing the number of familiar characters by the total number of familiar and unfamiliar characters; family percentage was taken to be the total number of family members or relatives out of total humans; Group percentage was the total number of grouped characters out of total humans; Animal percentage was taken to be the total number of animal characters out of total characters.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0006"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: %, percentage; <italic toggle="yes">f</italic>, frequency; NREMP, non-rapid eye movement parasomnia; iRBD, rapid eye movement sleep disorder.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
          <p>iRBD patients (60.00%) more often reported dreaming of male characters than NREMP patients (20.00%), but this did not reach statistical significance. They also reported dreaming of familiar characters or their family members more often than did patients with NREMP. Animals were similarly frequently reported in both groups.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2004-s3002">
          <title>Social Interaction, Aggression and Emotions</title>
          <p>The percentage of dreams in which aggression occurred was similar for both groups (28.57% in iRBD versus 20.00% in NREMP group).</p>
          <p>Regarding reported emotions, only negative emotions were recorded. Specifically, apprehension was reported by both groups and was the only emotion that was discernible in the iRBD group. In NREMP patients, the prevalent emotion was apprehension (66.67%), whilst confusion and sadness were also reported.</p>
          <p>Further breakdown of patients’ responses and major indicators are found in <xref rid="t0002 t0003 t0004" ref-type="table">Tables 2–4</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Hall &amp; Van de Castle Analysis of Social Interaction, in Particular, Aggression</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">RBD</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">NREMP</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">f</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dreams in which aggression occurs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total instances of aggression</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dreamer-involved aggression</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fight response</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flight response</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Major indicators</bold></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/C Index</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.44</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.26</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aggressor (%)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.00</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical Aggression Percent (%)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">25.00</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">60.00</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0007"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <italic toggle="yes">Explanation of terms used</italic>: Dreamer-involved aggression refers to the number of instances in which the dreamer was involved in aggression; fight response refers to the number of instances in which the dreamer retaliated or engaged in mutual aggression; flight response refers to the number of instances in which the dreamer receives aggression without retaliation and/or escapes from the situation; and A/C index is the Aggression-per-Character index, calculated by dividing the total instances of aggression by the total number of characters. The aggregate percentage was calculated by dividing the number of instances in which the dreamer initiated an aggressive act by the total number of instances of aggression. The percentage of physical aggression was the number of instances in which aggression was physical, out of the total instances of aggression.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0008"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: %, percentage; <italic toggle="yes">f</italic>, frequency; NREMP, non-rapid eye movement parasomnia; iRBD, rapid eye movement sleep disorder.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2005">
        <title>Speech Graph Analysis (SGA)</title>
        <p>The dream reports with scores above 2 on the Orlinsky scale (seven iRBD and 20 NREMP) were further analysed using speech graph analysis, as previously described.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> Visual inspection of speech graphs suggested distinct structural differences between the two groups (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). For instance, iRBD dream reports, with a mean word count (SD) of 23.43 (17.71) words, were typically sequential with little recursiveness, suggesting the linearity of the chronological narrative. Conversely, dream reports of patients with NREMP parasomnia, with a mean word count of 28.15 (16.35) words, displayed patterns of convolution, higher interconnectivity, system instability and recursiveness, predictive of higher scores for the largest strongly connected component (LSC), a graph connectivity and recursiveness measure in SGA.</p>
        <p>Accordingly, the findings of nonparametric Mann–Whitney U analyses of normalised (per number of nodes) LSC demonstrated significant difference between the iRBD and NREMP dream reports [Mann Whitney U = 109, P = 0.033; effect size r = 0.779, z = 2.16, η2 = 0.172]. Normalised LSC was significantly higher in NREMP group (M = 0.57, SE = 0.063), compared to iRBD group (M = 0.295, SE = 0.069). Post hoc analysis of other attributes did not reveal any other statistically significant trends; please refer to <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=435201.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Tables 2</ext-link></underline>–<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=435201.docx" ext-link-type="uri">4</ext-link></underline> for a detailed report.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The principal findings of our small exploratory study suggest similar rates of morning dream recall between (young) middle-aged iRBD and NREMP patients who have experienced a PSG-verified nocturnal parasomnic event. Moreover, we reported a higher percentage of white dreams<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> in iRBD patients and a higher rate of NREMP patients with no recall of dreams.</p>
      <p>Historically, white dreams have been described in terms of problems with encoding or retrieval<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> and defined by the feeling of having had an experience of dreaming whilst unable to account for that experience.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> More recently, however, it has been suggested that white dreaming may simply signify lower-quality dream experiences where neural activity is higher than in no dream recall condition but lower than in cases of dream recall.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> Thus, some white dreaming might result from “contentless” or “imageless” dreams, a minimal form of consciousness, with subjects experiencing no narrative structure.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> Arguably, it would follow that in iRBD, even in the early stages of neurodegeneration, distinct changes in sleep microstructure and a neurochemical/neurocircuitry milieu may contribute to less vivid dreams’ mental imagery, and therefore, a higher rate of recall of white dreams by some individuals.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Similarly, a higher rate of no dream recall in NREMP might be caused by ensuing down-states during NREM slow-wave sleep and even less well-defined dreams’ mental imagery.<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></p>
      <p>In keeping with this notion, characters recalled by NREMP patients were less well defined (Hall &amp; Van de Castle Dream Content Analysis: indefinite characters: 66.7% versus 16.7% in iRBD), and their overall dream recall significantly less coherent (eg, SGA analysis). Previously, we and others have suggested that the subconscious processing of external environmental cues during NREMP episodes may promote discontinuity and ambiguity in the mental imagery of dreamers.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> In this NREMP cohort, however, dream recall may have been further affected by significant sleep fragmentation, as evidenced by a higher arousal index compared to iRBD patients. Moreover, as shown in <xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>, the NREMP reports in our study demonstrate high convolution and recursiveness, thought-like dreams, and confusion regarding the chronology of events. This is in striking opposition to the temporally less ambiguous dream narrative of the iRBD group (eg, with story-like linearity and easily recounted distinct sequential flows of events).</p>
      <p>Notably, the SGA analysis indicated that NREMP dreamers had to repeatedly revert to internally experienced snapshot mental imagery while building a dream narrative (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=435201.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 1</ext-link></underline>). Alternatively, these findings could be attributed to a specific pattern of memory deficits with amplified emotional salience (for example, arising during associated pavor nocturnus or panic attacks).<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> All of this could theoretically affect NREMP patients’ recall, more than a similar request put to iRBD patients.</p>
      <p>Overall, we propose that our results support the feasibility of automatic differential diagnosis of dream narratives based on word-by-word speech graph analysis (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> Interestingly, it has been shown that schizophrenia and bipolar affective disorder patients, both previously associated with significant changes in sleep architecture,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> respond in a reciprocal manner to the dream-report task. For instance, the former were reported to sustain flattened speech, whereas the latter responded to increased confabulation.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> A body of work on other neuropsychiatric syndromes also suggests that dream-reports may be significantly more revealing than waking reports about the mental state of patients.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> Thus, the use of SGA may further aid true holistic treatment approaches.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></p>
      <p>In addition, the findings of our study further converge on previously reported fundamental principles of diverse processing across distinct sleep brain states.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> For instance, while the recent waking activities (episodic replay) may be reported in only 1–2% of dream reports, it has been shown that retrieval of declarative memories may be more accessible after REM sleep.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> Thus, depending on the neurochemical milieu and changes in sleep architecture that underlie the majority of sleep or neuropsychiatric disorders, dream reports may become more or less likely to be proximally anchored to recent events, while simultaneously also more or less likely to reveal psychopathologies based on mature memories, likely to be restructured over time.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></p>
      <p>To the best of our knowledge, this is only the second study to date that directly compared the dream characteristics of these two parasomnias.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Moreover, while our findings are in broad agreement with previous findings,<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> there are also notable differences that likely reflect the distinct sociodemographic characteristics of our younger (and age-matched) iRBD and NREMP patient cohorts. For example, we reported a similar rate of dream recall between the two parasomnias, which is in contrast to a previous study that reported a higher recall of dreams in NREMP patients (vs iRBD).<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> However, in an earlier study, parasomnia cohorts were not age-matched, and (much younger) NREMP patients were compared with a significantly older RBD group.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Interestingly, the authors did not find any differences when dream recall was assessed over a lifetime.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> This may further support the role of age and possibly the neurodegenerative effect on short-term memory capacity, and thus on recall.<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46–48</xref> Moreover, whilst both patient cohorts were diagnosed according to the strict American Academy of Sleep Medicine (AASM) criteria, as previously published,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> it is important to note that our iRBD cohort included uncommonly young patients, of which more than half were women (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). This unusual phenotype likely reflects that dream recall may be age and sex dependent, and thus, these data may not be fully representative of older, male iRBD patients. Reassuringly, and in broad keeping with our results, one well-conducted video-polysomnographic study of iRBD, showed that dream content was linked to video-recorded motor behaviours above chance level.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></p>
      <p>Previous work has suggested that oppositional defensive isomorphic flight or fight defence behaviors may arise in NREMP and iRBD patients under a perceived threat during dreaming, and similar behavioral patterns have been observed in this study.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> However, the small sample size and other inherent limitations of our observational retrospective study, which relied on self-administered questionnaires,<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> prevented further in-depth analysis of this phenomenon (<xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> In the past, proactive counterattack fighting defence mechanisms recorded in iRBD dreams have been compared to more avoidant (flight response) defence reactions in sleep terrors (NREMP).<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> The former is mechanistically linked to the disinhibition of archaic defence behaviors stemming from central pattern generators.<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> Interestingly, a recent study has suggested a negative link between age and levels of aggression in dream mentation in healthy participants, which has also been confirmed in patients with phenoconverted RBD.<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> Therefore, it is possible that indirect consequences of any such episode (eg, injuries, spousal/partner impact) in RBD patients play a significant role in enhancing the long-term memory of the incident.<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></p>
      <p>Another interesting finding in our study is that both groups of patients had proportionally similar numbers of reported dream characteristics (7/7 for iRBD and 19/20 for NREMP). However, characters recalled by iRBD patients appeared better defined, which may be a reflection of the vividness of the mental imagery of dreams during REM sleep that allows for better identification of the participating characters.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> However, it is also possible that this is due to inherent differences in dream imagery arising across tonic and phasic stages of the NREM-REM spectrum.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></p>
      <p>Moreover, examining the extremes of nightmares, such as in cases of post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD), sufferers commonly report experiencing a torturous replay of their trauma through nightmares and can often identify their attackers as their dreamt character.<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref> The ventral visual stream, a neurocircuitry pivotal for object recognition and categorization, has been shown to play a role in the development, severity, and response to nightmares in patients with PTSD and is likely to play an active role in the character identification process in nightmares.<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref> In one of our previous studies on iRBD patients, we highlighted the restricted truncal sagittal movements of enacted dreams with eyes closed as a reflection of allocentric navigation (brain-generated virtual space-maps), which involves maps that are represented/recorded in the hippocampal area, which are functionally linked with the ventral visual stream and amygdala.<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> Allegorically, iRBD patients could be likened to the viewer of a 3D cinema movie, who watches a film directed by allocentric dream landscapes, requiring no external spatio-temporal coordinates or input, and thus possibly more easily retrieving familiar characters from existing memory engrams. The seated viewer may react to a 3D movie only restrictively.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> In contrast, and in parallel, in NREMP dream mentations, egocentric spatial maps are utilized, with eyes typically open during parasomnia events, enriching their dream content and navigation process with visual information from the surroundings, all of which may generate mental imagery/perceptions of unspecified characters and gender, originating, for instance, from a shadow behind the bedroom door or at the ceiling.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></p>
      <p>Although our sample size prevents any authoritative exploration of putative sex differences in dream mentations, we note that aggression in male iRBD patients was predominantly reported as the same sex directed. For example, in this study, male patients were more likely to counterattack other male characters. Conversely, male NREMP patients were more likely to flee or avoid a female character during a perceived threat. Previous studies on sex differences in aggressive dream content between healthy college males and females have suggested heightened aggression in dreams of male dreamers, with perceived dream attackers reported more frequently as males.<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></p>
      <p>In conclusion, dream research, including this study, has many overt significant limitations inherent to poorly defined neuroscientific definitions of sleep stages, dreams and mental imagery, lack of reproducible findings, and sufficiently developed imaging methodologies. Finally, the role of memory in accessing experiences with no objective means by which dreams can be collected and independently validated poses additional unresolved issue.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref> Just as dream reports of our two parasomnia cohorts cannot be authoritatively linked to any specific sleep stage, there is no objective way to determine whether the morning recall by NREMP patients is that of NREM or possibly of REM dream origin or possibly a confabulation, and vice versa.<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref> Moreover, any extrapolation of our findings is further limited by its small size, as well as its observational nature.</p>
      <p>Notwithstanding, the findings of SGA quantitatively characterized RBD and NREMP cohort differences, and future well-defined studies with much larger samples will hopefully build on some of these hypotheses. Such studies will need to use longitudinal measures on the same participants, ideally while using various reproducible dream study protocols, combined with multimodal imaging.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>This research was funded in whole or in part by the Wellcome Trust [103952/Z/14/Z]. For open access, the author IR has applied a CC BY public copyright licence to any Author Accepted Manuscript version arising from this submission.</p>
      <p>This paper represents independent research in part funded by the NIHR Maudsley Biomedical Research Centre in South London and the Maudsley NHS Foundation Trust and King’s College London. The views expressed are those of the author(s) and not necessarily those of the NIHR or Department of Health and Social Care.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0005">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>Dr David O’Regan reports that he has received honoraria for lectures, presentations and articles from Neurodiem, TEVA, British Association of Psychopharmacology and Idorsia. He is on the advisory panel for Redefining Education on Sleep Therapy. He has insomnia-related patents with Closed Loop Medicine, with whom he has stock options (as a former employee). He is the current president of the Sleep Medicine Section at the Royal Society of Medicine, London. The authors report no other conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Siclari</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Valli</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arnulf</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dreams and nightmares in healthy adults and in patients with sleep and neurological disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>849</fpage>–<lpage>859</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(20)30275-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32949545</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Waters</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barnby</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blom</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Hallucination, imagery, dreaming: reassembling stimulus-independent perceptions based on Edmund Parish’s classic misperception framework</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>376</volume>(<issue>1817</issue>):<fpage>20190701</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2019.0701</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33308065</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fox</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nijeboer</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Solomonova</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Domhoff</surname>
<given-names>GW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Christoff</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dreaming as mind wandering: evidence from functional neuroimaging and first-person content reports</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Hum Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>412</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnhum.2013.00412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23908622</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Hall</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van De Castle</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">The Content Analysis of Dreams</italic></source>. Vol. <volume>xiv</volume>. <publisher-loc>East Norwalk, CT, US</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Appleton-Century-Crofts</publisher-name>; <year>1966</year>:<fpage>320</fpage>–<lpage>xiv</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gnoni</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duncan</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wasserman</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Nocturnal visual hallucinations in patients with disorders of arousal: a novel behavioral and EEG pattern</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Croat Med J</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>438</fpage>–<lpage>447</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3325/cmj.2022.63.438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36325668</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Uguccioni</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Golmard</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Fontreaux</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leu-Semenescu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brion</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arnulf</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Fight or flight? Dream content during sleepwalking/sleep terrors vs. rapid eye movement sleep behavior disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>391</fpage>–<lpage>398</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2013.01.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23601752</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Poole</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosenzweig</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dreaming of Godot</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>801</fpage>–<lpage>802</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(20)30315-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32949532</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wasserman</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gullone</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duncan</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Restricted truncal sagittal movements of rapid eye movement behaviour disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">NPJ Parkinson’s Dis</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>26</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41531-022-00292-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35292658</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Longe</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Omodan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leschziner</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosenzweig</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Non-REM parasomnias: a scoping review of dreams and dreamlike mentation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Croat Med J</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>525</fpage>–<lpage>535</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3325/cmj.2022.63.525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36597564</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gnoni</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Higgins</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nesbitt</surname>
<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cotard parasomnia: le delire de negation that occur during the sleep-wake dissociation?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>971</fpage>–<lpage>976</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.8430</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32195661</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nielsen</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A review of mentation in REM and NREM sleep: “covert” REM sleep as a possible reconciliation of two opposing models</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Brain Sci</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>851</fpage>–<lpage>866</lpage>. (). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0140525X0000399X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11515145</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Simor</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van der Wijk</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nobili</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peigneux</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The microstructure of REM sleep: why phasic and tonic?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>101305</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2020.101305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32259697</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Picard-Deland</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bernardi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Genzel</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dresler</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schoch</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Memory reactivations during sleep: a neural basis of dream experiences?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Trends Cognit Sci</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>568</fpage>–<lpage>582</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tics.2023.02.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36959079</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Klinzing</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Niethard</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Born</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mechanisms of systems memory consolidation during sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1598</fpage>–<lpage>1610</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41593-019-0467-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31451802</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sateia</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>International classification of sleep disorders-third edition: highlights and modifications</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>146</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1387</fpage>–<lpage>1394</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.14-0970</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25367475</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fasiello</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scarpelli</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gorgoni</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alfonsi</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Gennaro</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dreaming in parasomnias: REM sleep behavior disorder as a model</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):<fpage>6379</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm11216379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36362607</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Laroche</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Biabani</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drakatos</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>group cognitive behavioural therapy for non-rapid eye movement parasomnias: long-term outcomes and impact of COVID-19 lockdown</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Sci</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>347</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/brainsci13020347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36831890</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>O’Regan</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nesbitt</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Biabani</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A novel group cognitive behavioral therapy approach to adult non-rapid eye movement parasomnias</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>679272</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2021.679272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34276446</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wasserman</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bindman</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nesbitt</surname>
<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Striatal dopaminergic deficit and sleep in idiopathic rapid eye movement behaviour disorder: an explorative study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Sci Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S267037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33447113</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gelegen</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cash</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ilic</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Relevance of sleep and associated structural changes in GBA1 mouse to human rapid eye movement behavior disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>7973</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-11516-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35562385</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Drakatos</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Regan</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Profile of sleep disturbances in patients with recurrent depressive disorder or bipolar affective disorder in a tertiary sleep disorders service</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>8785</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-36083-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37258713</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dauvilliers</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schenck</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Postuma</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>REM sleep behaviour disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Dis Primers</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>19</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41572-018-0016-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30166532</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Neikrug</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ancoli-Israel</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Diagnostic tools for REM sleep behavior disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>415</fpage>–<lpage>429</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2011.08.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22169258</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Olson</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boeve</surname>
<given-names>BF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Silber</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Rapid eye movement sleep behaviour disorder: demographic, clinical and laboratory findings in 93 cases</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>123</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>331</fpage>–<lpage>339</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/123.2.331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10648440</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schenck</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hurwitz</surname>
<given-names>TD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mahowald</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>REM sleep behaviour disorder: an update on a series of 96 patients and a review of the world literature</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of Sleep Research</italic></source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>224</fpage>–<lpage>231</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.1993.tb00093.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10607098</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wing</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lam</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>REM sleep behaviour disorder in Hong Kong Chinese: clinical outcome and gender comparison</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurol Neurosurg</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>79</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1415</fpage>–<lpage>1416</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jnnp.2008.155374</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Raheel</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deegan</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Di Giulio</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sex differences in alpha-synucleinopathies: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1204104</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fneur.2023.1204104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37545736</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Takeuchi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sasai-Sakuma</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Inoue</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Gender differences in clinical findings and α-synucleiopathy-related markers in patients with idiopathic REM sleep behavior disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>216</fpage>–<lpage>219</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2019.11.1261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31978865</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Castelnuovo</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marelli</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mombelli</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salsone</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferini-Strambi</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Idiopathic RBD: the role of gender</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>267</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>2157</fpage>–<lpage>2158</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00415-020-09968-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32507986</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fernández-Arcos</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Iranzo</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Serradell</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gaig</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Santamaria</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The clinical phenotype of idiopathic rapid eye movement sleep behavior disorder at presentation: a study in 203 consecutive patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>132</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.5332</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26940460</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Gender differences in REM sleep behavior disorder: a clinical and polysomnographic study in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>414</fpage>–<lpage>418</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2014.10.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25660814</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bodkin</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schenck</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Rapid eye movement sleep behavior disorder in women: relevance to general and specialty medical practice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Women’s Health</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1955</fpage>–<lpage>1963</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/jwh.2008.1348</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schenck</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mahowald</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>REM sleep behavior disorder: clinical, developmental, and neuroscience perspectives 16 years after its formal identification in SLEEP</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>120</fpage>–<lpage>138</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/25.2.120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11902423</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Alfonsi</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>D’Atri</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scarpelli</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mangiaruga</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Gennaro</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep talking: a viable access to mental processes during sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>12</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2018.12.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30594004</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Valli</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frauscher</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gschliesser</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Can observers link dream content to behaviours in rapid eye movement sleep behaviour disorder? A cross-sectional experimental pilot study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.2011.00938.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21815957</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mota</surname>
<given-names>NB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vasconcelos</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lemos</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Speech graphs provide a quantitative measure of thought disorder in psychosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e34928</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0034928</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22506057</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Orlinsky</surname>
<given-names>DE</given-names></string-name>
<source>Psychodynamic and cognitive correlates of dream recall</source>. [<comment>Unpublished doctoral dissertation</comment>]. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago</publisher-name>; <year>1962</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Flanagan</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The content analysis of dreams. by Calvin s. hall and Robert l. van de castle new york: the century psychology series. 1966. pp. 320. price not given</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Br J Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>112</volume>(<issue>490</issue>):<fpage>963</fpage>–<lpage>964</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/bjp.112.490.963</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Leu-Semenescu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Uguccioni</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Golmard</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Can we still dream when the mind is blank? Sleep and dream mentations in auto-activation deficit</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>136</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>3076</fpage>–<lpage>3084</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awt229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24026624</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mota</surname>
<given-names>NB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Furtado</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maia</surname>
<given-names>PP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Copelli</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ribeiro</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Graph analysis of dream reports is especially informative about psychosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>3691</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep03691</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24424108</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fazekas</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nemeth</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Overgaard</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>White dreams are made of colours: what studying contentless dreams can teach about the neural basis of dreaming and conscious experiences</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>84</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2018.10.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30529433</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>DB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Toward a theory of dream recall</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Bull</italic></source>. <year>1974</year>;<volume>81</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>138</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/h0037616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4359972</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Siclari</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baird</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perogamvros</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The neural correlates of dreaming</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>872</fpage>–<lpage>878</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.4545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28394322</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nir</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tononi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dreaming and the brain: from phenomenology to neurophysiology</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Trends Cognit Sci</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>88</fpage>–<lpage>100</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tics.2009.12.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20079677</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vukadinovic</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosenzweig</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Abnormalities in thalamic neurophysiology in schizophrenia: could psychosis be a result of potassium channel dysfunction?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Neurosci Biobehav Rev</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>960</fpage>–<lpage>968</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2011.11.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22138503</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mangiaruga</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scarpelli</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bartolacci</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Gennaro</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Spotlight on dream recall: the ages of dreams</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Sci Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S135762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29391838</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stefani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gabelia</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Högl</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Long-term follow-up investigation of isolated rapid eye movement sleep without atonia without rapid eye movement sleep behavior disorder: a pilot study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1273</fpage>–<lpage>1279</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.5184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26156949</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Lortie-Lussier</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dale</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Koninck</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <part-title>Ontogenetic development of dreaming</part-title>. In: <string-name><surname>Hoss</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Valli</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gongloff</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, editors. <source><italic toggle="yes">Dreams: understanding Biology, Psychology, and Culture</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Santa Barbara, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Greenwood, ABC-Clio</publisher-name>; <year>2019</year>:<fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>208</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fantini</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Corona</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clerici</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferini-Strambi</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Aggressive dream content without daytime aggressiveness in REM sleep behavior disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1010</fpage>–<lpage>1015</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/01.wnl.0000179346.39655.e0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16217051</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tassinari</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rubboli</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gardella</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Central pattern generators for a common semiology in fronto-limbic seizures and in parasomnias. A neuroethologic approach</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>Suppl 3</issue>):<fpage>s225</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10072-005-0492-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16331401</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cavallotti</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stein</surname>
<given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Savarese</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Terzaghi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>D’Agostino</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Aggressiveness in the dreams of drug-naïve and clonazepam-treated patients with isolated REM sleep behavior disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2022.02.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35325765</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Germain</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Nightmares and Posttraumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Sleep Med Rep</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>74</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40675-016-0037-0</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Harnett</surname>
<given-names>NG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Finegold</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lebois</surname>
<given-names>LAM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Structural covariance of the ventral visual stream predicts posttraumatic intrusion and nightmare symptoms: a multivariate data fusion analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Transl Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>321</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41398-022-02085-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35941117</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Evensmoen</surname>
<given-names>HR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rimol</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Winkler</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Allocentric representation in the human amygdala and ventral visual stream</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cell Rep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>108658</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2020.108658</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33472067</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0055">
        <label>55.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Barros</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Uguccioni</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salkin-Goux</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leu-Semenescu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dodet</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arnulf</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Simple behavioral criteria for the diagnosis of disorders of arousal</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.8136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31957639</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0056">
        <label>56.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Paolino</surname>
<given-names>AF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dreams: sex differences in aggressive content</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Proj Tech Pers Assess</italic></source>. <year>1964</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>226</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/0091651X.1964.10120123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14175641</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0057">
        <label>57.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Horton</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Key concepts in dream research: cognition and consciousness are inherently linked, but do no not control “control”!</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Front Hum Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>259</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnhum.2020.00259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32765237</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
