<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38721523</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">11077295</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">460212</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S460212</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Sleep Duration Irregularity is Associated with Elevated Blood Pressure During Submaximal Exercise in Young Adults</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Gonzales and Dellinger</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Gonzales and Dellinger</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6629-8511</contrib-id><name><surname>Gonzales</surname><given-names>Joaquin U</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dellinger</surname><given-names>Jacob R</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Kinesiology and Sport Management, Texas Tech University</institution>, <addr-line>Lubbock</addr-line>, <addr-line>TX</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Joaquin U Gonzales, Department of Kinesiology and Sport Management, Texas Tech University, <addr-line>Box 43011</addr-line>, <addr-line>Lubbock</addr-line>, <addr-line>TX</addr-line>, <addr-line>79409-3011</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>, <phone content-type="general">Tel +1 806-834-5944</phone>, Email joaquin.gonzales@ttu.edu</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>02</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>460</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Gonzales and Dellinger.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Gonzales and Dellinger.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Purpose</title><p>Irregularity in nightly sleep duration is reported to associate with elevated blood pressure (BP), but it is unclear whether this association can be observed with BP measured during exercise after controlling for factors known to influence the exercise pressor reflex.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Twenty-nine young adults (22±4y; 19 men, 10 women) performed cycling exercise until volitional fatigue to assess peak oxygen uptake (VO<sub>2</sub>). Actigraphy was used to monitor sleep duration and daily physical activity for seven consecutive days after which participants completed two bouts of moderate-intensity cycling while BP and VO<sub>2</sub> were measured using a Tango+ device and indirect calorimetry, respectively. Systolic BP was averaged from the two bouts of exercise and expressed as a change from seated rest (∆SBP). Sleep duration regularity was calculated as standard deviation (SD) and coefficient of variation (CV).</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Systolic BP at seated rest, during exercise, and ∆SBP was 113±13, 152±21, and 38±13 mmHg, respectively. Sleep duration SD (range 10–146 min) and sleep duration CV (range 2–54%) when excluding weekend nights were significantly correlated with ∆SBP (r = 0.58 and r = 0.62, respectively; both <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.01) after adjusting for age, sex, body mass index, peak VO<sub>2</sub>, physical activity, resting systolic BP, chronotype, and the VO<sub>2</sub> response to exercise. Sleep duration regularity analyzed with weekend nights included (across all seven days) was also significantly correlated with ∆SBP (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>≤0.01), but had weaker correlation coefficients.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>These results indicate that sleep regularity, especially when excluding weekend nights, is associated with the rise in systolic BP during moderate-intensity exercise in young adults. Sleep duration regularity may be a useful tool to capture the impact of intermittent nights of insufficient sleep on BP dysregulation.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>sleep duration</kwd><kwd>sleep variability</kwd><kwd>blood pressure</kwd><kwd>exercise</kwd><kwd>VO<sub>2</sub></kwd><kwd>chronotype</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Texas Tech Graduate Research Fellowship</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This study was funded by a Texas Tech Graduate Research Fellowship (to JD).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="3"/><ref-count count="33"/><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Sleep is now recognized as an important lifestyle factor for optimal cardiovascular health. So much so that in 2022, the American Heart Association added sleep health to their “Life’s Essential 8” list of modifiable risk factors aimed at reducing the development of heart disease and stroke.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> The current recommendation for adults is to sleep 7–9 hours per night.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> This recommendation stems partly from research that finds sleep less than 7 hours per night (insufficient sleep) is associated with higher blood pressure (BP) in both cross-sectional comparisons as well as longitudinal analyses.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> A weakness, however, of focusing on self-reported or average weekly sleep duration is that it does not capture intermittent nights of insufficient sleep that may be present throughout the week. A single night of insufficient sleep has been shown to elevate systolic BP the subsequent morning.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Possible mechanisms that explain this phenomenon include augmented sympathetic activity and decreased baroreflex sensitivity that are reported to occur after sleep loss.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Thus, analyzing for sleep duration regularity may be a useful tool to capture the impact of intermittent nights of insufficient sleep on BP dysregulation.</p>
      <p>The most common method of assessing sleep duration regularity is through the calculation of standard deviation (SD) from nightly sleep duration across the measurement period. Using this approach, Hoopes et al reported no difference in resting BP between young adults with lower sleep duration SD and those with higher sleep duration SD.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Culver et al also observed no association between resting BP and sleep duration SD in young adults using bivariate correlations, but after adjusting for sex and body mass index (BMI) using partial correlations these researchers observed higher sleep duration SD to correlate with higher resting BP.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> This latter finding is consistent with research in middle-aged to older adults that report sleep duration SD to associate with risk factors for hypertension<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> as well as contribute to an increased risk of developing cardiovascular disease.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Considering the large and often fluctuating demands of young adults as they try to find a balance between college, work, and social life has been linked to higher sleep duration irregularity,<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> more research focused on this age group is needed to understand the influence of sleep variability on cardiovascular health.</p>
      <p>Fewer studies have assessed the association between sleep duration regularity and exercise BP. Meth et al found the change in systolic BP from rest to 1-minute after the YMCA step test to have a positive correlation with sleep duration irregularity (based on interquartile range) after adjusting for average sleep duration, age, sex, BMI, and physical activity the week prior to testing.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Shortcomings of this study, however, is that BP was not measured during exercise, intensity of exercise was not consistent between participants, and BP was measured 1-minute into recovery from exercise. In young adults, systolic BP decreases rapidly (~10–15 mm Hg) within the first minute of exercise and can vary based on cardiorespiratory fitness level.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Therefore, to address these limitations, the purpose of this study was to examine for a relationship between sleep duration regularity and BP measured during exercise at a set relative intensity and after controlling for variance explained by confounding variables including cardiorespiratory fitness level. We hypothesized that higher sleep duration irregularity would associate with an elevated BP response to exercise.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p>College students, both men (n = 20) and women (n = 10), between the ages of 18–39 years completed this study. One man was removed from the final analysis because BP was not measured during exercise due to poor electrode placement. In the end, data from 29 participants were included in the final analysis. Inclusion criteria included no recent history (&lt;6 months) of sleep problems, physically inactive as defined by less than three days per week of planned exercise, and non-obese as defined by a BMI &lt; 30 kg/m<sup>2</sup>. Exclusion criteria included taking medications or supplements to improve sleep, being a smoker and/or vaper, and a previous diagnosis of having diabetes mellitus, pulmonary disease, or coronary heart disease. Menstrual cycle phase was not controlled for in this study as past research reports no difference in heart rate or BP responses to moderate-intensity cycling between low and high hormone phases of the menstrual cycle in young women.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> Methods of participant recruitment for this study included weekly advertisements through the university Email announcement system, study fliers posted throughout the university campus, and announcements in undergraduate courses.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Study Design</title>
        <p>This study was reviewed and approved by the Human Research Protection Program at Texas Tech University (approval #IRB2021-1039), and its procedures conformed to standards set by the Declaration of Helsinki. Participants reported to the laboratory for two study visits across an eight-day period. All visits took place in the morning, and time for each visit was kept constant for each participant. Instructions prior to each visit were to avoid strenuous exercise for 24-hours and to abstain from caffeine and food intake for 12-hours and 4-hours, respectively. The first visit consisted of reviewing the consent form, completing a medical history questionnaire, screening, and a maximal cycling exercise test. No study measurements were taken before obtaining written informed consent from each participant. At the end of the first visit, participants were instructed to maintain their normal sleep behavior for seven consecutive days while sleep and physical activity was monitored using actigraphy. On the eighth day, participants reported to the laboratory for the second visit which involved heart rate variability testing and submaximal cycling exercise.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Study Measurements</title>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3001">
          <title>Maximal Exercise Test</title>
          <p>A ramp protocol on a cycle ergometer (Lode Corival, The Netherlands) was used to assess cardiorespiratory fitness. The exercise test consisted of a 3-minute warmup of cycling at 0W followed by a ramp increase in work rate at 30 W/min for men and 20 W/min for women until participants were unable to maintain their self-selected pedal rate (drop of ≥10 rpm). Breath-by-breath pulmonary gas exchange was measured continuously during exercise using indirect calorimetry (Ultima CardiO<sub>2</sub>, MedGraphics, St. Paul, MN, USA). Peak VO<sub>2</sub> was recorded as the highest 30-second average obtained at the end of exercise, and was considered a proxy of cardiorespiratory fitness level. All but one participant reached an exercise heart rate within 10 beats of their age-predicted maximum (range −13 to +7 bpm; 93–103% of predicted), and all participants reported a rating of perceived exertion ≥16 on the Borg 6–20 scale (range 16–20, median = 19).</p>
          <p>The gas exchange threshold (GET) was determined using the V-slope method<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> in conjunction with the ventilatory equivalent method.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> The VO<sub>2</sub> at the GET was adjusted for the delayed rise in VO<sub>2</sub> at the onset of exercise.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> This was done by shifting the linear VO<sub>2</sub> versus work rate (and time) relationship to the left, by subtracting two-thirds of the ramp work rate (20W for men and 13W for women) from the work rate initially identified at the GET.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> The adjusted work rate for 95% of the GET was then used to prescribe moderate-intensity exercise for all participants at the second visit.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3002">
          <title>Sleep Monitoring</title>
          <p>A triaxial accelerometer (GT9X, ActiGraph, Pensacola, USA) sampling at 30Hz was used to measure sleep duration. Participants wore the accelerometer at their wrist, and were instructed to only remove it when bathing or swimming. Actigraphy is reported to provide similar estimates of sleep duration than polysomnography,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> which is considered the gold-standard method for sleep monitoring. Sleep data was reduced to 60-second epochs and processed using a combination of Cole-Kripke and Tudor-Locke algorithms in ActiLife software (version 6.13.3, ActiGraph). The Cole-Kripke algorithm determined epochs as “sleep” or “wake”. The Tudor-Locke method determined sleep periods by identifying bedtime as five consecutive minutes of sleep epochs and wake as ten consecutive minutes of wake epochs at the end of a sleeping period. To complete a more accurate sleep analysis, participants were asked to keep record of their bed and wake times during the observation period. The self-reported clock times were used to refine sleep periods identified by ActiLife software to more accurately determine sleep duration. The standard deviation (SD) and coefficient of variation (CV) of nightly sleep duration was used to estimate sleep duration regularity. The CV was included as it has been frequently used in the literature to assess intraindividual night-to-night variability in sleep.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Lastly, the midpoint of sleep on weekend days (MSF) corrected for sleep debt on weekdays (MSFsc) was calculated as an index of chronotype.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> This variable was included in this study since internal circadian rhythm influence hemodynamic (eg, heart rate) responses to isometric<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> and aerobic exercise.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3003">
          <title>Daily Physical Activity</title>
          <p>Daily physical activity was objectively measured using a second triaxial accelerometer (GT3X+, ActiGraph, Pensacola, Florida) sampling at 30Hz. This accelerometer was worn at the left hip aligned with the foot, and participants were instructed to only remove it when bathing, swimming, or before bed-time. Counts per minute of physical activity data (using vector magnitude) were obtained by summing 1-second epoch data for each 60-second interval. Raw counts were processed using wear time criteria of ≥60 consecutive zeros and ≥10h per day of data using automated software (ActiLife v6, Pensacola, USA). Steps per day was recorded as an index of daily physical activity level.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3004">
          <title>Heart Rate Variability</title>
          <p>Electrocardiography (ECG) was recorded using a 3-lead electrocardiogram (PowerLab, ADInstruments, Colorado Springs, USA). Electrode sites on the body were wiped down with alcohol to ensure good contact with skin before electrodes were placed on the right arm, left arm, and left leg. Participants rested in the seated position for 10-minutes while ECG readings were collected. Instructions during the measurement were to breathe normally, remain relaxed by keeping eyes closed, feet flat on the ground, and hands resting on the legs.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Raw ECG readings from lead II were analyzed in the frequency domain using heart rate variability software (HRVanalysis v.1.2, ANS Lab Tools, Saint-Etienne, France) from the last 5-minutes of the ECG recording. Low frequency (LF, 0.04–0.15 Hz) and high-frequency power (HF, 0.15–0.40 Hz) were derived by the Fast Fourier Transform method. Natural logarithms of LF and HF power in milliseconds squared (ms<sup>2</sup>) are reported as these values were normally distributed. It is thought that parasympathetic modulation of cardiac rhythm is a major contributor to HF while LF reflects both parasympathetic and sympathetic activity at the heart. Consequently, the LF/HF ratio is considered by some investigators to reflect sympathetic modulations of cardiac rhythm.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3005">
          <title>Submaximal Cycling Exercise</title>
          <p>The exercise protocol consisted of 5-minuntes of low resistance cycling at 20W followed by two 4-minute bouts of moderate-intensity exercise at 95% of the GET separated by 5-minutes of cycling at 20W. Cycling was done on an upright Lode Corival cycle ergometer. Pulmonary gas exchange was measured using indirect calorimetry (Ultima CardiO<sub>2</sub>, MedGraphics, St. Paul, MN, USA). Oxygen uptake was averaged at rest and during the last 60-seconds of the initial 20W cycling bout as well as each bout of moderate-intensity exercise. The 60-second average VO<sub>2</sub> for each bout of moderate-intensity exercise was averaged together for analysis. Heart rate and BP were measured during exercise using a Tango+ automated device (SunTech Medical Inc., Morrisville, NC, USA). This device has been shown to provide accurate and reliable measures of systolic BP at rest and during maximal exercise testing as compared to an indwelling catheter.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> Three EKG electrodes were placed on the torso for measurement of heart rate, and a BP cuff was placed on the left arm. Heart rate and BP were measured at rest while the participant sat on the cycle ergometer, and during the last minute of each bout of moderate-intensity exercise. Participants were instructed to relax their left arm, fully extended at their side while maintaining their cycling cadence during BP measurements. As noted above, one participant was excluded from the blood pressure analysis as the device gave an error during measurement likely due to poor EKG placement or adherence to the skin. Heart rate and BP from each moderate-intensity bout were averaged together for analysis.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>Two-tailed paired t-tests were used to compare hemodynamics between rest and exercise conditions as the data were normally distributed. Pearson correlation was used to assess the relationship between sleep duration regularity and BP. Variables that were not normally distributed were transformed to follow a normal distribution using Johnson transformation. Partial correlations were used to assess the association between sleep duration regularity and BP after adjusting for age, sex, BMI, physical activity (daily steps), cardiorespiratory fitness (peak VO<sub>2</sub>), chronotype (MSFsc), resting systolic BP, and metabolic rate during exercise (change in VO<sub>2</sub> from baseline cycling at 20W to 95% of the GET). These covariates were selected to be consistent with past research<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> and control for variance by variables conceived to influence BP responses to exercise. Correlation coefficients and associated 95% confidence intervals are reported and can be interpreted as small (r = 0.1–0.3), medium (r = 0.3–0.5), and large (r = &gt;0.5).<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> Statistical significance was considered a priori at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.05.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Descriptive Data</title>
        <p>Average age, log LF, log HF, LF/HF ratio, and chronotype of participants were 22 ± 4y, 7.38 ± 0.90 ms<sup>2</sup>, 6.29 ± 1.01 ms<sup>2</sup>, 1.19 ± 0.15, and 4:55 a.m. (range 3:26–7:49 a.m.), respectively. By design, participants were non-obese with an average BMI of 22.9 ± 2.7 kg/m<sup>2</sup>, and were physically inactive as indicated by their daily step count of 7100 ± 2442 steps per day and low average peak VO<sub>2</sub> of 35 ± 4 mL/kg/min. Average sleep duration across all seven days was 361 ± 48 min (range 276–439 min), sleep duration SD was 62 ± 30 min (range 11–143 min), and sleep duration CV was 18 ± 10% (range 3–50%). After excluding weekend nights (Friday and Saturday), average sleep duration was 361 ± 50 min (range 270–449 min), sleep duration SD was 61 ± 33 min (range 10–146 min), and sleep duration CV was 17 ± 11% (range 2–54%).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Response to Submaximal Exercise</title>
        <p><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> presents heart rate and BP data at rest and during moderate-intensity exercise. Moderate-intensity exercise raised heart rate to 74 ± 7% of maximum, and in terms of metabolic demand, the change in VO<sub>2</sub> from baseline (20W) to moderate-intensity cycling was 9.84 ± 2.84 mL/kg/min. Systolic BP, but not diastolic BP, increased significantly during exercise (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.001; <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The change in systolic BP (∆SBP) from rest to exercise was 38 ± 13 mm Hg (range 22–75 mm Hg).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Hemodynamic Response to Cycling Exercise at 95% of the GET</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seated Rest</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exercise</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">t-value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Work rate (W)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 ± 22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart rate (bpm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 ± 7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">138 ± 14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Systolic BP (mm Hg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">113 ± 14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">152 ± 21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−15.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diastolic BP (mm Hg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 ± 8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 ± 10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Note</bold>: Values are mean ± SD.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: GET, gas exchange threshold; BP, blood pressure.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Association Between Sleep Regularity and BP</title>
        <p>Simple bivariate correlations between sleep duration regularity and measured variables are presented in <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Only chronotype and the ∆SBP from rest to exercise were found to correlate with sleep duration regularity. Specifically, chronotype had positive correlations with sleep duration SD (7-day: r = 0.61 [0.32, 0.80]; excluding weekend: r = 0.56 [0.24, 0.77]; both <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.001) and sleep duration CV (7-day: r = 0.69 [0.44, 0.84]; excluding weekend: r = 0.60 [0.31, 0.79]; both <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.001) indicating that later chronotypes had higher sleep duration irregularity. The ∆SBP from rest to exercise was positively correlated with sleep duration CV when analyzed across all 7-days (r = 0.39 [0.02, 0.66], <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.03) and when excluding weekend nights (r = 0.49 [0.15, 0.72], <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.004). Sleep duration SD was only correlated with the ∆SBP from rest to exercise when excluding weekend nights (r = 0.40 [0.04, 0.67], <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.02). Adjusting for all potential covariates using partial correlations strengthened the association between sleep duration regularity and the ∆SBP from rest to exercise for sleep duration SD (7-day: adjusted r = 0.50 [0.16, 0.73]; excluding weekend: adjusted r = 0.55 [0.23, 0.76]; both <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.01) and sleep duration CV (7-day: adjusted r = 0.58 [0.27, 0.78]; excluding weekend: adjusted r = 0.62 [0.34, 0.80]; both <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.001). <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> shows the relationship between sleep duration CV and the ∆SBP from rest to exercise after adjusting for covariates.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Pearson Correlation Coefficients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Entire Week (7-days)</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Excluding Weekend Nights</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">∆Systolic BP</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Duration</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Duration SD</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Duration CV</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Duration</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Duration SD</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Duration CV</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body mass index</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronotype</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daily Steps</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peak VO<sub>2</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.14</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Log LF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Log HF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.20</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LF/HF ratio</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.49**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.53**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∆VO2 (exercise)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resting systolic BP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.40*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resting diastolic BP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∆Systolic BP (exercise)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.40*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49**</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.05; **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>≤0.01.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: SD, standard deviation; CV, coefficient of variation; VO<sub>2</sub>, oxygen uptake; LF, low frequency power; HF, high frequency power; BP, blood pressure.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Scatter plot showing the relationship between sleep duration coefficient of variation (CV) and the change (∆) in systolic BP from rest to moderate-intensity cycling in young adults. Panel A shows sleep duration CV across seven days. Panel B shows sleep duration CV for weekdays excluding Friday and Saturday (weekend) nights. Values are residuals after the adjusting for age, sex, body mass index, daily steps, peak VO<sub>2</sub>, chronotype, resting systolic BP, and the change in VO<sub>2</sub> from baseline cycling at 20W to 95% of the gas exchange threshold using partial correlations.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-451-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
        <p>To determine whether the correlation between sleep regularity and exercise BP was independent of sleep duration, partial correlations were used to adjust average sleep duration. <xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> shows that sleep duration CV when excluding weekend nights remained significantly associated with the ∆SBP from rest to exercise after adjusting for average sleep duration (r<sup>2</sup> = 0.13, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.04). Interestingly, average sleep duration was no longer significantly correlated (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&gt;0.05) with the ∆SBP from rest to exercise after adjusting for sleep duration regularity (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Partial Correlation Coefficients with 95% Confidence Intervals</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Entire Week (7-days)</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Excluding Weekend Nights</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Duration†</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Duration SD</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Duration CV</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Duration‡</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Duration SD</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Duration CV</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>adjusted for average sleep duration</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∆Systolic BP (exercise)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22 [−0.15, 0.54]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 [−0.14, 0.55]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30 [−0.06, 0.60]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36* [0.01, 0.64]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>adjusted for sleep duration SD</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∆Systolic BP (exercise)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.26 [−0.57, 0.11]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.30 [−0.60, 0.07]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>adjusted for sleep duration CV</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∆Systolic BP (exercise)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.17 [−0.51, 0.20]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.20 [−0.53, 0.17]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Note</bold>: <sup>†</sup>7-day average sleep duration; <sup>‡</sup>average sleep duration excluding weekend nights. *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0006"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: SD, standard deviation; CV, coefficient of variation; BP, blood pressure.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The present study sought to determine whether a relationship exist between sleep duration regularity and the rise in BP during exercise. The main finding in this study was that greater irregularity in nightly sleep duration held a relationship of medium magnitude with higher systolic BP responses to exercise. This finding was independent of the average sleep duration when regularity was calculated as sleep duration CV after excluding weekend nights. More importantly, adjusting for covariates that may influence exercise BP did not reduce the association between sleep regularity and the rise in BP during exercise. These results support the notion that analyzing for sleep duration regularity may be a useful tool to capture the impact of intermittent nights of insufficient sleep on BP dysregulation.</p>
      <p>This study analyzed sleep duration regularity across one full week, and also after excluding weekend nights (Friday and Saturday night). This approach was used because past research finds higher reliability in measuring sleep duration using wrist actigraphy when excluding weekend nights.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> We included Sunday night in our analysis because Monday mornings would have a similar wake time requirement than other weekdays in our study population that consisted entirely of college students. Interestingly, average sleep duration and sleep duration regularity were similar whether analyzed across all seven days or when excluding weekend nights. However, our results clearly demonstrate that these two approaches to analyze sleep regularity makes a large difference in the strength of association between sleep regularity and exercise BP. First, we observed sleep duration CV to have slightly larger correlation coefficients than sleep duration SD in our bivariate correlation analysis, although both are considered of medium magnitude. Second, we showed that using the approach of excluding weekend nights when analyzing for sleep duration regularity resulted in stronger associations with exercise BP than including weekend nights. In fact, sleep duration CV when excluding weekend nights held an independent relationship with the rise in BP during exercise after adjusting for average sleep duration. These observations add new insight into the investigation of sleep duration regularity on BP, and provides strong support for excluding weekend nights when calculating sleep duration regularity in young adults.</p>
      <p>Past studies have recognized that average sleep duration and sleep duration regularity are two separate constructs. Indeed, similar average sleep durations have been reported between young adults with higher and lower sleep duration irregularity.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Even in the present study we observe heart rate variability (LF/HF ratio) to correlate with average sleep duration, but not sleep duration regularity demonstrating that these sleep health variables carry distinct information. However, one must recognize that a possible negative impact of having irregular nightly sleep durations may be a lower average sleep duration. The Multi-Ethnic Study of Atherosclerosis reported that participants with irregular sleep schedules and insufficient sleep averaged ~70 minutes lower average sleep duration than adults with regular sleep schedules and optimal sleep.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> Thus, these two measures of sleep health are likely to co-occur, particularly in adults with short sleep durations (&lt;7 hours per night) like those examined in the present study that had an average sleep duration of 6 hours per night. It is therefore theoretically possible that we would remove a large amount of variance in exercise BP explained by sleep duration regularity if we were to add average sleep duration to the full list of covariates in our partial correlational analysis. Instead, we chose to control for variance explained by average sleep duration and sleep duration regularity in a separate analysis to determine which variable held a significant correlation with exercise BP independent of the other. Interestingly, we find that sleep duration CV when excluding weekend nights was the only variable to remain significantly correlated with the rise in BP during exercise. Moreover, the 95% CI for this relationship did not overlap positive and negative values suggesting that sleep duration CV held a clear association with exercise BP independent of average sleep duration.</p>
      <p>The physiological mechanisms explaining our results are unclear from the present study. Heart rate variability was not associated with sleep duration regularity suggesting that autonomic dysregulation was not likely a contributing factor in the association between sleep duration irregularity and elevated BP responses to exercise observed in this study. We originally postulated that a person with higher sleep duration irregularity would suffer from insufficient sleep, and as a result, exhibit BP dysregulation stemming from sympathetic hyperactivity.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4–6</xref> However, our index of sympathetic modulations of the heart (LF/HF ratio) was not associated with sleep duration regularity or the rise in systolic BP during exercise. Other possible mechanisms, unexamined in this study, include baroreceptor sensitivity and peripheral vascular dysfunction. Zhong et al reported decreased baroreceptor sensitivity following acute sleep restriction in young adults,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> which is relevant to the present study if irregular nights of sleep consisted of short sleep durations. Impaired baroreceptor sensitivity is associated with elevated BP responses to exercise, even in adults with normal resting BP.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> Young adults with high sleep duration irregularity are also reported to have blunted leg blood flow responses to passive leg movement suggesting impaired microvascular vasodilation.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Peripheral vascular dysfunction could impair the regulation of vascular tone during exercise resulting in elevated BP. These possible mechanisms warrant further attention in future work.</p>
      <p>Limitations of this study include the population. We recruited young adults, all of which were college students. Sleep health in this population is poor due to academic, financial, and social pressure. Indeed, perceived stress is reported to explain ~25% of the variance in sleep quality in college students.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Thus, the generalizability of the present study to older aged populations with different sets of life demands and levels of perceived stress may be minimal. A second limitation of this study is that testing took place in the morning for all participants irrespective of chronotype. It is possible that our morning testing times contributed to an increase in sleep duration irregularity for later chronotypes that typically sleep later than our testing schedule permitted. However, if this did occur, it was only for one night of sleep in our analysis (ie, the night prior to the second study visit) since sleep monitoring started after the first study visit was complete. A third limitation of this work is that we did not account for dietary habits, assess hydration status, or collect measures of psychological stress that are well known to influence BP and BP reactivity. Lastly, we did not measure BP across multiple intensities of exercise in this study. It would be interesting to know whether sleep duration regularity is associated with exercise BP for higher intensities of exercise which are more often performed by athletes or adults undergoing exercise training.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>In summary, results from the present study show higher sleep duration irregularity to associate with an elevated BP responses to moderate-intensity cycling exercise in young inactive adults. The observed relationship was independent of confounding variables known to influence exercise BP as well as average sleep duration. These results support the notion that an irregular sleep pattern has the potential to contribute to BP dysregulation during exercise.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <p>BMI, body mass index; BP, blood pressure; GET, gas exchange threshold; CV, coefficient of variation; HF, high-frequency power; LF, low-frequency power; midpoint of sleep on weekend days corrected for sleep debt on weekdays (MSFsc); SD, standard deviation; SBP, systolic blood pressure; VO2, oxygen uptake.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p>Data analyzed for this are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0008">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lloyd-Jones</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>NB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Anderson</surname>
<given-names>CAM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Life’s essential 8: updating and enhancing the American heart association’s construct of cardiovascular health: a presidential advisory from the American heart association</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circulation</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>146</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e18</fpage>–<lpage>e43</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/cir.0000000000001078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35766027</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hirshkowitz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whiton</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Albert</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>National Sleep Foundation’s updated sleep duration recommendations: final report</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Health</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>243</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleh.2015.10.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29073398</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Knutson</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Cauter</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rathouz</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association between sleep and blood pressure in midlife: the CARDIA sleep study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>169</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1055</fpage>–<lpage>1061</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinternmed.2009.119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19506175</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lusardi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mugellini</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Preti</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zoppi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Derosa</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fogari</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of a restricted sleep regimen on ambulatory blood pressure monitoring in normotensive subjects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Hypertens</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>503</fpage>–<lpage>505</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0895-7061(95)00389-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8735182</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhong</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hilton</surname>
<given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gates</surname>
<given-names>GJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Increased sympathetic and decreased parasympathetic cardiovascular modulation in normal humans with acute sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Appl Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>98</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2024</fpage>–<lpage>2032</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/japplphysiol.00620.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15718408</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tai</surname>
<given-names>BWS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dawood</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macefield</surname>
<given-names>VG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yiallourou</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The association between sleep duration and muscle sympathetic nerve activity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Auton Res</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>647</fpage>–<lpage>657</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10286-023-00965-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37543558</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hoopes</surname>
<given-names>EK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berube</surname>
<given-names>FR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>D’Agata</surname>
<given-names>MN</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration regularity, but not sleep duration, is associated with microvascular function in college students</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>2</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsaa175</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Culver</surname>
<given-names>MN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McMillan</surname>
<given-names>NK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cross</surname>
<given-names>BL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration irregularity is associated with elevated blood pressure in young adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chronobiol Int</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1320</fpage>–<lpage>1328</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07420528.2022.2101373</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35844152</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Makarem</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zuraikat</surname>
<given-names>FM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aggarwal</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jelic</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>St-Onge</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Variability in sleep patterns: an emerging risk factor for hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Hypertens Rep</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>19</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11906-020-1025-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32086595</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mariani</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Redline</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep irregularity and risk of cardiovascular events: the multi-ethnic study of atherosclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>991</fpage>–<lpage>999</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2019.12.054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32138974</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lev Ari</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shulman</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pathways of sleep, affect, and stress constellations during the first year of college: transition difficulties of emerging adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Youth Studies</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>292</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13676261.2011.635196</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Meth</surname>
<given-names>EMS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van Egmond</surname>
<given-names>LT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benedict</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep duration regularity as a predictor of the cardiovascular response to acute exercise</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsab115</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nakamura</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fujiwara</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoshide</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Differences in exercise-induced blood pressure changes between young trained and untrained individuals</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Hypertens</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>843</fpage>–<lpage>848</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jch.14177</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hartwich</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aldred</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fisher</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Influence of menstrual cycle phase on muscle metaboreflex control of cardiac baroreflex sensitivity, heart rate and blood pressure in humans</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Exp Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>98</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>220</fpage>–<lpage>232</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/expphysiol.2012.066498</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22613743</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thompson</surname>
<given-names>KMA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Teixeira</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burr</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Millar</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cardiovascular responses to combined mechanoreflex and metaboreflex activation in healthy adults: effects of sex and low- versus high-hormone phases in females</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Appl Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>135</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1102</fpage>–<lpage>1114</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/japplphysiol.00775.2022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37795529</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Beaver</surname>
<given-names>WL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wasserman</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whipp</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A new method for detecting anaerobic threshold by gas exchange</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Appl Physiol</italic></source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>2020</fpage>–<lpage>2027</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3087938</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wasserman</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whipp</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koyal</surname>
<given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beaver</surname>
<given-names>WL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Anaerobic threshold and respiratory gas exchange during exercise</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Appl Physiol</italic></source>. <year>1973</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>236</fpage>–<lpage>243</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4723033</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Whipp</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davis</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Torres</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wasserman</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A test to determine parameters of aerobic function during exercise</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Appl Physiol</italic></source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6782055</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ghiarone</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ataide-Silva</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bertuzzi</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McConell</surname>
<given-names>GK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lima-Silva</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effect of acute nitrate ingestion on VO2 response at different exercise intensity domains</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Appl Physiol Nutr Metab</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1127</fpage>–<lpage>1134</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/apnm-2017-0198/M28658582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28658582</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Quante</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaplan</surname>
<given-names>ER</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cailler</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Actigraphy-based sleep estimation in adolescents and adults: a comparison with polysomnography using two scoring algorithms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Sci Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S151085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29403321</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Littner</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kushida</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Anderson</surname>
<given-names>WM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Practice parameters for the role of actigraphy in the study of sleep and circadian rhythms: an update for 2002</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>341</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/26.3.337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12749556</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kalogeropoulos</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burdayron</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laganière</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dubois-Comtois</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Béliveau</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pennestri</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep patterns and intraindividual sleep variability in mothers and fathers at 6 months postpartum: a population-based, cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ Open</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e060558</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2021-060558</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Roenneberg</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuehnle</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pramstaller</surname>
<given-names>PP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A marker for the end of adolescence</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Biol</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>R1038</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2004.11.039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15620633</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nebel</surname>
<given-names>LE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Howell</surname>
<given-names>RH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krantz</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Falconer</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gottdiener</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gabbay</surname>
<given-names>FH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The circadian variation of cardiovascular stress levels and reactivity: relationship to individual differences in morningness/eveningness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychophysiology</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>281</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8986.1996.tb00424.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8936396</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Remchak</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dosik</surname>
<given-names>JK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pappas</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gow</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shah</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malin</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Exercise blood pressure and heart rate responses to graded exercise testing in intermediate versus morning chronotypes with obesity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>325</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>H635</fpage>–<lpage>h644</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpheart.00149.2023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37505468</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Laborde</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mosley</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thayer</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Heart rate variability and cardiac vagal tone in psychophysiological research – recommendations for experiment planning, data analysis, and data reporting. Review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Frontiers in Psychology</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>213</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2017.00213</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Malik</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bigger</surname>
<given-names>JTJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Camm</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Heart rate variability - Standards of measurement, physiological interpretation, and clinical use</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circulation</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>93</volume>:<fpage>1043</fpage>–<lpage>1065</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8598068</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cameron</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stevenson</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reed</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McGrath</surname>
<given-names>BP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dart</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kingwell</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Accuracy of automated auscultatory blood pressure measurement during supine exercise and treadmill stress electrocardiogram-testing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Blood Press Monit</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>269</fpage>–<lpage>275</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00126097-200410000-00007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15472500</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Statistical Power Analysis for the Behavioral Sciences</italic></source>. <edition>2nd</edition> ed. <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</publisher-name>; <year>1988</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aili</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Åström-Paulsson</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stoetzer</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Svartengren</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hillert</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Reliability of actigraphy and subjective sleep measurements in adults: the Design of Sleep Assessments</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.6384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27707448</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goodman</surname>
<given-names>MO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Objectively regular sleep patterns and mortality in a prospective cohort: the multi-ethnic study of atherosclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of Sleep Research</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>:<fpage>e14048</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.14048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37752591</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sharman</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boutouyrie</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perier</surname>
<given-names>M-C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impaired baroreflex sensitivity, carotid stiffness, and exaggerated exercise blood pressure: a community-based analysis from the Paris prospective study III</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Heart J</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>599</fpage>–<lpage>606</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehx714</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lund</surname>
<given-names>HG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reider</surname>
<given-names>BD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whiting</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Prichard</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep patterns and predictors of disturbed sleep in a large population of college students</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Adolesc Health</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>124</fpage>–<lpage>132</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jadohealth.2009.06.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20113918</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
