<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38827392</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">11144403</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">439703</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S439703</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Clinical Trial Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effects of Intranasal Insulin Pretreatment on Preoperative Sleep Quality and Postoperative Delirium in Patients Undergoing Valve Replacement for Rheumatic Heart Disease</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Huang et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Huang et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Qingqing</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9427-3637</contrib-id><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Xiao</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>Ni</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Xin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Sixun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>Xuemei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Qin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2433-4158</contrib-id><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Gu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>Hai-Feng</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Anesthesiology, The General Hospital of Western Theater Command</institution>, <addr-line>Chengdu</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>College of Medicine, Southwest Jiaotong University</institution>, <addr-line>Chengdu</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Anesthesiology, North Sichuan Medical College</institution>, <addr-line>Nanchong</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Neurosurgery, The General Hospital of Western Theater Command</institution>, <addr-line>Chengdu</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Gu Gong, Department of Anesthesiology, The General Hospital of Western Theater Command, <addr-line>270 Tianhui Road, Rongdu Avenue, Jinniu District</addr-line>, <addr-line>Chengdu</addr-line>, <addr-line>Sichuan</addr-line>, <addr-line>610083</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, <phone content-type="general">Tel +8617360137572</phone>, <fax>Fax +86 028571770</fax>, Email gonggu68@163.com</corresp><fn id="ft0001"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>613</fpage><lpage>623</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>9</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Huang et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Huang et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Postoperative delirium (POD) is a common neurological complication associated with valve replacement. Preoperative sleep disturbance is a risk factor for POD development, and nasal insulin modulates the sleep-wake cycle. This study investigated the beneficial effects of intranasal insulin pretreatment on preoperative sleep quality and reducing POD in patients undergoing valve replacement for rheumatic heart disease.</p></sec><sec><title>Patients and Methods</title><p>This prospective, single-center, randomized controlled trial (RCT) included 76 adult patients aged 18–65 years undergoing valve surgery with cardiopulmonary bypass who were randomly allocated to receive intranasal insulin or normal saline interventions two days before surgery. POD incidence was on postoperative days 1 (T3), 2 (T4), and 3 (T5). Before the first intervention (T0), 1 d before surgery (T1), and before anesthesia on the day of surgery (T2), sleep quality was assessed and serum cortisol concentrations were measured. At T1 and T2, sleep quality related indicators monitored by sleep monitoring watches from the previous night were recorded.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Compared with the normal saline group, 3 days after surgery, the insulin group showed a significantly reduced incidence of POD; significantly increased deep sleep, REM sleep, deep sleep continuity, and total sleep quality scores at T1 and T2; and significantly reduced serum cortisol concentration, PSQI scale, light sleep ratio, and wakefulness at T1 and T2.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The administration of 20 U of intranasal insulin twice daily, from 2 days preoperatively until 10 minutes preanesthesia on the day of surgery, can improved preoperative sleep quality significantly and reduced POD incidence in patients with rheumatic heart disease undergoing valve replacement.</p></sec><sec><title>Clinical Trial Registration</title><p>This study was registered with the Chinese Clinical Trial Registry (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="http://www.chictr.org.cn" ext-link-type="uri">www.chictr.org.cn</ext-link></underline>, with the unique identifier ChiCTR2100048515; July 9, 2021).</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>postoperative delirium</kwd><kwd>rheumatic heart disease</kwd><kwd>valve replacement</kwd><kwd>preoperative sleep quality</kwd><kwd>intranasal insulin</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>ater Command (grant number 2021-XZYG-C25), the Joint key project (grant number 2019LH01) and Sichuan Natural Science Foundation Pr</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This study was supported by the Hospital Management Project of the General Hospital of the Western Theater Command (grant number 2021-XZYG-C25), the Joint key project (grant number 2019LH01) and Sichuan Natural Science Foundation Project (No. 2022NSFSC0746).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="5"/><ref-count count="35"/><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Rheumatic heart disease occurs when the mitral, tricuspid, aortic, or pulmonary valves develop lesions due to rheumatic fever that interfere with normal blood flow, resulting in abnormal heart function.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Currently, valve replacement is the most effective surgical treatment. Preoperative negative emotions such as fear and anxiety, in patients undergoing valve replacement surgery due to uncertainties regarding the operation procedure can seriously affect patient sleep quality.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Sleep is crucial for maintaining optimal brain function.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Research<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> has shown that insufficient sleep can lead to an increase in the release of inflammatory cytokines, thereby activating microglia. When microglia are activated, they release inflammatory cytokines, exacerbating damage to the nervous system. In addition, insufficient sleep can cause excessive excitement of the hypothalamic pituitary adrenal axis, leading to the transfer of a large amount of cortisol produced to the central nervous system, activating the BDNF/TrkB signaling pathway, causing neuronal apoptosis in the hippocampus, and thus causing cognitive impairment.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> In patients with obstructive sleep apnea syndrome, sleep efficiency is often affected, leading to excessive sleepiness, fatigue during the day, and an increased risk of cardiovascular or neurodegenerative diseases.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> In recent years, sleep has gradually become a hot topic in clinical research owing to its potential impact on cognitive function. Among these research findings is that preoperative sleep disruption predicts postoperative delirium (POD).<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Ibala et al<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> performed sleep polysomnography measurements the night before surgery in hospitalized elderly patients scheduled for elective major cardiac surgery for cardiopulmonary bypass and observed an association between longer sleep duration and POD. Liu et al’s<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> research indicates that preoperative sleep disorders make patients undergoing craniotomy more prone to POD. The study by Han et al<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> also suggests that preoperative sleep disorders may be an independent predictor of delirium in patients aged 60 years or older undergoing proximal femoral surgery. Therefore, the use of sleep-promoting drugs in the perioperative period may have a positive effect on POD prevention. New research has found that intranasal insulin may be a useful way to normalize the activity of the nocturnal hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis and improve sleep-related endocrine regulation.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> We also previously reported that the repeated nasal administration of insulin before surgery can reduce the incidence of POD in patients undergoing radical gastrointestinal tumor resection.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> However, no studies have investigated the combination of intranasal insulin, sleep, and POD. This study explored the effects of preoperative intranasal insulin administration on preoperative sleep quality and POD in patients undergoing valve replacement for rheumatic heart disease and discovered nasal insulin administered significantly improved preoperative sleep quality and reduced POD incidence. This result provides new ideas for preventing POD.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Study Design</title>
        <p>This prospective, double-blind, randomized controlled study was approved by the Ethics Committee of the General Hospital of Western Theater Command (Ethics Approval No. 2019ky64), conducted in accordance with the principles in the Helsinki Declaration, and registered with the Chinese Clinical Trial Registry at <underline><ext-link xlink:href="http://www.chictr.org.cn" ext-link-type="uri">www.chictr.org.cn</ext-link></underline> (unique identifier ChiCTR2100048515, July 9, 2021) before patient enrollment. All participants provided written informed consent. This study was conducted at the General Hospital of the Western Theater Command between August 2021 and January 2022.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Study Participants</title>
        <p>Patients aged 18–65 years who underwent heart valve replacement surgery with a procedure that took 2–6 h under cardiopulmonary bypass (CPB) were screened for the trial. Patients with an American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) physical status of II or III were included in this randomized study. The Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) was used to rule out cognitive dysfunction during the preoperative period. The exclusion criteria were: 1) preoperative rheumatic activities; 2) heparin resistance; 3) abnormal coagulation function; 4) severe liver or kidney or pulmonary damage; 5) difficulty in withdrawing from CPB; 6) preoperative left ventricular ejection fraction &lt;30%; 7) previous hypertension and diabetes; 8) history of insulin allergy; 9) alcohol consumption; 10) preoperative inability to communicate (coma, profound dementia or language impairment, severe visual and hearing impairment); 11) history of neurological or psychiatric diseases; 12) chronic or recent use of melatonin or hypnotics. The withdrawal criteria included 1) insulin use via a non-nasal route during the trial, 2) reoperation within 3 days after the initial operation, 3) unpredicted adverse events (eg, drug allergies, surgical accidents, or anesthesia-related adverse events), and 4) loss to follow-up (patient discharge or death within 3 days postoperatively).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Randomization and Blinding</title>
        <p>After admission, patients were selected based on inclusion and exclusion criteria and randomly divided into INS group and IN group in a 1:1 ratio using a random number table method. A random number table was generated by a researcher using IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows, version 26.0 (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, USA). The second researcher placed random numbers and group numbers in opaque envelopes of the same size and color. Each envelope has a screening number written on the cover, which is the serial number of the subjects who entered the screening. Random allocation is performed by the third researcher, who hands an envelope with patient serial number and hospitalization number information to an anesthesiologist after the patient enters the operating room. All enrolled patients are managed during the perioperative period by this anesthesiologist, who conducts preoperative visits, is responsible for patient grouping information, records relevant basic information, and collects and keeps corresponding records of intraoperative conditions. The generation, concealment, and allocation of randomization were completed by three different researchers who did not participate in the subsequent part of the experiment. The trial was blinded to both the subjects and their families, and other personnel, including surgeons, nurses, follow-up personnel, and data statisticians, were unaware of the patient’s grouping. Postoperative follow-up and related data entry are conducted by trained researchers.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Anesthetic Management</title>
        <p>The two groups of patients were prohibited from drinking or eating for 8 h before surgery according to the general anesthesia standards. Peripheral venous access was established and left radial artery and right deep vein punctures were performed under B-wave ultrasound guidance to monitor arterial and central venous pressures and to establish central venous access. Anesthesia was induced by intravenous injection of 0.03 mg/kg midazolam, 0.3 mg/kg etomidate, and 0.5u g/kg sufentanil. After the disappearance of the eyelid reflex, 0.2 mg/kg cisatracurium was administered intravenously for muscle relaxation, and tracheal intubation was performed. The pressure control volume guarantee (PCV-VG) mode was adopted during ventilation, using the following parameters: tidal volume, 6–8 mL/kg; concentration of inhaled oxygen (FIO<sub>2</sub>), 100%; ratio of inhalation to exhalation=1:2; and partial pressure end-tidal carbon dioxide (PETCO<sub>2</sub>), 35–45 mmHg maintained by adjusting the tidal volume and respiratory rate. During the surgery, anesthesia was maintained by continuous infusion of 0.5 μg/kg/h dexmedetomidine combined with inhalation of sevoflurane, with the lowest alveolar effective concentration of sevoflurane ≥0.6. In addition, during the surgery, intermittent intravenous injection of 0.08 mg/kg cisatracurium and 0.5 ug/kg sufentanil was used to maintain the bispectral index (BIS) at 40–60. Vascular active drugs such as norepinephrine, dobutamine, milrinone, nitroglycerin, and isoproterenol were used to maintain hemodynamic stability during the operation. During cardiopulmonary bypass (CPB), the temperature was maintained between 28°C and 30°C, the flow between 2.0 and 2.4 L/ (min/m<sup>2</sup>), and mean arterial pressure (MAP) between 50 and 80 mm Hg. Before discontinuing CPB, the patients were warmed back to 36–37°C. All patients received patient-controlled intravenous analgesia (PCIA) using the following formula: sufentanil (100 ug) + butorphanol tartaric acid injection (5 mg) + ondansetron (16 mg), diluted to 100 mL in normal saline, infused at a rate of 3 mL/h. All patients were transferred to the intensive care unit (ICU) with tracheal catheters after surgery. After arriving at the ICU, remimazolam and remifentanil were used for sedation and analgesia, respectively, until the tracheal catheter was removed according to the tracheal extubation standard.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Interventions</title>
        <p>Starting 2 days preoperatively, patients in the NS and INS groups received 0.5 mL of intranasal saline (0.5 mL) or insulin (20 U), respectively, twice daily at 09:00 AM and 19:00 PM using a nasal mucosal atomization device with a syringe (Wuxi Good Life Technology Co., Ltd., Jiangsu, China). The final dose was administered 10 min before induction of anesthesia on the operative day for five administrations.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2006">
        <title>Data Collection and Measurements</title>
        <p>The demographics and medical histories of the patients were recorded, including age, sex, body mass index (BMI), MMSE score, ASA classification, New York Heart Association (NYHA) grade, operation time, CPB time, intraoperative blood transfusion volume, total amount of crystalloids administered during surgery, intraoperative blood loss, urine volume, and numerical rating scale (NRS) score during the first three postoperative days.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2007">
        <title>Primary Endpoint</title>
        <p>The patients completed a preoperative cognitive state test using the MMSE before the first intervention. The primary outcome was the incidence of delirium within the first three postoperative days.</p>
        <p>In this study, the same researcher who was trained before the study and was not involved in the clinical care of the patients assessed delirium using the confusion assessment method for the intensive care unit (CAM-ICU) twice daily between 8:00–10:00 and 18:00–20:00. The CAM-ICU is a commonly used international scoring method that can help monitor the development and regression of delirium.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> The first evaluated the patient’s sedation status using the Richmond Agitation Scale (RASS). If the patient was able to awaken (RASS ≥-3 points), we continued the evaluation for delirium using CAM-ICU. If the RASS score was −4 or −5, the delirium assessment was conducted in the next time period. The CAM-ICU evaluation included the following characteristics: a) acute changes or fluctuations in the consciousness state, b) attention deficit, c) changes in the level of consciousness, and d) disordered thinking. Delirium was defined as the presence of a and b combined with either c or d. We also evaluated the occurrence of POD using the Delirium Scale Analysis System (CAM-CR)<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> with reference to the diagnostic criteria for delirium in the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (4<sup>th</sup> Edition) (DSMIV),<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> at the same time points as the CAM-ICU evaluation. The CAM-CR evaluation assigned a total possible score of 44 points according to the severity of 11 scoring items, including acute onset, attention disorder, confusion, change in consciousness level, disorientation, memory decline, perception disorder, psychomotor sexual arousal, psychomotor retardation, fluctuation, and change in sleep-wake cycle. Scores of ≤19, 20–22, and ≥22 points indicated no delirium, suspected delirium, and delirium, respectively.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2008">
        <title>Secondary Endpoints</title>
        <sec id="s0002-s2008-s3001">
          <title>Biochemical Tests</title>
          <p>At three time points before the first intervention (T0), 1 d before surgery (T1), and before the anesthesia on the day of the surgery (T2), 3 mL of venous blood was extracted and centrifuged to obtain serum, which was frozen and stored at −80°C. Serum cortisol concentrations were measured using enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA). The reagents were purchased from Shanghai Fanke Biotechnology Co., Ltd., and the measurements were performed according to the manufacturer’s instructions.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2008-s3002">
          <title>Assessment of Sleep Quality</title>
          <p>The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> includes seven scoring items: sleep quality, time to fall asleep, sleep time, sleep efficiency, sleep disorders, daytime dysfunction, and hypnotics. Each item is scored using four grades (0, 1, 2, and 3). The cumulative score for each scoring item is the total score of the PSQI (total score: 0–21), with higher scores indicating worse sleep quality.</p>
          <p>The deep sleep ratio, light sleep ratio, rapid eye movement (REM) sleep ratio, number of awakenings, deep sleep continuity score, and total sleep quality score from the previous night were recorded using a sleep monitoring watch (HUAWEI WATCH GT 2e) and were summarized.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2008-s3003">
          <title>Assessment of Postoperative Pain</title>
          <p>The NRS<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> score for pain was 0, 1–3, 4–6, and 7–1- points for no, mild, moderate, and severe pain, respectively.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2009">
        <title>Adverse Events</title>
        <p>Continuous glucose monitoring system (Shenzhen Silicon-based Sensing Technology Co., Ltd., Shenzhen, China) was used to dynamically track blood glucose levels during the trial. The glucometer recorded the number of hypoglycemia events per day and the average blood glucose values of the patients. Hypoglycemia was defined as a blood glucose value on a continuous dynamic blood glucose monitor of &lt;3.9 mmol/L.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2010">
        <title>Sample Size and Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>The sample size calculation was based on the total incidence of delirium within 3 days after surgery and was calculated using PASS 15 software. Research has shown that the incidence of postoperative delirium in cardiac surgery ranges from 4.1% to 54.9%.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Looking back at the past three years, the incidence of postoperative delirium in our hospital is approximately 46%.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Pre-trials showed a 15% incidence of POD in patients following repeated 20 U intranasal insulin interventions. Hence, this trial required 31 patients in each group with a power of 80% at a significance of α = 0.05. We recruited 76 patients (38 in each group, assuming a 20% dropout rate).</p>
        <p>The collected data were analyzed using IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows, version 26.0 (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, USA). Outcome analyzes were based on Per-Protocol. Continuous data were first tested using the Shapiro–Wilk test to verify a normal distribution. Continuous data with normal distributions are expressed as means ± standard deviation (SD) and analyzed using the independent <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test. Continuous data with non-normal distributions are expressed as medians (interquartile range) and analyzed using the Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test. Categorical variables are expressed as frequencies or percentages and analyzed using Pearson’s chi-square or Fisher’s exact tests. Repeated measures analysis of variance was used to determine the significance of the differences in the changes over time in mean serum cortisol across the groups, with a Dunnett’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test applied to each time point, separately for each group. P &lt;0 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2011">
        <title>Quality Control</title>
        <p>Data accuracy was monitored by the Quality Control Division of the Clinical Research Ethics Committee of the General Hospital of Western Theater Command.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Patient Inclusion</title>
        <p>We initially enrolled 76 patients in this study. After considering the inclusion, exclusion, and withdrawal criteria, the final statistical analyses included data from 71 patients (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). The two groups had similar demographics and medical histories. Patient age, sex, BMI, MMSE score, ASA classification, NYHA grade, operation time, CPB time, intraoperative blood transfusion volume, total amount of crystalloids administered during surgery, intraoperative blood loss, urine volume, or numerical rating scale (NRS) score during the first 3 postoperative days did not differ between the groups (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Patient Demographics and Clinical Data</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS group (n=35)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">INS group (n=36)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.791<sup>$</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex (male)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (40%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (33.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.560<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body mass index (kg/m²)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.34 ± 2.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.25 ± 2.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.164<sup>&amp;</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MMSE score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.71 ± 2.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.89 ± 1.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.723<sup>&amp;</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASA classification</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.350<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (25.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (16.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (74.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (83.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NYHA grade</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.386<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (25.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (22.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (40%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (55.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (34.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (22.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Operation time (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">254.46 ± 47.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256.61 ± 42.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.841<sup>&amp;</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bypass duration (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">114.57 ± 32.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109.64 ± 31.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.515<sup>&amp;</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intraoperative blood transfusion volume (mL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">700 (200)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">700 (275)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.977<sup>$</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total amount of crystalloids provided during surgery (mL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">350 (100)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">400 (200)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.062<sup>$</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intraoperative blood loss (mL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">600 (300)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">600 (275)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.884<sup>$</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine output (mL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">801.43 ± 274.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">812.50 ± 215.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.851<sup>&amp;</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NRS score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5 (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.490<sup>$</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.990<sup>$</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.701<sup>$</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Data are presented as mean ± SD, median (interquartile range), or percentage (proportion). <sup>$</sup>Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test; <sup>&amp;</sup>Independent <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test; <sup>#</sup>Pearson chi-square test.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: T3, postoperative day 1; T4, postoperative day 2; T5, postoperative day 3; MMSE, Mini-Mental State Examination; ASA, American Society of Anesthesiologists; NYHA, New York Heart Association; NRS, numerical rating scale.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Study flow diagram.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-613-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>POD Prevalence and CAM-CR Scores</title>
        <p>Compared to the NS group, the INS group demonstrated a decreased POD prevalence within 3 days postoperatively [51.4% (95% CI, 34.28–68.28) vs 22.2% (95% CI, 10.72–39.58), respectively, P = 0.011]. Compared to the NS group, the CAM-CR scores of the INS group significantly decreased on the first and second postoperative days (P&lt;0.05) (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Incidence of POD and CAM-CR Scores During the First Three Postoperative Day</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postoperative Days</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS group (n=35)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">INS group (n=36)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">cOR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">POD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1AM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (48.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (22.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.31 (1.18–9.24)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020<sup>a#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 PM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (45.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (16.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.21 (1.40–12.65)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008<sup>a#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 AM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (40%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (13.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.13 (1.29–13.21)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013<sup>a#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 PM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (28.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (8.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.40 (1.10–17.68)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027<sup>a#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 AM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (11.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.52 (1.18–42.59)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.199*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 PM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (5.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.239*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within 3 days of surgery</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (51.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (22.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.71 (1.33–10.36)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011<sup>a#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAM-CR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 AM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000<sup>a$</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 PM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000<sup>a$</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 AM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000<sup>a$</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 PM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000<sup>a$</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 AM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.178<sup>$</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 PM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.344<sup>$</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Data are presented as percentage (proportion) or median (interquartile range). <sup>a</sup>P &lt; 0.05 for comparison between two groups. <sup>$</sup>Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test; <sup>#</sup>Pearson chi-square test; *Fisher’s exact test.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: CAM-CR, Delirium Scale Analysis System; POD, postoperative delirium.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>PSQI Scores and Sleep Monitoring-Related Indicators Before Surgery</title>
        <p>Compared with the NS group, the INS group showed significantly reduced PSOI scores, light sleep ratio, and number of awakenings and significantly higher deep sleep ratio, REM sleep ratio, deep sleep continuity score, and total sleep quality score (P&lt;0.05) (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>PSQI Scores and Sleep Monitoring-Related Indicators Before Surgery</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time Point</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS group (n=35)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">INS group (n=36)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.739</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Deep sleep ratio (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Light sleep ratio (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">REM sleep ratio (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Number of awakenings</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Deep sleep continuity score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81 (4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81 (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Total sleep quality score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 (21)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.5 (7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 (18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000<sup>a</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Data are presented as median (interquartile range). Comparisons between two groups were performed using the Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test. <sup>a</sup>P &lt; 0.05 for comparison between two groups.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0006"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index; NS, normal saline; INS, insulin; REM, random eye movement; T0, before the first intervention; T1, one day before surgery; T2, before anesthesia on the day of the surgery.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Serum Cortisol Concentrations at Different Time Points</title>
        <p>Compared to the baseline values at T0, the NS and INS groups showed significantly increased and decreased serum cortisol concentrations, respectively, at T1 and T2 (both P&lt;0.05). Compared to the NS group, the serum cortisol concentration in the INS group at T1 and T2 was significantly reduced (P&lt;0.05) (<xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Serum Cortisol Concentrations at Different Time Points (Mmol/L)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time Point</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS group (n=35)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">INS group (n=36)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic>(group)/ <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic>(time)/ <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic>(group*time)/ <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">192.61 ± 12.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">195.35 ± 12.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic>=26.032<break/><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic>=11.803<break/><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic>=115.927<break/><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">212.00 ± 16.50 <sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">185.99 ± 13.92 <sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">210.50 ± 17.57 <sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">183.19 ± 15.28 <sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0007"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Data are expressed as mean ± SD. Comparisons between two groups were performed using the Dunnett-<italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test. Repeated measurements were compared using repeated measure ANOVA. <sup>a</sup>P &lt;0.05 vs T0; <sup>b</sup>P &lt;0.05 vs the NS group; * multiplication symbol.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0008"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: NS, normal saline; INS, insulin; T0, before the first intervention; T1, one day before surgery; T2, before anesthesia on the day of the surgery.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2005">
        <title>Adverse Events</title>
        <p>During the trial, none of the patients experienced hypoglycemic reactions. The average blood glucose levels at T1 and T2 were similar between the two groups (P&gt;0.05) (<xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Average Blood Glucose Values at Different Time Points (Mmol/L)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time Point</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS group (n=35)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">INS group (n=36)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.38+0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.37+0.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.922</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.27+0.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.35+0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.355</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0009"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: are expressed as mean ± SD. Comparisons between two groups were performed using the independent <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0010"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: NS, normal saline; INS, insulin; T1, one day before surgery; T2, before anesthesia on the day of the surgery.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In this study, the results show that In patients with rheumatic heart disease undergoing valve replacement, nasal insulin administered two days before surgery significantly improved preoperative sleep quality and reduced POD incidence.</p>
      <p>POD in patients undergoing cardiac surgery is an acute psychiatric disorder that is a common, serious, and even fatal complication of CPB. POD may lead to patient intolerance of luminal drains and endotracheal intubation;<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> increased incidence of complications such as cardiovascular disease, pneumonia, and urinary tract infection; prolonged hospital stay; increased medical costs and mortality;<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> and high incidence of negative clinical effects, seriously affecting postoperative recovery.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> The incidence of delirium after cardiac surgery ranges from 4.1% to 54.9%.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> In this study, the incidence of POD in the NS group was as high as 51.4%; therefore, corresponding preventive measures should be implemented for such patients.</p>
      <p>Multiple multifactorial intervention studies have reported that sleep disorders increase the risk of POD.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> Preoperative tension in patients often leads to disturbances in the sleep-awakening cycle (with a significant increase in the percentage of awakening time to total sleep time), leading to abnormal hyperactivity of the HPA axis (which plays an important role in maintaining alertness and regulating sleep), excessive cortisol secretion, and effects on cognitive function.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> In addition, sleep disorders or decreased sleep quality may cause an increase in pro-inflammatory cytokine levels; a decrease in the number of central hippocampal neurons; changes in the density of hippocampal dendritic spines; changes in the number, morphology, and function of synapses; and a decrease in white matter volume and quality, leading to impaired memory function and spatial cognition in patients. Surgical trauma, pain, and other factors could further exacerbate the lack of concentration, emotional fluctuations, and cognitive decline caused by the disturbance of the sleep-awakening cycle before surgery, ultimately leading to POD.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27–29</xref> In their meta-analysis of 12 studies on the relationship between preoperative sleep disorders and POD, Fadayomi et al<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> found that preoperative sleep disorders may be related to POD. The findings of these studies demonstrate the association between disordered sleep and POD risk. However, whether the treatment of patients with preoperative sleep disorders can reduce the morbidity, incidence rate, and medical costs of POD remains to be determined. Another systematic review<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> showed that some data support health strategies targeting sleep and circadian rhythm regulation as useful methods for preventing POD. Guo et al<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> randomly assigned 160 elderly patients with oral cancer who underwent tumor resection surgery divided into two groups. One group received routine treatment, while the other received non-drug interventions. The non-drug intervention improved some of the discomfort caused by sleep disorders and reduced the incidence of POD while reducing cortisol concentrations and increasing melatonin concentrations.</p>
      <p>Insulin administered through the nose can cross the blood-brain barrier and reach the central nervous system. Insulin inhibits secretion by the HPA axis by acting on the hypothalamic nucleus and marginal structures (such as the hippocampus) that can express many insulin receptors, ultimately improving sleep cycle disorders.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Ritze et al<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> showed a decrease in serum cortisol concentration after 2 weeks of nasal administration of insulin before nighttime sleep, which was beneficial for memory formation. Feld et al<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> studied the effect of nasal insulin on sleep in 16 men and 16 women, in which brain insulin improved memory by inhibiting active forgetting during sleep and reducing interference by encoding new information. In the present study, compared with the saline group, patients in the insulin group had better preoperative sleep quality and lower serum cortisol concentration and POD incidence. These findings suggest that the nasal administration of insulin may inhibit the HPA axis, reduce cortisol release, and improve sleep, thereby reducing the occurrence of POD. This research result can provide strong evidence for perioperative nasal insulin preconditioning to prevent postoperative delirium. The specific mechanism by which intranasal insulin can reduce postoperative delirium by improving sleep needs to be further explored through animal experiments in the future.</p>
      <p>However, this study has some limitations: 1) The sample size is relatively small, which may affect the results of some statistical analyses. These results require further validation in large-scale multicenter studies including a wider variety of patients. 2) The follow-up time for POD was relatively short, which can lead to omissions in the evaluation of postoperative delirium patients. 3) The type of valve replacement surgery was not determined. 4) The treatment plan for patients with POD was not tracked. 5) The duration of the reduction of serum cortisol concentration by intranasal insulin has not been followed up, and the exploration time can be extended in the future to more fully elucidate the benefits of intranasal insulin.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Our experimental results indicate that repeated nasal insulin administration before surgery may reduce the incidence of POD within 3 days after surgery, improve preoperative sleep quality, and reduce preoperative serum cortisol concentration in patients with rheumatic heart disease undergoing valve replacement surgery.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We thank the medical staff who participated in this study. We would also like to thank the English editor (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="http://www.Editage.com" ext-link-type="uri">www.Editage.com</ext-link></underline>).</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <p>ASA, American Society of Anesthesiologists; BIS, bispectral index; CAM-CR, Delirium Scale Analysis System; CAM-ICU, confusion assessment method for the intensive care unit; CPB, cardiopulmonary bypass; DSMIV, Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (4th Edition); HPA, hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal; FIO<sub>2</sub>, concentration of inhaled oxygen; ICU, intensive care unit; INS, insulin; MAP, mean arterial pressure; MMSE, Mini-Mental State Examination; NRS, numerical rating scale; NS, normal saline; PCIA, patient-controlled intravenous analgesia; PCV-VG, pressure control volume guarantee; PETCO<sub>2</sub>, partial pressure end-tidal carbon dioxide, POD, postoperative delirium; PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index; RASS, Richmond Agitation Scale; REM, rapid eye movement; SD, standard deviation; T0, before the first intervention; T1, 1 day before surgery; T2, before anesthesia on the day of surgery; T3, postoperative day 1; T4, postoperative day 2; T5, postoperative day 5.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s0007">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p>The raw data for this study have been uploaded to <underline><ext-link xlink:href="http://www.medresman.org.cn" ext-link-type="uri">www.medresman.org.cn</ext-link></underline> and are also available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0008">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation, or in all these areas; took part in drafting, revising or critically reviewing the article; gave final approval of the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0009">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Panduranga</surname>
<given-names>VT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gorantla</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ahmed</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sabu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mallappallil</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>John</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A rare case of congestive heart failure due to isolated aortic valve disease in a middle-aged man secondary to rheumatic fever</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Med Cases</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>154</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14740/jmc4090</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37303970</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Preoperative slow-wave sleep is associated with postoperative delirium after heart valve surgery: a prospective pilot study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<fpage>e13920</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.13920</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37147892</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gaykova</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Circadian rest-activity rhythms, delirium risk, and progression to dementia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>93</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1145</fpage>–<lpage>1157</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ana.26617</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36808743</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ni</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dong</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Preoperative sleep disturbance exaggerates surgery-induced neuroinflammation and neuronal damage in aged mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mediators Inflamm</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>2019</volume>:<fpage>8301725</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2019/8301725</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31011286</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gray</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Milner</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McEwen</surname>
<given-names>BS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dynamic plasticity: the role of glucocorticoids, brain-derived neurotrophic factor and other trophic factors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroscience</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>239</volume>:<fpage>214</fpage>–<lpage>227</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroscience.2012.08.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22922121</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Maniaci</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Di Luca</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lechien</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Lateral pharyngoplasty vs. traditional uvulopalatopharyngoplasty for patients with OSA: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1539</fpage>–<lpage>1550</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-021-02520-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34978022</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Maniaci</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Riela</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Iannella</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Machine learning identification of obstructive sleep apnea severity through the patient clinical features: a retrospective study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Life</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>702</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/life13030702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36983857</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>O’Gara</surname>
<given-names>BP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marcantonio</surname>
<given-names>ER</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Subramaniam</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep, pain, and cognition: modifiable targets for optimal perioperative brain health</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Anesthesiology</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>135</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1132</fpage>–<lpage>1152</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ALN.0000000000004046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34731233</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ibala</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mekonnen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gitlin</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A polysomnography study examining the association between sleep and postoperative delirium in older hospitalized cardiac surgical patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e13322</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.13322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33759264</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impact of Preoperative Sleep Disturbances on Postoperative Delirium in Patients with Intracranial Tumors: a Prospective, Observational, Cohort Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Sci Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1093</fpage>–<lpage>1105</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S432829</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38149043</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effect of preoperative sleep disorders on delirium in proximal femoral surgery patients aged 60 or older</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Anesthesiol</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>376</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12871-023-02331-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37978346</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Thienel</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilhelm</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benedict</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Born</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hallschmid</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Intranasal insulin decreases circulating cortisol concentrations during early sleep in elderly humans</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurobiol Aging</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>170</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neurobiolaging.2017.03.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28385552</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Qin</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Repeated preoperative intranasal administration of insulin decreases the incidence of postoperative delirium in elderly patients undergoing laparoscopic radical gastrointestinal surgery: a randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blinded clinical study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Geriatr Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1202</fpage>–<lpage>1211</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jagp.2021.02.043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33757723</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Durlach</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khoury</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Donato</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Delirium and subsyndromal delirium in the intensive care unit: in-hospital outcomes and prognosis at discharge</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Med Clin</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>S0025-7753</volume>(<issue>23</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.medcli.2023.05.012</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bai</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The effect of parecoxib sodium on postoperative delirium in elderly patients with Hip arthroplasty</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Pharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>947982</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphar.2023.947982</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37025488</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mo</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ou</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Risk factors of postoperative delirium after cardiac surgery: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cardiothorac Surg</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13019-021-01496-w</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mazgelytė</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Valatkevičiūtė</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Songailienė</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Utkus</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burokienė</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Karčiauskaitė</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association of hair glucocorticoid levels with sleep quality indicators: a pilot study in apparently healthy perimenopausal and menopausal women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Endocrinol</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1186014</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fendo.2023.1186014</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Côté</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The one-week prevalence of neck pain and low back pain in post-secondary students at two Canadian institutions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chiropr Man Therap</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>23</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12998-023-00496-y</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Frias</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deenadayalan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Erichsen</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Efficacy and safety of co-administered once-weekly cagrilintide 2·4 mg with once-weekly semaglutide 2·4 mg in type 2 diabetes: a multicentre, randomised, double-blind, active-controlled, Phase 2 trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>402</volume>(<issue>10403</issue>):<fpage>720</fpage>–<lpage>730</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(23)01163-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37364590</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yuan</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of dexmedetomidine combined with sufentanil on postoperative delirium in young patients after general anesthesia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Med Sci Monit</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>8925</fpage>–<lpage>8932</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12659/MSM.911366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30531676</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ushio</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Egi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fujimoto</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Obata</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mizobuchi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Timing, threshold, and duration of intraoperative hypotension in cardiac surgery: their associations with postoperative delirium</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>4062</fpage>–<lpage>4069</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.jvca.2022.06.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35915006</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hulde</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zittermann</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tigges-Limmer</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Preoperative risk factors and early outcomes of delirium in valvular open-heart surgery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>70</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>558</fpage>–<lpage>565</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0041-1740984</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35042244</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Soh</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shim</surname>
<given-names>JK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Choi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kwak</surname>
<given-names>YL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Preoperative transcranial Doppler and cerebral oximetry as predictors of delirium following valvular heart surgery: a case-control study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Monit Comput</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>715</fpage>–<lpage>723</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10877-019-00385-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31482364</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yan</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effect of sleep disorder on delirium in post-cardiac surgery patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Can J Neurol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>627</fpage>–<lpage>633</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/cjn.2020.62</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32234103</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Evans</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nadler</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Preud’homme</surname>
<given-names>XA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Pilot prospective study of post-surgery sleep and EEG predictors of post-operative delirium</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Neurophysiol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>128</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1421</fpage>–<lpage>1425</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinph.2017.05.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28618293</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buckley</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schatzberg</surname>
<given-names>AF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>On the interactions of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis and sleep: normal HPA axis activity and circadian rhythm, exemplary sleep disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Endocrinol Metab</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>90</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>3106</fpage>–<lpage>3114</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.2004-1056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15728214</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dong</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jia</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Relationship of sleep disturbance and postoperative delirium: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Gland Surg</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1192</fpage>–<lpage>1203</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/gs-22-312</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35935571</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Correlation between preoperative sleep disorders and postoperative delayed neurocognitive recovery in elderly patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Zhong Nan Da Xue Xue Bao Yi Xue Ban</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1251</fpage>–<lpage>1259</lpage>. <comment>English, Chinese</comment>.doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11817/j.issn.1672-7347.2021.210015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34911860</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cerejeira</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Batista</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nogueira</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vaz-Serra</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mukaetova-Ladinska</surname>
<given-names>EB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The stress response to surgery and postoperative delirium: evidence of hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis hyperresponsiveness and decreased suppression of the GH/IGF-1 Axis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Geriatr Psychiatry Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>185</fpage>–<lpage>194</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0891988713495449</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23864592</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fadayomi</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ibala</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bilotta</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Westover</surname>
<given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Akeju</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A systematic review and meta-analysis examining the impact of sleep disturbance on postoperative delirium</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>e1204</fpage>–<lpage>e1212</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/CCM.0000000000003400</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30222634</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>YW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Promoting sleep and circadian health may prevent postoperative delirium: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized clinical trials</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>101207</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2019.08.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31505369</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impact of multicomponent, nonpharmacologic interventions on perioperative cortisol and melatonin levels and postoperative delirium in elderly oral cancer patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Gerontol Geriatr</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>112</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.archger.2015.10.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26547518</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mamik</surname>
<given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Asahchop</surname>
<given-names>EL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>WF</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insulin treatment prevents neuroinflammation and neuronal injury with restored neurobehavioral function in models of HIV/AIDS neurodegeneration</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>41</issue>):<fpage>10683</fpage>–<lpage>10695</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1287-16.2016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27733618</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ritze</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kern</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ebner</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jahn</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benedict</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hallschmid</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Metabolic and cognitive outcomes of subchronic once-daily intranasal insulin administration in healthy men</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Endocrinol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>663</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fendo.2018.00663</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Feld</surname>
<given-names>GB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilhem</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benedict</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Central nervous insulin signaling in sleep-associated memory formation and neuroendocrine regulation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropsychopharmacology</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1540</fpage>–<lpage>1550</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/npp.2015.312</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26448203</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
