<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38911316</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">11192637</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">459690</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S459690</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Difficulty Falling Asleep is Associated with Poorer Therapeutic Outcomes in Unilateral Hypoglossal Nerve Stimulation</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Pordzik et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Pordzik et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pordzik</surname><given-names>Johannes</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Petrowski</surname><given-names>Katja</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6462-3763</contrib-id><name><surname>Ludwig</surname><given-names>Katharina</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Seifen</surname><given-names>Christopher</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Matthias</surname><given-names>Christoph</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7299-7346</contrib-id><name><surname>Gouveris</surname><given-names>Haralampos</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Otolaryngology, Head and Neck Surgery &amp; Sleep Medicine Center, University Medical Center Mainz</institution>, <addr-line>Mainz</addr-line>, <addr-line>55131</addr-line>, <country>Germany</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Medical Psychology and Medical Sociology, Medical Center of the Johannes Gutenberg University Mainz</institution>, <addr-line>Mainz</addr-line>, <country>Germany</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Johannes Pordzik, <institution>Department of Otolaryngology, Head and Neck Surgery &amp; Sleep Medicine Center, University Medical Center Mainz</institution>, <addr-line>Mainz</addr-line>, <addr-line>55131</addr-line>, <country>Germany</country>, Email johannes.pordzik@unimedizin-mainz.de</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>6</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>813</fpage><lpage>821</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Pordzik et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Pordzik et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Purpose</title><p>The coexistence of insomnia and obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) is very prevalent. Hypoglossal nerve stimulation (HGNS) is an established second-line therapy for patients suffering OSA. Studies investigating the effect of the different aspects of insomnia on the therapeutic outcome are largely missing. Therefore, this study aimed to understand the impact of the different aspects of insomnia on the therapeutic outcome under HGNS therapy in clinical routine.</p></sec><sec><title>Patients and Methods</title><p>This is a retrospective study including 30 consecutive patients aged 55.40 ± 8.83 years (8 female; 22 male) undergoing an HGNS implantation in our tertiary medical center between 2020 and 2023. All patients underwent preoperative polysomnography (PSG) according to AASM. First follow-up PSG was performed 95.40 ± 39.44 days after activation (30 patients) and second follow-up PSG was performed 409.89 ± 122.52 days after activation (18 patients). Among others, the following PSG-related parameters were evaluated: apnea–hypopnea index (n/h) (AHI) and oxygen desaturation index (n/h) (ODI). Insomnia was assessed by the insomnia severity index (ISI) questionnaire. Preoperatively, all patients included filled out each ISI item. Spearman's-rho correlation coefficient was calculated for correlations.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Preoperative score of ISI item 1 (difficulty falling asleep) was 1.93 ± 1.34 and preoperative cumulative ISI score (item1-7) was 18.67 ± 5.32. Preoperative AHI was 40.61 ± 12.02 (n/h) and preoperative ODI was 38.72 ± 14.28 (n/h). In the second follow-up, the mean difference in AHI was ∆ 10.47 ± 15.38 (n/h) and the mean difference in ODI was ∆ 8.17 ± 15.67 (n/h). Strong significant correlations were observed between ISI item 1 (difficulty falling asleep) and both ∆ AHI (r: −0.65, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.004) and ∆ ODI (r: −0.7; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.001) in the second follow-up.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Difficulty falling asleep may hence negatively influence HGNS therapeutic outcome. Insomnia-related symptoms should be considered in the preoperative patient evaluation for HGNS.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>hypoglossal nerve stimulation</kwd><kwd>obstructive sleep apnea</kwd><kwd>insomnia</kwd><kwd>polysomnography</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>funding</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>No funding was received for this study.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="4"/><ref-count count="26"/><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) is a highly prevalent sleep disorder. OSA is characterized by recurrent episodes of partial and/or complete upper airway obstructions during sleep that lead to apnea and hypopnea.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Besides OSA, insomnia is another highly prevalent sleep disorder. Insomnia is defined as an individually reported difficulty with sleep.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Even though both are considered as separate diseases, they often occur concomitantly. Insomnia-related symptoms are reported by up to 50% of patients suffering OSA and up to 40% of patients suffering from chronic insomnia also meet the diagnostic criteria for OSA.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> The coexistence of insomnia and obstructive sleep apnea (COMISA) is clinical highly relevant. COMISA is associated with worse therapeutic outcomes and higher costs compared to the treatment of either OSA or insomnia.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> The standard in OSA therapy is continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) therapy.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Hypoglossal nerve stimulation (HGNS) is an established therapeutic options for patients not tolerating PAP-therapy.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> PAP-therapy compliance is especially reduced in patients suffering COMISA.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Previous studies have reported an association between insomnia and poorer apnea–hypopnea index (AHI) reduction<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> as well as shorter usage of HGNS during the night<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> and patient-reported outcomes such as daytime sleepiness.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> In contrast, one study showed no significant difference in therapy adherence and efficacy between ISI severity subgroups.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Insomnia is a complex sleeping disorder involving different symptoms such as difficulty falling asleep, difficulty staying asleep and/or waking too early, and is often related to hyperalertness and fatigue.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Insomnia may be suspected by a brief screening seven‐item questionnaire named the insomnia severity index (ISI) addressing all aforementioned aspects.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> A few studies already aimed to investigate the impact of insomnia on objective and patient-reported outcomes such as AHI reduction, therapy adherence and daytime sleepiness.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9–12</xref> However, studies investigating the effect of the different aspects of insomnia on the therapeutic outcome are largely missing. Therefore, this exploratory study aimed to understand the impact of the different aspects of insomnia on the therapeutic outcome under HGNS therapy in clinical routine.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <p>This study included 30 consecutive patients undergoing an implantation of inspiration-coupled HGNS (Inspire Medical Systems, Inc., Golden Valley, MN, USA) between 2020 and 2023. Patients included had to fulfil the indication criteria for HGNS therapy<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> such as intolerance to PAP therapy, body mass index (BMI) &lt; 35 kg/m<sup>2</sup>, absence of complete velar concentric collapse on drug-induced sleep endoscopy (DISE), apnea–hypopnea index (AHI) 15–65/h with &lt;25% central apneas on polysomnography (PSG), and the absence of chronic major psychiatric or neurodegenerative disease. All patients included had filled in a complete preoperative ISI questionnaire. The German version of the ISI questionnaire was used.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> The following questions are included and must be voted on a five-point Likert scale:</p>
      <p>Please rate the CURRENT (ie LAST 2 WEEKS) SEVERITY of your insomnia problem(s)
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Difficulty falling asleep</p></list-item><list-item><p>Difficulty staying asleep</p></list-item><list-item><p>Problems waking up too early</p></list-item><list-item><p>How satisfied/dissatisfied are you with your current sleep pattern?</p></list-item><list-item><p>How NOTICEABLE to others do you think your sleep problem is in terms of impairing the quality of your life?</p></list-item><list-item><p>How worried/distressed are you about your current sleep problem?</p></list-item><list-item><p>To what extent do you consider your sleep problem to INTERFERE with your daily functioning (eg daytime fatigue, mood, ability to function at work/daily chores, concentration, memory, mood, etc). currently?</p></list-item></list></p>
      <p>An increasing score indicates an increasing clinically relevant insomnia.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> All patients underwent preoperative polysomnography (PSG) according to the AASM standard. Furthermore, a velar concentric collapse was ruled out by preoperative DISE. First PSG follow-up was performed 95.40 ± 39.44 days after activation and second follow-up was performed 409.89 ± 122.52 days after activation. First follow-up was performed in all 30 patients, second follow-up was performed in 18 patients. All follow-up PSGs were performed without any in-laboratory titration. Stimulation parameters under PSG were identical to the patient’s stimulation parameters as used at the patients’ homes for at least one week before in-laboratory PSG.</p>
      <p>The following PSG-related parameters were investigated: apnea–hypopnea index (n/h) (AHI), cumulative time under apnea and hypopnea (min), snoring index (n/h) (SI), oxygen desaturation index (n/h) (ODI), percentage of total sleep time under oxygen saturation lower than 90% (t90) and total number of arousal events per hour (arousal index (n/h)). PSG was evaluated by our team's experts in the field of sleep medicine.</p>
      <p>All patients provided informed consent to the use of their data for research purposes. The data were evaluated in a pseudonymized fashion. Only health data that are collected in the clinical routine were analyzed retrospectively. So-called “third parties” did not have access to the data and publication occurs exclusively in anonymized form. The Ethics Committee of the Rhineland-Palatinate Medical Association refrains from providing advice in such cases, citing the State Hospital Act (§36 and §37) (see also: <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.laek-rlp.de/ausschuesse-kommissionen/ethikkommission/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.laek-rlp.de/ausschuesse-kommissionen/ethikkommission/</ext-link></underline>).</p>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>Statistical analysis was performed using SPSS 27 (IBM, Armonk, NY, USA). All data were expressed as mean ± standard deviation. Wilcoxon’s signed-rank test was performed for inner-group comparison. Preoperative as well as for the short-term follow-up all patients included filled out each ISI item. Only 12 patients filled out each ISI item in the long-term follow-up. Spearman's-rho correlation coefficient was calculated for correlations. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.05 was considered a statistically significant result. For correlation coefficients Bonferroni correction was performed. Therefore <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.004 was considered a statistically significant result. Post-hoc power calculation was performed using an online power calculator<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> with α=0.05 and n=18.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>Patients were aged <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 55.40 ± 8.83 years at the time of implantation of the HGNS system with an average BMI of <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 29.69 ± 4.32 kg/m<sup>2</sup>. Eight patients were female, 22 patients were male. Preoperative AHI was <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 40.61 ± 12.02 (n/h), preoperative complete time of apnoea and hypopnea was <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 86.2 ± 40.2 (min), preoperative snoring index <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 244.26 ± 181.14 (n/h), preoperative ODI was <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 38.72 ± 14.28 (n/h), preoperative t90 (%) was <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 8.85 ± 10.35 and preoperative arousal index was <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 23.68 ± 15.59 (n/h).</p>
      <p>Preoperative scores of the separate ISI questionnaire were as follows: Question 1 was <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 1.93 ± 1.34, question 2 was <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 2.8 ± 1.00, question 3 was <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 1.97 ± 1.27, question 4 was <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 3.5 ± 0.73, question 5 was <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 2.33 ± 1.21, question 6 was <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 3.20 ± 1.03, question 7 was <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 2.97 ± 1.13. Mean of cumulative preoperative ISI was <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 18.67 ± 5.32 (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Mean of cumulative ISI was <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 12.7 ± 6.62 in the short-term follow-up and <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 10.08 ± 7.13 in the long-term follow-up. Preoperative cumulative ISI and cumulative ISI in the short-term follow-up differed (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.001) significantly as well as in the long-term follow-up (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.003). Preoperative Cronbach’s Alpha for items 1–7 was <italic toggle="yes">α</italic>=0.8 (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>ISI Score in the Preoperative, Short-Term Follow-Up and Long-Term Follow-Up</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI Score M (SD)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI 1 M (SD)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI 2 M (SD)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI 3 M (SD)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI 4 M (SD)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI 5 M (SD)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI 6 M (SD)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI 7 M (SD)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cronbach‘s Alpha for Items 1–7</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Preoperative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.67 ± 5.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.93 ± 1.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.80 ± 1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.97 ± 1.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.50 ± 0.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.33 ± 1.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.20 ± 1.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.97 ± 1.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short-term</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.70 ± 6.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47 ± 1.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.97 ± 1.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37 ± 1.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.13 ± 1.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.73 ± 1.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.93 ± 1.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.17 ± 1.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long-term</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.08 ± 7.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 ± 1.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75 ± 0.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42 ± 1.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67 ± 1.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 ± 1.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 ± 1.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50 ± 1.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Preoperative, short-term and long-term ISI score and score for each item of the ISI; Cronbach’s alpha for items 1–7; preoperative (α=0.80), short-term (α=0.88) and long-term (α=0.91).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p>In the short-term follow-up, the mean difference in AHI was ∆ 15.01 ± 12.15 (n/h), the mean difference in complete time of apnea and hypopnea was ∆ 34.40 ± 36.31 (min), the mean difference in snoring index was ∆ 89.68 ± 115.43 (n/h), the mean difference in ODI was ∆ 9.18 ± 13.21 (n/h), the mean difference in t90 was ∆ 2.49 ± 11.47 (%) and the mean difference in arousal index was ∆ 8.38 ± 16.51 (n/h) (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Patients and PSG Parameters</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Preoperative Parameter M (SD)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">∆ Short-term Follow-up M (SD)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">∆ Long-term Follow-up M (SD)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.40 ± 8.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.69 ± 4.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI (n/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.61 ± 12.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.01 ± 12.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.47 ± 15.38</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cumulative time under apnea and hypopnea (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.30 ± 40.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.40 ± 36.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.78 ± 34.23</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ODI (n/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.72 ± 14.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.18 ± 13.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.17 ± 15.67</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Snoring index (n/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">244.26 ± 181.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.68 ± 115.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.81 ± 158.75</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">t90 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.85 ± 10.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.49 ± 11.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.94 ± 10.44</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arousal index (n/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.68 ± 15.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.38 ± 16.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23 ± 14.32</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Clinical parameters: age, BMI; PSG-related parameters: AHI, ODI, complete time of apnoea and hypopnea (min), snoring index (n/h) (SI), oxygen desaturation index (n/h) (ODI), percentage of oxygen desaturation lower than 90% (t90) and total number of arousal events per hour (arousal index (n/h)).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p>In the long-term follow-up, the mean difference in AHI was ∆ 10.47 ± 15.38 (n/h), the mean difference in complete time of apnea and hypopnea was ∆ 25.78 ± 34.23 (min), the mean difference in snoring index was ∆ 65.81 ± 158.75 (n/h), the mean difference in ODI was ∆ 8.17 ± 15.67 (n/h), the mean difference in t90 was ∆ 3.94 ± 10.44 (%) and the mean difference in arousal index was ∆ 1.23 ± 14.32 (n/h) (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p>
      <p>In the short-term follow-up, no significant correlations were shown between the separate score for each one out of the seven ISI items and ∆ AHI, ∆ cumulative time of apnea and hypopnea, ∆ snoring index, ∆ ODI, ∆ t90 or ∆ arousal index (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Correlation Between ISI Score and Each ISI Item and ∆ PSG Parameter (Short-Term)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">∆ PSG Parameter</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI Preoperative</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI 1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI 2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI 3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI 4</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI 5</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI 6</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI 7</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">∆ AHI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.293</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.155</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.311</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.053</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.220</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.152</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.116</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.947</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.413</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.095</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.782</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.243</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.423</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">∆ Snoring index</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.062</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.199</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.081</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.152</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.254</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.088</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.224</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.745</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.291</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.671</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.423</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.175</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.644</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.234</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">∆ Cumulative apnea hypopnea time</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.212</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.032</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.107</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.245</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.045</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.260</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.866</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.574</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.191</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.513</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.598</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.815</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">∆ ODI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.341</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.158</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.338</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.086</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.177</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.093</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.065</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.963</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.405</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.068</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.653</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.349</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.626</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">∆ t90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.077</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.041</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.174</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.060</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.179</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.138</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.686</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.715</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.831</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.359</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.754</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.343</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.467</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">∆ Arousal index</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.267</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.212</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.135</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.226</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.280</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.181</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.139</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.154</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.261</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.476</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.230</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.134</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.339</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.463</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Correlation between ∆ PSG parameters such as ∆ AHI, ∆ snoring index, ∆ cumulative apnea hypopnea time, ∆ ODI, ∆ t90, ∆ arousal index and each item of the ISI questionnaire in the short-term follow-up.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p>In the long-term follow-up, significant strong negative correlations were shown between question one of the ISI questionnaire and ∆ AHI (r: −0.65, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.004), ∆ ODI (r: −0.7; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>= 0.001), ∆ t90 (r: −0.51; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.03) and ∆ arousal index (r: −0.64; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.04) (<xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> and <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figures 1</xref> and <xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Correlation Between ISI Score and Each ISI Item and ∆ PSG Parameter (Long-Term)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">∆ PSG Parameter</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI Preoperative</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI 1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI 2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI 3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI 4</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI 5</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI 6</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI 7</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">∆ AHI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.647*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.217</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.038</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.279</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.132</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.178</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.186</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.386</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.880</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.262</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.602</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.479</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.460</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">∆ ODI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.693*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.106</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.238</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.142</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.124</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.234</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.677</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.925</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.341</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.574</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.624</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.350</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">∆ Snoring index</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.141</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.216</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.104</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.404</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.042</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.104</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.578</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.898</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.388</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.682</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.868</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.682</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">∆ Cumulative apnea hypopnea time</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.411</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.094</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.180</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.278</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.230</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.026</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.165</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.090</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.710</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.474</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.264</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.359</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.917</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.512</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">∆ t90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.511</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.143</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.035</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.315</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.092</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.226</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.184</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.572</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.890</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.203</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.716</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.366</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.465</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">∆ Arousal index</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.644*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.519</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.425</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.084</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.102</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.107</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.076</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.078</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.741</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.686</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.671</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.763</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Correlation between ∆ PSG parameters such as ∆ AHI, ∆ snoring index, ∆ cumulative apnea hypopnea time, ∆ ODI, ∆ t90, ∆ arousal index and each separate item of the ISI questionnaire in the long-term follow-up. *Bonferroni corrected significant correlations.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Scatterplot ∆ AHI (n/h) in the long-term follow-up and preoperative ISI item 1.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-813-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig>
<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Scatterplot ∆ ODI (n/h) in the long-term follow-up and preoperative ISI item 1.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-813-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
      <p>A post-hoc power of 0.87 for the correlation coefficient between question one of the ISI questionnaire and ∆ AHI (r: −0.65) and a post-hoc power of 0.93 for the correlation coefficient between question one of the ISI questionnaire and ∆ ODI (r: −0.70) were calculated.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>We provide evidence for strong significant negative correlations between patient-reported scores to item one of the ISI questionnaire (i.e. difficulty falling asleep) and objective HGNS therapy outcome metrics such as the AHI, ODI and arousal index in long-term follow-up.</p>
      <p>This is one of the first studies investigating the association between the different insomnia-related symptoms on PSG-related metrics. A strong negative correlation between preoperative difficulty falling asleep and important PSG-related metrics in the one-year follow-up could be shown. One possible explanation for this fact could be a reduced therapy compliance (reduced device usage) in patients suffering some specific insomnia-related symptoms. The co-occurrence of OSA and insomnia may impair OSA treatment by reducing compliance with PAP therapy.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> Further studies demonstrated especially insomnia-related symptoms associated with lower PAP therapy adherence.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> PAP adherence is reduced in patients with initial and late insomnia at baseline.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Even if PAP adherence is reduced in patients suffering COMISA, insomnia-related symptoms are reduced under PAP therapy<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> as well as under HGNS therapy.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Insomnia symptoms are reported by up to 50% of patients suffering OSA and up to 40% patients suffering chronic insomnia also meet the diagnostic criteria for OSA.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> PAP-intolerance is a key indication criterion for considering HGNS treatment. Therefore, patients who are HGNS therapy candidates may actually be patients with more pronounced insomnia-related symptoms. Adherence to HGNS therapy may therefore be higher in patients without comorbid insomnia. However, two studies investigated the effect of insomnia on the HGNS therapy adherence.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Both reported no association between insomnia and HGNS therapy adherence. There was no significant difference between HGNS adherence in patients with OSA only compared to COMISA.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Furthermore, in the ADHERE registry no significant difference in therapy adherence between the group with preoperative ISI&lt;15 and preoperative ISI&gt;15 was observed.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> However, a general reduction in HGNS-therapy adherence over time was observed.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> This is a potential explanation of why a significant negative correlation was observed between preoperative difficulty falling asleep and important PSG-related metrics in the one-year follow-up but not in the short-term follow-up. Patients with increased difficulty falling asleep could therefore be more affected by reduced therapy adherence over time.</p>
      <p>There are different studies investigating the impact of insomnia on the therapeutic outcome under HGNS therapy measured by PSG-related parameters<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> as well as on patient-reported outcomes<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> and vice versa.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> However, the results are to date inconsistent. One study proved no significant difference in AHI reduction between a group with a preoperative ISI score &lt;15 and a group with a preoperative ISI score &gt;15.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Another study could prove a significant negative correlation between preoperative ISI score and postoperative AHI reduction in the short-term follow-up after three months.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></p>
      <p>Most of the existing studies reported an improved ISI score under HGNS therapy. One study demonstrated a clinically relevant ISI score reduction in a higher percentage of those patients treated with a HGNS therapy compared to PAP therapy.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> A significant ISI score reduction under HGNS therapy in the short-term follow-up has been reported before.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> In the ADHERE registry all patients had an improved ISI score at follow-up visits (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.001). These patients with higher preoperative ISI scores showed a greater reduction in insomnia-related symptoms compared to those with lower preoperative ISI scores, ISI≥15 compared with ISI&lt;15 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.05).<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> The same study showed significant improvement for the ISI score and for each item in the ISI score from baseline to post-titration (PT) and baseline to final visit:<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> ISI was reduced by −7 ± 6.17 from baseline to the first PSG-based titration and by −8.06 ± 7.27 from baseline to final visit. These results are comparable to the results of our study. We are reporting here a preoperative ISI score of 18.67 ± 5.32, a post-operative short-term ISI score of 12.7 ± 6.62 and a long-term post-operative ISI score of 10.08 ± 7.13 points. Furthermore, each item of the ISI score was improved from baseline to the first PSG-based titration post-titration with a further improvement post-titration to final visit.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Our study also showed an improvement in each item in the short-term follow-up with a further improvement in the long-term follow-up, except for item 3. Of note, our patients did not receive any in-laboratory HGNS device titration during the PSG night. Therefore, our reported results may more closely depict the respective metrics at the patients’ home.</p>
      <p>The result of our study with greater improvement in insomnia-related symptoms with longer therapy seems to be counterintuitive to the result of more improvement of PSG-related parameters in the short-term follow-up compared to long-term follow-up in our study. This indicates that not only PSG-related parameters are associated with insomnia-related patient-reported outcomes. Previously, one study provided evidence that cognitive behavioural therapy combined with PAP is superior to PAP alone on insomnia-related outcomes.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> Other authors showed an improvement in PAP therapy adherence and insomnia-related symptoms in patients suffering COMISA under cognitive behavioural therapy for insomnia.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> We therefore suggest that comorbid insomnia in OSA patients under consideration for or after HGNS implantation should gain more attention. Further studies, especially investigating the added value of any additional behavioural therapy for patients suffering comorbid OSA and insomnia under HGNS therapy, may provide clinical insight on this important issue.</p>
      <sec id="s0004-s2001">
        <title>Limitations</title>
        <p>Relevant limitations of our study are the relatively small sample size and the retrospective nature of this study. However, a sufficient post-hoc power of 0.87 for the correlation coefficient between question one of the ISI questionnaire and ∆ AHI (r: −0.65) in the long-term follow-up and a post-hoc power of 0.93 for the correlation coefficient between question one of the ISI questionnaire and ∆ ODI (r: −0.70) in the long-term follow-up were calculated. Furthermore, not all patients filled out the ISI questionnaire in the long-term follow-up. Data on therapy adherence were not available. Therefore, a possible association between difficulty falling asleep and therapy adherence cannot be proven, based on our available data. However, the gained data are of high quality and provide new information about the therapeutic outcome of patients treated by HGNS.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>To the best of our knowledge this is one of the first studies investigating the association between the different separate insomnia-related symptoms on PSG-metrics in patients undergoing HGNS implantation. A strong significant correlation between question one of the ISI questionnaire (difficulty falling asleep) and both ∆ AHI (r: −0.65, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.004) and ∆ ODI (r: −0.7; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>= 0.001) in the long-term follow-up could be shown. Difficulty falling asleep seems to be a significant and relevant clinical factor, associated with worse HGNS therapeutic outcome. Therefore, insomnia-related symptoms should be considered both at the time point of decision to implant a HGNS as well as postoperatively after implantation. Further studies are necessary to understand the impact of insomnia on HGNS therapeutic outcome and to investigate the potential benefits of further therapies, such as behavioral therapies, on HGNS therapeutic outcome in patients with PAP-intolerance suffering from COMISA.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <p>COMISA, coexistence of insomnia and obstructive sleep apnea; OSA, obstructive sleep apnea;</p>
      <p>HGNS, hypoglossal nerve stimulation; CPAP, continuous positive airway pressure; PAP, positive airway pressure; PSG, polysomnography; ISI, insomnia severity index; AHI, apnea–hypopnea index; BMI, body mass index; DISE, drug-induced sleep endoscopy; ODI, oxygen desaturation index (n/h).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Ethics Approval and Consent to Participate</title>
      <p>All patients provided informed consent to the use of their data for research purposes. The data were evaluated in a pseudonymized fashion. Only health data that are collected in the clinical routine were analyzed retrospectively. So-called “third parties” did not have access to the data and publication occurs exclusively in anonymized form. The Ethics Committee of the Rhineland-Palatinate Medical Association refrains from providing advice in such cases, citing the State Hospital Act (§36 and §37) (see also: <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.laek-rlp.de/ausschuesse-kommissionen/ethikkommission/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.laek-rlp.de/ausschuesse-kommissionen/ethikkommission/</ext-link></underline>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s0008">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p>The data underlying this article cannot be shared publicly for the privacy of individuals that participated in the study. The data will be shared on reasonable request to the corresponding authors.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0009">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>H.G. reports research grants by Inspire Medical Systems, Inc. (MN, USA) that are unrelated to this study. The other authors have no conflicts of interest to declare in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rundo</surname>
<given-names>JV</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea basics</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cleve J Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>86</volume>(<issue>9 Suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3949/ccjm.86.s1.02</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Roth</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia: definition, prevalence, etiology, and consequences</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>5 Suppl</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sweetman</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lack</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McEvoy</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Bi-directional relationships between co-morbid insomnia and sleep apnea (COMISA)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>101519</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2021.101519</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34229295</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Krakow</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Melendrez</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferreira</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence of insomnia symptoms in patients with sleep-disordered breathing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>120</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1923</fpage>–<lpage>1929</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.120.6.1923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11742923</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tasbakan</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gunduz</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pirildar</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Basoglu</surname>
<given-names>OK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Quality of life in obstructive sleep apnea is related to female gender and comorbid insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1013</fpage>–<lpage>1020</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-018-1621-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29352360</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Qaseem</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holty</surname>
<given-names>J-EC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Owens</surname>
<given-names>DK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dallas</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Starkey</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shekelle</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Management of obstructive sleep apnea in adults: a clinical practice guideline from the American College of Physicians</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Internal Med</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>159</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>471</fpage>–<lpage>483</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-159-11-201312030-00009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24061345</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Strollo</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Soose</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maurer</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Upper-airway stimulation for obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>370</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>149</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1308659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24401051</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wickwire</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Birnbaum</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Collop</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep maintenance insomnia complaints predict poor CPAP adherence: a clinical case series</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>772</fpage>–<lpage>776</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2010.03.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20673741</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pordzik</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ludwig</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seifen</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia in patients undergoing hypoglossal nerve stimulation therapy for obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biology</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>98</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biology12010098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36671790</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kaffenberger</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chandna</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaki</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Reduced usage of upper airway stimulation therapy in patients with comorbid insomnia and obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1997</fpage>–<lpage>2004</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.10752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37589148</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Steffen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baptista</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ebner</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jeschke</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Konig</surname>
<given-names>IR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bruchhage</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia affects patient-reported outcome in sleep apnea treated with hypoglossal nerve stimulation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Laryn Iinves otolar</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>877</fpage>–<lpage>884</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lio2.761</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dhanda Patil</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ishman</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thaler</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suurna</surname>
<given-names>MV</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Impact of insomnia on hypoglossal nerve stimulation outcomes in the adhere registry</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Laryngoscope</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>134</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>471</fpage>–<lpage>479</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lary.30933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37560883</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ong</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crawford</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia and obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Clini</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>389</fpage>–<lpage>398</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsmc.2013.04.004</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bastien</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vallières</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morin</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Validation of the Insomnia Severity Index as an outcome measure for insomnia research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>307</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1389-9457(00)00065-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11438246</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Steffen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heiser</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Galetke</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Die Stimulation des Nervus hypoglossus in der Behandlung der obstruktiven Schlafapnoe–Aktualisiertes Positionspapier der Arbeitsgemeinschaft Schlafmedizin der DGHNO-KHC</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Laryngo-Rhino-Otologie</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>100</volume>(<issue>01</issue>):<fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/a-1327-1343</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33316830</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gerber</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lemola</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Validation of the German version of the insomnia severity index in adolescents, young adults and adult workers: results from three cross-sectional studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12888-016-0876-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26739960</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hemmerich</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Poweranalyse für Korrelationen</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">StatistikGuru Re</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>2020</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wickwire</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Collop</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia and sleep-related breathing disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>137</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1449</fpage>–<lpage>1463</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20525657</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bahr</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cámara</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gouveris</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tuin</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Current treatment of comorbid insomnia and obstructive sleep apnea with CBTI and PAP-therapy: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>804</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fneur.2018.00804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30420826</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pieh</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bach</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Popp</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia symptoms influence CPAP compliance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Bre</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-012-0655-9</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bjornsdottir</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Janson</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sigurdsson</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Symptoms of insomnia among patients with obstructive sleep apnea before and after two years of positive airway pressure treatment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1901</fpage>–<lpage>1909</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.3226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24293765</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pascoe</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aylor</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of Hypoglossal Nerve Stimulation With Improvements in Long-term, Patient-Reported Outcomes and Comparison With Positive Airway Pressure for Patients With Obstructive Sleep Apnea. <italic toggle="yes">JAMA otolaryngology-- head &amp; neck surgery</italic></article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Otolaryngology-- Head &amp; Neck Surgery</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>148</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaoto.2021.2245</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34762105</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dhanda Patil</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hong</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ishman</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Hypoglossal nerve stimulation in veterans with comorbid insomnia and sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Otolar Neck Surg</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>164</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1345</fpage>–<lpage>1353</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0194599820982638</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Coca</surname>
<given-names>KK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heiser</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huntley</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Hypoglossal nerve stimulation usage by therapy nonresponders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Otolar Head and Neck Surg</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>166</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>786</fpage>–<lpage>790</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/01945998211036867</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ong</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crawford</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dawson</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A randomized controlled trial of CBT-I and PAP for obstructive sleep apnea and comorbid insomnia: main outcomes from the MATRICS study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsaa041</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Alessi</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fung</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dzierzewski</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Randomized controlled trial of an integrated approach to treating insomnia and improving the use of positive airway pressure therapy in veterans with comorbid insomnia disorder and obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsaa235</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
