<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39071545</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">11282454</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">472595</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S472595</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Quantitative Electroencephalography in Term Neonates During the Early Postnatal Period Across Various Sleep States</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Zhang et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Zhang et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Ruijie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Xinran</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Lu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5120-7077</contrib-id><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Xinao</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Xuefeng</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Yan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5622-6020</contrib-id><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Chuyan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3525-8752</contrib-id><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Feng</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Jimei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Neonatology, Obstetrics and Gynecology Hospital of Fudan University</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Center for Molecular Medicine, Children’s Hospital of Fudan University</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Neurology, Children’s Hospital of Fudan University, National Children’s Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Rehabilitation Medicine, The First Affiliated Hospital of Nanjing Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Nanjing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Jimei Wang; Feng Jiang, <institution>Department of Neonatology, Obstetrics and Gynecology Hospital of Fudan University</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <addr-line>200011</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, Email wjm821920@163.com; dxyjiang@163.com</corresp><fn id="ft0001"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>1011</fpage><lpage>1025</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>07</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Zhang et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Zhang et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Neonatal sleep is pivotal for their growth and development, yet manual interpretation of raw images is time-consuming and labor-intensive. Quantitative Electroencephalography (QEEG) presents significant advantages in terms of objectivity and convenience for investigating neonatal sleep patterns. However, research on the sleep patterns of healthy neonates remains scarce. This study aims to identify QEEG markers that distinguish between different neonatal sleep cycles and analyze QEEG alterations across various sleep stages in relation to postmenstrual age.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>From September 2023 to February 2024, full-term neonates admitted to the neonatology department at the Obstetrics and Gynecology Hospital of Fudan University were enrolled in this study. Electroencephalographic (EEG) recordings were obtained from neonates aged 37–42 weeks, within 1–7 days post-birth. The ROC curve was employed to evaluate QEEG features related to amplitude, range EEG (rEEG), spectral density, and connectivity across different sleep stages. Furthermore, regression analyses were performed to investigate the association between these QEEG characteristics and postmenstrual age.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The alpha frequency band’s spectral_diff_F3 emerged as the most potent discriminator between active sleep (AS) and quiet sleep (QS). In distinguishing AS from wakefulness (W), the theta frequency’s spectral_diff_C4 was the most effective, whereas the delta frequency’s spectral_diff_P4 excelled in differentiating QS from W. During AS and QS phases, there was a notable increase in entropy within the delta frequency band across all monitored brain regions and in the spectral relative power within the theta frequency band, correlating with postmenstrual age (PMA).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Spectral difference showcases the highest discriminative capability across awake and various sleep states. The observed patterns of neonatal QEEG alterations in relation to PMA are consistent with the maturation of neonatal sleep, offering insights into the prediction and evaluation of brain development outcomes.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>quantitative EEG</kwd><kwd>neonates</kwd><kwd>sleep</kwd><kwd>postmenstrual age</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>2023 Young Clinical Full-time Research Team of Shanghai Medical College, Fudan University Funder: Shanghai Medical College Fudan University Recipient: Xinran Dong. Science and Technology Innovation Program of Shanghai (20Z11900603 to Jimei Wang)</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>2023 Young Clinical Full-time Research Team of Shanghai Medical College, Fudan University Funder: Shanghai Medical College Fudan University Recipient: Xinran Dong. Science and Technology Innovation Program of Shanghai (20Z11900603 to Jimei Wang).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="8"/><ref-count count="43"/><page-count count="15"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Sleep is fundamental to the growth, development, and restoration of the body, with its role being critically important in newborns and infants during the first year of life<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>—a time characterized by rapid developmental changes.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Sleep significantly contributes to brain maturation, enhancing learning and memory by optimizing synaptic architecture during periods of reduced neural network efficiency, thus facilitating energy conservation.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> REM sleep twitching is crucial not only for the development of sensory perception but also for motor skills.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> NREM sleep specifically enhances memories tagged as relevant during waking periods, refining and optimizing memory networks.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> In mammals, sleep can improve learned motor skills<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> and promote infants’ recognition of stimuli.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></p>
      <p>Additionally, sleep is not merely a simple negation of physiological sleep deprivation and disorders; it must also adapt to individual, social, and environmental needs to achieve physical and mental health.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> It is essential for emotional regulation, influencing the regulation of neurochemicals that affect emotional and stress responses.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> During early developmental stages, the quality of sleep is a critical determinant of future cognitive abilities and is associated with the emergence of psychopathological symptoms.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Early sleep disturbances are linked with a range of negative outcomes, including compromised health, emotional dysregulation, impaired decision-making, reduced concentration, increased obesity risk, and diminished academic performance.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></p>
      <p>The gold standard for monitoring neonatal sleep patterns is video electroencephalogram-polysomnography (EEG-PSG).<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> EEG technology is widely utilized in the assessment of neonatal conditions and to monitor the efficacy of treatment such as hypoxic-ischemic encephalopathy and epileptic discharges, among other neurological disorders.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> However, interpreting raw EEG data for neonatal sleep staging is a resource-intensive task that demands substantial expertise and time, with skilled professionals required to analyze complex data over extended periods.</p>
      <p>Quantitative Electroencephalography (QEEG) represents a progressive approach that builds on the traditional visual analysis of electroencephalographic data to extract specific metrics.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> This quantitative technique offers the potential to replace the intricate, laborious, and subjective process of manual EEG interpretation with a streamlined, rapid, and reproducible computer-assisted methodology, though it currently cannot completely detach from expert interpretation.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Unlike deep learning methods such as multi-branch convolutional neural networks,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> QEEG relies on hand-crafted feature-based classification, extracting various features from the time domain, frequency domain, and spatial domain.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> This allows for continuous, objective measurement of EEG activity and can be easily scaled to monitor a large number of newborns.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></p>
      <p>While QEEG has been widely applied in the evaluation of brain development in newborns with medical conditions,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> research on the sleep of healthy newborns remains limited. Furthermore, there is a dearth of information on the evolution of QEEG parameters during the early postnatal period in correlation with postmenstrual age (PMA). This study utilizes 810 parameters composed of leads, spectral, and EEG features to examine full-term infants within the first week after birth to (1) delineate the range of QEEG parameters and identify those most effective in distinguishing between different sleep states; (2) explore the variations in QEEG parameters in relation to the progression of PMA.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p>This study recruited 60 neonates from September 2023 to February 2024 at a prominent obstetrics and gynecology hospital in China, which averages 8000 deliveries per year. The neonatal cohort presented various conditions, such as neonatal infections, hyperbilirubinemia, and wet lung. Inclusion criteria for the neonates were a gestational age between 37 and 42 weeks; no requirement for resuscitation post-delivery; and an Apgar score greater than 8 at 5 minutes post-birth. Exclusion criteria encompassed a maternal history of epilepsy<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> or diabetes;<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> birth weight below 2.5 kg;<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> presence of congenital malformations or chromosomal abnormalities; inclusion in a multiple birth;<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> or technical issues with the EEG apparatus, like low power or electrode detachment. Since some infants do not require phototherapy, to ensure experimental consistency, we conducted EEG collections only when neonates were not undergoing phototherapy. All neonates in our cohort were in good general condition with no disease exacerbation during their hospital stay, and they were followed up in the outpatient clinic without any readmissions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Recording Protocol</title>
        <p>An attended polysomnogram lasting 3–6 hours was conducted after the infant was considered medically stable, necessitating no respiratory support and able to undergo a bedside polysomnogram. A polysomnographic technologist, present at the bedside, carefully documented behavioral observations throughout the session. The polysomnograms were later scored offline by the technologist and reviewed by an expert from the Children’s Hospital of Fudan University, who had specialized training and extensive experience in data annotation. The infants were housed in open bassinets, with routine care and feeding schedules (typically every three hours) maintained. Except during interventions like diaper changes, when recording was paused to reduce data interference, infants primarily stayed in the bassinets.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>EEG Monitoring</title>
        <p>EEG data were recorded using a Nicolet One machine (sampling frequency: 500 Hz), with electrode placement adhering to the neonate-modified 10–20 system endorsed by the American Clinical Neurophysiology Society.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> Electrodes were positioned at the frontal pole (Fp1, Fp2), frontal (F3, F4), central (C3, C4), mid-temporal (T3, T4), and parietal (P3, P4) scalp regions, with a reference electrode at Cz. The parietal region (P3/P4) was chosen over the occipital (O1/O2) to minimize artifacts. The comprehensive setup included a 10-channel EEG, bilateral electrooculogram, chin electromyogram, oxygen saturation, electrocardiogram, and digital video recording.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>EEG Sleep Staging Principles</title>
        <p>Neonatal sleep staging was conducted in accordance with the AASM guidelines, utilizing EEG, EOG, and EMG data. The primary EEG derivations employed were F3-Cz, C3-Cz, and P3-Cz, with F4-Cz, C4-Cz, and P4-Cz serving as secondary options. Sleep stages were determined in 30-second intervals based on identifiable biomarkers within each epoch. The EEG trace, ancillary channel data, and video review were integral to identifying sleep states, in line with the American Clinical Neurophysiology Society’s standard terminology and categorization for neonatal continuous EEG monitoring.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> For example, quiet sleep (QS) was classified into tracé alternant or slow-wave EEG patterns, whereas active sleep (AS) was identified by continuous, low-voltage waves. Additionally, the power spectrum of the EEG was crucial for differentiating between sleep stages, contributing to a more efficient analysis process.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>EEG Pre-Processing and QEEG Features</title>
        <p>The preprocessing steps employed the Auto-Neo-electroencephalography system from the Children’s Hospital of Fudan University. Data were filtered (0.3 to 50 Hz), denoised, and subjected to Independent Component Analysis (ICA) to remove electrooculographic artifacts.</p>
        <p>The QEEG features adhered to the characteristic indicators for neonates as outlined by John M. O’Toole and Geraldine B. Boylan.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> An exhaustive extraction of 810 neural signal features was performed, encompassing amplitude, rEEG, spectral density, and connectivity. Initially, the signal data were segmented into four frequency bands: delta (0.5–4 Hz), theta (4–8 Hz), alpha (8–13 Hz), and beta (13–30 Hz), across ten channels. For each band and channel, a set of features were calculated: six related to amplitude (total power, standard deviation, skewness, kurtosis, envelope mean, envelope standard deviation), eight to rEEG (mean, median, lower margin, upper margin, width, standard deviation, coefficient of variation, asymmetry), and five to spectral aspects (absolute power, relative power, flatness (Wiener entropy), entropy (Shannon entropy), difference), resulting in 760 features [(6+8+5) * 4 (frequency bands) * 10 (channels)]. Additionally, three spectral features (95th and 50th percentile spectral edge frequencies, fractal dimension) across ten channels yielded 30 features (3 * 10 channels). Moreover, five connectivity features (brain symmetry index, correlation (Pearson), mean coherence, maximum coherence, frequency of maximum coherence) per frequency band resulted in 20 features. In total, this approach enabled the extraction of 810 (760+30+20) neural signal features per sample, illustrating a comprehensive methodology for the quantitative analysis of neural signals.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2006">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>Descriptive statistical measures, namely mean and standard deviation (SD), were employed to summarize the normative data of QEEG across different states of consciousness, including awake, AS, and QS. The assessment of data normality was conducted using histogram analysis and the Shapiro–Wilk test. To determine the differences in QEEG parameters across various sleep states, a comprehensive analysis utilizing repeated measures of variance (the Friedman test) was performed. If the global analysis indicated significant results, post-hoc pairwise comparisons were conducted using the Wilcoxon signed-rank test. To adjust for the heightened risk of Type I error arising from multiple pairwise comparisons across the three sleep states, a Bonferroni correction was applied to the p-values from these posthoc tests. A p-value of less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant. Additionally, the discriminative ability of QEEG parameters to differentiate between the sleep states was assessed using receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves. The 95% confidence interval for the area under the curve (AUC) was determined using DeLong’s method. The optimal cutoff points for each QEEG parameter were identified by maximizing the Youden index (sensitivity + specificity - 1).</p>
        <p>The influence of postmenstrual age (PMA) on QEEG features was examined through multivariable linear regression analysis using the Stepwise Method. This method allowed for the calculation of β weights (standardized regression coefficients), which indicate the extent of change, in standard deviation units, in the dependent variable for each standard deviation increase in the independent variable. To reduce the risk of Type I error associated with multiple comparisons, a more stringent significance threshold of 0.01 was set for all multivariable linear regression analyses.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Demographics</title>
        <p><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> presents demographic details for the 54 full-term neonates included in the study, comprising 26 males and 28 females. Among the 54 infants, 15 were delivered by cesarean section. Of these, 36 infants (66.67%) were admitted due to hyperbilirubinemia, 20 infants (37.04%) due to infections, and 1 infant (1.85%) due to wet lung. These neonates underwent EEG examinations within the first 7 days post-birth, contingent on their physical condition. The mean gestational age (standard deviation) was 39.50 (1.14) weeks, the mean post-menstrual age was 40.11 (1.12) weeks, the age post-birth was 4.31 (1.68) days, and the birth weight was 3309.06 (328.65) grams. On average, each newborn was recorded for 248.08 (46.37) minutes.
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">N = 54</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± std</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sex, Female/male</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28/26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Mode of delivery, CS/VD</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15/39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Record time (mins)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">248.08 ± 46.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">188~361</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gestational age (weeks)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.50 ± 1.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.14~41.29</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Postmenstrual age (weeks)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.11 ± 1.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.71~41.86</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Chronological age (days)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.31 ± 1.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1~7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Birth weight (grams)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3309.06 ± 328.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2640~4200</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Reasons for admission</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hyperbilirubinemia</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (66.67%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Infections</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (37.04%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Wet lung</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.85%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: CS, cesarean section; VD, vaginal delivery.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <p>We also compared whether cesarean delivery, hyperbilirubinemia, and infections influence EEG indices. Since only one newborn was diagnosed with wet lung, we did not analyze this potential influencing factor. The only significant finding was in the theta frequency band’s spectral flatness (AS_4_8_spectral_flatness_Fp1) in lead F1, which differed between the cesarean and vaginal delivery groups, with a P-value of 0.0133. However, given that we analyzed a total of 810 indices and found only one positive result, this finding is not convincing.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>QEEG Differentiation of Various Sleep Stages</title>
        <p>With numerous computational indices at our disposal, we highlighted the top 20 indices based on the AUC from the ROC analysis, capable of differentiating between various sleep stages.</p>
        <p><xref rid="f0001 f0002" ref-type="fig">Figures 1A, 2A</xref>, and <xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">3A</xref> rank the top 20 QEEG parameters by their efficacy in distinguishing between awake and sleep states, as determined by the ROC analysis AUC. Predominantly, spectral differences within the alpha and beta frequency bands were the most effective in differentiating between AS and QS, as depicted in <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>. The alpha band spectral difference at the F3 lead emerged as the most discriminating parameter with an AUC of 0.88, closely followed by the beta band spectral difference at the C4 lead with an AUC of 0.87. In distinguishing between Awake and AS stages (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>), the theta band spectral difference and relative power showed significant differentiation capability, with the theta spectral difference at the C4 and C3 leads achieving an AUC of 0.93, and the beta band spectral relative power at the P4 lead reaching an AUC of 0.91. Theta band spectral differences at the F3, F4, P3, P4, and T3 leads, alongside theta band spectral relative power at the C4 and alpha band spectral relative power at the P4 leads, all surpassed an AUC of 0.90. Regarding the differentiation between QS and Wakefulness (<xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>), the delta band spectral differences and the 50% spectral edge frequency across various bands showed strong discriminative capacities, with the delta band spectral difference at the P4 lead attaining the highest AUC of 0.94, and the 50% spectral edge frequencies at the C4 across all bands each exhibiting an AUC of 0.88.
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The ROCAUC of the top 20 parameters that differentiate between AS and QS. (<bold>A</bold>) shows the top 20 indicators that distinguish between AS and QS periods and their corresponding ROC-AUC values. The blue bars represent the ranking of ROC-AUC values, and the T-shaped black lines indicate the standard error. (<bold>B</bold>) displays the ROC curves, with the legend showing the color lines corresponding to the 20 indicators. The values and specific details of these indicators can be found in <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link></underline>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1011-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig>
<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The ROCAUC of the top 20 parameters that differentiate between AS and W. (<bold>A</bold>) shows the top 20 indicators that distinguish between AS and W periods and their corresponding ROC-AUC values. The blue bars represent the ranking of ROC-AUC values, and the T-shaped black lines indicate the standard error. (<bold>B</bold>) displays the ROC curves, with the legend showing the color lines corresponding to the 20 indicators. The values and specific details of these indicators can be found in <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 2</ext-link></underline>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1011-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig>
<fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The ROCAUC of the top 20 parameters that differentiate between QS and W. (<bold>A</bold>) shows the top 20 indicators that distinguish between QS and W periods and their corresponding ROC-AUC values. The blue bars represent the ranking of ROC-AUC values, and the T-shaped black lines indicate the standard error. (<bold>B</bold>) displays the ROC curves, with the legend showing the color lines corresponding to the 20 indicators. The values and specific details of these indicators can be found in <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 3</ext-link></underline>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1011-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
        <p><xref rid="f0001 f0002" ref-type="fig">Figures 1B, 2B</xref>, and <xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">3B</xref> display the ROC curves for QEEG parameters that effectively differentiate between awake and sleep states. <xref rid="t0002 t0003 t0004" ref-type="table">Tables 2–4</xref> detail the AUC values for the top 5 parameters along with their 95% confidence intervals. Detailed information on the top 20 parameters by AUC can be found in <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Tables 1</ext-link></underline>–<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">3</ext-link></underline>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The Top 5 Parameters Capable of Distinguishing Between as and QS</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indicator</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUC</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUC 95% CI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Best Cutoff</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8_13_spectral_diff_F3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(4.74e-5, 6.68e-4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.29e-4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13_30_spectral_diff_C4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.50e-5, 4.43e-4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.79e-5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8_13_spectral_diff_F4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.07e-4, 6.84e-4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.45e-4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8_13_spectral_diff_C4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5.22e-5, 6.81e-4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.80e-4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13_30_spectral_diff_T3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3.02e-5, 4.05e-4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65e-4</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: AUC, area under the receiver operator characteristics curve; CI, confidence interval; Cutoff values associated with minimal false-negative and positive results are shown. Data are expressed with a 95% CI.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>The Top 5 Parameters Capable of Distinguishing Between as and W</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indicator</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUC</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUC 95% CI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Best Cutoff</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4_8_spectral_diff_C4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6.43e-6, 4.02e-4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34e-4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4_8_spectral_diff_C3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5.28e-6, 4.18e-4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.64e-4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13_30_spectral_relative_power_P4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.62e-3, 6.44e-2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42e-2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4_8_spectral_diff_P4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3.19e-6, 4.32e-4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.22e-5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4_8_spectral_diff_T3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6.99e-6, 4.16e-4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70e-4</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: AUC, area under the receiver operator characteristics curve; CI, confidence interval; Cutoff values associated with minimal false-negative and positive results are shown. Data are expressed with a 95% CI.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>The Top 5 Parameters Capable of Distinguishing Between QS and W</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indicator</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUC</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUC 95% CI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Best Cutoff</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5_4_spectral_diff_P4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.23e-6, 1.55e-4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.56e-5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5_4_spectral_diff_C4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.49e-6, 1.50e-4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.47e-5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5_4_spectral_diff_C3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.09e-6, 1.51e-4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71e-5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5_4_spectral_diff_F4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.59e-6, 2.06e-4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.58e-5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5_4_spectral_diff_T4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.41e-6, 1.25e-4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00e-5</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: AUC, area under the receiver operator characteristics curve; CI, confidence interval; Cutoff values associated with minimal false-negative and positive results are shown. Data are expressed with a 95% CI.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>QEEG Changes with Postmenstrual Age</title>
        <p><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figures 1</ext-link></underline>–<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">3</ext-link></underline> illustrate the trends in QEEG changes relative to PMA. <xref rid="t0005 t0006 t0007" ref-type="table">Tables 5–7</xref> present the regression model coefficients and P-values for the wakefulness, AS, and QS phases, respectively. When encountering multiple leads all correlating with post-menstrual age for the same indicator, we have retained only the two leads with the best fit (ie, the highest R<sup>2</sup>) in <xref rid="t0006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref> and <xref rid="t0007" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>. The complete data for these indicators can be found in <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Tables 4</ext-link></underline> and <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">5</ext-link></underline>. During wakefulness (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 1A</ext-link></underline><bold>–</bold><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">C</ext-link></underline> and <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>), there was an observed increase in both Wiener and Shannon entropy within the beta frequency band of the frontal lobe correlating with PMA. In the AS phase (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 2</ext-link></underline> and <xref rid="t0006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>) and the QS phase (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 3</ext-link></underline> and <xref rid="t0007" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>), an increase in entropy within the delta frequency band across all monitored brain regions was noted (AS: <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 2B</ext-link></underline><bold>–</bold><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Q</ext-link></underline>) (QS: <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 3A</ext-link></underline><bold>–</bold><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">P</ext-link></underline>). Additionally, the spectral relative power within the theta frequency band also showed an upward trend with PMA during both AS (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 2S</ext-link></underline>–<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Z</ext-link></underline>) and QS (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 3R</ext-link></underline>–<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Y</ext-link></underline>) phases.
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>The Pattern of Changes in QEEG Parameters During the Wakeful State Across Postmenstrual Age</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral Power</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signal Features</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<sup>2</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beta</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13_30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_entropy_F3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_entropy_F4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_flatness_F3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0006"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>The Variation Pattern of QEEG Parameters During as Across Postmenstrual Age</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral Power</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signal Features</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<sup>2</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beta</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5_4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_edge_frequency_95_C3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_entropy_C4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_entropy_F4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_entropy_P3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_flatness_F3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0037</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_flatness_F4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0039</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4_8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_edge_frequency_95_C3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_relative_power_C3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_relative_power_F4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8_13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rEEG_asymmetry_P3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0035</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_edge_frequency_95_C3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_entropy_P4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_flatness_C4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0005</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_relative_power_C3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0006</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_relative_power_F4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0005</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13_30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rEEG_CV_P3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0046</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_edge_frequency_95_C3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0007"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>The Variation Pattern of QEEG Parameters During QS Across Postmenstrual Age</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral Power</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signal Features</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<sup>2</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beta</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_entropy_F3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0029</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_entropy_F4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0033</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_flatness_F3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0048</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_flatness_F4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0054</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4_8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_diff_P3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.54E-06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_relative_power_C3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.413</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_relative_power_P3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_entropy_F3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_entropy_P4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_flatness_F3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_relative_power_C3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_relative_power_P3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13_30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rEEG_asymmetry_C3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0074</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rEEG_asymmetry_P3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0076</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rEEG_CV_F4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.0064</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_diff_C3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.33E-06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spectral_diff_T3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.34E-06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
        <p>Specifically, during the AS phase, there was a decrease in rEEG asymmetry within the alpha frequency band at the P3 lead (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 2AA</ext-link></underline>), and in the beta frequency band across the temporal and parietal lobes during the QS phase (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 3AG</ext-link>-<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">AJ</ext-link></underline>) associated with increasing PMA. Moreover, the 95% spectral edge frequency in every frequency band within the midline central area exhibited an upward trend with PMA during the AS phase (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 2A</ext-link></underline>, <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">R</ext-link></underline>, <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">AB</ext-link></underline> and <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">AH</ext-link></underline>).</p>
        <p>In the QS phase, an increase in spectral relative power within the alpha frequency band across the frontal, central, and parietal lobes was observed with advancing PMA (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 3AD</ext-link></underline>–<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">AF</ext-link></underline>), while entropy showed a decrease (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 3Z</ext-link></underline>–<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">AC</ext-link></underline>). Additionally, there was an increase in spectral difference within the beta frequency band across the frontal, central, and parietal lobes correlated with PMA (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 3AL</ext-link></underline>–<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472595.docx" ext-link-type="uri">AR</ext-link></underline>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The index that was most capable of distinguishing between AS and QS stages was the spectral difference within the alpha frequency band at the F3 electrode (spectral_diff_F3). The theta frequency spectral difference at the C4 electrode (spectral_diff_C4) proved to be the most effective in differentiating AS from wakefulness (W), while the delta frequency spectral difference at the P4 electrode (spectral_diff_P4) was the best at distinguishing QS from W. During the AS and QS phases, there was an observed increase in entropy within the delta frequency band across all monitored brain regions and an increase in the spectral relative power within the theta frequency band with PMA. Additionally, there was a decrease in rEEG asymmetry within the alpha frequency band at the P3 lead during the AS phase, and a decrease in the beta frequency band rEEG asymmetry across the temporal and parietal lobes during the QS phase, associated with increasing PMA.</p>
      <p>The association of QEEG parameters with outcomes in neonatal sleep research, particularly concerning growth and development, was notable A greater proportion of quiet sleep and higher state entropy were correlated with poorer neurological examination scores, whereas decreased delta power during quiet sleep was associated with better examination outcomes (rho = −0.43, p = 0.023).<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></p>
      <sec id="s0004-s2001">
        <title>Innovative EEG Metrics for Differentiating Sleep Stages</title>
        <p>This study employed hundreds of EEG indices to differentiate between sleep stages, identifying the most discriminative markers. The primary indices for distinguishing between sleep and wakefulness phases were mainly spectral difference measures, an aspect not extensively explored in previous research. Other indices like spectral entropy and Spectral Edge Frequency (SEF) had been validated in earlier studies for their ability to differentiate sleep stages.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></p>
        <p>Spectral difference, defined as the change in spectra between consecutive time segments in a spectrogram<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> – a visual representation of the frequency spectrum of a signal over time obtained through Short-Time Fourier Transform (STFT)--was significantly discriminative. The superior discriminative power of spectral difference in distinguishing between various sleep stages may be attributed to the distinct predominant frequency bands characteristic of neonatal wakefulness and sleep phases.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> For example, wakefulness was typically marked by theta activity with low-voltage, irregular delta waves, AS by mixed-wave activity, and QS predominantly by delta slow waves, with occasional theta waves. This variation in primary frequency bands across sleep states highlighted the effectiveness of spectral difference as a discriminating feature.</p>
        <p>We introduced the parameter of spectral flatness, also known as Wiener entropy, along with Shannon entropy (spectral entropy), to quantify the uniformity of the spectral distribution.<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> These metrics showed trends that consistently aligned with changes in corrected gestational age. Notably, during the quiet and active sleep phases, the entropy within the Delta frequency band increased with corrected gestational age, indicating a rise in complexity within this band,<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> which includes a broader spectrum of waveforms. This increase may signify the gradual transition from neonatal sleep patterns to those typical of childhood, characterized by the emergence of slow-wave sleep (0.5Hz-2Hz).<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></p>
        <p>rEEG has been shown to vary with corrected gestational age in preterm infants and is associated with growth and developmental outcomes.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> In term neonates, we observed that rEEG asymmetry in the beta frequency band decreased with increasing corrected gestational age. Voltage asymmetry in a single channel, attributed to positional shifts over time, originates from a limited number of neurons firing synchronously at the same frequency during infancy.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> However, as age progresses, the number of synchronously firing neurons increases, leading to a gradual synchronization of brain discharges. Consistent with previous findings,<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> our results also confirmed that during both AS and QS phases, theta waves increased with corrected gestational age, serving as an indicator of brain maturation. Particularly noteworthy was the gradual increase in the relative spectral power of the Alpha frequency band during the QS phase with advancing corrected gestational age, potentially associated with the progressive emergence of sleep spindles (10Hz-16Hz).<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> This observation underscores the developmental progression in neural activity patterns, indicative of advancing neurological maturity and the evolving complexity of sleep architecture in the developing brain.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2002">
        <title>Innovations and Advantages of This Study</title>
        <p>Our study results have established the EEG characteristics of low-risk term infants admitted to the neonatal unit within the first week after birth. In <xref rid="t0008" ref-type="table">Table 8</xref>, we have listed the contributions made by previous researchers on neonatal sleep QEEG. Previous researchers have long used QEEG to explore differences in various sleep stages,<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> but they only identified differences without using ROC analysis to determine which metrics contributed the most. Additionally, they primarily focused on AS and QS stages, neglecting the awake period.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> Considering that newborns exhibit significant movement during sleep, including the awake period in the study provides a more comprehensive and rigorous analysis. Recent studies have used some metrics from Amplitude, Spectral, and Connectivity features to explore which indicators can better distinguish between the three stages.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> Unlike previous studies with smaller sample sizes,<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> our inclusion of 54 normal neonates enabled us to provide more robust evidence. By extracting a comprehensive set of features, we identified more effective metrics for distinguishing different sleep stages.
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0008" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 8</label><caption><p>Comparison of Different Research for QEEG in Neonatal Sleep Stages</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Year</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Authors</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demographics</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">EEG channel</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Features</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep stage</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Results</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comparison of quantitative EEG characteristics of quiet and active sleep in newborns<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Karel Paul, Vladimír Krajca, et al</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 healthy newborns (10 full-term and 11 pre-term)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fp1, Fp2, C3, C4, O1, O2, T3, T4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AV, Mm, δ1, δ2, θ1, θ2, α, D1 and D2; L and MF; No and t%*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Two sleep classes (AS and QS)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AS vs QS: (a) the number and length of quasi-stationary segments, (b) voltage and (c) power in delta and theta bands</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EEG in the healthy term newborn within 12 hours of birth<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I Korotchikova, S Connolly, et al</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 normal newborn babies</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F4, F3, Cz, T4, T3, P4, P3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEF, H, and δ<sub>R</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Two sleep classes (AS and QS)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEF and H were significantly higher (p &lt; 0.0001) and δ<sub>R</sub> was significantly lower (p &lt; 0.0001) in AS than in QS.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quantitative electroencephalogram in term neonates under different sleep states<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ian Yuan, Georgia Georgostathi, et al</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 normal neonates37 to 46 weeks suspected seizure or differential diagnosis of apneic episodes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fp1-C3, Fp2-C4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total power, power ratio, coherence, entropy, and SEF 50 and 90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Three sleep classes (AS, QS and Wake)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Awake vs AS: Entropy beta AUC-ROC &gt; 0.84; Awake vs QS: Entropy beta, entropy delta1, theta power %, and SEF50 AUC-ROC &gt; 0.78AS vs QS: theta power % AUC-ROC &gt; 0.69</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: *The features used in paper: AV—standard deviation of the sample values in the segment; Mm—the difference between maximal positive and minimal negative values of the samples in the segment; D1—maximum of absolute values of the first derivative of the samples in the segment; D2—maximum of absolute values of the second derivative of the samples in the segment; MF—average frequency of the EEG activity in the segment; t%—time percentage of the relevant class occurrence; No—number of segments of the relevant class; L—average duration of the relevant class segments.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0006"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: AS, active sleep; QS, quiet sleep; SEF, spectral edge frequency; H, spectral entropy; δ<sub>R</sub>: relative delta power.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <p>Specifically, the alpha band spectral difference at the F3 lead was the most discriminating parameter between AS and QS, with an AUC of 0.88. The theta spectral difference at the C4 and C3 leads showed significant differentiation capability between Awake and AS stages, achieving an AUC of 0.93. The delta band spectral difference at the P4 lead demonstrated strong discriminative capacity between QS and Wakefulness, attaining the highest AUC of 0.94. Finally, we have provided, for the first time, a distribution of healthy neonatal brain EEG characteristics and explored the relationship between quantitative EEG features and postnatal age. This extensive collection of features has allowed us to develop machine learning-based models for individual-level predictions, laying the foundation for precision medicine.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Limitations and Future Research Directions</title>
      <p>The limitations of our study include its design as a single-center experiment. While we collected a relatively large sample size compared to prior studies,<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> validation through multi-center studies would be advantageous for future research, enhancing the generalizability and robustness of the findings. This expanded approach could offer a more comprehensive understanding of the research topic. Additionally, due to the presence of numerous artifacts in the occipital lobe, we were unable to monitor the occipital brain regions. Future research may need to employ innovative equipment to ensure comprehensive monitoring of each brain area.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>In summary, our study identified more effective QEEG metrics for distinguishing between awake and sleep states, as well as delineated the developmental characteristics of cortical activity across different sleep-wake states in a normal neonatal cohort. Notably, the spectral difference emerged as the parameter with the highest overall discriminative capacity for differentiating between awake and various sleep states. The observed patterns of neonatal QEEG changes in relation to PMA align with the developmental trajectory of neonatal sleep. The application of QEEG analysis provides valuable objective data that can enhance traditional methods of neonatal sleep staging, thereby facilitating the development of more comprehensive machine-learning models aimed at predicting neurodevelopmental outcomes. This integration of QEEG with machine learning approaches holds the potential to advance our understanding and monitoring of neonatal brain development significantly.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We would like to acknowledge Shanghai Songjiang Center For Primate Brain Research and the Shanghai Quanlan Technology development team for their hard work on the LANMAO Sleep Recorder both in hardware and software.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s0007">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p>The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0008">
      <title>Ethics Approval and Consent to Participate</title>
      <p>The research ethics committee of the Obstetrics and Gynecology Hospital of Fudan University approved this study (approval No. (2023) 99), and informed written consent was obtained from the parents before participation. The study adhered to the ethical standards delineated in the Declaration of Helsinki guidelines.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0009">
      <title>Consent for Publication</title>
      <p>All authors consent to publication.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0010">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation, or in all these areas; took part in drafting, revising or critically reviewing the article; gave final approval of the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0011">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Graven</surname>
<given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Browne</surname>
<given-names>JV</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and brain development: the critical role of sleep in fetal and early neonatal brain development</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Newborn Infant Nurs Rev</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>179</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.nainr.2008.10.008</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hong</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maloney</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Keens</surname>
<given-names>TG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perez</surname>
<given-names>IA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep in Infants</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>198</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>P15</fpage>–<lpage>p6</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.1988P15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30320526</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pierce</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thompson</surname>
<given-names>BL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gharib</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of perceived maternal stress during the perinatal period with electroencephalography patterns in 2-month-old infants</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Pediatr</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>173</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>561</fpage>–<lpage>570</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapediatrics.2019.0492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30958515</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gan</surname>
<given-names>WB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>REM sleep selectively prunes and maintains new synapses in development and learning</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>437</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.4479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28092659</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tononi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cirelli</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and the price of plasticity: from synaptic and cellular homeostasis to memory consolidation and integration</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuron</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>81</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>12</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2013.12.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24411729</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Blumberg</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coleman</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gerth</surname>
<given-names>AI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McMurray</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Spatiotemporal structure of REM sleep twitching reveals developmental origins of motor synergies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Biol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):<fpage>2100</fpage>–<lpage>2109</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2013.08.055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24139739</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stickgold</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Walker</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep-dependent memory triage: evolving generalization through selective processing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.3303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23354387</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vyazovskiy</surname>
<given-names>VV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harris</surname>
<given-names>KD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and the single neuron: the role of global slow oscillations in individual cell rest</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>443</fpage>–<lpage>451</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn3494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23635871</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep health: can we define it? Does it matter?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.3298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24470692</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mindell</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep, mood, and development in infants</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infant Behav Dev</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>102</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.infbeh.2015.08.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26386882</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Brinkman</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reddy</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sharma</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <part-title>Physiology of Sleep</part-title>. In: <source><italic toggle="yes">StatPearls</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Treasure Island (FL)</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>StatPearls Publishing LLC</publisher-name>; <year>2024</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sadeh</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tikotzky</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kahn</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep in infancy and childhood: implications for emotional and behavioral difficulties in adolescence and beyond</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Opin Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>453</fpage>–<lpage>459</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25247458</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bertrand</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Transient neonatal sleep fragmentation results in long-term neuroinflammation and cognitive impairment in a rabbit model</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Exp Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>327</volume>:<fpage>113212</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.expneurol.2020.113212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31987835</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chaput</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gray</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poitras</surname>
<given-names>VJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Systematic review of the relationships between sleep duration and health indicators in school-aged children and youth</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Appl Physiol Nutr Metab</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>6 Suppl 3</issue>):<fpage>S266</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/apnm-2015-0627</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27306433</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dos Santos</surname>
<given-names>AÁ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rocha</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nunes</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Behavior and EEG concordance of active and quiet sleep in preterm very low birth weight and full-term neonates at matched conceptional age</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Early Human Dev</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>90</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>507</fpage>–<lpage>510</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.earlhumdev.2014.06.014</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Barbeau</surname>
<given-names>DY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weiss</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep Disturbances in Newborns</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Children</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>10</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/children4100090</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nash</surname>
<given-names>KB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bonifacio</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Glass</surname>
<given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Video-EEG monitoring in newborns with hypoxic-ischemic encephalopathy treated with hypothermia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>76</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>556</fpage>–<lpage>562</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0b013e31820af91a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21300971</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hoque</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chakkarapani</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thoresen</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A comparison of cooling methods used in therapeutic hypothermia for perinatal asphyxia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatrics</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>126</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e124</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2009-2995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20530071</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>O’Toole</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boylan</surname>
<given-names>GB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Quantitative Preterm EEG analysis: the need for caution in using modern data science techniques</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Pediatr</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>174</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fped.2019.00174</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31131267</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ryan</surname>
<given-names>MAJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malhotra</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Electrographic monitoring for seizure detection in the neonatal unit: current status and future direction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatr Res</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41390-024-03207-2</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Siddiqa</surname>
<given-names>HA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>ZN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Single-Channel EEG data analysis using a multi-branch CNN for neonatal sleep staging</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">IEEE Access</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>29910</fpage>–<lpage>29925</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ACCESS.2024.3365570</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Abbasi</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abbas</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ahmad</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Automatic neonatal sleep stage classification: a comparative study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Heliyon</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e22195</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e22195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38058619</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>O’Toole</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mathieson</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raurale</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Neonatal EEG graded for severity of background abnormalities in hypoxic-ischaemic encephalopathy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Data</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>129</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41597-023-02002-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36899033</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trabatti</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weeke</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Early qualitative and quantitative amplitude-integrated electroencephalogram and raw electroencephalogram for predicting long-term neurodevelopmental outcomes in extremely preterm infants in the Netherlands: a 10-year cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Digit Health</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>e895</fpage>–<lpage>e904</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2589-7500(23)00198-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37940489</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shellhaas</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wusthoff</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsuchida</surname>
<given-names>TN</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Profile of neonatal epilepsies: characteristics of a prospective US cohort</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>89</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>893</fpage>–<lpage>899</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000004284</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28733343</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Videman</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tokariev</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stjerna</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roivainen</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gaily</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vanhatalo</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of prenatal antiepileptic drug exposure on newborn brain activity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsia</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>252</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/epi.13281</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26705760</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Castro Conde</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>González González</surname>
<given-names>NL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>González Barrios</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>González Campo</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suárez Hernández</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sosa Comino</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Video-EEG recordings in full-term neonates of diabetic mothers: observational study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>98</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>F493</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/archdischild-2013-304283</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23873907</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stevenson</surname>
<given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lai</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Starkman</surname>
<given-names>HE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Colditz</surname>
<given-names>PB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wixey</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Electroencephalographic studies in growth-restricted and small-for-gestational-age neonates</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatr Res</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>92</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1527</fpage>–<lpage>1534</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41390-022-01992-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35197567</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vucinovic</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kardum</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bonkovic</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Resic</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ursic</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vukovic</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep EEG composition in the first three months of life in monozygotic and dizygotic twins</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Eeg Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1550059413497000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24323198</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shellhaas</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsuchida</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The American clinical neurophysiology society’s guideline on continuous electroencephalography monitoring in neonates</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Neurophysiol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>611</fpage>–<lpage>617</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/WNP.0b013e31823e96d7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22146359</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tsuchida</surname>
<given-names>TN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wusthoff</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shellhaas</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>American clinical neurophysiology society standardized EEG terminology and categorization for the description of continuous EEG monitoring in neonates: report of the American clinical neurophysiology society critical care monitoring committee</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Neurophysiol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>173</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/WNP.0b013e3182872b24</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23545767</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>O’ Toole</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boylan</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>NEURAL: quantitative features for newborn EEG using Matlab</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">arXiv e-prints</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>2017</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shellhaas</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burns</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barks</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chervin</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Quantitative sleep stage analyses as a window to neonatal neurologic function</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>82</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>390</fpage>–<lpage>395</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000000085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24384644</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Korotchikova</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Connolly</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ryan</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>EEG in the healthy term newborn within 12 hours of birth</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Neurophysiol</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>120</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1046</fpage>–<lpage>1053</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinph.2009.03.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19427811</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yuan</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Georgostathi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Quantitative electroencephalogram in term neonates under different sleep states</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Monit Comput</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>591</fpage>–<lpage>602</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10877-023-01082-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37851153</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Berry</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abreu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bibbs</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The AASM manual for the scoring of sleep and associated events</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Rul Terminol Techn Specific Dar Illin Am Acad Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>176</volume>(<issue>2012</issue>):<fpage>7</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dubnov</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Generalization of spectral flatness measure for non-Gaussian linear processes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">IEEE Signal Process Lett</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>698</fpage>–<lpage>701</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/LSP.2004.831663</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Burns</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rajan</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Combining complexity measures of EEG data: multiplying measures reveal previously hidden information</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">F1000Res</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>137</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12688/f1000research.6590.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26594331</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Hoban</surname>
<given-names>TF</given-names></string-name>. <part-title>Evolution of Sleep from Birth to Adolescence and Sleep Disorders in Children</part-title>. In: <string-name><surname>Chokroverty</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, editor. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Disorders Medicine: Basic Science, Technical Considerations and Clinical Aspects</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer New York</publisher-name>; <year>2017</year>:<fpage>1139</fpage>–<lpage>1158</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>O’Reilly</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Navakatikyan</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Filip</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Greene</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Marter</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Peak-to-peak amplitude in neonatal brain monitoring of premature infants</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Neurophysiol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>123</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2139</fpage>–<lpage>2153</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinph.2012.02.087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22608473</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Whitehead</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laudiano-Dray</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meek</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fabrizi</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Emergence of mature cortical activity in wakefulness and sleep in healthy preterm and full-term infants</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>8</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsy096</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Corsi-Cabrera</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cubero-Rego</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ricardo-Garcell</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harmony</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Week-by-week changes in sleep EEG in healthy full-term newborns</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>4</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsz261</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Paul</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krajca</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roth</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Melichar</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petránek</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Comparison of quantitative EEG characteristics of quiet and active sleep in newborns</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>543</fpage>–<lpage>552</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2003.08.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14607349</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
