<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39464514</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">11512559</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">483425</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S483425</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effect of General Anesthesia vs Regional Anesthesia on Sleep Disturbance in Elderly Patients After Discharge from the Hospital for 3 Months</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Cheng et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Cheng et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Haihong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Wei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Nasuhi</surname><given-names>Valeria Nahadi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Xiaoqiang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Chenyuan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Hang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Hongwei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Anesthesiology, Tongde Hospital Affiliated to Zhejiang Chinese Medical University (Tongde Hospital of Zhejiang Province)</institution>, <addr-line>Hangzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Zhejiang</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>The Second School of Clinical Medicine, Zhejiang Chinese Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Hangzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Zhejiang</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Hongwei Wang, <institution>Department of Anesthesiology, Tongde Hospital Affiliated to Zhejiang Chinese Medical University (Tongde Hospital of Zhejiang Province)</institution>, <addr-line>Hangzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Zhejiang</addr-line>, <addr-line>310012</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, <phone content-type="general">Tel +86 13857169356</phone>, Email wanghw1022@163.com</corresp><fn id="ft0001"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>1679</fpage><lpage>1686</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>03</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Cheng et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Cheng et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Purpose</title><p>This study aims to investigate the impact of anesthetic methods on the occurrence of postoperative sleep disorders in elderly patients following their discharge from the hospital for 3 months.</p></sec><sec><title>Patients and Methods</title><p>This retrospective observational cohort study included elderly patients aged &gt;60 years who had undergone general and regional anesthesia from 1 June 2023 to 31 December 2023. These patients were then assessed for sleep by telephone callback using the Athens Insomnia Scale after discharge from the hospital three months later. The duration of pain and sleep disturbance experienced by patients following discharge was also recorded.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Following propensity score matching, 308 individuals were included in the study (154 in the GA group and 154 in the RA group). Compared with general anesthesia (11.7%), regional anesthesia (5.2%) reduced the prevalence of sleep disorders in elderly patients after discharge from the hospital. However, the duration of sleep disturbance and pain exhibited no statistically significant difference between the two groups (p=0.818; p=0.211).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Regional anesthesia was associated with a reduction in the incidence of sleep disorders in elderly patients after discharge from the hospital for 3 months.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>sleep disturbance</kwd><kwd>regional anesthesia</kwd><kwd>general anesthesia</kwd><kwd>elderly patient</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="3"/><ref-count count="28"/><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Postoperative sleep disturbance refers to the occurrence of insomnia, drowsiness, sleep structure changes, and increased awakening frequency, which is one of the manifestations of postoperative brain dysfunction.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> One study reported that about 23% of patients experienced sleep problems after surgery.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Postoperative sleep disturbances can result in early postoperative fatigue, episodic hypoxemia, hemodynamic instability, and altered mental status. These factors can negatively impact postoperative outcomes.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Elderly patients commonly have a combination of illnesses and frailty.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Anesthesia, surgery, pain, and other multiple impacts make patients vulnerable to developing postoperative sleep disorders.</p>
      <p>General anesthesia is a drug-induced state of reduced consciousness that is believed to cause postoperative circadian rhythm disruption. It is regarded as a significant risk factor for the disruption of the patient’s sleep architecture and quality.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Research has shown that subarachnoid block is more beneficial than general anesthesia in elderly patients following hip fracture surgery, as subarachnoid block reduces the impairment of melatonin rhythm and sleep disturbances and reduces postoperative cognitive dysfunction.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> The study found that patients who underwent abdominal hysterectomy under subarachnoid block experienced significantly better sleep quality than those who underwent the procedure under general anesthesia.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></p>
      <p>Postoperative sleep disorders are associated with various postoperative complications, including paroxysmal hypoxemia, pain sensitization, cognitive dysfunction, and fluctuations in blood pressure and heart rhythm due to sympathetic excitation.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10–12</xref> The occurrence of sleep disturbance after surgery is prevalent among elderly patients.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> However, few studies have compared the effect of anesthesia methods on post-discharge sleep disorders in surgical patients. We hypothesize that elderly patients undergoing regional anesthesia (RA group) experience fewer post-discharge sleep disorders compared to those who undergo general anesthesia (GA group).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Ethical Approval and Patients</title>
        <p>This single-center retrospective observational cohort study was approved by the Ethics Committee of Tongde Hospital of Zhejiang Province (2023–092(K)) and complied with the Declaration of Helsinki. As all patients in the study had been discharged from the hospital, they were subsequently contacted by telephone. Following the obtaining of verbal consent from the patients at the time of the telephone callback, the next stage of the scale assessment was initiated. We got permission from the Ethics Committee of Tongde Hospital of Zhejiang Province to do the study without written consent and kept it in the form of telephone recordings. The study was also registered on the Chinese Clinical Trial Registry (ChiCTR2300076157). This study is reported in line with the STROBE statement.</p>
        <p>We accessed the hospital database, and recruitment for this study began on 1 June 2023 and ended on 31 December 2023. Inclusion Criteria: (1) patients older than 60 years of age, of either sex; (2) American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) physical status grade I–III; (3) telephone follow-up with verbal consent to participate in this study; (4) non-neurosurgical, non-cardiac surgery with general anesthesia (lasting more than 2 hours) or regional anesthesia (spinal anesthesia, epidural anesthesia, and brachial plexus block). Exclusion criteria: (1) patients with a history of sleep apnea syndrome and/or preoperative sleep disorders; (2) patients requiring long-term use of hypnotics and sedatives; (3) patients with a history of mental and psychological disorders and recent use of antipsychotic drugs and antidepressant drugs; (4) patients who are unwilling to participate or unable to communicate; (5) patients with severe cardiopulmonary disorders.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Study Protocol</title>
        <p>Demographic information, ASA physical status, type of anesthesia, and co-morbidities were recorded for each enrolled patient. To assess sleep disorders, we used the Athens Insomnia Scale (AIS),<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> which was designed by the Ohio State University College of Medicine in 1985. Because of the accuracy of its self-rating results and its ease of use, it has been widely used in clinical practice and has become a standard scale recognized by the international medical community for the assessment of insomnia. The AIS is a self-rating psychometric instrument designed to quantify sleep difficulties based on ICD-10 criteria. It consists of eight items: the first five relate to sleep onset, awakenings during the night, final awakening, total sleep time and sleep quality, and the last three refer to well-being, functional capacity, and daytime drowsiness. Insomnia can be diagnosed if the AIS score is 6 points or higher. The AIS score ranges from 0 to 24 points.</p>
        <p>The researchers collected data from patients who were discharged for three months after surgery. We followed up on the patients’ sleep status by telephone after discharge. Prior to the telephone callback, we screened the patients’ medical and medication histories. Prepared the discourse (without implying the patient, but a callback on the entire postoperative recovery) and performed an AIS score if the patient mentioned poor sleep and more than 3 times per week. We tried to be as objective as possible in our assessment. Sleep disorders are diagnosed when the AIS score exceeds 6. The primary outcome was the incidence of post-discharge sleep disorders, and the secondary outcomes were the duration of sleep disturbance and pain.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Sample Size</title>
        <p>A previous study found that the incidence of sleep deprivation during hospitalization was 22.95% for patients who received general anesthesia and 8.6% for those who received subarachnoid block.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> We applied the PASS 15 Power Analysis and Sample Size Software (NCSS, LLC. Kaysville, Utah, USA, ncss.com/software/pass) to determine our sample size. We selected the “proportions-two independent proportions-test (inequality)-test for two proportions” to count the number of patients required per group for 90% power to distinguish the variance, with a two-tailed significance level of 0.05. As a result, we computed a sample size of 132 patients per group. Considering the missing sample size after propensity score matching, we decided to recruit 172 patients in each group.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>Continuous variables with normal distribution were presented as mean ± standard deviation (SD). Non-normal variables were presented as median (interquartile range). The distribution of continuous variables was analyzed using the Kolmogorov–Smirnov normality test. Categorical data were expressed as percentages (%). Independent-sample <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test or Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test was used to analyze continuous variables. The χ2 test was used to analyze categorical variables.</p>
        <p>To reduce the likelihood of selection bias and baseline disparities between the RA and GA groups, propensity score matching (PSM) was conducted initially. The groups were matched in a 1:1 ratio using a caliper value of 0.02. The propensity score was calculated by using the following covariates: age, sex, smoking status, drinking status, and comorbid conditions. A binary logistic regression was conducted to examine the correlation between the anesthesia method and sleep disturbance after discharge. The level of statistical significance was set at a two-sided P value of &lt;0.05. Statistical analyses were performed using IBM SPSS Statistics 25.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>Between 1 June and 31 December 2023, a total of 561 participants aged over 60 years were enrolled in this trial. During follow-up phone calls, 103 individuals declined participation or were unreachable, 59 were excluded due to depression, insomnia, or related conditions, and 53 were unable to participate due to communication difficulties or an invalid phone number. Ultimately, 346 individuals were successfully followed up and included in the study (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>).
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Flow diagram of included patient numbers.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1679-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
      <p>There were no significant differences between the two groups at baseline before and after PSM, except for BMI and length of stay. (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Patient Demographics and Perioperative Characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Prematching</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Postmatching</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GA (172)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">RA (174)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GA(154)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">RA(154)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient age mean±SD, y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.8±6.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.5±7.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.657</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.7±6.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.7±7.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.980</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender, male/female (n)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89/83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91/83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.918</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80/74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80/74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, mean±SD, kg/m2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.4±2.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.7±2.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.5±2.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.7±2.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education qualification, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.665</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.856</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 Illiteracy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15(8.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16(9.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13(8.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15(9.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 Primary schools</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78(45.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74(42.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67(43.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62(40.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 high school</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68(39.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77(44.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65(42.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70(45.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3College and higher education</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11(6.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7(4.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9(5.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7(4.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASA physical status, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.570</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.413</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15(8.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14(8.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15(9.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14(9.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">148(86)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">146(83.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">131(85.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">126(81.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9(5.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14(8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8(5.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14(9.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking status, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44(25.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38(21.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.413</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38(24.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35(22.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.688</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drinking status, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17(9.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17(9.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.972</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14(9.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17(11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.570</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Preoperative comorbidity, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110(64.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96(55.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92(59.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92(59.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23(13.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37(21.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23(14.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25(16.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.753</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coronary heart disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10(5.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10(5.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.979</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10(6.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9(5.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.813</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of stay M (P 25, P 75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9(5, 13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10(6, 17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9(5, 13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10(6, 17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: BMI, body mass index; ASA, American Society of Anesthesiologists;</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p>The frequency of sleep disorders after discharge was higher in the GA (13.4%, 11.7%) compared to the RA group (6.3%, 5.2%) before and after matching (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Meanwhile, sleep disorders during hospitalization also showed a significant difference between the two groups before (p = 0.025) and after matching (p = 0.033) (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). However, both the duration of post-discharge sleep disturbance and pain showed no difference between the GA group and the RA group whether in prematching (p = 0.574, 0.772) or postmatching (p = 0.818, 0.211). There was also no difference in the sleep scores (AIS) on the GA and the RA groups before PSM (p =0.504) and after PSM (p = 0.578) (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The Comparison of Sleep Disorders Between the Group GA and the Group RA</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Prematching</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Postmatching</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GA (172)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">RA (174)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GA(154)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">RA(154)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Disorders During</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (4.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14(9.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5(3.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospitalisation n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Disorders Following</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (13.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (6.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18(11.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8(5.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital Discharge n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Secondary Outcomes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Prematching</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Postmatching</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GA (23)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">RA (11)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GA(18)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">RA(8)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of Sleep</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90(30, 90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90(30, 90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.574</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90(30, 90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90(30, 90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.818</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disturbance Following</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Discharge M (P 25, P 75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of Pain Following</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0 (0, 30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0, 90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.772</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5 (0, 30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0, 22.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.211</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Discharge M (P 25, P 75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AIS score M (mean±SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6±3.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.5±2.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.504</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6±3.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4±3.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.578</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviation</bold>: AIS, Athens Insomnia Scale.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p>Binary logistic regression was employed to investigate the risk factors linked to sleep disorders following discharge. Postdischarge sleep disorders are more likely to occur after general anesthesia than after regional anesthesia (p = 0.021; OR, 2.93; 95% CI, 1.18–7.28) (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).
<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Forest Plot of Factors Analyzed for Association with Incidence of Sleep Disturbance after Discharge from the Hospital in Binary Logistic Regression.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1679-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The important findings of this study were the presence of sleep disturbance in older patients who had no preoperative sleep disturbance after discharge, and the persistence of sleep disturbance for up to 3 months. Our study showed that in the older population, postdischarge sleep disturbance occurred after both general anesthesia and regional anesthesia. However, there was a higher incidence of sleep disorders in elderly patients who underwent general anesthesia than in this who underwent regional anesthesia, both during hospitalization (11%) and after discharge (13.4%), which is consistent with the previous literature.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> Gibian et al found that patients were still suffering from sleep disturbances an average of 90 days after surgery.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> This finding is also in line with our research. Our results indicate that older individuals experience sleep disturbances for up to three months after discharge, which seriously impacts the postoperative recovery of elderly patients.</p>
      <p>The results of this study show that general anesthesia is significantly associated with the incidence of postdischarge sleep disorders in elderly patients. General anesthesia is a drug-induced hyporesponsive state of consciousness.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Brain blood flow imaging studies have shown that anesthetic-induced loss of consciousness is similar to non-rapid eye movement,<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> and anesthesia leads to a decrease in both rapid eye movement sleep and slow wave sleep, a reduction in total sleep time, and an increase in sleep fragmentation. Similar to previous studies, when we administered the AIS scale questionnaire to patients who continued to have sleep disturbances after discharge, they reported not getting enough sleep overall, waking up easily during the night, and having difficulty falling asleep. Van Zuylen et al have also demonstrated that surgical procedures requiring general anesthesia result in a significant phase shift of diurnal sleep-wake rhythms and a deterioration of sleep quality.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Furthermore, general anesthetics such as propofol and thiopental sodium increase the activity of GABA neurons in the ventrolateral preoptic nucleus (VLPO) of the hypothalamus and induce sleep, and the hypothalamus, which is involved in sleep regulation, may be the target of general anesthetics for sedation and hypnosis.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> GABA also plays a significant role in resetting the circadian clock in response to changes in the light/dark cycle.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> This is crucial for gaining an understanding of the effects of general anesthesia on circadian rhythms, as most anesthetics are GABA agonists. In the meantime, some studies have demonstrated that GA has the capacity to modify the internal clock and disrupt circadian rhythms.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></p>
      <p>In contrast, regional anesthesia has less impact on postoperative sleep disturbances in older patients (5.2%). Factors affecting postoperative sleep disorders are complex, such as the severity of surgical trauma, age, anesthetic mode, postoperative pain, postoperative complications, anesthetics and analgesics, environmental and psychological factors.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> The lower incidence of postdischarge sleep disorders in elderly patients under regional anesthesia compared to general anesthesia may be attributed to several factors: (1) Regional anesthesia is a local anesthetic that does not suppress the central nervous system and has less impact on brain function. (2) Regional anesthesia can effectively block the stress response triggered by incoming injurious stimuli, such as surgical operations, by inhibiting the upward transmission pathway of the reflex arc of the corresponding injurious stimuli. Song et al found that regional anesthesia reduces the impairment of melatonin rhythm and sleep. In their study, surgical trauma and inflammatory cytokine levels were similar between the GA and RA groups, except for pain scores. Therefore, it is thought that the differences in melatonin secretion between the two groups may be related to the anesthetic method and associated pain management.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> However, a randomized, controlled, open multicenter trial (82 patients who received spinal anesthesia and 80 patients who received general anesthesia) demonstrated that the sleep quality was better in the SA group than in the GA group, but they attributed this to lower opioid consumption in the SA group.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> In our study, there was no statistically significant difference in the duration of pain and disturbance between the two groups (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>), but the median duration of pain was shorter than the duration of sleep disorders. This means that patients may continue to experience sleep disturbance even when their pain was no longer present after they have been discharged from the hospital, which requires further study.</p>
      <p>There are several limitations in our study. First, this retrospective study was unable to use objective indicators to record changes in patients’ sleep rhythms, such as polysomnography and sleep logs, to track patients’ sleep-wake patterns. Second, since the consultation was conducted via telephone, it was difficult to accurately assess the patient’s level of pain using visual analogue scale or numerical rating scale. Third, although we tried to identify and exclude patients with unclear recall of their post-discharge sleep disorders as objectively as possible, recall bias may still exist. Forth, this cohort study was observational and exploratory. Consequently, we are unable to rule out the chance of unmeasured group confounding. Prospective, randomized, controlled, multicentre studies are needed to further clarify the long-term effects of methods of anesthesia on sleep disturbance in older patients.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>In summary, regional anesthesia was associated with a reduction in the incidence of sleep disorders in elderly patients after discharge from the hospital for 3 months. Our findings suggest that the choice of anesthetic method may influence the incidence of sleep disturbances in elderly patients. Further research is needed.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We are grateful to those who have given us guidance on the statistical methods and the linguistic nuances of this experiment.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0006">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>All authors have no conflicts of interest, financial or otherwise to disclose for this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rosenberg</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disturbances after non-cardiac surgery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>129</fpage>–<lpage>137</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/smrv.2000.0121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12531050</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rosenberg-Adamsen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kehlet</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dodds</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosenberg</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Postoperative sleep disturbances: mechanisms and clinical implications</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Br J Anaesth</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>76</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>552</fpage>–<lpage>559</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bja/76.4.552</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8652329</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kain</surname>
<given-names>ZN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caldwell-Andrews</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleeping characteristics of adults undergoing outpatient elective surgery: a cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Anesthesia</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>505</fpage>–<lpage>509</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclinane.2003.02.002</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Krenk</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jennum</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kehlet</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disturbances after fast-track Hip and knee arthroplasty</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Br J Anaesth</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>109</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>769</fpage>–<lpage>775</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bja/aes252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22831887</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hoogendijk</surname>
<given-names>EO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Afilalo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ensrud</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kowal</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Onder</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fried</surname>
<given-names>LP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Frailty: implications for clinical practice and public health</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>394</volume>(<issue>10206</issue>):<fpage>1365</fpage>–<lpage>1375</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(19)31786-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31609228</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dent</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>FC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bergman</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Woo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Romero-Ortuno</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Walston</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Management of frailty: opportunities, challenges, and future directions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>394</volume>(<issue>10206</issue>):<fpage>1376</fpage>–<lpage>1386</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(19)31785-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31609229</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disturbances after general anesthesia: current perspectives</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fneur.2020.00629</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yuan</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of general versus subarachnoid anaesthesia on circadian melatonin rhythm and postoperative delirium in elderly patients undergoing Hip fracture surgery: a prospective cohort clinical trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">EBioMedicine</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>103490</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ebiom.2021.103490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34280784</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kjølhede</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Langström</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nilsson</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wodlin</surname>
<given-names>NB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nilsson</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The impact of quality of sleep on recovery from fast-track abdominal hysterectomy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>08</volume>(<issue>04</issue>):<fpage>395</fpage>–<lpage>402</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.2032</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rampes</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Divecha</surname>
<given-names>YA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alam</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Postoperative sleep disorders and their potential impacts on surgical outcomes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Biomed Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>271</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7555/JBR.33.20190054</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chouchou</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khoury</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chauny</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Denis</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lavigne</surname>
<given-names>GJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Postoperative sleep disruptions: a potential catalyst of acute pain?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2013.07.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24074687</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gögenur</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Middleton</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burgdorf</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rasmussen</surname>
<given-names>LS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Skene</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosenberg</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Impact of sleep and circadian disturbances in urinary 6-sulphatoxymelatonin levels, on cognitive function after major surgery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Pineal Res</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>184</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-079X.2007.00460.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17645696</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Su</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>D-X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Improve postoperative sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Opin Anaesthesiol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ACO.0000000000000538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29120927</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Soldatos</surname>
<given-names>CR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dikeos</surname>
<given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paparrigopoulos</surname>
<given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Athens insomnia scale: validation of an instrument based on ICD-10 criteria</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychosomatic Res</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>555</fpage>–<lpage>560</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-3999(00)00095-7</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lei</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fu</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ye</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Propofol and sufentanil may affect the patients’ sleep quality independently of the surgical stress response: a prospective nonrandomized controlled trial in 1033 patients’ undergone diagnostic upper gastrointestinal endoscopy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Anesthesiol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>53</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12871-017-0341-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28359259</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gibian</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bartosiak</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lucey</surname>
<given-names>BP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Riegler</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>King</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barrack</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disturbances following total knee arthroplasty</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Arthroplasty</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>S120</fpage>–<lpage>S124</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2023.01.066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36773659</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pitaro</surname>
<given-names>NL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Herrera</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alasadi</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep disturbance trends in the short-term postoperative period for patients undergoing total joint arthroplasty</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Acad Orthopaedic Surg</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>e859</fpage>–<lpage>e867</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kushikata</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yosmda</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yasuda</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tose</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hirota</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matsuki</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and anesthesia--part 2, on the relationship between sleep and general anesthesia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Masui Japanese J Anesthesiol</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1148</fpage>–<lpage>1154</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nelson</surname>
<given-names>LE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Franks</surname>
<given-names>NP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maze</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Rested and refreshed after anesthesia? Overlapping neurobiologic mechanisms of sleep and anesthesia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Anesthesiology</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>100</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1341</fpage>–<lpage>1342</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000542-200406000-00003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15166550</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Alkire</surname>
<given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hudetz</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tononi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Consciousness and anesthesia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Science</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>322</volume>(<issue>5903</issue>):<fpage>876</fpage>–<lpage>880</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1149213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18988836</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>van Zuylen</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meewisse</surname>
<given-names>AJG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ten Hoope</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of surgery and general anaesthesia on sleep–wake timing: CLOCKS observational study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Anaesthesia</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>77</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/anae.15564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34418064</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mashour</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hudetz</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Bottom-up and top-down mechanisms of general anesthetics modulate different dimensions of consciousness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Neural Circuits</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>44</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fncir.2017.00044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28676745</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fukuda</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yasuda</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect sites of anesthetics in the central nervous system network--looking into the mechanisms for natural sleep and anesthesia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Masui Japanese J Anesthesiol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>544</fpage>–<lpage>558</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Myung</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hong</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>DeWoskin</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Schutter</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Forger</surname>
<given-names>DB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Takumi</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>GABA-mediated repulsive coupling between circadian clock neurons in the SCN encodes seasonal time</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>112</volume>(<issue>29</issue>):<fpage>E3920</fpage>–<lpage>3929</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26130804</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ralph</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Menaker</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>GABA regulation of circadian responses to light. I. Involvement of GABAA-benzodiazepine and GABAB receptors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurosci: Off J Soc Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>2858</fpage>–<lpage>2865</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.09-08-02858.1989</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Coppola</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caccioppola</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chiumello</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Internal clock and the surgical ICU patient</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Opin Anaesthesiol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>184</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ACO.0000000000000816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31815822</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Poulsen</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Warman</surname>
<given-names>GR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sleigh</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ludin</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheeseman</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>How does general anaesthesia affect the circadian clock?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2016.12.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28162920</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Haack</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simpson</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sethna</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaur</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mullington</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep deficiency and chronic pain: potential underlying mechanisms and clinical implications</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropsychopharmacology</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>216</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41386-019-0439-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31207606</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
