<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39473629</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">11520919</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">490206</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S490206</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Pre-Sleep Arousal Scale (PSAS): Translation and Evaluation of Its Psychometric Properties in an Arabic Version</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">AlSaleh et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">AlSaleh et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>AlSaleh</surname><given-names>Aseel</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3047-1834</contrib-id><name><surname>Husain</surname><given-names>Waqar</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Trabelsi</surname><given-names>Khaled</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ghazzawi</surname><given-names>Hadeel</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0347-8053</contrib-id><name><surname>Ammar</surname><given-names>Achraf</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0006" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0007" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saif</surname><given-names>Zahra</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0008" ref-type="aff">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pandi-Perumal</surname><given-names>Seithikurippu R</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0009" ref-type="aff">
<sup>9</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6668-2874</contrib-id><name><surname>AlRasheed</surname><given-names>Maha M</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0011" ref-type="aff">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1706-6167</contrib-id><name><surname>BaHammam</surname><given-names>Ahmed S</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0012" ref-type="aff">
<sup>12</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0013" ref-type="aff">
<sup>13</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8990-1320</contrib-id><name><surname>Jahrami</surname><given-names>Haitham</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0008" ref-type="aff">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0014" ref-type="aff">
<sup>14</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Family and Community Medicine, College of Medicine and Health Sciences, Arabian Gulf University</institution>, <addr-line>Manama</addr-line>, <country>Bahrain</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Humanities, COMSATS University Islamabad, Islamabad Campus</institution>, <addr-line>Islamabad</addr-line>, <country>Pakistan</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>High Institute of Sport and Physical Education of Sfax, University of Sfax</institution>, <addr-line>Sfax</addr-line>, <addr-line>3000</addr-line>, <country>Tunisia</country></aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Research Laboratory: Education, Motricity, Sport and Health, EM2S, LR19JS01, University of Sfax</institution>, <addr-line>Sfax</addr-line>, <addr-line>3000</addr-line>, <country>Tunisia</country></aff><aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label><institution>Nutrition and Food Technology Department, Agriculture School, The University of Jordan</institution>, <addr-line>Amman</addr-line>, <country>Jordan</country></aff><aff id="aff0006"><label>6</label><institution>Department of Training and Movement Science, Institute of Sport Science, Johannes Gutenberg-University Mainz</institution>, <addr-line>Mainz</addr-line>, <addr-line>55099</addr-line>, <country>Germany</country></aff><aff id="aff0007"><label>7</label><institution>Research Laboratory, Molecular Bases of Human Pathology, LR19ES13, Faculty of Medicine of Sfax, University of Sfax</institution>, <addr-line>Sfax</addr-line>, <addr-line>3000</addr-line>, <country>Tunisia</country></aff><aff id="aff0008"><label>8</label><institution>Department of Psychiatry, Government Hospitals</institution>, <addr-line>Manama</addr-line>, <country>Bahrain</country></aff><aff id="aff0009"><label>9</label><institution>Centre for Research and Development, Chandigarh University</institution>, <addr-line>Mohali</addr-line>, <addr-line>Punjab</addr-line>, <addr-line>140413</addr-line>, <country>India</country></aff><aff id="aff0010"><label>10</label><institution>Division of Research and Development, Lovely Professional University</institution>, <addr-line>Phagwara</addr-line>, <addr-line>Punjab</addr-line>, <addr-line>144411</addr-line>, <country>India</country></aff><aff id="aff0011"><label>11</label><institution>Department of Clinical Pharmacy, College of Pharmacy, King Saud University</institution>, <addr-line>Riyadh</addr-line>, <addr-line>11451</addr-line>, <country>Saudi Arabia</country></aff><aff id="aff0012"><label>12</label><institution>The University Sleep Disorders Center, Department of Medicine, College of Medicine, King Saud University, King Saud University</institution>, <addr-line>Riyadh</addr-line>, <country>Saudi Arabia</country></aff><aff id="aff0013"><label>13</label><institution>King Saud University Medical City, King Saud University</institution>, <addr-line>Riyadh</addr-line>, <country>Saudi Arabia</country></aff><aff id="aff0014"><label>14</label><institution>Department of Psychiatry, College of Medicine and Health Sciences, Arabian Gulf University</institution>, <addr-line>Manama</addr-line>, <country>Bahrain</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Haitham Jahrami, <institution>Department of Psychiatry, College of Medicine and Health Sciences, Arabian Gulf University</institution>, <addr-line>Manama</addr-line>, <country>Bahrain</country>, Email haitham.jahrami@outlook.com</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>1725</fpage><lpage>1735</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 AlSaleh et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>AlSaleh et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Purpose</title><p>The Pre-Sleep Arousal Scale (PSAS) is a well-recognized instrument utilized for measuring cognitive and somatic arousal before sleep. Although the PSAS is useful, an Arabic version of the scale has not yet been developed and validated. The current study aimed to translate the PSAS into Arabic language and evaluate its psychometric properties, such as reliability and validity, in an Arabic-speaking population.</p></sec><sec><title>Patients and Methods</title><p>A cross-sectional survey was conducted with 438 participants who completed the Arabic version of the PSAS, along with other validated measures of insomnia, anxiety, and sleep effort.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The results indicated that the Arabic version of the PSAS maintained the original scale’s two-factor structure. The factor loadings for PSAS-Cognitive ranged from 0.57 to 0.75, and for PSAS-Somatic, from 0.45 to 0.70, with all loadings being statistically significant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001). The Arabic version of the PSAS exhibited high internal consistency (McDonald’s <italic toggle="yes">ω</italic> = 0.86; Cronbach’s <italic toggle="yes">α</italic> = 0.86; Guttman’s <italic toggle="yes">λ</italic>2 = 0.86; Greatest Lower Boun<italic toggle="yes">d</italic> = 0.90) and test–retest reliability (ICC = 0.88) over two weeks. The PSAS demonstrated good concurrent and convergent validity. We documented significant large differences between individuals with “no insomnia” and those with “insomnia” symptoms across cognitive, somatic, and total pre-sleep arousal (all <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt;0.001). The insomnia group consistently scored higher scores for PSAP and its subscales.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>These findings suggest that the Arabic version of the PSAS is a reliable and valid tool for assessing pre-sleep arousal in Arabic-speaking individuals.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Arabic version</kwd><kwd>insomnia</kwd><kwd>pre-sleep arousal</kwd><kwd>PSAS</kwd><kwd>psychometric properties</kwd><kwd>reliability</kwd><kwd>validity</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="4"/><ref-count count="50"/><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Sleep is a basic human need that is pivotal for health including physical health, mental health, cognitive function, and emotional well-being.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Adequate sleep quality and quantity are associated with numerous health benefits,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> including enhanced immune function,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> learning and memory,<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> emotional stability,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> mental health,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> and cardiovascular health.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Contrariwise, chronic sleep deprivation or poor sleep quality can lead to negative health outcomes such as obesity,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> diabetes,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> hypertension,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> depression,<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> and even premature death.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Insufficient sleep can disrupt hormone balance,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> impacting appetite regulation,<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> metabolism,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> and overall health, potentially leading to weight gain<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> and metabolic diseases.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Therefore, prioritizing optimal sleep hygiene and addressing sleep-related dysfunctions are essential for promoting longevity and general well-being.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></p>
      <p>Insomnia, as defined by criteria, is a prevalent sleep disorder characterized by difficulties in initiating or maintaining sleep or experiencing non-restorative sleep despite adequate opportunity and circumstances for sleep. It is diagnosed based on criteria outlined in the International Classification of Sleep Disorders (ICSD-3-TR),<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-5),<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> and the International Classification of Diseases, 11th Revision (ICD-11).<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> These criteria emphasize the presence of sleep difficulties that occur at least three times per week and persist for at least three months, causing significant distress or impairment in social, occupational, or other important areas of functioning.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16–18</xref> Understanding these diagnostic criteria is crucial for identifying insomnia, as it helps distinguish it from other sleep disorders and guides appropriate treatment interventions.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16–18</xref></p>
      <p>Hyperarousal, which involves cognitive and somatic components, plays an important role in insomnia by disrupting sleep onset and maintenance.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> Research findings indicate that individuals with insomnia project higher levels of pre-sleep arousal, both cognitive and somatic.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Hyperarousal is also associated with increased cortical arousal during both non-rapid eye movement (NREM) and rapid eye movement (REM) sleep.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Earlier studies reveal that self-reported pre-sleep arousal mediates the relationship between sleep-wake state discrepancy and the severity of insomnia.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Individuals with insomnia also demonstrate altered heart rate dynamics during the sleep onset period reflecting lower vagal activity and reduced heart rate variability.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> These findings highlight the significance of addressing hyperarousal (ie, cognitive and somatic) in the measurement and treatment of insomnia to improve sleep quality and overall well-being.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></p>
      <p>The Pre-Sleep Arousal Scale (PSAS) was developed by Nicassio et al in 1985.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> The PSAS is a widely used instrument in research and clinical practice, with about 800 citations according to MEDLINE as of August 2024. The PSAS assesses pre-sleep arousal through two domains or subscales: cognitive and somatic.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Cognitive arousal involves thoughts and worries that prevent sleep onset.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Somatic arousal involves physiological symptoms such as palpitation or muscular tension.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> The original PSAS has projected good reliability and validity across diversified populations as it has been translated into other languages, such as Portuguese,<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> Japanese,<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Swedish.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> The correlation between cognitive arousal and increased cortical arousal during NREM and REM sleep measured by the PSAS suggests a link between pre-sleep worry and rumination with nighttime arousal levels, highlighting the scale’s importance in understanding insomnia mechanisms.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></p>
      <p>The absence of a published validated Arabic version of the PSAS (or similar measure) poses a limitation in assessing pre-sleep arousal components in Arabic-speaking populations. Psychometric studies in the field of sleep medicine have highlighted the importance of having culturally adapted and validated scales to ensure accurate measurements in different populations.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29–32</xref> Developing and validating an Arabic version of the PSAS could enhance its utility in assessing pre-sleep arousal in Arabic-speaking individuals, contributing to more comprehensive research and clinical practices in this population.</p>
      <p>This study aimed to fill the above gap by translating the PSAS into Arabic and evaluating its psychometric properties, including reliability and structural validity. The translation process followed established guidelines to ensure the linguistic and cultural suitability of the Arabic version; thus, we hypothesize that the psychometric properties of the Arabic version of the PSAS echo the original English language version.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Material and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>The Translation Processes</title>
        <p>The objective of this study was to translate and validate the PSAS scale<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> into Arabic. Prior to translation, Dr. Nicassio provided written approval in July 2024 for the questionnaire to be translated and validated in Arabic. We employed a rigorous method known as forward-backward translation to carry out the process of translation. Initially, the two members of our research team (HG &amp; HJ) translated the English version of PSAS into Modern Standard Arabic. Subsequently, a proficient linguist (ZS), who is also affiliated with the research team, conducted an independent backward translation of the Arabic version into English. Three collaborators of the research team (AA, KT, and WHS) reviewed the linguist’s back-translated English version alongside the original English version of the PSAS to ensure accuracy and equivalence. Based on this comparison, any necessary changes were made to the Arabic version. The Arabic version of the questionnaire was tested with a group of 25 individuals from the target demographic to evaluate the clarity and understanding of the items. After the pilot, feedback was gathered on how well participants understood the questions and the overall structure of the questionnaire. This feedback was analyzed, leading to necessary revisions to enhance the questionnaire, ensuring it was culturally relevant and linguistically precise for the intended audience. Following this stage, the questionnaire demonstrated clarity, and no further changes were required. Participants who took part in the pilot test were excluded from the main analyses according to our study methodology protocol. Furthermore, an expert panel consisting of professionals in sleep medicine and psychology reviewed the questionnaire to ensure that the items were both understandable and relevant for the target population, including patients with insomnia. This combination of pilot testing and expert consultation allowed for necessary revisions to enhance the questionnaire’s cultural appropriateness and linguistic accuracy, ensuring that it effectively addressed the needs of the intended audience. Following these adjustments, the final version of the questionnaire demonstrated clarity, and no further changes were deemed necessary.</p>
        <p>To validate the translated Arabic version for use in Arabic-speaking populations, the final translated version of the PSAS was later assessed for its psychometric properties, including validity and reliability, on a large sample of individuals whose mother tongue is Arabic.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Data Collection Approach</title>
        <p>The Arabic version of the PSAS questionnaire was distributed via various social media channels in predetermined Arab countries, which was agreed upon among the researchers, including Bahrain, Saudi Arabia, Jordan, and Tunisia. For this purpose, various social media platforms were used. This includes, but is not limited to, instant messaging services (eg, LINE, Telegram, Viber, and WhatsApp) as well as social media platforms (eg, Discord, Facebook, Instagram, LinkedIn, Pinterest, and Twitter/X). This approach of utilizing social media platforms has been successfully employed in previous studies to translate and validate several scales in sleep medicine.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29–32</xref> Prior to the initiation of the survey, all participants gave their informed consent. The questionnaire asked about age, sex, marital status, and other sociodemographic details. It also included the PSAS scale in Arabic translation. In addition, the participants completed the Athens Insomnia Scale (AIS),<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Generalized Anxiety Disorder Scale-7 (GAD-7),<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> and Glasgow Sleep Effort Scale (GSES).<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> To evaluate test–retest reliability, the participants were asked to retake the PSAS around two weeks following the original administration. We excluded individuals with a known history of mental illness, chronic medical conditions, or those currently undergoing treatment for such conditions.</p>
        <p>In our online data collection process, we implemented several measures to ensure data quality and prevent duplicate participation. We excluded no participants from the final analysis. To prevent re-participation, we employed procedures to identify and remove potential duplicate submissions. Furthermore, for each country, we used unique, single-use survey links distributed through our recruitment channels, further reducing the likelihood of multiple participations by the same individual.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Participation and Power Calculation</title>
        <p>Factor analysis required a minimum sample size of about 160 respondents for Arabic validation. For every question on the questionnaire, five to ten participants were required. Nonetheless, a total of 438 people filled out the forms, with 100–120 participants from each of the following countries: Bahrain, Saudi Arabia, Jordan, and Tunisia. These countries were deliberately selected to represent the broad spectrum of Arabic dialects across different regions.</p>
        <p>To ensure the integrity of our data all fields were mandatory thereby avoiding any missing data in our analyses.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Instruments</title>
        <sec id="s0002-s2004-s3001">
          <title>Pre-Sleep Arousal Scale (PSAS)</title>
          <p>The Pre-Sleep Arousal Scale (PSAS) includes 16 items.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> The items are divided into two subscales namely cognitive and somatic arousal.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> The response to each item ranges between 1 and 5, in which 1 = not at all and 5 = extremely.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Thus, the total score ranges between 16 and 80.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> A high total score indicates greater pre-sleep arousal, suggesting higher difficulty in falling asleep.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> In the original English-language version of the PSAS good reliability was demonstrated by the PSAS items and subscales (<italic toggle="yes">α</italic>= 0.79–0.81; test-retest <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.72–0.76).<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> The PSAS distinguishes between people who have “insomnia” and those with “no insomnia” symptoms.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2004-s3002">
          <title>Athens Insomnia Scale (AIS)</title>
          <p>The eight-item self-assessment list included in the AIS was created in 2000 by Soldatos et al based on the diagnostic criteria of insomnia proposed by the International Classification of Diseases (ICD-10).<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> The eight questions measure the following: the time at which sleep is initiated, the duration and quality of sleep, the frequency and duration of complaints, the commencement of insomnia that caused discomfort, and the interference with day-to-day activities.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Each item is given a 4-point rating: 0 represents absolutely no difficulty, 1 indicates a minor problem, 2 indicates unquestionably a problem, and 3 indicates a very serious problem.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> A higher score signifies higher symptoms of insomnia.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> The total score runs from 0 to 24. The optimal conformation score for pathological insomnia was found to be 6 which was used in this research study to define individuals with insomnia.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> Participants scoring below 6 were considered to have no significant insomnia symptoms, while those scoring 6 or higher were classified as having insomnia. This distinction helps in accurately identifying and assessing the severity of insomnia within the study population. A recent meta-analysis found that the AIS has an excellent internal consistency and retest reliability of 0.84 (95% CI: 0.81 to 0.86) and 0.86 (95% CI: 0.80 to 0.92), respectively.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> The Arabic version was employed in this research which has excellent psychometric properties, <italic toggle="yes">α</italic> =0.84.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2004-s3003">
          <title>Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7 Scale (GAD-7)</title>
          <p>One tool for determining the severity of GAD is the GAD-7 self-assessment scale. Spitzer et al established a basic score that was designed at the outset for primary care settings to facilitate the identification of GAD.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> The seven items in the GAD-7 assess nearly all of the major diagnostic characteristics of generalized anxiety disorder (GAD) (ie, tense sensations, anxiety, or on edge and excessive concern over things not similar to things).<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> A 4-point Likert scale is used to rate the items (0 = not at all, 1 = several days, 2 = more than half of the days, and 3 = almost every day).<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> This score has a range of 0 to 21, with a higher number denoting more severe GAD. It was shown that the ideal cutoff score for GAD was 10.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> In the current investigation, the GAD-7 Arabic version—which boasts an exceptional internal consistency of &gt;0.85—was employed.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> The Arabic version was employed in this research, which has excellent psychometric properties, <italic toggle="yes">α</italic> = 0.85.<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2004-s3004">
          <title>Glasgow Sleep Effort Scale (GSES)</title>
          <p>Seven items make up the GSES and are identified as essential elements of sleep effort.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> Each item has a response option that ranges from 0 to 2: where 0 means not at all, 1 means somewhat, and 2 means very much.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> The overall result can be anything from 0 to 14. A high overall score suggests that getting sleep requires more effort.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> The Arabic version was employed in this research, which has excellent psychometric properties, <italic toggle="yes">α</italic> = 0.87.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Ethical Conformity</title>
        <p>The study was carried out in compliance with the 1964 helsinki Declaration and its subsequent revisions (1975, 1983, 1989, and 1996). The Research Committee of the Government Hospitals in Bahrain reviewed and approved the study (Code: REC/2024-187). Participation in the study was voluntary. The Participants could withdraw from the study at any time without facing any penalties. Every participant in the study was an adult, aged at least eighteen years. Participants did not receive any financial or non-financial incentives.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2006">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>For continuous data, descriptive statistics were computed, including mean, standard deviation (±SD), skewness, and kurtosis.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> Multiple coefficients were used to analyze the PSAS’s dependability.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> These offered a thorough assessment of internal consistency and included the Greatest Lower Bound, Guttman’s <italic toggle="yes">λ</italic>2, McDonald’s <italic toggle="yes">ω</italic>, and Cronbach’s <italic toggle="yes">α</italic>.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> We used the intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC) to measure the test–retest reliability.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> ICC is an analytical tool used to evaluate the degree of consistency or agreement between measurements made at various times.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></p>
        <p>The structural validity of the two-component model of cognitive and somatic arousal was assessed using confirmatory factor analysis (CFA)<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> using the Maximum likelihood estimator with no rotation. To establish the appropriateness of the model, factor loadings, residual variances, and other fit indices were computed.<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> Construct validity was further evaluated by calculating the Heterotrait-Monotrait Ratio (HTMT) and Average Variance Extracted (AVE).<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> Fit quality was assessed using the comparative fit index (CFI) and the Tucker-Lewis index (TLI) with a cutoff of CFI &gt; 0.90 and TLI &gt; 0.90.<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> Additional calculations were conducted for the root mean square error of approximation (RMSEA) and its 95% confidence interval (95% CI), the normal chi-square (3 &gt; χ2/df &lt; 2), and the root mean square residual (RMSR &lt; 0.08).<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></p>
        <p>The decision to conduct a CFA rather than an Exploratory Factor Analysis (EFA) was based on the existing literature, where the PSAS has been translated into several other languages and consistently demonstrated a stable two-factor structure.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25–27</xref>,<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> Given this well-established factorial stability, we hypothesized that the Arabic version would exhibit a similar structure. Therefore, performing a CFA was appropriate to confirm this expected model in our study. Additionally, previous research indicates that both EFA and CFA would likely yield similar solutions, supporting the robustness of the two-factor model across different cultural contexts.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25–27</xref>,<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></p>
        <p>Correlations between the PSAS subscales, PSAS total scores, and related measures (AIS, GAD-7, and GSES) were used to evaluate concurrent validity.</p>
        <p>Independent samples <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-tests were used to compare the PSAS scores of individuals with and without insomnia to assess criterion validity.</p>
        <p>Statistical analysis was performed using the R Statistical Foundation R version 4.4.0 (Puppy Cup), released on 2024–04-24. A p-value &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>The study sample comprised 438 participants with a mean age of 34.86 years (<italic toggle="yes">SD</italic> = 4.25). The sex distribution was relatively balanced, with 236 females (53.9%) and 202 males (46.1%).</p>
      <p>The PSAS consists of two factors: Cognitive (F1) and Somatic (F2). The Cognitive-PSAS had a mean of 15.03 (<italic toggle="yes">SD</italic> = 6.34) with slight positive skewness (0.12) and negative kurtosis (−0.20). The Somatic-PSAS showed a higher mean of 18.55 (<italic toggle="yes">SD</italic> = 5.69) with moderate negative skewness (−0.48) and positive kurtosis (0.46). The total PSAS score averaged 33.58 (<italic toggle="yes">SD</italic> = 10.57). The AIS, GAD-7, and GSES yielded a mean of 5.22 (<italic toggle="yes">SD</italic> = 3.19), 9.4 (<italic toggle="yes">SD</italic> = 5.2), and 6.37 (<italic toggle="yes">SD</italic> = 4.16), respectively (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Descriptive Statistics of the Study Sample (N =438)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skewness</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kurtosis</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (in years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Female (236, 53.9%) and Male (202, 46.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F1 Cognitive-PSAS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.20</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F2 Somatic-PSAS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AIS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.58</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAD-7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.53</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSES Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.94</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Factor 1 = PSAS-Cognitive. Factor 2 = PSAS-Somatic.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: PSAS, pre-sleep arousal scale; AIS, Athens insomnia scale; GAD-7, Generalized Anxiety Disorder Scale - 7 items; GSES, Glasgow sleep effort scale.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p>The reliability analysis of the PSAS was conducted on the entire sample of 438 participants, examining both the Cognitive and Somatic subscales. For the PSAS-Cognitive subscale, McDonald’s <italic toggle="yes">ω</italic>, Cronbach’s <italic toggle="yes">α</italic>, and Guttman’s <italic toggle="yes">λ</italic>2 all showed identical values of 0.86 (95% CI: 0.84, 0.88), while the Greatest Lower Bound was slightly higher at 0.90 (95% CI: 0.88, 0.92). For the PSAS-Somatic subscale, the reliability coefficients were also strong, with McDonald’s <italic toggle="yes">ω</italic>, Cronbach’s <italic toggle="yes">α</italic>, and Guttman’s <italic toggle="yes">λ</italic>2 all at 0.80 (95% CI: 0.77, 0.83 for <italic toggle="yes">ω</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">α</italic>; 0.76, 0.83 for <italic toggle="yes">λ</italic>2), and the Greatest Lower Bound at 0.85 (95% CI: 0.83, 0.88). Test–retest reliability of the PSAS after two weeks was 0.88 (95% CI: 0.86, 0.90). When analyzing the impact of removing individual items from the PSAS-cognitive subscale or the PSAS-somatic subscale, the reliability coefficients remained unchanged (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Reliability Analysis of the PSAS (N =438)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Domain/Item</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">McDonald’s <italic toggle="yes">ω</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cronbach’s <italic toggle="yes">α</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guttman’s <italic toggle="yes">λ</italic>2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greatest Lower Bound</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSAS-Cognitive</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.86 (0.84, 0.88)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.86 (0.84, 0.88)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.86 (0.84, 0.88)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.90 (0.88, 0.92)</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">If item deleted - PSAS-Cognitive</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSAS-Somatic</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.80 (0.77, 0.83)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.80 (0.77, 0.83)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.80 (0.76, 0.83)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.85 (0.83, 0.88)</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">If item deleted - PSAS-Somatic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Factor 1 = PSAS-Cognitive. Factor 2 = PSAS-Somatic. All values are expressed as estimate (95% confidence intervals).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p>The structural validity analysis of the PSAS was conducted by examining a two-factor model consisting of Cognitive (F1) and Somatic (F2) subscales. Factor loadings for all items under both subscales were statistically significant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001), indicating that each item contributes meaningfully to its respective factor. For the Cognitive subscale (F1), factor loadings ranged from 0.57 to 0.75, with PSAS2 showing the highest loading (0.75) and PSAS5 the lowest (0.57). Residual variances for this subscale ranged from 0.43 to 0.68, suggesting varying degrees of item-specific variance not accounted for by the factor (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Confirmatory Factor Analysis/Structural Validity of the PSAS (N =438)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Factor</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Indicator</th><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Factor Loading</th><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Residual Variance</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimate</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">z</italic>-Value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-Value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimate</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">z</italic>-Value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: F1 = PSAS-Cognitive. F2 = PSAS-Somatic. All values are standardized. The estimator used is Maximum Likelihood (ML). The baseline model has a <italic toggle="yes">Χ²</italic> of 2392.89 with 120 degrees of freedom. The factor model shows a <italic toggle="yes">Χ²</italic> of 336.42 with 103 degrees of freedom (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001). Fit Indices: Comparative Fit Index (CFI): 0.90 Tucker-Lewis Index (TLI): 0.88 Bentler-Bonett Non-normed Fit Index (NNFI): 0.88 Bentler-Bonett Normed Fit Index (NFI): 0.86 Parsimony Normed Fit Index (PNFI): 0.74 Bollen’s Relative Fit Index (RFI): 0.84 Bollen’s Incremental Fit Index (IFI): 0.90 Relative Noncentrality Index (RNI): 0.90 Information Criteria: Log-likelihood: −9637.20 Number of free parameters: 49 Akaike Information Criterion (AIC): 19,372.40 Bayesian Information Criterion (BIC): 19,572.43 Sample-size Adjusted Bayesian Information Criterion (SSABIC): 19,416.93. Other Fit Measures: Root Mean Square Error of Approximation (RMSEA): 0.07 RMSEA 90% Confidence Interval Lower Bound: 0.06 RMSEA 90% Confidence Interval Upper Bound: 0.08 RMSEA <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value: 1.73 × 10^-5 Standardized Root Mean Square Residual (SRMR): 0.05 hoelter’s Critical N (<italic toggle="yes">α</italic> = 0.05): 167.25 hoelter’s Critical N (<italic toggle="yes">α</italic> = 0.01): 182.36 Goodness of Fit Index (GFI): 0.96 McDonald Fit Index (MFI): 0.77 Expected Cross Validation Index (ECVI): 0.99. Average Variance Extracted (AVE) PSAS-Cognitive: 0.44 PSAS-Somatic: 0.34. Heterotrait-Monotrait Ratio (HTMT) The HTMT ratio for PSAS-Cognitive to PSAS-Somatic is 0.64.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p>The Somatic subscale (F2) demonstrated factor loadings ranging from 0.45 to 0.70, with PSAS9 having the highest loading (0.70) and PSAS12 the lowest (0.45). Residual variances for this subscale were generally higher, ranging from 0.52 to 0.79, indicating more item-specific variance compared to the Cognitive subscale (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p>
      <p>The model fit indices suggest an acceptable fit: CFI (0.90) and TLI (0.88) are at or close to the recommended threshold of 0.90. The RMSEA of 0.07 (90% CI: 0.06–0.08) indicates a reasonable fit, while the SRMR of 0.05 suggests a good fit. The chi-square test was significant (<italic toggle="yes">Χ²</italic> = 336.42, df = 103, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt;0.001), which is common in large samples (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p>
      <p>The AVE for PSAS-Cognitive (0.44) and PSAS-Somatic (0.34) are below the ideal threshold of 0.50, suggesting that more variance is due to measurement error than to the underlying construct. The HTMT of 0.64 between the two factors indicates good discriminant validity (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p>
      <p>The convergent validity analysis of the PSAS was conducted on a sample of 438 participants, examining correlations between the PSAS subscales (Cognitive and Somatic), total PSAS score, and related measures, including the AIS, GAD-7, and GSES (<xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Convergent Validity of the PSAS (N = 438)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cognitive</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Somatic</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AIS</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAD-7</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSES Total</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1. Cognitive</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2. Somatic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.543*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3. PSAS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.892*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.864*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4. AIS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.442*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.339*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.447*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5. GAD-7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.518*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.412*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.533*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.501*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6. GSES Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.313*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.215*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.303*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.722*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.358*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Factor 1 = PSAS-Cognitive. Factor 2 = PSAS-Somatic. *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt;0.05.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0006"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: PSAS, pre-sleep arousal scale; AIS, Athens insomnia scale; GAD-7, Generalized Anxiety Disorder Scale - 7 items; GSES, Glasgow sleep effort scale.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p>The Cognitive and Somatic subscales of the PSAS showed a moderate positive correlation (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.543, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05), indicating that while related, they measure distinct aspects of pre-sleep arousal. Both subscales were strongly correlated with the total PSAS score (Cognitive: <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.892, Somatic: <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.864, both <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05), as expected, given that they compose the total score (<xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p>
      <p>The PSAS and its subscales demonstrated moderate positive correlations with the AIS, supporting their relationship with insomnia symptoms. The Cognitive subscale (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.442, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) showed a slightly stronger correlation with the AIS compared to the Somatic subscale (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.339, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05), suggesting that cognitive arousal might be more closely linked to insomnia symptoms in this sample (<xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p>
      <p>Similarly, the PSAS and its subscales showed moderate to strong positive correlations with the GAD-7, indicating a relationship between pre-sleep arousal and anxiety symptoms. Again, the Cognitive subscale (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.518, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) demonstrated a stronger correlation with anxiety compared to the Somatic subscale (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.412, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) (<xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p>
      <p>The GSES Total score showed significant, positive correlations with the PSAS and its subscales (PSAS Total: <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.303, Cognitive: <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.313, Somatic: <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.215, all <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). This suggests a relationship between pre-sleep arousal and sleep effort, with cognitive arousal showing a slightly stronger association (<xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p>
      <p>The independent samples <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test revealed significant differences between “no insomnia” individuals and those with “insomnia” symptoms across all PSAS and its factors. PSAS scores showed the largest disparity. Healthy participants (<italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 30.7, <italic toggle="yes">SD</italic> = 9.57) exhibited markedly lower pre-sleep arousal than those with insomnia (<italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 38.9, <italic toggle="yes">SD</italic> = 10.32), <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>(436) = −8.29, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, <italic toggle="yes">d</italic> = −0.832. Cognitive scores were significantly lower in the healthy group (<italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 13.4, <italic toggle="yes">SD</italic> = 5.66) compared to the insomnia group (<italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 18.1, <italic toggle="yes">SD</italic> = 6.44), <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>(436) = −7.87, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, <italic toggle="yes">d</italic> = −0.790. Somatic symptoms also differed significantly. The healthy group (<italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 17.3, <italic toggle="yes">SD</italic> = 5.62) reported fewer somatic complaints than the insomnia group (<italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 20.8, <italic toggle="yes">SD</italic> = 5.12), <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>(436) = −6.39, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, <italic toggle="yes">d</italic> = −0.642.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Our results demonstrated robust reliability for both the cognitive and somatic components of the PSAS. The cognitive subscale showed slightly higher reliability than the somatic subscale. The analyses maintained the original two-factor structure of the PSAS similar to other languages.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25–27</xref> The results also provided evidence for the convergent validity of the PSAS. The PSAS and its subscales show the anticipated correlations with measures of insomnia, anxiety, and sleep effort.</p>
      <p>The study demonstrated strong reliability for both cognitive and somatic components of the PSAS, with the cognitive subscale showing slightly higher reliability. This finding indicates that the PSAS consistently measures pre-sleep arousal across its two main dimensions. Moreover, confirming the original two-factor structure in the new linguistic context of Arabic supports the cross-cultural validity of the PSAS. This result aligns with previous studies in other languages, suggesting that the concept of pre-sleep arousal, divided into cognitive and somatic components, is relatively universal across different cultures.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25–27</xref>,<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></p>
      <p>The convergent validity analysis revealed moderate to strong correlations between the PSAS and related measures of insomnia symptoms (ie, AIS), anxiety (ie, GAD-7), and sleep effort (ie, GSES). Notably, the Cognitive subscale consistently showed stronger correlations with these measures compared to the Somatic subscale. This suggests that cognitive arousal may play a more significant role in sleep disturbances and related psychological factors than somatic arousal. This finding has important implications: (a) It suggests that cognitive arousal may play a more significant role in sleep disturbances than somatic arousal. (b) The stronger relationship between cognitive arousal and anxiety measures indicates a potential overlap between cognitive processes involved in anxiety and those affecting sleep. (c) These results highlight the importance of addressing cognitive factors in sleep interventions.</p>
      <p>The strengths of our study include its large sample size, comprehensive psychometric evaluation, and the inclusion of multiple related measures for convergent validity assessment. The use of various reliability coefficients and structural equation modeling provides a robust evaluation of the scale’s psychometric properties. However, the limitations must also be noted. First, any causal inferences about the relationships between pre-sleep arousal and other variables are not possible, and the study was cross-sectional. Second, the sample’s demographic characteristics were not fully described, which may limit the generalizability of our findings.</p>
      <p>Future research should address these limitations by conducting longitudinal studies to examine the stability of pre-sleep arousal over time and its predictive validity for sleep outcomes. Additionally, studies should explore the PSAS’s performance across diverse populations, including different age groups and clinical samples. Further investigation into the lower AVE values is warranted, potentially leading to item refinement or the development of additional items to better capture the constructs.</p>
      <p>This study has other limitations that should be considered. First, data collection was conducted online, which may introduce biases related to internet accessibility and self-selection, potentially limiting the generalizability of the findings. Second, the study did not include objective measures such as polysomnography (PSG) or actigraphy to validate self-reported data, which could have provided more comprehensive insights into the participants’ sleep patterns. Third, while the sample size was adequate for confirmatory factor analysis, it remains relatively small, which might affect the robustness of the results. Furthermore, we chose not to perform an EFA due to the established two-factor structure in other languages; however, conducting an EFA might have provided further insights into the factor structure in the Arabic context. Furthermore, the study did not employ Item Response Theory (IRT) or network analysis, which could have offered a deeper understanding of the relationships between items and the underlying constructs. Future research should address these limitations by incorporating objective sleep measures, increasing sample size, and exploring alternative analytical approaches.</p>
      <p>The significant differences in PSAS scores between individuals with and without insomnia highlight the scale’s potential clinical utility.<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> Practitioners can use the PSAS to assess pre-sleep arousal levels in patients with sleep complaints, with particular attention to cognitive arousal, which showed stronger associations with insomnia symptoms and anxiety.<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> This information can guide targeted interventions, such as cognitive restructuring techniques for those with high cognitive arousal or relaxation strategies for those with elevated somatic arousal.<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></p>
      <p>The stronger relationship between cognitive arousal and sleep-related measures suggests that cognitive interventions may be particularly beneficial in treating sleep disturbances.<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> Clinicians should consider incorporating cognitive techniques, such as mindfulness or cognitive behavioral therapy for insomnia (CBT-I), into their treatment plans for patients with high pre-sleep cognitive arousal.<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></p>
      <p>The findings of this study open several avenues for future research and practice in sleep science and clinical psychology. Researchers should investigate how cultural and environmental factors moderate the relationship between pre-sleep arousal and sleep outcomes, as this exploration could reveal the universality and cultural specificity of sleep-related cognitive and somatic processes. From a methodological standpoint, integrating ecological momentary assessment techniques with the PSAS could provide a more nuanced understanding of how pre-sleep arousal fluctuates in real time and its immediate impact on sleep quality. For clinicians, the stronger association between cognitive arousal and sleep disturbances highlights the need to develop and test targeted cognitive interventions that specifically address nighttime rumination and worry. Exploring the potential use of the PSAS as a screening tool in primary care settings could facilitate the early identification of individuals at risk for developing chronic insomnia and enable timely interventions. Future research should also examine the responsiveness of the PSAS to various sleep interventions, which could establish its utility as an outcome measure in clinical trials and help refine treatment protocols for sleep disorders.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Our findings demonstrate that the Arabic PSAS retained the two-factor structure of the original scale, with all factor loadings being statistically significant. The PSAS revealed strong internal consistency and test–retest reliability over two weeks. Furthermore, the PSAS displayed good concurrent and convergent validity. These results suggest that the Arabic version of the PSAS is a reliable and valid tool for measuring pre-sleep arousal in individuals who speak Arabic. Our findings provide evidence for the use of the Arabic version of PSAS as a reliable measure in sleep research and clinical assessment.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0006">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>Pre-Sleep Arousal Scale (PSAS): translation and evaluation of its psychometric properties in an Arabic version is available online at OSF HOME: <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://osf.io/4cdhw/" ext-link-type="uri">https://osf.io/4cdhw/</ext-link></underline>. The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ramar</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malhotra</surname>
<given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carden</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep is essential to health: an American Academy of Sleep Medicine position statement</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2115</fpage>–<lpage>2119</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.9476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34170250</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Grandner</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep, health, and society</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Clin</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>139</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsmc.2022.03.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35659068</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Garbarino</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lanteri</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bragazzi</surname>
<given-names>NL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Magnavita</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scoditti</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Role of sleep deprivation in immune-related disease risk and outcomes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Commun Biol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1304</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s42003-021-02825-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34795404</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Davidescu</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Galea-Holhoș</surname>
<given-names>LB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Voiță-Mekereș</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davidescu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of Sleep Deprivation on Learning and Memory: a Review Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Biochem Technol</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>4–2023</issue>):<fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.51847/01ztnjmk66</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ten Brink</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dietch</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tutek</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suh</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gross</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Manber</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and affect: a conceptual review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>101670</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2022.101670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36088755</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Palagini</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hertenstein</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Riemann</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nissen</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep, insomnia and mental health</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e13628</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.13628</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35506356</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Korostovtseva</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bochkarev</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sviryaev</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and cardiovascular risk</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Clin</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>485</fpage>–<lpage>497</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsmc.2021.05.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34325825</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cooper</surname>
<given-names>CB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Neufeld</surname>
<given-names>EV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dolezal</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep deprivation and obesity in adults: a brief narrative review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ Open Sport Exercise Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e000392</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjsem-2018-000392</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Parameswaran</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ray</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep, circadian rhythms, and type 2 diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Endocrinol</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>96</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>12</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cen.14607</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bock</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vungarala</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Covassin</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Somers</surname>
<given-names>VK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep duration and hypertension: epidemiological evidence and underlying mechanisms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Hypertens</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ajh/hpab146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34536276</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mitter</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Crescenzo</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kee</surname>
<given-names>KLY</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep deprivation as a treatment for major depressive episodes: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>101647</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2022.101647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35700677</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liew</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aung</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep deprivation and its association with diseases-a review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>192</fpage>–<lpage>204</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.07.048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32951993</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Knutson</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spiegel</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Penev</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Cauter</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The metabolic consequences of sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>178</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2007.01.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17442599</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jahrami</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abdelaziz</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Binsanad</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The Association between Symptoms of Nomophobia, Insomnia and Food Addiction among Young Adults: findings of an Exploratory Cross-Sectional Survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>711</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph18020711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33467561</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lim</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Najafi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Afifi</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The need to promote sleep health in public health agendas across the globe</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e820</fpage>–<lpage>e826</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s2468-2667(23)00182-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37777291</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>AASM</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">International Classification of Sleep Disorders–Third Edition, Text Revision (ICSD-3-TR)</italic></source>. <publisher-name>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</publisher-name>. <year>2023</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>APA</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders</italic></source>. <edition>5th edn</edition> ed. <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>WHO</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">ICD-11: International Classification of Diseases (11th Revision)</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dressle</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Riemann</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Hyperarousal in insomnia disorder: current evidence and potential mechanisms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e13928</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.13928</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37183177</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sharman</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perlis</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bastien</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barclay</surname>
<given-names>NL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ellis</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elder</surname>
<given-names>GJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pre-Sleep Cognitive Arousal Is Negatively Associated with Sleep Misperception in Healthy Sleepers during Habitual Environmental Noise Exposure: an Actigraphy Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clocks Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>88</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/clockssleep4010010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35323164</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fernandez-Mendoza</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vgontzas</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia is Associated with Cortical Hyperarousal as Early as Adolescence</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1029</fpage>–<lpage>1036</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.5746</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26951400</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pérusse</surname>
<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pedneault-Drolet</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rancourt</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Turcotte</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>St-Jean</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bastien</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>REM sleep as a potential indicator of hyperarousal in psychophysiological and paradoxical insomnia sufferers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Psychophysiol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>95</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>372</fpage>–<lpage>378</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpsycho.2015.01.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25596383</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nicassio</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mendlowitz</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fussell</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petras</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The phenomenology of the pre-sleep state: the development of the pre-sleep arousal scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Res Ther</italic></source>. <year>1985</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>271</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0005-7967(85)90004-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4004706</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Spiegelhalder</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fuchs</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ladwig</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Heart rate and heart rate variability in subjectively reported insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.2010.00863.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20626615</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ruivo Marques</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen Gomes</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nicassio</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Azevedo</surname>
<given-names>MHP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pre-Sleep Arousal Scale (PSAS): psychometric study of a European Portuguese version</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>60</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2017.10.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29482814</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Okajima</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ishii</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ochi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nicassio</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Development and Validity of the Japanese Version of the Pre-Sleep Arousal Scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Tohoku J Exp Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>252</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1620/tjem.252.169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33055430</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jansson-Fröjmark</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Norell-Clarke</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Psychometric properties of the Pre-Sleep Arousal Scale in a large community sample</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychosomat Res</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>110</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychores.2011.10.005</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pesonen</surname>
<given-names>A-K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Makkonen</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elovainio</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Halonen</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Räikkönen</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuula</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Presleep physiological stress is associated with a higher cortical arousal in sleep and more consolidated REM sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Stress</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>667</fpage>–<lpage>675</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10253890.2020.1869936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33461366</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Trabelsi</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Almarzooqi</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aljaloud</surname>
<given-names>KS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Adapting the athlete sleep behavior questionnaire (ASBQ) for Arabic-speaking populations: translation, reliability testing, and validation using classical theory and item response theory</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>119</volume>:<fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>275</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2024.04.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38710132</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>AlMashouk</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abu-Saleh</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghazzawi</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trabelsi</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jahrami</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Translating and establishing the psychometric properties of the Jenkins Sleep Scale for Arabic-speaking individuals</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>236</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12888-024-05714-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38549105</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Alghamdi</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abu-Saleh</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Almohaya</surname>
<given-names>YA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Examining the reliability and validity of the arabic version of the Glasgow Sleep Effort Scale (GSES)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1831</fpage>–<lpage>1838</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-024-03053-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38735910</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Alghamdi</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abanumai</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Althobaiti</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The Psychometric Properties of the Arabic Version of the Anxiety and Preoccupation About Sleep Questionnaire (APSQ)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Sci Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/nss.S449354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38322015</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Soldatos</surname>
<given-names>CR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dikeos</surname>
<given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paparrigopoulos</surname>
<given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Athens Insomnia Scale: validation of an instrument based on ICD-10 criteria</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychosom Res</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>555</fpage>–<lpage>560</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0022-3999(00)00095-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11033374</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Spitzer</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kroenke</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Löwe</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A brief measure for assessing generalized anxiety disorder: the GAD-7</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>166</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1092</fpage>–<lpage>1097</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.166.10.1092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16717171</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Broomfield</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Espie</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Towards a valid, reliable measure of sleep effort</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>401</fpage>–<lpage>407</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.2005.00481.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16364141</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jahrami</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trabelsi</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saif</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Manzar</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>BaHammam</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vitiello</surname>
<given-names>MV</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Reliability generalization meta-analysis of the Athens Insomnia Scale and its translations: examining internal consistency and test-retest validity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>111</volume>:<fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2023.09.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37776584</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sawaya</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Atoui</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hamadeh</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zeinoun</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nahas</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Adaptation and initial validation of the Patient Health Questionnaire - 9 (PHQ-9) and the Generalized Anxiety Disorder - 7 Questionnaire (GAD-7) in an Arabic speaking Lebanese psychiatric outpatient sample</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>239</volume>:<fpage>245</fpage>–<lpage>252</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2016.03.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27031595</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Uygur</surname>
<given-names>OF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Uygur</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Validity and reliability of the Turkish version of the Glasgow Sleep Effort Scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>98</volume>:<fpage>144</fpage>–<lpage>151</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2022.06.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35853331</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mishra</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pandey</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Singh</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gupta</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sahu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Keshri</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Descriptive statistics and normality tests for statistical data</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Card Anaesth</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/aca.ACA_157_18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30648682</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Deng</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Testing the Difference Between Reliability Coefficients Alpha and Omega</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Educ Psychol Meas</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>77</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>185</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0013164416658325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29795909</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chenani</surname>
<given-names>KT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Madadizadeh</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Guideline for selecting types of reliability and suitable intra-class correlation coefficients in clinical research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Biostatist Epidemio</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>305</fpage>–<lpage>309</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Widaman</surname>
<given-names>KF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Helm</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>. <part-title>Exploratory factor analysis and confirmatory factor analysis</part-title>. In: <source><italic toggle="yes">APA Handbook of Research Methods in Psychology: Data Analysis and Research Publication</italic></source>. <edition>2nd ed</edition>. <publisher-name>American Psychological Association</publisher-name>; <year>2023</year>;Vol. <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>379</fpage>–<lpage>410</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Goretzko</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Siemund</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sterner</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Evaluating model fit of measurement models in confirmatory factor analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Educ Psychol Meas</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>84</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>123</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/00131644231163813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38250508</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>LT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bentler</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cutoff criteria for fit indexes in covariance structure analysis: conventional criteria versus new alternatives</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Struct Equ Model</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10705519909540118</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>LT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bentler</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Evaluating model fit</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Struct Equ Model</italic></source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>1995</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vochem</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Strobel</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maier</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Pre-Sleep Arousal Scale (PSAS) and the Time Monitoring Behavior-10 scale (TMB-10) in good sleepers and patients with insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>98</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2019.01.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30853192</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Basishvili</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oniani</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sakhelashvili</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia, Pre-Sleep Arousal, Psychosocial Factors and Changes in Sleep Pattern during the Second Wave Lockdown of the COVID-19 Pandemic in Georgia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Sci</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>17</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/brainsci12010017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35053761</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kalmbach</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reffi</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Reducing cognitive arousal and sleep effort alleviates insomnia and depression in pregnant women with DSM-5 insomnia disorder treated with a mindfulness sleep program</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Adv</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>zpad031</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleepadvances/zpad031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37645455</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Walker</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Muench</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perlis</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vargas</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cognitive Behavioral Therapy for Insomnia (CBT-I): a Primer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clinical Psychology and Special Education</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>123</fpage>–<lpage>137</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17759/cpse.2022110208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36908717</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Espie</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Revisiting the Psychobiological Inhibition Model: a conceptual framework for understanding and treating insomnia using cognitive and behavioural therapeutics (CBTx)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e13841</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.13841</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36747476</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
