<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33244284</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7685379</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">271318</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S271318</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Evaluating the Effects of Different Sleep Supplement Modes in Attenuating Metabolic Consequences of Night Shift Work Using Rat Model</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Zheng et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Zheng et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zheng</surname>
            <given-names>Pei-pei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Li-na</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Jie</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chang</surname>
            <given-names>Xin-miao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ding</surname>
            <given-names>Shan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2054-901X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Xiao</surname>
            <given-names>Fei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0003">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Guo</surname>
            <given-names>Li-xin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label>Department of Endocrinology, <institution>Beijing Hospital, National Center of Gerontology; Institute of Geriatric Medicine, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>
<addr-line>100730</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Peking University Fifth School of Clinical Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>
<addr-line>100730</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label>The Key Laboratory of Geriatrics, <institution>Beijing Institute of Geriatrics, Bejing Hospital, National Center of Gerontology, National Health Commission; Institute of Geriatric Medicine, Chinese Academy of Medical Science</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <addr-line>100730</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Li-xin Guo <institution>Department of Endocrinology, Beijing Hospital, National Center of Gerontology; Institute of Geriatric Medicine, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>NO. 1 DaHua Road, Dong Dan</addr-line>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line><addr-line>100730</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country><phone>Tel/Fax +86-10-65282171</phone> Email lixinguo_med@163.com</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>20</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2020</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2020</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>12</volume>
      <fpage>1053</fpage>
      <lpage>1065</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2020</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>04</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2020</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2020 Zheng et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2020</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Zheng et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p>To study the effects of chronic-simulated night shift work using the rat model and examines if a particular sleep supplement mode could be better in alleviating the effects.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>The male Wistar rats were randomly divided into the control (CTL: 8 rats) and night shift work (NW: 24 rats) groups of rats. Based on the sleep supplement strategy, the NW group was further segregated into three subgroups (8 rats each); late sleep supplement group (LSS), early sleep supplement group (ESS), and intermittent sleep supplement group (ISS). Sleep deprivation was achieved using the standard small-platform-over water method. Parameters such as animal body weight and food intake were measured daily. The intraperitoneal glucose tolerance test, fasting plasma insulin concentration, insulin resistance index and insulin sensitivity were measured twice, in the 4th and 8th weeks of the study. Plasma corticosterone concentration and pathological changes in islets (insulitis) were measured at the end of the 8th week.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>In NW group, night work resulted in a gain of body weight and albeit lower than that of the CTL group. NW rats also had higher food intake, showed impaired glucose metabolism and higher plasma corticosterone concentration. The sleep supplement experiments suggested that compared to the other modes, intermittent sleep supplement had significantly low changes in the body weight, glucose metabolism and the islet cells.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>Similar to previous studies, we also found that night shift work adversely impacts the body weight and glucose metabolism in rats. However, upon evaluating different sleep supplement strategies, we found the intermittent sleep supplement strategy to be most effective.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>night work</kwd>
        <kwd>sleep deprivation</kwd>
        <kwd>sleep supplement</kwd>
        <kwd>sleep debt</kwd>
        <kwd>body weight</kwd>
        <kwd>glucose metabolism</kwd>
        <kwd>insulitis</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
            <institution-wrap>
              <institution>no funding</institution>
            </institution-wrap>
          </funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>This study was funded by special fund project for clinical medical from Chinese Medical Association (Grant No. 343) and National Science Fundation of China (Grant No. 81670763).</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="9"/>
        <ref-count count="41"/>
        <page-count count="13"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>With the rising economy and impending technology, 24-hour work culture has become a new norm in the society. Multiple shifts and long working hours are the genuine necessity of medical care, transportation, public services, and essential manufacturing industries. Due to this, around 20% of the word workers are now the shift workers.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></p>
      <p>Several epidemiological studies reported negative health outcomes in night shift workers, especially in the form of diabetes mellitus or metabolic syndrome.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Sleep deprivation modifies glucose homeostasis<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> and impairs glucose tolerance.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Interestingly, a 1999 human study, published in Lancet, suggested that negative health impacts of sleep deprivation can be relieved upon sleep supplementation. The study was conducted on a group of 11 healthy young men. In brief, results found that 6 days of sleep deprivation altered the glucose tolerance, plasma thyrotropin, nocturnal cortisol concentration, and sympathetic activity in these men. However, after the next 6 days of full sleep supplementation, the effects were alleviated.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Notably, the study only focused on acute sleep deprivation (6 days).</p>
      <p>Similarly, multiple sleep deprivation studies have also been carried out in animal models, especially in rats. Results showed that sleep deprivation led to increased food intake and levels of blood glucose, insulin and serum corticosterone. Overall, glucose homeostasis was found to be impaired.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6–9</xref> But, here too, most studies only focused on the sleep deprivation model, ranging from 4 days to 4 weeks.</p>
      <p>Surprisingly, the effect on the body weight is not consistent among the two groups of studies. Sleep deprivation in animal models claimed for declining weight whereas human epidemiological surveys reported for the weight gain.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Importantly, a few studies that simulated real-life human work patterns in rats showed weight gain contrary to the previous studies. In those studies, rats were sleep deprived for 5 days, followed by a recovery period of 2 days, named as “week-weekend” protocol, which lasted for a period of 4 weeks. These results strongly advocated for the “week-weekend” protocol since it was very comparable to the human situation.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></p>
      <p>However, presently there is no study on chronic (long-term) sleep deprivation in rats. Few studies have been carried out to understand continuous sleep deprivation, but these were without a recovery period. Hitherto, the effects of chronic sleep deprivation on body weight and glucose metabolism are largely unknown. It can be argued that acute vs chronic sleep deprivation could be an important criterion that led to contradictory effects on body weights in human vs rat studies. Therefore, in this study, along with the week-weekend protocol, an eight-week sleep deprivation period was used to evaluate the effects of simulated night work.</p>
      <p>In the real world, due to social life obligations, humans prefer different modes of sleep recovery period(s). The timing of bed hours could vary as per their convenience; immediately after the night work, before the next night work or divided into two periods. A particular sleep supplement mode could be better, and suggested, to overcome the adverse effects of sleep deprivation. Therefore, we decided to carry out the experiments along these lines. For this, sleep-deprived rats were divided into three subgroups and were subjected to the respective sleep supplement modes. Results obtained here are of better clinical value as these are close to the real-life experience in humans.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Animals</title>
        <p>Thirty-two healthy male Wistar rats were obtained at 8 weeks of age from SPF (Beijing) Lab Animals Technology Co. Ltd, and the quality was approved by the Center for Experimental Animals, Chinese people’s Liberation Army Academy of Military Medical Sciences. The rats were housed in individual cages, at constant temperature (23±1°C), circulating air, and a 12 h light-dark cycle with lights on at 7:00. Water and food were ad libitum. All experimental procedures were carried out in accordance with the National Institutes of Health Laboratory Animal feeding, China and were ethically approved by the Animal Administration Department of Beijing Hospital.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Experimental Design and Set-Up of Chronic Sleep Deprivation</title>
        <p>Rats were randomly divided into two groups, the control (CTL: 8 rats) and night shift work (NW: 24 rats) groups. The NW group was further divided into three subgroups; early sleep supplement group (ESS, n=8), late sleep supplement group (LSS, n=8) and intermittent sleep supplement group (ISS, n=8). NW group was subjected to sleep deprivation using the standard small-platform-over water (flower pot) method. In brief, the rat cage is equipped with a circle with a diameter of 6.5 cm platform that largely remains immersed in water, leaving the upper 1 cm above the water level. The water temperature was 23±1°C. The rats were placed on top of the platform and had free access to food and water. During NREM (non-rapid eye movement) sleep, muscle tone is retained and rat can stay on the platform but during REM (rapid eye movement) sleep, animals lose postural tone (atonia) and slip into the water to get awakened. This method suppresses REM sleep and induces approximately 25% reduction of slow wave sleep, during the period in the water container, in addition to numerous awakening episodes.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> For every sleep supplementation (sleep recovery), the water in the cage was exchanged for the wood shave and vice versa. Additionally, the other environmental parameters, including platform, remained unchanged in both two conditions. The rats from the CTL group were placed in the similar cages containing wood shave and platform throughout the experiment and were free to sleep based on the daylight cycle. The water and the wood shave in the cages were replaced twice a day (7:00 and 19:00) and twice a week (Monday &amp; Friday), respectively. Before beginning the experiments, all rats were habituated to wood shave in their cages for 2 weeks. Besides, NW rats were also habituated to the sleep deprivation by placing them on the water immersed platform for 2 hrs on 3 consecutive days. The experiments were carried out using the week-weekend protocol. During the weekdays (5 days on duty), the CTL group was left in their cages for normal activities, while the NW was subjected to sleep deprivation from 07:00 to 19:00. Later, these were allowed to sleep for a total of 8 hrs, LSS group was allowed from 23:00 to 07:00, the ESS from 19:00 to 03:00, and the ISS from 19:00 to 23:00 and 03:00 to 07:00 hrs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref>). On the weekend (2 days off), all rats were left undisturbed.<fig id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Schematic overview of the schedule of sleep deprivation for the control group (CTL), the late sleep supplement group (LSS), the early sleep supplement group (ESS), and the intermittent sleep supplement group (ISS). For each treatment group, periods of wakefulness induced by water platform are shown in pinkish-grey and periods without sleep deprivation are shown in green.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-12-1053-g0001"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviation:</bold> L:D cycle, light-dark cycle.</attrib></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Bodyweight and Food Intake Measurements</title>
        <p>For each rat, the basal weight was measured at the beginning of the experiment and then the daily weight was measured at 7:00, every day, till the end of the study. The difference for each day was calculated using the basal weight. Similarly, food intake measurements were performed at 7:00 and 19:00, every day, by calculating the difference from the previous day.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Intraperitoneal Glucose Tolerance Test (GTT) and the Concentration of Plasma Corticosterone</title>
        <p>GTT was carried out at 10:00 on the 27th and 55th day (the first day of the weekend) of the study. Rats were tested at the same circadian time by having 4 hrs of light and were fasted for 16 hrs. A bolus of glucose (2 g of glucose per kg of body weight, 50% glucose solution) was injected i.p in all groups. Blood samples were collected from the intraorbital venous plexus at 0 (basal), 15, 30, 60, 90 and 120 minutes. For all the samples, plasma glucose concentrations were measured using a plasma glucose monitor, at once (Johnson One Touch Ultra, glucose oxidase method). 0.5 mL of additional basal blood samples (t=0) were collected, in EP tube on ice, to test the plasma insulin concentration on the 27th and 55th day and plasma corticosterone concentration on the 55th day of the study. Samples were then centrifuged at 3000 rpm for 10 min at 4°C and the obtained plasma was stored at −80°C until further analysis. The concentration of insulin was measured by the Rat Insulin ELISA Kit; the concentration of corticosterone was measured by Rat Corticosterone ELISA Kit. Both of the kits were purchased from Wuhan Boster Biological Technology Co. Ltd. Insulin resistance index (HOMA-IR) and insulin sensitivity (HOMA-IS) were calculated using the concentration of fasting plasma glucose and insulin [HOMA-IR = FPG (Fasting plasma glucose, mmol/L) × FINS (Fasting insulin mIU/L)/22.5; HOMA-IS=1/HOMA-IR].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Pathological Changes of Islets (Insulitis)</title>
        <p>The rats were sacrificed to isolate pancreases on the 56th day of the study. The specimens were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde solution for 24 hrs and embedded in paraffin. Two different sections (40 μm apart) were obtained from each pancreas. Insulitis was graded by observing five islets under a light microscope after routine H&amp;E staining. Scheme was as following: grade 0, intact islets without inflammatory infiltration; grade 1, peri-islet inflammation or &lt;25% islet area involved; grade 2, infiltration into islets, 25% to 50% islet areas involved; grade 3, &gt;50% islets involved.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2006">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>All continuous variables obeyed normal distribution. Corticosterone, body weight gain, food intake, glucose of every time point during GTT, AUC of GTT, fasting insulin, HOMA-IR, HOMA-IS and islet inflammation score were analyzed by <italic>t</italic>-test between NW and CTL groups, and by ANOVA among CTL, LSS, ESS and ISS groups. Generalized additive model (GAM) was used to build nonlinear regression models between weight and time. Results of GTT and weight gain along with time were analyzed by repeated-measures ANOVA. Post hoc tests (multiple comparisons) were employed to detect significant pairs. SPSS version 25 (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, USA) and GraphPad Prism version 6.01 (GraphPad Software Inc., San Diego, CA, USA) were used for data analysis and figure generation. A p-value &lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Plasma Concentration of Corticosterone</title>
        <p>Increased corticosterone level is a known biomarker of sleep loss.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> On the 55th day (8 w.) of the study, we found that corticosterone levels were significantly high in the NW group of rats compared with the CTL group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2A</xref> t=3.746, P=0.001, 77.53±1.3 vs 68.73±1.4μg/L). This confirmed that the model of chronic sleep deprivation was successfully established. Further, there was an increase of corticosterone level in LSS, ESS and ISS when compared with CTL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2B</xref> P&lt;0.05). Noticeably, ESS had the highest level among all (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2C</xref> P&lt;0.05).<fig id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>COR in 8w. Data are average values ± SEM. Significant differences (P&lt;0.05): *NW vs CTL (<bold>A</bold>); *LSS, ESS or ISS vs CTL (<bold>B</bold>); *ESS or ISS vs LSS (<bold>C</bold>); <sup>#</sup>ISS vs ESS (<bold>C</bold>).</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-12-1053-g0002"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Body Weight</title>
        <p>In contrast to the CTL group, during the first week of the study, the NW group of rats showed negative weight gain (weight loss). However, trends reversed post 1 week and remained the same till the end of the study, ie rats started gaining weight similar to the CTL group. Rat weight gain changed for each supplement individually appeared similar through time, and GAM models predicting changes through time were all significant and explained a high amount of variation in rat weight response (&gt;95%). Besides, there were significant differences among four groups, and significant dips in the weight gain curves can be noticed on the 26th, 27th, and 54th day of study, due to the 16 h of fasting, for the collection of blood samples required for the metabolic analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3</xref> F=12.779, P&lt;0.001).<fig id="f0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The trend of weight gain along with the time. GAM and repeated-measures ANOVA for weight gain and time among different sleep supplement models.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-12-1053-g0003"/></fig></p>
        <p>Notably, comparative data at the end of 4th and 8th weeks are shown that the overall body weight gain in the NW group was still significantly lower than that in the CTL group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">C</xref>. 4w, t=8.338, P&lt;0.001; 8w, t=4.486, P&lt;0.001). We also noticed that LSS was the least among all (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">D</xref>.4w, F=21.837, P&lt;0.001; 8w, F=64.635, P&lt;0.001).<fig id="f0004" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Average body weight in 4w (<bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>), 8w (<bold>C</bold> and <bold>D</bold>), the first week (<bold>E</bold> and <bold>F</bold>), weekday and weekend (<bold>G</bold> and <bold>H</bold>). Data are average values±SEM. Significant differences (P&lt;0.05): *NW vs CTL in the left column; *ESS or ISS vs LSS, <sup>#</sup>ISS vs ESS in the right column.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-12-1053-g0004"/></fig></p>
        <p>When we made a comparison, only for the first week, the daily body weight gain was still lower in NW (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4E</xref> P&lt;0.001). Furthermore, we identified noticeable changes in ISS as compared with LSS and ESS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4F</xref>, P&lt;0.001).</p>
        <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4G</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">H</xref> shows averaged body weight data for weeks 2, 3, 5, 6 and 7. During this period, the effects of sleep deprivation on body weight were stable. Here, average body weight represents weight gain divided by the number of days (35, 25, or 10 days). Although the average body weight was significantly reducing during the weekdays, the weekends showed the opposite (weight gain) in the NW group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4G</xref> weekday, t=−9.504, P&lt;0.001; weekend, t=19.917, P&lt;0.001). Further, there was a significant difference among the LSS, ESS and ISS groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4H</xref> weekday, F=23.305, P&lt;0.001; weekend, F=15.290, P&lt;0.001; 7 days total, F=14.676, P&lt;0.001). Importantly, among all, ISS showed the least weight gain during the weekends.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Food Intake</title>
        <p>At the beginning of the experiment, the food intake changed with time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5A</xref>). However, for weeks 2, 3, 5, 6 and 7, when the effects of sleep deprivation on food got stabilized, the average food intake was significantly higher in NW compared to the CTL group, during the weekdays, weekend or the 7 days altogether (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5B</xref> weekday, t=4.325, P=0.001; weekend, t=2.597, P=0.021; 7 days altogether, t=4.017, P=0.001). Further, the average food intake was highest for the ISS during the weekdays, weekend or the 7 days altogether and light off, among the NW subgroups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5C</xref>. P&lt;0.05; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5D</xref>. P&lt;0.05).<fig id="f0005" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>The trend of the food intake along with the time (<bold>A</bold>). Average food intake in 7 days total, weekday and weekend during week 2–3 and week 5–7 (<bold>B</bold> and <bold>C</bold>). Average food intake in light on and light off during week 2–3 and week 5–7 (<bold>D</bold>). Data are average values ± SEM. Significant differences (P&lt;0.05): *NW vs CTL (<bold>B</bold>); *LSS or ESS or ISS vs CTL, <sup>#</sup>ESS or ISS vs LSS, <sup>§</sup>ISS vs ESS (<bold>C</bold> and <bold>D</bold>).</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-12-1053-g0005"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Intraperitoneal Glucose Tolerance Test (GTT)</title>
        <p>In the 4th and 8th weeks of the study, we found that the glucose metabolism in the NW group was impaired compared to the CTL group of rats (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">G</xref>. 4w, F=7.863, P=0.011; 8w. F=10.351, P=0.006). The glucose area under the curve (AUC) is a widely used index for the glucose excursion after glucose loading. Analysis of AUC also confirmed the aforesaid findings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">J</xref>. 4w, t=4.034, P=0.001; 8w t=4.506, P&lt;0.001). There was also a significant difference among all the four groups, and the GTT in LSS and ESS groups, rather than ISS groups, were significantly impaired when compared with CTL group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6B</xref> and H. 4w, F=41.176, P&lt;0.001, post hoc Turkey test: LSS vs CTL P=0.001, ESS vs CTL P&lt;0.001; 8w, F=23.898, P&lt;0.001, post hoc Turkey test: LSS vs CTL P&lt;0.001, ESS vs CTL P&lt;0.001). Those findings were also supported by the AUC data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6E</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">K</xref>. 4w, LSS vs CTL P=0.004, ESS vs CTL P&lt;0.001; 8w, LSS vs CTL P&lt;0.004, ESS vs CTL P&lt;0.001).<fig id="f0006" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Glucose tolerance in 4w (<bold>A</bold>–<bold>C</bold>) and 8w (<bold>G</bold>–<bold>I</bold>). AUC of glucose tolerance in 4w (<bold>D</bold>–<bold>F</bold>) and 8w (<bold>J</bold>–<bold>L</bold>). Data are average values ± SEM. Significant differences (P&lt;0.05): In the left column, *NW vs CTL. In the middle column, *CTL vs the other groups. In the C and I, *between groups (LSS, ESS and ISS). In the (<bold>F</bold> and <bold>L</bold>), *ESS or ISS vs LSS; <sup>#</sup>ISS vs ESS.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-12-1053-g0006"/></fig></p>
        <p>Furthermore, there was also a significant difference among the NW subgroups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">I</xref>. 4w, F=39.005, P&lt;0.001; 8w, F=16.842, P=0.001). Interestingly, among the groups, ISS had least impacted glucose metabolism (P&lt;0.05), and the finding was also supported by the AUC data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6F</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">L</xref>. P&lt;0.05).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2005">
        <title>Fasting Plasma Concentration of Insulin and Insulin Sensitivity</title>
        <p>In the 4th and 8th weeks of the study, the fasting insulin levels, HOMA-IR and HOMA-IS of CTL and NW groups showed no difference (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0007">Figure 7A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0007">C</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0008">Figure 8A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0008">C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0008">E</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0008">G</xref>). However, there was a significant difference among CTL, LSS, ESS and ISS groups in the 4th weeks but not significant enough in the 8th week (fasting insulin: <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0007">Figure 7B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0007">D</xref>. 4w, F=29.709, P=0.003; HOMA-IR: <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0008">Figure 8B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0008">D</xref>. 4w, F=33.334, P=0.003; HOMA-IS: <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0008">Figure 8F</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0008">H</xref>. 4w, F=52.908, P=0.001). Importantly, the post hoc test found that fasting insulin levels of ISS were closer to the CTL group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0007">Figure 7B</xref>. P=0.05), whereas levels of LSS and ESS were significantly lower (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0007">Figure 7B</xref>. P=0.007. P=0.009). And also revealed an increase of HOMA-IR in ISS (P=0.006), but decrease in LSS (P=0.016) compared to the CTL group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0008">Figure 8B</xref>), which was opposite to the HOMA-IS in LSS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0008">Figure 8F</xref>, P=0.003).<fig id="f0007" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Fasting insulin in 4w (<bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>) and 8w (<bold>C</bold> and <bold>D</bold>). Data are average values ± SEM. Significant differences (P&lt;0.05): in the left column, *NW vs CTL; in the right column, *LSS, ESS or ISS vs CTL.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-12-1053-g0007"/></fig><fig id="f0008" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>HOMA-IR and HOMA-IS in 4w (<bold>A, B, E</bold> and <bold>F</bold>) and 8w (<bold>C, D, G</bold> and <bold>H</bold>). Data are average values ± SEM. Significant differences (P&lt;0.05): in the left column, *NW vs CTL; in the right column, *LSS, ESS or ISS vs CTL.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-12-1053-g0008"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2006">
        <title>Pathological Changes of Islets (Insulitis)</title>
        <p>In the 8th week, the occurrence of insulitis in NW was significantly higher compared to the CTL group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0009">Figure 9A</xref> t=3.9339, P&lt;0.001). Furthermore, there was a significant difference among the CTL, LSS, ESS and ISS groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0009">Figure 9B</xref> F=6.708, P&lt;0.001). The post hoc test revealed higher insulitis in LSS compared to the CTL group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0009">Figure 9B</xref> P&lt;0.05) and lower insulitis in ESS and ISS than that of the LSS group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0009">Figure 9C</xref> P&lt;0.05). However, there was no significant difference between ESS and ISS. Yet, we thought that insulitis in ISS was a little better over ESS.<fig id="f0009" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Islet inflammation score in 8w. Data are average values ± SEM. Significant differences (P&lt;0.05): *NW vs CTL (<bold>A</bold>); *LSS, ESS or ISS vs CTL (<bold>B</bold>); *ESS or ISS vs LSS (<bold>C</bold>).</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-12-1053-g0009"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>This research was designed to study the metabolic effects of chronic (long-term) sleep deprivation using the rat model. An earlier study reported weight loss in sleep-deprived rats for the first week.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> In our study too, we noticed a loss of weight in the same period. Later, upon prolonged sleep deprivation, we found an incremental gain of weight, till the end of the study, ie up to the 8th week. At the weekends, rats were allowed to have regular sleep with rest. Particularly, compared to the weekdays, weight gain was prominent over the weekends, along with the increased food intake. Interestingly, these results suggest that this week-weekend model can prevent weight loss in sleep-deprived rats. However, the weight of the NW group was still lower than that of the CTL group and they did not turn obese both in the studies of us and Barf’s team, which was not in accordance with humans or rats with Selgado-Delgado model. This may have been caused by our longer sleep deprivation time compared with Selgado-Delgado model and our heavier stress compared with human. Corticosterone is closely associated with stress and REM sleep-deprived rats exhibit higher corticosterone release, coinciding with lower body weight gain.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Due to the wakefulness, increased sympathetic activity increases energy expenditure. Apart from this, chronic sleep deprivation has shown to have inhibitory effects on the expression of <italic>Srebp1</italic> and <italic>Scd1</italic> in the liver, which reduces triglyceride levels, to ultimately reduce the lipid biosynthesis.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> Long-term sleep deprivation is also known to reduce blood lipid levels and retroperitoneal adipose tissue.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> Besides, protein catabolism is triggered to meet the energy demands that lead to further weight loss.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> The above indicates that the night shift work using rat model has more stress than human in the similar sleep deprivation periods, which caused weight loss.</p>
      <p>In our study, we found that sleep deprivation led to impaired glucose metabolism and increased fasting plasma glucose, but no significant effect on insulin resistance index (HOMA-IR) or insulin sensitivity (HOMA-IS). This suggested that chronic sleep deprivation led to islet dysfunction. The major cause of impaired glucose metabolism was due to the lack of insulin secretion, but not due to insulin resistance. A similar phenomenon has been reported previously.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Using stimulated insulin secretion assays, they showed that impaired insulin secretion was related to the high energy expenditure in islet cells. To understand further, we studied histopathological changes in pancreatic islets using H&amp;E staining. We found that the insulitis score was significantly higher in NW, compared to the CTL group. This explains the hypoinsulinism and high energy expenditure in the islets. Apart from this, a study also suggests that sleep deprivation increases levels of inflammatory factors that could trigger insulitis.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> However, the molecular mechanism for the same is still unknown.</p>
      <p>Interestingly, we found a decrease in fasting insulin and an increase in basal and 15-minutes time points plasma glucose among the NW subgroups in the 4th week, but not in the 8th week. These results are in line with the changes of hormone metabolism in stress, like increased glucagon, increased cortisol and decreasing insulin. This suggested that the results of chronic sleep deprivation were more representative in the 8th week with the improvement of stress. Improving sleep, reducing sleep deprivation, and returning to normal rhythmic sleep in night workers may slow down or even stop the process of metabolic abnormalities.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> However, due to social obligations, time to bed and time in bed are flexible in humans. It would be interesting to know if a particular mode would be beneficial over others. To explore this, sleep-deprived rats were subjected to three different, most usual, sleep supplement modes. Comparing the results we found that Intermittent (ISS) and early (ESS) sleep supplement groups had the least effect on body weight over late sleep supplement group (LSS) from night work, which was consistent with the more food consumption. Although there was no significant difference in body weight between ISS and ESS, we found that the ISS group loosed the least weight in the first week and was also first to recover for an increasing trend. Interestingly, apart from weight benefits, ISS also had the least negative effect on glucose metabolism over the other two groups. For insulitis, we saw that both ISS and ESS were better than LSS; however, here too, ISS seemed to be a little better over ESS. It could be that due to limited observation time or the stress caused by the water platform in our experiments, we failed to notice the quantifiable pathological differences between the ISS and ESS groups. Overall, our finding suggests that ISS may be the best way to negate the metabolic consequences of the night work. We believe that several factors contributed to this result. Firstly, circadian misalignment arises when sleep or waking state occurs at inappropriate circadian times; ie, waking state occurs at the time the internal circadian clock is fostering sleep.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Circadian misalignment can be intermittent as during shift work or chronic as in circadian rhythm sleep-wake disorders.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Similarly, circadian clock genes are often disturbed by exogenous factors like sleep disturbance, anesthesia and surgery. A series of clock genes (<italic>Per, Cry, Clock and Bmal1</italic>) interact to drive cell circadian rhythms.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27–29</xref> The clock genes regulate metabolic genes to adapt to the body’s circadian metabolic needs.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> Hepatocyte metabolic genes, such as <italic>Ppary, Pparα, Pparβ, Pgc-α1, and Sirt1</italic> have also been found associated with the clock genes.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> Night shift work disrupts inter-regulation between clock genes and metabolic genes. Abnormal interaction of both clock and metabolic genes caused by circadian rhythm disorder can result in impaired glucose metabolism.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33–35</xref> Apart from this production of melatonin, an important factor for circadian rhythm gets decreased in sleep deprivation rats.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> That also leads to a variety of metabolic abnormalities, including glucose metabolic disorders.<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37–39</xref> We postulate that ISS is the best mode of sleep supplementation due to its ability to partially recover the previous sleep rhythms, by effectively bridging the normal circadian rhythm to the supplement sleep. Secondly, we found that glucocorticoids were higher in NW subgroups. REM sleep-deprived rats indeed exhibit higher corticosterone<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> and it was suggested that change in cortisol levels was also associated with glucose homeostasis disorders in night shift workers.<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> Apart from that, REM sleep-deprived rats show increased energy consumption<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> and increased expression of IL-6 and TNF-a in the white adipose tissue,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> indicating that, even though this deprivation causes loss of fat tissue, sleep deprivation can also lead to increased inflammation. Given that, the lower glucocorticoids and the lighter REM deprivation of ISS in our study might account for its advantage over others. Thirdly, adult rats become hyperphagic after sleep deprivation or sleep restriction because of the reduced leptin receptor and increased NPY-Y2 receptor expression in the hypothalamus.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> Interestingly, sleep-deprived rats eat fewer than normal rats during the period of sleep supplement which was opposite to the period of sleep deprivation and most likely because they rather sleep than eat when presented an opportunity to sleep.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> In our study, the average food intake of NW subgroups was also fewer than CTL, and ISS ate the most during light off (the period of sleep supplement) among NW subgroups, which indicated the least effect on metabolism about sleep deprivation compared to others.</p>
      <p>Our preliminary exploration has found that the effects of different sleep supplement modes in attenuating metabolic consequences of night shift work using rat model are meaningful, it is worthy to invest more financial and effort to the further exploration of the specific changes of metabolic pathways and mechanisms through EEG, EMG, study design with less stress et al and it is also of great value to explore the metabolism changes among different sleep supplement models in the real world, at that time, the use of generalized additive model will be more effective to compare the statistically significant difference adjusted for possible confounders among different groups.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Simulated night work brings unhealthy effects on the body weight and glucose metabolism. The comparison of different sleep supplement modes after night work suggested that intermittent sleep supplement is superior in reducing the metabolic consequences of sleep deprivation.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Ethics approval</title>
      <p>All experimental procedures were carried out in accordance with the National Institutes of Health Laboratory Animal feeding, China and were ethically approved by the Animal Administration Department of Beijing Hospital.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>All authors contributed to data analysis, drafting or revising the article, have agreed on the journal to which the article will be submitted, gave final approval of the version to be published, and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0008" sec-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors report no conflicts of interest for this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Folkard</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tucker</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macdonald</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Work shift duration: a review comparing eight hour and 12 hour shift systems</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Occup Environ Med</italic></source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>229</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/oem.55.4.217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9624275</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vetter</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dashti</surname>
<given-names>HS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lane</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Night shift work, genetic risk, and type 2 diabetes in the UK Biobank</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes Care</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>762</fpage>–<lpage>769</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc17-1933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29440150</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lim</surname>
<given-names>YC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoe</surname>
<given-names>VCW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Darus</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bhoo-Pathy</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between night-shift work, sleep quality and metabolic syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Occup Environ Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>716</fpage>–<lpage>723</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30032104</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wilms</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leineweber</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mölle</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep loss disrupts morning-to-evening differences in human white adipose tissue transcriptome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Endocrinol Metab</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1687</fpage>–<lpage>1696</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30535338</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Spiegel</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leproult</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Cauter</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Impact of sleep debt on metabolic and endocrine function</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet (London, England)</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>354</volume>(<issue>9188</issue>):<fpage>1435</fpage>–<lpage>1439</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(99)01376-8</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Barf</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Desprez</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meerlo</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scheurink</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Increased food intake and changes in metabolic hormones in response to chronic sleep restriction alternated with short periods of sleep allowance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>302</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>R112</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpregu.00326.2011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22012696</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Decrease in circulating fatty acids is associated with islet dysfunction in chronically sleep-restricted rats</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Mol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2102</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms17122102</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Salgado-Delgado</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saderi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Basualdo Mdel</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guerrero-Vargas</surname>
<given-names>NN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Escobar</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buijs</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Shift work or food intake during the rest phase promotes metabolic disruption and desynchrony of liver genes in male rats</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e60052</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0060052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23565183</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rosa Neto</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lira</surname>
<given-names>FS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Venancio</surname>
<given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep deprivation affects inflammatory marker expression in adipose tissue</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lipids Health Dis</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>125</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-511X-9-125</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21034496</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hipolide</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suchecki</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pimentel de Carvalho Pinto</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chiconelli Faria</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tufik</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luz</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Paradoxical sleep deprivation and sleep recovery: effects on the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis activity, energy balance and body composition of rats</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neuroendocrinol</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>238</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2826.2006.01412.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16503918</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Machado</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suchecki</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tufik</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep homeostasis in rats assessed by a long-term intermittent paradoxical sleep deprivation protocol</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Brain Res</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>160</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>356</fpage>–<lpage>364</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbr.2005.01.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15863232</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sai</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rivereau</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Granier</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haertle</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martignat</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Immunization of non-obese diabetic (NOD) mice with glutamic acid decarboxylase-derived peptide 524-543 reduces cyclophosphamide-accelerated diabetes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Exp Immunol</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>105</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>330</fpage>–<lpage>337</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2249.1996.d01-751.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8706342</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hairston</surname>
<given-names>IS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruby</surname>
<given-names>NF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brooke</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep deprivation elevates plasma corticosterone levels in neonatal rats</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurosci Lett</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>315</volume>(<issue>1–2</issue>):<fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-3940(01)02309-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11711207</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Barf</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Dijk</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scheurink</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Metabolic consequences of chronic sleep restriction in rats: changes in body weight regulation and energy expenditure</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiol Behav</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>107</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>322</fpage>–<lpage>328</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.physbeh.2012.09.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22995976</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kikuchi-Utsumi</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ohinata</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hashimoto</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuroshima</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Repeated immobilization stress increases uncoupling protein 1 expression and activity in Wistar rats</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Jpn J Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2170/jjphysiol.53.205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14529581</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Moraes</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Venancio</surname>
<given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suchecki</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep deprivation alters energy homeostasis through non-compensatory alterations in hypothalamic insulin receptors in Wistar rats</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Horm Behav</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>705</fpage>–<lpage>712</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yhbeh.2014.08.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25304978</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jump</surname>
<given-names>DB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tripathy</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Depner</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Fatty acid-regulated transcription factors in the liver</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Annu Rev Nutr</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>269</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-nutr-071812-161139</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23528177</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yadav</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ahn</surname>
<given-names>SV</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A prospective study of total sleep duration and incident metabolic syndrome: the ARIRANG study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1511</fpage>–<lpage>1515</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2015.06.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26611949</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Venancio</surname>
<given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suchecki</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prolonged REM sleep restriction induces metabolic syndrome-related changes: mediation by pro-inflammatory cytokines</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Behav Immun</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2014.12.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25532784</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Everson</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Szabo</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blanc</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Repeated exposure to severely limited sleep results in distinctive and persistent physiological imbalances in rats</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e22987</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0022987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21853062</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Reinhardt</surname>
<given-names>EL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fernandes</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Markus</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fischer</surname>
<given-names>FM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Night work effects on salivary cytokines TNF, IL-1beta and IL-6</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chronobiol Int</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07420528.2018.1515771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30230913</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Killick</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoyos</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Melehan</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dungan</surname>
<given-names>GC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poh</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>PY</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Metabolic and hormonal effects of ‘catch-up’ sleep in men with chronic, repetitive, lifestyle-driven sleep restriction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Endocrinol (Oxf)</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>83</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>498</fpage>–<lpage>507</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cen.12747</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25683266</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baron</surname>
<given-names>KG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reid</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Circadian misalignment and health</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int Rev Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>154</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/09540261.2014.911149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24892891</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gronfier</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wright</surname>
<given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kronauer</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Czeisler</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Entrainment of the human circadian pacemaker to longer-than-24-h days</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):<fpage>9081</fpage>–<lpage>9086</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0702835104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17502598</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wright</surname>
<given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bogan</surname>
<given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wyatt</surname>
<given-names>JK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Shift work and the assessment and management of shift work disorder (SWD)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2012.02.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22560640</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sack</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Auckley</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Auger</surname>
<given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Circadian rhythm sleep disorders: part I, basic principles, shift work and jet lag disorders. An American Academy of Sleep Medicine review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1460</fpage>–<lpage>1483</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/30.11.1460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18041480</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Reppert</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weaver</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Coordination of circadian timing in mammals</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nature</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>418</volume>(<issue>6901</issue>):<fpage>935</fpage>–<lpage>941</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature00965</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12198538</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Takahashi</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Circadian clock genes are ticking</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Science (New York, NY)</italic></source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>258</volume>(<issue>5080</issue>):<fpage>238</fpage>–<lpage>240</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1384127</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tei</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Okamura</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shigeyoshi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Circadian oscillation of a mammalian homologue of the Drosophila period gene</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nature</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>389</volume>(<issue>6650</issue>):<fpage>512</fpage>–<lpage>516</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/39086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9333243</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lamia</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Storch</surname>
<given-names>KF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weitz</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Physiological significance of a peripheral tissue circadian clock</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>105</volume>(<issue>39</issue>):<fpage>15172</fpage>–<lpage>15177</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0806717105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18779586</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Grimaldi</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bellet</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Katada</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>PER2 controls lipid metabolism by direct regulation of PPARgamma</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cell Metab</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>509</fpage>–<lpage>520</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2010.10.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21035761</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Evans</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barish</surname>
<given-names>GD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>YX</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>PPARs and the complex journey to obesity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Med</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>361</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm1025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15057233</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Albrecht</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Timing to perfection: the biology of central and peripheral circadian clocks</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuron</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>74</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>246</fpage>–<lpage>260</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2012.04.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22542179</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kumar Jha</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Challet</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kalsbeek</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Circadian rhythms in glucose and lipid metabolism in nocturnal and diurnal mammals</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Cell Endocrinol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>418</volume>(<issue>Pt 1</issue>):<fpage>74</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mce.2015.01.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25662277</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Figueiro</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Radetsky</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Plitnick</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rea</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Glucose tolerance in mice exposed to light-dark stimulus patterns mirroring dayshift and rotating shift schedules</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>40661</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep40661</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28079162</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dong</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Role of melatonin in sleep deprivation-induced intestinal barrier dysfunction in mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Pineal Res</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e12574</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jpi.12574</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30929267</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vinogradova</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Anisimov</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Melatonin prevents the development of the metabolic syndrome in male rats exposed to different light/dark regimens</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biogerontology</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>401</fpage>–<lpage>409</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10522-013-9437-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23784085</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ulhoa</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marqueze</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burgos</surname>
<given-names>LG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moreno</surname>
<given-names>CR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Shift work and endocrine disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Endocrinol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>2015</volume>:<fpage>826249</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25892993</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>West</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ray</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Loudon</surname>
<given-names>ASI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bechtold</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Misalignment with the external light environment drives metabolic and cardiac dysfunction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Commun</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>417</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-017-00462-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28900189</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chaput</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drapeau</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poirier</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Teasdale</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tremblay</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Glycemic instability and spontaneous energy intake: association with knowledge-based work</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychosom Med</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>70</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>797</fpage>–<lpage>804</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PSY.0b013e31818426fa</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18725427</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Menezes</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Moraes</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ribeiro-Silva</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Silva</surname>
<given-names>SMA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suchecki</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luz</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Chronic REM sleep restriction in young rats increases energy expenditure with no change in food intake</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Exp Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>105</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1339</fpage>–<lpage>1348</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/EP088474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32589295</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
