<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34194254</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">8238550</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">315556</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S315556</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Review</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>To Nap or Not to Nap? A Systematic Review Evaluating Napping Behavior in Athletes and the Impact on Various Measures of Athletic Performance</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Lastella et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Lastella et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1793-3811</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Lastella</surname>
            <given-names>Michele</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1047-3878</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Halson</surname>
            <given-names>Shona L</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7537-079X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Vitale</surname>
            <given-names>Jacopo A</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0003">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3203-418X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Memon</surname>
            <given-names>Aamir R</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0004">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7036-7823</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Vincent</surname>
            <given-names>Grace E</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Appleton Institute for Behavioural Science, Central Queensland University</institution>, <addr-line>Adelaide</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>School of Behavioural and Health Sciences, Australian Catholic University</institution>, <addr-line>Brisbane</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Laboratory of Movement and Sport Science, IRCCS Istituto Ortopedico Galeazzi</institution>, <addr-line>Milan</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Institute of Physiotherapy &amp; Rehabilitation Sciences, Peoples University of Medical &amp; Health Sciences for Women</institution>, <addr-line>Nawabshah</addr-line>, <addr-line>Shaheed Benazirabad</addr-line>, <country>Pakistan</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Michele Lastella <institution>Appleton Institute for Behavioural Science, Central Queensland University</institution>, <addr-line>Adelaide</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country><phone>Tel +61 413407956</phone> Email m.lastella@cqu.edu.au</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>24</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>13</volume>
      <fpage>841</fpage>
      <lpage>862</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2021 Lastella et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Lastella et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p>The objective of this systematic review was to 1) determine how studies evaluated napping behavior in athletes (frequency, duration, timing and measurement); 2) explore how napping impacted physical performance, cognitive performance, perceptual measures (eg, fatigue, muscle soreness, sleepiness and alertness), psychological state and night-time sleep in athletes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>Five bibliographic databases were searched from database inception to 11 August 2020. Observational and experimental studies comprising able-bodied athletes (mean age ≥12 years), published in English, in peer-reviewed journal papers were included. The Downs and Black Quality Assessment Checklist was used for quality appraisal.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>Thirty-seven studies were identified of moderate quality. Most studies did not include consistent information regarding nap frequency, duration, and timing. Napping may be beneficial for a range of outcomes that benefit athletes (eg, physical and cognitive performance, perceptual measures, psychological state and night-time sleep). In addition, napping presents athletes with the opportunity to supplement their night-time sleep without compromising sleep quality.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>Athletes may consider napping between 20 to 90 min in duration and between 13:00 and 16:00 hours. Finally, athletes should allow 30 min to reduce sleep inertia prior to training or competition to obtain better performance outcomes. Future studies should include comprehensive recordings of nap duration and quality, and consider using sleep over a 24 hour period (daytime naps and night-time sleep period), specifically using objective methods of sleep assessment (eg, polysomnography/actigraphy).</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>athlete</kwd>
        <kwd>health behavior</kwd>
        <kwd>performance</kwd>
        <kwd>physical health</kwd>
        <kwd>psychological health</kwd>
        <kwd>sleep</kwd>
        <kwd>sports</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="3"/>
        <table-count count="4"/>
        <ref-count count="98"/>
        <page-count count="22"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Napping is a ubiquitous behavior and an important public health tool to offset the adverse short- and long-term impacts of inadequate sleep.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> By definition, a nap is any sleep period with a duration of less than 50% of the average major sleep period of an individual.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> A nap is often referred to as a ‘short sleep’ which is distinct from, and considerably shorter than an individual’s normal sleep episode.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Naps may be further categorized into three main types: a) the prophylactic nap: a nap taken in anticipation of sleep loss; b) the replacement nap: a nap taken in response to sleep loss; and c) the appetitive nap: a nap taken for convenience and/or enjoyment.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Another consideration absent within the sleep literature is the idea that athletes take naps as they are educated that napping may result in recovery and performance benefits. Napping during the day can increase the amount of sleep obtained in a 24-hour period and many athletes report including daytime napping in their training program.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> For example, Sargent et al<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> demonstrated that more naps were taken on training days compared to rest days, and strategic napping during the day, as well as sleep hygiene practices (ie, healthy sleep practices) at night need to be considered. While several studies have investigated the impact of restricting or extending sleep on a number of outcomes of athletic performance (eg, sprint times, reaction time),<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> there has been comparatively less focus on the impact of napping.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> It is possible that the lack of dedicated napping research in athletes may limit the ability of athletes, coaches and sports professionals to effectively implement strategic napping within their training programs.</p>
      <p>Athletes are exposed to many stressors that impair sleep, including high training loads, competition demands, early morning training, travel and altitude exposure.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> As a result, athletes are often unable to obtain the recommended adult night-time sleep duration of 7–9 h per night.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> The majority of research examining athletes’ sleep has focused on the impact of night-time sleep on performance and recovery.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Yet, napping represents an opportunity to supplement the night-time sleep period, which may assist athletes in obtaining recommended sleep. Previous research on non-athletes has shown that napping can improve daytime sleepiness, mood and cognitive performance,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12–14</xref> with the magnitude of these effects comparable to other sleep restriction countermeasures (eg, caffeine, modafinil).<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> However, despite the recent interest in napping in athletes,<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> the impact of napping on athletes is yet to be systematically investigated. Therefore, the first aim of this study was to determine how studies evaluated napping behavior in athletes (frequency, duration, timing and measurement). The second aim of the study was to explore how napping impacted physical performance, cognitive performance, perceptual measures (eg, fatigue, muscle soreness, sleepiness and alertness), psychological state and night-time sleep in athletes. This review will provide key recommendations for practitioners and athletes, as well as directions for future research.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Protocol Registration</title>
        <p>This systematic review followed the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta Analyses (PRISMA) guidelines.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> The protocol for this review was registered in the PROSPERO database for systematic reviews (CRD42020208652).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Search Strategy</title>
        <p>Five bibliographic databases (PsychINFO, PubMed, Scopus, SportDiscus, and Web of Science) were searched for relevant peer-reviewed journal papers from database inception to 11 August 2020. Articles were published in English and the search strategy combined napping terms (“nap”, “daytime sleep”, “siesta”, “midday sleep”, “midday nap”, “afternoon nap”, “daytime sleepiness”) with athlete terms (“athlete/s”, “elite athletes”, “competitive athlete”, “sport”, “player”). In addition to the primary database searches, secondary searchers of reference lists of studies and citing articles meeting the inclusion criteria were carefully hand searched for potential inclusion of additional studies. The detailed search strategy is shown in <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=315556.docx">Supplementary Material</ext-link></underline>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Eligibility Criteria</title>
        <p>Studies were included according to the PEOS (Population, Exposure, Outcomes, Study design) format. The PEOS format was preferred over other reporting frameworks (eg, PICO) as the included studies were a mix of observational and interventional designs, which align more closely with the PEOS format.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></p>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3001">
          <title>Population</title>
          <p>Studies with able-bodied athletes, where the mean age of participants was ≥12 years were included. Athletes between 12 and 18 years were included as young athletes as the International Olympic Committee underlies that athletes, especially young athletes should obtain sufficient sleep quantity and quality.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Athlete was defined as someone who “engages in physical activity or sports with the primary goal of improving performance to bolster athletic excellence and/or achievement”.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> This did not include non-athletes, such as habitual exercisers, industrial or occupational athletes (eg, military, firefighters, ski patrol) and healthy sedentary or recreationally active volunteers.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3002">
          <title>Exposure</title>
          <p>A nap was defined as “a short sleep” which is distinct from and substantially shorter than an individual’s normal sleep episode.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> In more quantifiable terms, it was defined as “any sleep period with a duration of less than 50% of the average main sleep period of an individual”.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Subjective (eg, self-report) and/or objective (eg, polysomnography, actigraphy) measures of sleep within the nap period were considered for inclusion.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3003">
          <title>Outcome</title>
          <p>Outcomes included a) physical performance (eg, sprint times, time to exhaustion, grip strength, jump height), b) cognitive performance (eg, reaction time, levels of attention, levels of alertness), c) psychological state (eg, mood, well-being), and d) night-time sleep.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3004">
          <title>Study Design</title>
          <p>Studies that were observational (eg, cross-sectional, case-control, cohort) or experimental (eg, randomized, non-randomized trials, interventional trials) in nature were included.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3005">
          <title>Other Criteria</title>
          <p>Full-text articles published in a peer-reviewed journal and in English language were included. Narrative reviews, systematic reviews, commentaries, viewpoints, editorials and errata documents were excluded. In addition, studies investigating napping behavior of Muslim (fasting) athletes during Ramadan were excluded as fasting may impact athlete’s sleep.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Study Selection</title>
        <p>All search results were imported into EndNote X7 software (Thomson Reuters, San Francisco, CA, USA). After removing duplicates, articles were independently screened by two reviewers (ML and ARM), based on title and abstract to determine their eligibility for inclusion. The full-texts of all included articles were then sourced and independently screened by two reviewers (ML and ARM) to ensure they met eligibility criteria. At all stages, conflicts were resolved through consensus or by involvement of a third reviewer (GEV).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Data Extraction</title>
        <p>Using a standardized form, the following data were extracted independently by two reviewers (ML and ARM). Any discrepancies were identified and resolved through discussion or by involving a third reviewer (GEV). The extracted data included i) publication details (eg, authors surname, publication year, country); ii) study design (eg, cross-sectional); iii) sample characteristics (eg, age and sex); iv) type of sport; v) napping measurement (eg, actigraphy, self-report); and vi) napping outcomes (eg, duration, frequency and context).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2006">
        <title>Methodological Quality Assessment</title>
        <p>The methodological quality of included studies was assessed using the Downs and Black Quality Assessment Checklist,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> adjusted by the study design of included studies. Two reviewers (ARM and ML) conducted the assessment independently, with cases of uncertainty resolved by involving a third reviewer (GEV). For papers where one of the reviewers (ML) was a co-author, methodological quality assessment of studies was performed independently by two reviewers (ARM and GEV). Included studies were scored on 28 items for interventional, 20 for cohort and 16 for cross-sectional study designs. The overall quality scores were converted to a percentage value and rated as low (0–49%), moderate (50–89%) and high (≥90%).<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Study Identification and Selection</title>
        <p>The database searches yielded 2730 studies (PsychINFO: 73; PubMed: 122; Scopus: 1029; SportDiscus: 974; and Web of Science: 532). Secondary searches identified an additional relevant study. Duplicate records were removed (n = 630) and the remaining 2101 records were assessed on the basis of title and abstract, with a further exclusion of 1992 studies. A total of 109 studies were eligible for full-text assessment. Of these, 72 studies were excluded because of the following reasons: participants were not athletes (n = 20), the study did not report napping data (n = 31), reviews (n = 7), no full-text (n = 9), non-scientific (n = 2), and Ramadan (n = 3). Thus, a total of 37 studies were included in the final review.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24–57</xref> The search process and number of studies retrieved at each stage are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref>.<fig id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>PRISMA flow diagram for the studies included in the review. <bold>Notes:</bold> Adapted from Moher D, Liberati A, Tetzlaff J, Altman DG, PRISMA Group. Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses: the PRISMA statement. <italic>PLoS Med</italic>. 2009;6(7):e1000097.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Creative Commons Attribution License.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-841-g0001"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Study Characteristics</title>
        <p>Thirty-seven studies were included in the systematic review, with detailed characteristics in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Tables 1</xref> and <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Due to the amount of diversity and heterogeneity across studies, conducting a meta-analysis was not appropriate. The studies were published between 2009 and 2020 and consisted of 3489 participants.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24–57</xref> Both males and females were included in 35.1% (n = 13) of studies,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34–36</xref>,<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> 8.1% (n = 3) of studies included females exclusively,<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref> and 48.6% (n = 18) studies included males only.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24–26</xref>,<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45–47</xref>,<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52–56</xref> Three studies (8.1%) did not report sex.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> The mean age of athletes was 23±4 years. Study designs were as follows: cross-sectional (n = 6),<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25–30</xref> longitudinal/cohort (n = 14),<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31–39</xref>,<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,<xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref> randomized experimental (n = 14),<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42–49</xref>,<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52–56</xref> and non-randomized experimental (n = 3).<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> Athletes participated in 11 different sports (ie, karate, judo, netball, rowing, rugby, running, soccer, swimming, shooting marksmanship, track and field, and ultramarathon).<table-wrap id="t0001" orientation="landscape" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Studies Reporting Nap Characteristics (Frequency, Duration, Timing and Measurement) in Athletes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Author, Year, Country, Study Design</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">N, Sex, Age</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sport, Nap Assessment</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nap Duration</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time of Nap (hh:mm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Naps</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency of Naps</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caia et al 2017<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref><break/>Australia<break/>Longitudinal, observational</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7<break/>M: 7<break/>24±2 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rugby League, professional<break/>Sleep diary, Actigraphy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pre-season</italic>: 51±19 min<break/><italic>Competition</italic>: 39±17 min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pre-season</italic>: 8 naps in 7 days<break/><italic>Competition</italic>: 8 naps in 7 days</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 naps taken out of 14 days</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carter al 2020<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref><break/>USA<break/>Longitudinal, observational</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">121<break/>M: 65, F: 56<break/>M: 21±1 years<break/>M: 20±1 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multi-sport, individual, team sport<break/>Sleep diary, Actigraphy (no naps included)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M: 69±10 min<break/>F: 72±7 min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fullagar et al 2016<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><break/>England<break/>Longitudinal, observational</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15<break/>M:1526±5 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soccer, professional<break/>Sleep diary, Actigraphy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Day of arrival</italic>: 65±15 min<break/><italic>Match day 1</italic>: 100±35 min<break/><italic>Match day 2</italic>: 91±38 min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Day of arrival</italic><break/>Start: 14:27 ± 01:29<break/>Wake up: 15:32 ± 01:19<break/><italic>Match day 1</italic><break/>Start: 14:54±01:28<break/>Wake up: 16:34±01:06<break/><italic>Match day 2</italic><break/>Start: 14:53±0:14<break/>Wake up: 16:30±0:32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Day of arrival</italic>: 6/15 participants napped<break/><italic>Match day 1</italic>: 7/15 participants napped<break/><italic>Match day 2</italic>: 11/15 participants napped</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fullagar et al 2016<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref><break/>Germany<break/>Randomized cross-over</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20<break/>M: 20<break/>NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soccer, semi-professional<break/>Sleep diary, Actigraphy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sleep hygiene condition</italic>: Baseline: 56±21 min<break/>Match night +1: 66±19 min<break/><italic>Non-sleep hygiene condition</italic>:<break/>Baseline: 42±34 min<break/>Match night +1: 81±2 min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sleep hygiene condition</italic>: 5 naps<break/><italic>Non-sleep hygiene condition</italic>: 7 naps</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fullagar et al 2016<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref><break/>Germany, Netherlands<break/>Longitudinal, observational</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16<break/>M: 1626±8 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soccer, professional<break/>Self-report questionnaire</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Training day</italic>: 57±36 min<break/><italic>Day game</italic>: 30±0 min<break/><italic>Night match</italic>: 67±29 min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Training day</italic>: 10 participants (63%) napped at least once<break/><italic>Day game</italic>: 1 participant (1%) napped<break/><italic>Night match</italic>: 3 participants (20%) napped</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hurdiel et al 2018<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref><break/>France<break/>Longitudinal, observational</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">147<break/>M: 92<break/>&gt;20 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ultramarathon<break/>Self-report questionnaire</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.6% napped (64 out of 92)<break/>14.5±9.5 min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jones et al 2019<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref><break/>Australia<break/>Longitudinal, observational</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70<break/>M: 26, F: 4421±4 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multi-sport, elite<break/>Sleep diary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73±48 min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 participants reported napping (21%±4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kolling et al 2016<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref><break/>Germany<break/>Longitudinal, observational</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55<break/>M: 30, F: 2518±1 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rowing, junior elite<break/>Sleep diary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64±32 min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12:00–15:00: 80%<break/>&lt;12:00: 13%<break/>15:00–18:00: 7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58–82% participants reported napping</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lastella et al 2015<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><break/>Australia Longitudinal, observational</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">124<break/>M: 104, F: 2022±13 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multi-sport, elite<break/>Sleep diary, Actigraphy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Individual sport</italic>: 45±41 min<break/><italic>Team sport</italic>: 59±62 min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Individual sport</italic>: 114 naps<break/><italic>Team sport</italic>: 70 naps</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Individual Sport</italic>: 15% napped<break/><italic>Team Sport</italic>: 11% napped</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mah et al 2018<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref><break/>USA<break/>Longitudinal, observational</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">628<break/>M: 343, F: 28,520±1 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multi-sport, college<break/>Self-report questionnaire</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Habitual</italic>:<break/>Did not nap: 9%<break/>&lt;10 min nap: 0%<break/>10–30 min nap: 22%<break/>30–60 min nap: 43%<break/>60–120 min nap: 23%<break/>&gt;120 min nap: 2%<break/><italic>Pre-game</italic>:<break/>Did not nap: 44%<break/>&lt;10 min nap: 3%<break/>10–30 min nap; 26%<break/>30–60 min nap: 19%<break/>60–120 min nap: 8%<break/>&gt;120 min nap: 1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Habitual</italic>: 80% nap at least once per week<break/><italic>Pre-game</italic>: 11% napped</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Martin et al 2018<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref><break/>Canada, USA, Italy<break/>Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">636<break/>M: 541, F: 95<break/>NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ultramarathon<break/>Self-report questionnaire</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Non-training days</italic>:<break/>34% napped for 10–20 min<break/>37% napped for 30–60 min<break/><italic>Training days</italic>:<break/>20% napped for 10–20 min<break/>40% napped for 30–60 min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Work days</italic>: 20% napped<break/><italic>Non-training days</italic>: 19% napped<break/><italic>Training days</italic>: 25% napped</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Romyn et al 2016<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref><break/>Australia Longitudinal, observational</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8<break/>F: 8<break/>20±2 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Netball, elite<break/>Sleep diary, Actigraphy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Training</italic>: 46±28<break/><italic>Competition</italic>: 28±34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Training</italic>: 10 naps across 4 days<break/><italic>Competition</italic>: 8 naps across 3 days</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sargent et al 2014<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><break/>Australia<break/>Longitudinal, observational</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70<break/>M: 46, F: 2420±3 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multi-sport, elite<break/>Sleep diary, Actigraphy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49±46 min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total 139 naps recorded<break/><italic>Training days</italic>: 115 naps<break/><italic>Rest days</italic>: 24 naps</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 participants (57%) did not report napping<break/><italic>Training days</italic>: 15% napped<break/><italic>Rest days</italic>: 16% napped</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sargent et al 2014<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref><break/>Australia Longitudinal, observational</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7<break/>F: 7<break/>23±2 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Swimming, elite<break/>Sleep diary, Actigraphy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Training days</italic>: 12±30 min<break/><italic>Rest days</italic>: 0 naps</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Training days</italic>: 26 naps across 12 days</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 naps on rest days (rest day = 2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stevens et al 2018<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref><break/>Australia<break/>Prospective cohort</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12<break/>NR<break/>48±14 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triathlon, masters<break/>Sleep-diary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Baseline</italic>: 12±7 min<break/><italic>Pre-flight</italic>: 45±0 min<break/><italic>Flight</italic>: 0±0 min<break/><italic>Training</italic>: 72±31 min<break/><italic>Pre-race</italic>: 45±15 min<break/><italic>Post-race</italic>: 0±0 min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42% (5 out of 12) athletes napped</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Baseline</italic>: 67% napped<break/><italic>Pre-flight</italic>: 8% napped<break/><italic>Flight</italic>: 0% napped<break/><italic>Training</italic>: 67% napped<break/><italic>Pre-race</italic>: 17% napped<break/><italic>Post-race</italic>: 0% napped</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thornton et al 2017<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref><break/>Australia<break/>Longitudinal, observational</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31<break/>M: 3125±4 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rugby, professional<break/>Sleep diary, Actigraphy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Camp<break/>Morning (&lt;12:00):<break/>30±15 min<break/>Afternoon (&gt;12:00):<break/>32±18 min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Morning nap (&lt;12:00)</italic>:<break/>Bedtime: 07:05±00:35<break/>Get up time: 07:52±00:39<break/><italic>Afternoon nap (&gt;12:00)</italic>:<break/>Bedtime: 12:46±00:40<break/>Get up time: 12:54±00:41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Morning</italic>: 71 naps recorded<break/><italic>Afternoon</italic>: 85 naps recorded in the<break/><italic>Home</italic>: 7 participants (23%) napped<break/><italic>Camp</italic>: 25 participants (83%) napped</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Venter et al 2010<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref><break/>South Africa<break/>Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">890<break/>M: 507, F: 38,322±3 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multi-sport, elite (team sports only)<break/>Self-report questionnaire</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32% never napped<break/>47% sometimes napped<break/>17% napped regularly<break/>4% always napped</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Walsh et al 2019<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref><break/>Scotland<break/>Longitudinal, observational</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12<break/>M: 9,<break/>F: 3<break/>21±2 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Swimming<break/>Sleep diary, Actigraphy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rest</italic>: 6±10 min<break/><italic>Taper</italic>: 12±16 min<break/><italic>Training</italic>: 23±20 min<break/><italic>Competition</italic>: 25±24 min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rest</italic>: 4 (33%) participants napped<break/><italic>Taper</italic>: 9 (75%) participants napped<break/><italic>Training</italic>: 11 (92%) participants napped<break/><italic>Competition</italic>: 9 (75%) participants napped</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> F, female; M, male; NR, not reported.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="t0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The Effects of Naps on Physical and Cognitive Performance, Perceptual Measures of Fatigue and Muscle Soreness, Sleepiness and Alertness, Psychological State, and Night-Time Sleep</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Author, Year</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Restriction, Nap Opportunity, Performance Measures</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effects of Napping (Physical Performance; Cognitive Performance; Perceptual Measures of Fatigue and Muscle Soreness, Sleepiness and Alertness; Psychological State; and Night-Time Sleep)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ajjimaporn et al 2020<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sleep restriction</italic>: Control 3 h sleep<break/><italic>Nap opportunity</italic>: N20<break/><italic>Performance measures</italic>: Running-based anaerobic sprint test (RAST), Isometric dynamometer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Physical performance</italic>: RAST in Control vs N20: ↓ Maximum power, ↔ Minimum power, ↑ Fatigue, ↑ Leg strength, ↑ RPE<break/>RAST in 3 h vs 3 h ± N20: ↑ Maximum power, ↑ Minimum power, ↑ Mean power, ↔ Fatigue, ↑ Leg strength, ↔ RPE<break/><italic>Cognitive performance</italic>: ↔ Auditory</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blanchfield et al 2018<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sleep restriction</italic>: No<break/><italic>Nap opportunity</italic>: No nap vs N20<break/><italic>Performance measures</italic>: Motorized treadmill</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Physical performance</italic>: ↑ RPE, ↑ Time to exhaustion (only for participants that slept &lt;7 h)<break/><italic>Perceptual measures of fatigue and muscle soreness, sleepiness and alertness</italic>: (ESS) Sleepiness ↓ immediately but returned to ↔ 90 min post nap<break/><italic>Psychological state</italic>: ↔ BRUMS</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boukhris et al 2020<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sleep restriction</italic>: No<break/><italic>Nap opportunity</italic>: No nap vs N40 vs N90<break/><italic>Performance measures</italic>: Isometric dynamometer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Physical performance</italic>: ↑ RPE, ↑ 5MSRT, ↑ Muscle contraction, ↑ Higher distance, ↑ Total distance, ↑ Perceived recovery, ↑ Fatigue index, ↑ DOMS, ↑ DOMS after N90 compared to N40, ↑ all physical performances in N90 than N40<break/><italic>Cognitive performance</italic>: ↑ Attention, ↑ attention in N90 than N40<break/><italic>Perceptual measures of fatigue and muscle soreness, sleepiness and alertness</italic>: ↑ (SSS) Sleepiness, ↑ (SSS) Sleepiness in N90 compared to N40<break/><italic>Psychological state</italic>: ↑ POMS, ↑ tension, depression, fatigue, total mood score, ↔ confusion, ↑ perceived recovery, ↑ perceived recovery in N90 than N40</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brotherton et al 2019<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sleep restriction</italic>: Control 3 h for two nights<break/><italic>Nap opportunity</italic>: N60 ended 3 h before performance<break/><italic>Performance measures</italic>: Force velocity platform</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Physical performance</italic>: Control vs Nap: ↔ Grip strength, ↔ Bench press average power, ↑ Bench press average force, ↑ Bench Press peak velocity, ↔ Time-to-peak velocity, ↔ Leg press average power, ↔ Leg press average force, ↔ Leg press peak velocity, ↔ Leg press distance<break/>3 h vs 3 h ± N60: ↑ Grip strength, ↑ Bench press average power, ↑ Bench press average force, ↑ Bench press peak velocity, ↑ Time-to-peak velocity, ↑ Leg Press, ↑ Leg Press average power, ↔ Leg press average force, ↔ Leg press peak velocity, ↑ Leg press distance<break/><italic>Perceptual measures of fatigue and muscle soreness, sleepiness and alertness</italic>: ↑ (SSS) Sleepiness, ↑ (VAS) Alertness<break/><italic>Psychological state</italic>: Sleep Restricted vs Sleep Restricted with Nap: ↑ POMS, vigour, anger, calm, happiness, confusion, depression, fatigue, ↑ Tiredness, ↔ tension<break/>Normal Sleep vs Sleep Restricted with Nap:: ↑ POMS, vigour, calm, happiness, confusion, depression, fatigue, ↑ Tiredness, ↔ anger, tension, ↑ Tiredness</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daaloul et al 2019<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sleep restriction</italic>: Control vs 4 h sleep vs 4 h sleep with nap<break/><italic>Nap opportunity</italic>: No nap vs N30<break/><italic>Performance measures</italic>: Optojump optical jump system</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Physical performance</italic>: Control vs 4 h sleep ± N30: ↔ Karate-specific test, ↔ Squat jump, ↔ CMJ, ↑ Time to exhaustion<break/>4 h sleep vs 4 h sleep ± N30: ↑ Karate-specific test, ↑ Squat jump, ↑ CMJ, ↑ Time to exhaustion, ↑ Fatigue<break/><italic>Cognitive performance</italic>: ↑ Reaction time, ↑ Mental rotation, ↑ Lower body reaction<break/><italic>Perceptual measures of fatigue and muscle soreness, sleepiness and alertness</italic>: ↑ (VAS) Alertness</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Davies et al 2010<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sleep restriction</italic>: No<break/><italic>Nap opportunity</italic>: N90 60 min after endurance training vs N90 120 min after endurance training<break/><italic>Performance measures</italic>: Rowing ergometer, Motorized treadmill</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Physical performance</italic>: ↑ Readiness to perform for exercise 2 h post compared to 1 h post<break/><italic>Perceptual measures of fatigue and muscle soreness, sleepiness and alertness</italic>: ↔ (VAS) Alertness</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Driller et al 2016<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sleep restriction</italic>: No<break/><italic>Nap opportunity</italic>: 45 min in floatation device</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Physical performance</italic>: ↔ Muscle soreness<break/><italic>Psychological state</italic>: Multidimensional mood-state questionnaire = ↑ Worn-out, ↑ At-ease, ↑ Tense, ↑ Fresh, ↑ Exhausted</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hammouda et al 2018<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sleep restriction</italic>: 4.5 h sleep<break/><italic>Nap opportunity</italic>: No nap vs N20 vs N90<break/><italic>Performance measures</italic>: Running-based anaerobic sprint test (RAST)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Physical performance</italic>: Both Napping Conditions: ↑ RAST, ↑ Maximum power, ↑ Minimum power, ↑ Mean power, ↑ Fatigue, ↑ N90 than N20</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Knechtle et al 2012<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sleep restriction</italic>: Ultramarathon<break/><italic>Nap opportunity</italic>: Nap vs no nap<break/><italic>Performance measures</italic>: Race finish time</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Physical performance</italic>: Nap ↓ race finish time</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">O’Donnell et al 2018<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sleep restriction</italic>: No<break/><italic>Nap opportunity</italic>: Short nap (&lt;20 min) vs Long nap (&gt;20 min)<break/><italic>Performance measures</italic>: Linear transducer device</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Physical performance</italic>: Short nap ↑ CMJ, ↑ Coach performance, ↔ Subjective energy, ↔ Subjective player performance, ↔ Jump height</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pelka et al 2017<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sleep restriction</italic>: No<break/><italic>Nap opportunity</italic>: N20 vs Systematic breathing<break/><italic>Performance measures</italic>: Non-motorized treadmill, Contact platform</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Physical performance</italic>: ↔ Sprint, ↔ CMJ<break/><italic>Psychological state</italic>: ↔ Subjective rating</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pelka et al 2017<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sleep restriction</italic>: No<break/><italic>Nap opportunity</italic>: N20 vs Yoga vs Systematic breathing<break/><italic>Performance measures</italic>: Non-motorized treadmill</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Physical performance</italic>: ↑ Speed, ↔ Maximum power output<break/><italic>Psychological state</italic>: ↔ Subjective recovery and stress</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Petit et al 2014<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sleep restriction</italic>: Control 9 h TIB 5 h phase advance<break/><italic>Nap opportunity</italic>: N20<break/><italic>Performance measures</italic>: Cycle</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Physical performance</italic>: ↔ Wingate, ↔ Peak Power<break/><italic>Night-time sleep</italic>: Control condition and 5 h phase advance: ↓ Sleep onset latency, ↔ other sleep variables (eg, TST, SE, sleep stages)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Petit et al 2018<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sleep restriction</italic>: Control 9 h TIB 5 h phase advance<break/><italic>Nap opportunity</italic>: N21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cognitive performance</italic>: Control condition: ↑ Vigilance, ↑ Attentional performance<break/>5 h phase advance ± nap: ↑ Vigilance, ↑ Attentional performance<break/><italic>Perceptual measures of fatigue and muscle soreness, sleepiness and alertness</italic>: Control condition: ↑ (VAS) Alertness<break/>5 h phase advance: ↔ (VAS) Alertness</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poussel et al 2015<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sleep restriction</italic>: Ultramarathon<break/><italic>Nap opportunity</italic>: Nap vs no nap<break/><italic>Performance measures</italic>: Race finish time</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Physical performance</italic>: Napping = ↓ race finish time</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Romdhani et al 2020<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sleep restriction</italic>: 4.5 h sleep<break/><italic>Nap opportunity</italic>: No nap vs N20 vs N90<break/><italic>Performance measures</italic>: Running-based anaerobic sprint test (RAST)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Physical performance</italic>: N20 condition: RAST ↑ Maximum power, ↔ Minimum power, ↔ Mean power, ↑ Fatigue<break/>N90 condition: ↑ Maximum power, ↑ Minimum power, ↑ Mean power, ↑ Fatigue, ↑ RPE<break/>Overall ↑ N90 than N20<break/><italic>Cognitive performance</italic>: ↑ N20 Reaction time<break/><italic>Perceptual measures of fatigue and muscle soreness, sleepiness and alertness</italic>: ↑ (ESS) Sleepiness<break/><italic>Psychological state</italic>: ↑ Wellness, ↑ POMS<break/>N90 vs N20: ↑ Wellness, ↑ POMS</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Romyn et al 2018<xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sleep restriction</italic>: 9 h vs 8 h + 1 h nap vs 7 h + 2 h nap<break/><italic>Nap opportunity</italic>: N60 vs N120<break/><italic>Performance measures</italic>: Race finish time</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Night-time sleep</italic>: ↔ Sleep</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suppiah et al 2019<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sleep restriction</italic>: No<break/><italic>Performance measures</italic>: Timing gates</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Physical performance</italic>: ↔ Shooting performance, ↓ Sprint performance<break/><italic>Perceptual measures of fatigue and muscle soreness, sleepiness and alertness</italic>: In shooting athletes = ↑ Sleepiness (in shooting athletes), ↓ Alertness: In track and field athletes = ↔ Sleepiness, ↔ Alertness</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thornton et al 2017<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sleep restriction</italic>: No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Night-time sleep</italic>: ↑ Sleep, ↑ TIB, ↑ SE</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> ↑, positive effect of napping; ↓, negative effect of napping; ↔, no effect of napping; 5MSRT, 5 Metre Shuttle Run Test; BRUMS, Brunel Mood State Questionnaire; CMJ, counter movement jump; ESS, Epworth Sleepiness Scale; N before any number indicates mins of nap (eg, N20 = 20 min nap); POMS, Profile of Mood State Questionnaire; RAST, Running-based Anaerobic Sprint Test; RPE, rating of perceived exertion; SE, sleep efficacy; SSS, Stanford Sleepiness Scale; TIB, time in bed; TST, total sleep time; VAS, Visual Analogue Scale.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Study Quality</title>
        <p>Overall, the risk of bias score ranged from 43.8% to 92.9%, with 2.7% (n = 1)<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> considered high quality, 91.9% (n = 34)<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24–27</xref>,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29–47</xref>,<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51–57</xref> considered moderate quality, and 5.4% (n = 2)<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref> considered low quality. The overall risk of bias for each study is presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2A</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">C</xref>) and results for each item of the Downs and Black Checklist are provided in <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=315556.docx">Supplementary material</ext-link></underline>.<fig id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The overall risk of bias for each study (<bold>A</bold>) cross-sectional design (<bold>B</bold>) longitudinal design and (<bold>C</bold>) experimental design.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-841-g0002"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Measuring Naps</title>
        <p>Overall, four main types of sleep assessments (eg, questionnaires, sleep diaries, actigraphy, and polysomnography) were used in the included studies. The most common form of sleep assessment was subjective, with ten (27%) studies employing self-report questionnaires<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26–30</xref>,<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> and seven (18.9%) studies employing self-report sleep diaries.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref> Thirteen (35.1%) studies utilized wrist actigraphy as an objective form of sleep assessment,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40–44</xref>,<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> whereas six studies (16.2%) used polysomnography, the gold standard in sleep assessment.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,<xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref> One study (2.7%) did not report any form of sleep assessment, however, sleep duration was controlled in a laboratory environment.<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2005">
        <title>Napping Characteristics</title>
        <p>In total, 16 (43.2%) studies reported napping characteristics of either frequency, duration and/or timing of naps taken by athletes.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24–26</xref>,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34–41</xref> There was no consistency across studies for napping frequency (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Ten (27%) studies reported the percentage of athletes who napped at least once throughout the data collection period.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref> For example, Walsh et al<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> showed that 33% of the participants (national and international level swimmers) reported napping at least once during a rest period, 75% napped during a taper period, 92% napped during a training period, and 75% napped during the competition period. Five (13.5%) studies reported the total amount of naps taken during the data collection period.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> For example, Caia et al<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> reported a total of 16 naps were taken during 14 days of data collection with 8 naps taken during a 7-day pre-season period and 8 naps taken during a 7-day competition period in professional Rugby League players. Overall, the percentage of participants that napped across studies ranged between 11% and 100% (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p>
        <p>The nap durations across all studies inclusive of training, rest, and competition phases ranged from 6 to 120 min. Nap durations were similar between training (43±28 min) and competition (44±24 min) days. However, nap durations were considerably shorter on rest days (6±10 min).<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></p>
        <p>Only three (8.1%) studies reported nap timing,<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref> however reporting was inconsistent. For instance, Fullagar et al<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> reported the exact nap start and end times (see <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), whereas Kolling et al<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> reported the percentage of naps taken before 12:00, between 12:00 and 15:00 and between 15:00 and 18:00. Specifically, soccer players in the Fullagar et al<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> study initiated naps at 14:44±01:03 and ended naps at 16:12±00:59. Rugby League players in the Thornton et al<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> study were allocated specific times within the training schedule for napping such that naps were taken in the early morning (number of naps &lt;12:00 = 71; start 07:05±00:35, end 07:52±00:18) or afternoon (number of naps &lt;12:00 = 85; start 12:46±00:40, end 13:40±00:47).</p>
        <p>In summary, the percentage of participants that napped across studies ranged between 11% and 100%, with highest percentage of naps reported during training compared to rest days. While there was a large variability in the duration of naps (6–120 min), nap durations on training and competition days were similar (43–44 min). Studies reporting data on the timing of naps were scarce with minimal consistency.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2006">
        <title>Impact of Napping</title>
        <p>In total, 17 (45.9%) studies examined at least one element of performance (eg, physical, cognitive), perceptual measures of fatigue or muscle soreness, perceived exertion and/or psychological state (eg, mood, stress). The following results section is divided into a) physical performance, b) cognitive performance, c) perceptual measures of fatigue, muscle soreness, sleepiness and alertness; d) psychological state; and e) night-time sleep.</p>
        <sec id="s0003-s2006-s3001">
          <title>Physical Performance</title>
          <p>The impact of napping behavior on physical performance was assessed using various sport-specific measurement tests (see <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Nine (24.7%) studies found positive effects of napping on measures of physical performance,<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42–46</xref>,<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref> five (13.5%) studies revealed no impact of napping<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref> and only two (5.4%) studies revealed napping had a negative impact on performance.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref> In the nine studies reporting positive effects of napping on measures of physical performance, participants were either a) well-rested or b) sleep restricted.</p>
          <p>In well-rested athletes from both individual and team sports, Pelka et al<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> examined the impact of napping (20 min nap) on maximum power using counter-movement jumps (ie, using a force platform) and maximum speed (ie, non-motorized treadmill) using two 6×4 second sprint sessions with 20 seconds breaks. While Pelka et al<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> observed no differences in physical performance (speed or maximal power) between the napping and the control condition, improvements in average maximum speed, but not maximum power output were noted. In well-rested elite netballers, O’Donnell et al<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref> observed improvements in peak jump velocity (via counter-movement jumps) following short naps (&lt;20 min) compared to longer naps (&gt;20 min) and the no nap condition. The authors found that the mean jump velocity was increased following longer naps compared to the no nap condition. However, no differences were observed between conditions for jump height. Further, Boukhris et al<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> conducted a comprehensive study examining three different napping conditions (no nap, 40 min nap, 90 min nap) in amateur team sport athletes (soccer, rugby, handball). The findings revealed that maximal voluntary isometric contraction and total distance improved following both the 40 min and 90 min napping conditions compared to no nap. When exploring the differences between nap duration, the 90 min nap condition had greater benefits for maximal voluntary isometric contraction and total distance compared to the 40 min nap condition.</p>
          <p>In sleep restricted athletes (range: 3.0–4.5 h), findings revealed consistent positive effects of napping on physical performance.<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> Ajjimaporn et al<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> and Brotherton et al<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> both restricted sleep to 3 h of sleep per night in amateur soccer players and weightlifters, respectively. Ajjimaporn et al<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> observed improvements in maximum isometric leg strength (via leg dynamometry) and mean power output following a 20 min nap. Although maximal power improved following a nap, this finding did not reach statistical significance.<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> Brotherton et al<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> examined weightlifting performance using grip strength, bench and leg press between three conditions (control 7.5 h sleep, 3.0 h sleep, 3.0 h sleep plus 60 min nap). Comparisons between the control condition and the 3 h sleep restriction accompanied with a 60-min nap revealed no differences between the control and napping condition. However, the comparisons between 3 h sleep restriction and 3 h sleep restriction plus the 60 min nap condition revealed significant benefits for weightlifting performance, with grip strength, bench press (ie, power, peak velocity, force) and leg press (ie, power, distance) all higher following the 60 min nap compared to the no nap condition. Daaloul et al<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> examined the impact of a 30 min nap after 4 h of sleep compared to 7 h of sleep on squat jumps, counter-movement jumps and a karate-specific test. While there was no initial impact of napping on squat jump and counter-movement jumps, following the fatigue induced by the karate-specific tests, the 30 min nap improved squat jump, countermovement jump performance and time to exhaustion compared to the no nap conditions. Further, Hammouda et al<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> and Romdhani et al<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> used the same napping conditions (no nap, 20 min nap, 90 min nap) following 4.5 h of sleep restriction to examine anaerobic capacity and power using the running anaerobic sprint test.<xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref> Both studies reported significant improvements in power output and fatigue indices. It was also observed that the 90 min nap had greater effects on performance compared to the 20 min nap (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Blanchfield et al<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> examined runners’ time to exhaustion with and without a 90 min afternoon nap. While runners improved their time to exhaustion, previous night-time sleep duration predicted change in time to exhaustion such that naps had a greater influence on runners’ time to exhaustion when they slept less than 7 h the previous night.</p>
          <p>Four (10.8%) studies reported napping during an ultramarathon.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> While Martin et al<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> explored the sleep habits of ultramarathon runners during training, the authors did not examine the impact of napping during an ultramarathon (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). In addition, Hurdiel et al<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> reported that 70% of runners reported napping during the ultramarathon obtaining an average of 23±22 min of sleep. The authors found that the race finish time was positively related to the amount of sleep obtained during the ultramarathon. In contrast, Knechtle et al<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> and Poussel et al<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> observed that runners that napped during an ultramarathon finished the race significantly slower than those who did not nap. Knechtle et al<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> found that a total of 57% runners napped during the ultramarathon with nap durations ranging from 30 to 175 min, while Poussel et al<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> revealed that 28% took at least one nap with the majority of participants napping between 15 and 30 min.</p>
          <p>Only two (5.4%) studies reported that napping negatively affected physical performance.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref> While Suppiah et al<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref> demonstrated that 20 m sprint times were slower following a nap compared to no nap, other measures of performance in this study (other sprint distance times and shooting performance) were not different between the nap and no nap condition. Further, the study by Knechtle et al<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> was conducted during a continuous ultra-cycling race (~24 hours in duration) which examined the finish time and found that stopping to nap during the race logically delays the finish time of competitors who napped.</p>
          <p>In summary, the physical performance benefits of napping are greater in sleep restricted athletes compared to well-rested athletes. While shorter naps (~20 min) show physical performance benefits, longer naps (~90 min) were likely to yield more benefits to physical performance.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2006-s3002">
          <title>Cognitive Performance</title>
          <p>Five (13.5%) studies examined the impact of cognitive performance following napping. Four of the five studies demonstrated a positive influence of napping on cognitive performance.<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> Boukhris et al<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> examined three conditions (no nap, 40 min nap, 90 min nap) without sleep restriction. While the authors observed that both nap conditions improved attention using the digit cancellation test,<xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref> the 90 min nap condition resulted in greater improvements in attention compared to the 40 min nap condition.</p>
          <p>Daaloul et al<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> and Romdhani et al<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> examined cognitive performance under sleep restricted conditions of 4.0 h and 4.5 h of sleep, respectively. Daaloul et al<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> observed improvements in both simple visual reaction time and lower leg reaction time tasks as well as a mental rotation task following a 30 min nap in karate athletes. However, Romdhani et al<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> observed improvements in simple reaction time and multiple-choice reaction times following the 20 min nap condition only and not the 90 min nap condition. In comparison to the aforementioned studies, Ajjimaporn et al<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> examined reaction time using an auditory reaction time task to examine the impact of a 20 min nap following 3 h of sleep restriction. The authors observed no differences between the control, sleep restricted and napping conditions.<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> Finally, Petit et al<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref> examined the impact on vigilance and attention following a 21 min nap in a 9 h time in bed condition versus a 5 h phase advance condition to simulate jet lag. Regardless of the condition, the 21 min nap improved vigilance and attention performance (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p>
          <p>In summary, napping improves cognitive performance in the form of visual reaction time, attention and mental rotation tasks. However, no differences were found when reaction time was examined using an auditory reaction time task.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2006-s3003">
          <title>Perceptual Measures of Fatigue and Muscle Soreness, Sleepiness and Alertness</title>
          <p>The positive impact of napping on perceived exertion, subjective fatigue and/or vigour was evident in four of the five studies examining the effects of napping on various perceptual measures.<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42–44</xref>,<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> O’Donnell et al<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref> demonstrated energy levels remained unchanged in netballers who napped versus those who did not nap. However, it is important to note that O’Donnell et al<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref> employed a 5-point Likert scale which may have minimized the variability in responses.<xref rid="cit0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref> Consistent with the notion of sleep inertia and readiness to perform, Davies et al<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> observed that athletes reported greater readiness to perform 2 h post nap versus 1 h post-nap. However, there was no comparison between athletes’ preparedness or readiness to perform compared to a no nap condition.</p>
          <p>Two (5.4%) studies examined muscle soreness following napping.<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> Driller and Argus<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> examined the impact of floating in an enclosed, warm, saline-dense water tank for 45 min as a form of recovery in 60 international level athletes. While a single 45 min floatation session improved perceived muscle soreness, 27 athletes who napped during the floatation session did not report any differences in their perceived recovery (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). It is possible that in this study, laying in an enclosed, warm, saline-dense water tank had benefits on muscle soreness itself independent of napping. Boukhris et al<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> conducted a comprehensive study examining three different napping conditions (no nap, 40 min nap, 90 min nap). The findings related to recovery revealed that napping had a favourable effect on delayed onset muscle soreness<xref rid="cit0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref> and perceived recovery status.<xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref> Further, Boukhris et al<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> revealed that the longer nap (90 min) resulted in decreased delayed onset muscle soreness and increased perceived recovery, indicating that longer naps may have a greater impact on recovery than shorter naps (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p>
          <p>Four (10.8%) studies examined the impact of napping on perceived exertion<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,<xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref> using the original Borg scale<xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref> or the validated French version<xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref> of the Borg scale. All studies revealed napping had a positive impact on perceived exertion such that athletes’ rating of perceived exertion was lower following a nap, particularly under sleep restricted conditions.<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,<xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref></p>
          <p>In summary, evidence supports the role of napping in improving perceptual measures of fatigue and muscle soreness, however not perceived energy levels. Naps have the potential to improve athletes’ rating of perceived exertion.</p>
          <p>Seven (18.9%) studies employed a measure of sleepiness and/or alertness (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The three main scales employed to assess sleepiness were the Epworth Sleepiness Scale (n = 1),<xref rid="cit0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref> the Karolinska Sleepiness Scale (n = 1)<xref rid="cit0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref> and the Stanford Sleepiness Scale (n = 2).<xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref> In addition, three studies examined alertness using a 100-mm visual analogue scale.<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45–47</xref> All four studies examining sleepiness demonstrated that napping (nap duration range: 20–90 min) improved sleepiness (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43–45</xref>,<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> Although Blanchfield et al<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> reported sleep inertia with an initial increase in sleepiness immediately following a 20 min nap, runners’ sleepiness scores returned to baseline levels after 90 min.</p>
          <p>Similar to sleepiness, two out of three studies reported improved alertness following naps (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> There was variability in the timing of administration of alertness scales with Daaloul et al<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> and Davies et al<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> administering the scales either immediately or within 15 min upon wakening, whereas Brotherton et al<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> administered the scales 3 h post-nap. Interestingly, out of the three studies examining alertness, Davies et al<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> was the only study that did not deprive prior sleep such that participants were not in a sleep-deprived state before napping and subsequently no differences in alertness between the nap and no nap condition were observed.</p>
          <p>In summary, napping was found to improve sleepiness and alertness. There was some evidence to indicate sleep inertia; however, this dissipated 90 min post-nap. In circumstances where athletes were well rested, there were no differences for alertness between nap and no nap conditions.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2006-s3004">
          <title>Psychological State</title>
          <p>Eight (20.6%) studies examined the psychological impact of napping (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). In these studies, participants were either a) well-rested or b) sleep restricted. In well-rested athletes, Boukhris et al<xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref> revealed that tension, depression, vigour, fatigue and total mood disturbance scores, assessed via the French version of the Profile of Mood State questionnaire,<xref rid="cit0072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref> improved following both a 40 min and 90 min nap compared to no nap. However, no differences were observed for confusion. Likewise, Driller and Argus<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> revealed positive changes in 5 mood-state variables (ie, worn-out, at-ease, tense, fresh, and exhausted), assessed via the multidimensional mood-state questionnaire,<xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref> following a 45 min nap opportunity (mean nap duration: 26±13 min). In contrast, three studies found no differences between napping and no napping conditions on measures of psychological state (eg, Brunel Mood State questionnaire, Profile of Mood State questionnaire and the Short Recovery and Stress Scale) in well-rested athletes.<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></p>
          <p>Perhaps unsurprisingly, in circumstances where athletes were sleep restricted, napping had a consistent positive impact on mood.<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> In studies where sleep was restricted (3.0–4.5 h per night),<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> napping significantly improved mood as assessed by the Profile of Mood States questionnaire.<xref rid="cit0073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref> Further, Romdhani et al<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> showed that longer naps (90 min vs 20 min nap) resulted in greater positive effects on mood. These data are consistent with data in non-athletic populations indicating that in sleep-deprived individuals, napping showed positive effects on mood.<xref rid="cit0074" ref-type="bibr">74–76</xref></p>
          <p>In summary, data consistently show that napping results in improved mood states. The improvements in mood following napping were more pronounced following both sleep restriction and longer naps.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2006-s3005">
          <title>Night-Time Sleep</title>
          <p>Two (5.4%) studies reported the impact of daytime naps on night-time sleep.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref> Thornton et al<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> reported that rugby league athletes in their study were encouraged to nap between 15 and 45 min to avoid any disruptions to their night-time sleep, with nap durations ranging from 30 to 32 min. Athletes that napped during the day went to bed earlier, increased their night-time sleep duration by 30 min and improved their sleep efficiency by 1% compared to those who did not nap. In contrast, Petit et al<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref> examined the effects of a 20 min nap scheduled following a normal sleep condition and a 5 h phase advance condition. The main findings indicated that a 20 min nap between 13:00 and 14:00 h (normal condition) and between 08:00–09:00 h (5 h phase advance condition) increased sleep onset latency but did not alter any other sleep variables, including sleep staging. In the normal sleep condition, sleep onset latency increased from 13±6 min to 24±12 min. In the 5 h phase advance condition, sleep onset latency increased from 7±4 to 12±13 min. It is important to acknowledge that these recommendations apply to those athletes with regular circadian timing and may not be appropriate for those with extreme chronotypes.</p>
          <p>In summary, there are inconsistent findings regarding the effects of daytime naps on night-time sleep onset latency. Daytime nap durations of up to 45 min may increase the time taken to fall asleep at night in athletes.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>This systematic review is the first to explore a) how studies evaluated napping behavior in athletes (frequency, duration, timing and measurement) and b) how napping impacted physical performance, cognitive performance, perceptual measures (eg, fatigue, muscle soreness, sleepiness and fatigue), psychological state and night-time sleep in athletes. This information is important for athletes and practitioners who provide advice and education to athletes regarding napping.</p>
      <sec id="s0004-s2001">
        <title>Why and When Athletes Nap?</title>
        <p>Sleep is essential for optimising recovery and athletic performance.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref> It is well established that athletes’ sleep and wake behaviors are dictated by rest days as well as training and competition schedules such that early morning training, multiple training sessions per day<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> and night-time competition.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Sleep disturbances in response to sport-specific conditions show high inter- and intra-individual variability and athletes may experience insomnia symptoms associated with greater sleep fragmentation indices, longer sleep latencies and excessive daytime sleepiness. In this context, daytime napping represents a common compensatory strategy used by athletes to increase sleep duration over a 24 hour period and potentially counteract daytime sleepiness associated with sleep restriction.<xref rid="cit0078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref> Rest days in athletes may present athletes with opportunities to extend their main night-time sleep duration such that they are less likely to nap on rest days.<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></p>
        <p>This review showed evidence of athletes engaging in two main types of naps a) the prophylactic nap: a nap taken in anticipation of sleep loss<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> and b) the replacement nap: a nap taken in response to sleep loss.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> No studies specifically identified athletes as engaging in the appetitive nap. Although there is no evidence that athletes take naps for convenience or enjoyment, Gupta et al<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> applied Harrison and Horne’s<xref rid="cit0079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref> idea of “sleepability” such that athletes may have a greater ability to nap on demand without prior sleep debt. Gupta et al<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> utilized polysomnography to assess sleep latency associated with a 20 min nap opportunity taken at 15:00 h and observed that high-performance athletes showed significantly shorter daytime sleep latencies than non-athletes controls. Further, this difference was maintained even when data were adjusted for pre-trial sleepiness scores and total sleep time. These results suggest that napping may actually reflect the athletes’ “sleepability”, and that the opportunity to take a nap is not necessarily associated with sleep restriction and daytime sleepiness. Field-based studies in athletes’ habitual environment are needed to provide further insight into napping behaviors.</p>
        <p>The recuperative value of a nap is dependent on when the nap is taken in regard to the 24 hour circadian rhythm.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> For example, the maximum period of daytime circadian sleepiness occurs in the mid-afternoon (13:00–16:00 h) and is often referred to as the post-lunch dip.<xref rid="cit0080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref> Experimental studies conducted in non-athlete populations have indicated that naps taken during this time have a greater recuperative value than naps taken at other times of the day.<xref rid="cit0081" ref-type="bibr">81–83</xref> Despite the established recuperative benefits of napping between 13:00 and 16:00 h, only three studies recorded the timing of naps taken by athletes.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref> Interestingly, these studies generally reported athletes napped between 13:00 and 16:00 h and, similarly, Thornton et al<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> observed that only 7% of naps were taken after 15:00. As noted by Sargent et al<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> and Lastella et al<xref rid="cit0084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref> where sleep and wake behaviors were dictated by the timing of training and competition schedules, it is possible that naps were taken between 13:00 and 16:00 h as a result of the opportunity provided between daily training/competition schedules.</p>
        <p>Importantly, no study has investigated the association between athletes’ chronotype (the expression of circadian rhythmicity in an individual) and the timing of napping. Chronotype may largely influence sleep behavior, training schedules and the physical or cognitive performance in athletes, with evening-types having delayed sleep onset and offset times and showing peak times for performance later in the day than morning-types.<xref rid="cit0085" ref-type="bibr">85–87</xref> Therefore, the impact of chronotype on napping behavior in athletes warrants further investigation. Regardless of the reasoning for the timing of naps recorded in this review, the optimal time to nap was identified as the maximum period of circadian sleepiness occurring in the mid-afternoon (13:00–16:00 h).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2002">
        <title>The Impact of Napping</title>
        <p>Overall, the percentage of participants that napped across studies ranged between 11% and 100%.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> In the current review, naps not only consistently reduced sleepiness and increased alertness,<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44–47</xref>,<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> but also produced favourable outcomes on physical and cognitive performance as well perceptual and measures of psychological state (eg, mood) (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). While the evidence to support the benefits of napping in well-rested athletes was clear,<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> the physical, cognitive and mood state benefits of napping were greater in sleep restricted athletes.</p>
        <p>Cognitive performance is particularly sensitive to sleep restriction such that cognitive functions are the first level of functioning to become compromised.<xref rid="cit0088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>,<xref rid="cit0089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref> Upon investigating the studies that examined cognitive performance following napping, it was evident that regardless of participants prior sleep debt, all studies demonstrated a positive influence of napping on cognitive performance.<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> The duration of naps in studies that investigated cognitive performance outcomes ranged from 20 to 90 min, and several domains of cognition were explored (eg, reaction time, mental rotation, psychomotor vigilance, and attention tasks). Of interest the length of the nap likely influences the strength of cognitive performance improvements. For example, Boukhris et al<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> observed greater cognitive effects on a digit-cancellation task designed to examine attention with a longer nap (90 min) compared to a shorter nap (20 min).</p>
        <p>Overall, napping between 20 and 90 min improved sleepiness as observed in four studies.<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43–45</xref>,<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> Blanchfield et al<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> did demonstrate initial signs of sleep inertia with a slight increase in sleepiness immediately following a 20 min nap; however, sleepiness returned to baseline levels after 90 min. Similar findings were observed for alertness with two of the three studies demonstrating positive effects for alertness following naps which was thought to be related to the dissipation of sleep homeostatic pressure.<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> In non-athletes, studies have shown that short naps provide a wide range of benefits from increasing alertness to improving cognitive outcomes.<xref rid="cit0076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>,<xref rid="cit0090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref> Conversely, Davies et al<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> did not observe any difference in alertness following a 90 min daytime nap and a potential explanation for this result was that they did not deprive sleep in runners a priori.</p>
        <p>Regardless of whether athletes were well rested<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref> or sleep restricted,<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> napping had a consistent positive impact on measures of psychological state. However, in circumstances where athletes were sleep restricted, napping had a marked positive impact on psychological state.<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> For example, in studies where sleep was restricted (3.0–4.5 h per night), napping significantly improved mood.<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> Further, Romdhani et al<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> showed that longer naps (90 min vs 20 min nap) had greater psychological benefits to mood. These data are consistent with the data on non-athlete populations indicating that napping showed promising effects on psychological state in sleep-deprived individuals.<xref rid="cit0090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref></p>
        <p>Based on the findings of the present review, there is minimal evidence to indicate that napping is detrimental for athlete’s physical performance. While two studies revealed napping had a negative impact on measures of physical performance,<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref> it is important to acknowledge that Knechtle et al<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> examined race finish times during a ~24 hour ultramarathon such that participants napped during the race itself. Suppiah et al<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref> on the other hand, examined the influence of napping in youth athletes sprint performance under well-rested conditions (ie, 7.8 h time in bed). While there was a decline in the fastest 20 m sprint time between nap and no nap conditions, no differences were observed for any other reaction time or sprint performance measures.<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref> Although Suppiah et al<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref> discuss sleep inertia as a plausible explanation for the decline in sprint times, athletes in this study were woken up immediately prior to the onset of Stage 3 sleep (ie, slow wave sleep) to minimize the effects of sleep inertia. Given this was the only negative finding related to physical performance within the study as well as across all studies examined within this review, it is reasonable to conclude that napping does not have a negative impact on physical performance.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2003">
        <title>Considerations When Implementing Napping for Athletes</title>
        <sec id="s0004-s2003-s3001">
          <title>Sleep Inertia</title>
          <p>Sleep inertia is a transitional state of impaired cognitive performance and reduced alertness upon waking.<xref rid="cit0091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref> Often colloquially described as a feeling of “grogginess”, the level of sleep inertia impairment is greatest upon waking and usually takes 15–30 min to fully dissipate. However, some studies in non-athletes have observed performance impairments for up to 2 h post-wake.<xref rid="cit0092" ref-type="bibr">92</xref> Data derived from non-athlete populations indicate that the duration and/or severity of sleep inertia following a nap can be influenced by a number of factors, including a) prior sleep loss/sleep debt; b) being woken up from slow wave sleep;<xref rid="cit0093" ref-type="bibr">93</xref> c) the amount or percentage of slow-wave sleep in a nap<xref rid="cit0094" ref-type="bibr">94</xref> and d) time of day.<xref rid="cit0095" ref-type="bibr">95</xref> While many studies in the current review suggest that sleep inertia may explain their findings (eg, reductions in physical performance<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref> and alertness<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> following a nap), no studies to date have specifically investigated the impact of sleep inertia following napping opportunities on measures of performance in athletes.</p>
          <p>Given the known impacts of sleep inertia on measures of performance and alertness in non-athletes, athletes should ensure that there is adequate time (at least 30 min in most cases) for sleep inertia to dissipate following a nap before commencing training or competition. In some cases, it may be possible to accelerate this dissipation by employing known sleep inertia countermeasures, which can be employed proactively (ie, before the nap) or reactively (ie, after a nap). Examples of these countermeasures include caffeine, bright light, sound, temperature and physical activity, and these countermeasures have been reviewed extensively elsewhere.<xref rid="cit0096" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>,<xref rid="cit0097" ref-type="bibr">97</xref> However, it should be noted that none of these strategies can reliably dissipate sleep inertia within the first 15 min upon waking.<xref rid="cit0096" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>,<xref rid="cit0097" ref-type="bibr">97</xref> Further, if the goal of the napping opportunity is to benefit performance and/or recovery, and there is no immediate need to perform within 30 min of waking, then the impact of sleep inertia is negligible.</p>
          <p>A recent study by our team investigated the possibility whether athletes exercising prior to their night-time sleep periods would exhibit greater amounts of slow-wave sleep in their night-time sleep period, which could subsequently impact the severity and/or duration of sleep inertia.<xref rid="cit0098" ref-type="bibr">98</xref> This hypothesis could potentially mean that athletes may be more susceptible to the impacts of sleep inertia given (in most cases) that their level of exercise is greater than the general population.<xref rid="cit0098" ref-type="bibr">98</xref> However, this study concluded that exercise of a moderate-intensity performed 90 min before bed did not negatively impact sleep inertia and there was no relationship between the amount of slow wave sleep in the preceding sleep period and sleep inertia.<xref rid="cit0098" ref-type="bibr">98</xref> Therefore, it seems unlikely that athletes have a greater likelihood of experiencing enhanced duration and/or severity of sleep inertia compared to non-athletes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0004-s2003-s3002">
          <title>Ensuring a Nap Does Not Impact Night-Time Sleep</title>
          <p>Napping has the potential to disrupt night-time sleep. This is dependent on several factors including the duration of the nap, the timing of the nap and prior sleep debt. In general, the longer the nap, the greater the reduction in sleep propensity; thus, if a nap is taken for a longer period later in the day, and the athlete still attempts to sleep at their habitual time of day, the main night-time sleep period, particularly sleep onset latency, may be disrupted. However, only one study by Petit et al<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref> showed that sleep onset latency increased the night following a 20 min nap opportunity. As stated previously, the optimal time to nap is when the maximum period of circadian sleepiness occurs in the mid-afternoon (13:00–16:00 h), this timing should also protect delays in sleep onset latency and any intrusion into the night-time sleep period.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Limitations</title>
      <p>The current systematic review has limitations which should be acknowledged. First, articles were only considered for inclusion if they were published in peer-review journals and written in English, resulting in potential language bias. Second, some studies may have reported napping conditions yet failed to indicate if participants had initiated sleep. For example, Brotherton et al<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> stated that participants were required to sleep/rest in a quiet room for 60 min yet, did not provide any data on the number of participants that initiated sleep. Third, articles on napping behavior of Muslim (fasting) athletes during Ramadan and athletes with a disability (eg, Paralympic athletes) were not included in the review. Finally, there is a lack of data reporting nap quality, specifically examining sleep efficiency and/or fragmentation indices (eg, the amount of movement during naps). This is predominantly a reflection of the rapid growth pertaining to sleep in athletes such that main night-time sleep periods have been at the forefront of sleep in athlete research. It is imperative for future studies to provide data examining the napping behaviors of athletes to ensure that sports practitioners and researchers are able to comprehensively examine both quantity and quality of naps in athletes.</p>
      <p>Although the overall evidence included in this review was of moderate quality with the majority of experimental or longitudinal studies, it was observed that most of the studies: a) did not include detailed information for nap timing and duration, b) had inconsistencies in reporting of nap frequency, c) focused specifically on the night-time sleep period, and d) relied on self-report data (ie, sleep diaries or questionnaires) to explore napping behavior. Future studies should, therefore, include comprehensive recordings of nap duration and quality, and consider using sleep over a 24 hour period (daytime naps and night-time sleep period), specifically using objective methods of sleep assessment (eg, polysomnography and actigraphy).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Research investigating napping behaviors indicates that napping is common practice among athletic populations. While napping presents athletes with the opportunity to supplement their night-time sleep, evidence also indicates that napping may be beneficial for a range of measures (eg, physical performance, cognitive performance and mood) in athletes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3</xref>). Data from the present review suggest that athletes should aim to nap for between 20 and 90 min between 13:00 and 16:00 hours. Finally, athletes should allow 30 min to reduce sleep inertia prior to training or competition to obtain better performance outcomes. Future studies should utilize objective measurement tools to comprehensively evaluate the frequency, duration, timing of naps in athletes and the resulting impact on athletic performance.<fig id="f0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Overview of the evidence examining the impact of napping on various measures of athletic performance.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-841-g0003"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>The authors would like to extend their appreciation to all researchers that have contributed to the growth of the literature examining the sleep and napping behaviors in athletes.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0007" sec-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors report no conflicts of interest or disclosures for this work. This research did not receive funding from any agency.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Faraut</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Andrillon</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vecchierini</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Napping: a public health issue. From epidemiological to laboratory studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>100</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2016.09.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27751677</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Dinges</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>. <chapter-title>Napping patterns and effects in human adults</chapter-title>. In: <string-name><surname>Dinges</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Broughton</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, editors. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep and Alertness: Chronobiological, Behavioral and Medical Aspects of Napping</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Raven Press</publisher-name>; <year>1989</year>:<fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>204</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lovato</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lack</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effects of napping on cognitive functioning</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Prog Brain Res</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>185</volume>:<fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-444-53702-7.00009-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21075238</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Broughton</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dinges</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <chapter-title>Napping: a ubiquitous enigma</chapter-title>. In: <string-name><surname>Dinges</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Broughton</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, editors. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep and Alertness: Chronobiological, Behavioral and Medical Aspects of Napping</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Raven Press</publisher-name>; <year>1989</year>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lastella</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roach</surname>
<given-names>GD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Halson</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep/wake behaviours of elite athletes from individual and team sports</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Sport Sci</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>94</fpage>–<lpage>100</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17461391.2014.932016</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sargent</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lastella</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Halson</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The impact of training schedules on the sleep and fatigue of elite athletes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chronobiol Int</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1160</fpage>–<lpage>1168</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/07420528.2014.957306</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25222347</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lastella</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Memon</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vincent</surname>
<given-names>GE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Global research output on sleep research in athletes from 1966 to 2019: a bibliometric analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clocks Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>119</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/clockssleep2020010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33089195</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gupta</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morgan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>North</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Napping in high-performance athletes: sleepiness or sleepability?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Sport Sci</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17461391.2020.1743765</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Roberts</surname>
<given-names>SSH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Teo</surname>
<given-names>W-P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Warmington</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of training and competition on the sleep of elite athletes: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Br J Sports Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>513</fpage>–<lpage>522</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bjsports-2018-099322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30217831</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vitale</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Banfi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Galbiati</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of a night game on actigraphy-based sleep quality and perceived recovery in top-level volleyball athletes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Sports Physiol Perform</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>265</fpage>–<lpage>269</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/ijspp.2018-0194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30040006</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hirshkowitz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whiton</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Albert</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>National Sleep Foundation’s sleep time duration recommendations: methodology and results summary</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Health</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleh.2014.12.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29073412</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Takahashi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arito</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Maintenance of alertness and performance by a brief nap after lunch under prior sleep deficit</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>813</fpage>–<lpage>819</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/e361732004-005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11007448</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tamaki</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shirota</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hayashi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Restorative effects of a short afternoon nap (&lt; 30 min) in the elderly on subjective mood, performance and EEG activity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Res Online</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>139</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11382911</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tietzel</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lack</surname>
<given-names>LC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The recuperative value of brief and ultra‐brief naps on alertness and cognitive performance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>218</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2869.2002.00299.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12220317</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Halson</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep in elite athletes and nutritional interventions to enhance sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sports Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>Suppl S1</issue>):<fpage>S13</fpage>–<lpage>S123</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40279-014-0147-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24791913</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Moher</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liberati</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tetzlaff</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses: the PRISMA statement</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS Med</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e1000097</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19621072</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Munn</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stern</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aromataris</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>What kind of systematic review should I conduct? A proposed typology and guidance for systematic reviewers in the medical and health sciences</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Med Res Methodol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>5</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12874-017-0468-4</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bergeron</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mountjoy</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Armstrong</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>International Olympic Committee consensus statement on youth athletic development</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Br J Sports Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>843</fpage>–<lpage>851</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bjsports-2015-094962</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26084524</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McKinney</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Velghe</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fee</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Defining athletes and exercisers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>123</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>532</fpage>–<lpage>535</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjcard.2018.11.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30503799</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Swann</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moran</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Piggott</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Defining elite athletes: issues in the study of expert performance in sport psychology</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Sport Exerc</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychsport.2014.07.004</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dinges</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Orne</surname>
<given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whitehouse</surname>
<given-names>WG</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Temporal placement of a nap for alertness: contributions of circadian phase and prior wakefulness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>329</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/10.4.313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3659730</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Downs</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Black</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The feasibility of creating a checklist for the assessment of the methodological quality both of randomised and non-randomised studies of health care interventions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Epidemiol Community Health</italic></source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>384</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jech.52.6.377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9764259</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bonnar</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bartel</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kakoschke</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep interventions designed to improve athletic performance and recovery: a systematic review of current approaches</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sports Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>683</fpage>–<lpage>703</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40279-017-0832-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29352373</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fullagar</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Skorski</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duffield</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The effect of an acute sleep hygiene strategy following a late-night soccer match on recovery of players</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chronobiol Int</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>490</fpage>–<lpage>505</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/07420528.2016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27031035</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fullagar</surname>
<given-names>HH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duffield</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Skorski</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep, travel, and recovery responses of national footballers during and after long-haul international air travel</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Sports Physiol Perform</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>86</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/ijspp.2015-0012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25946072</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fullagar</surname>
<given-names>HH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Skorski</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duffield</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impaired sleep and recovery after night matches in elite football players</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sports Sci</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>1333</fpage>–<lpage>1339</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02640414.2015.1135249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26750446</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Knechtle</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wirth</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knechtle</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>No improvement in race performance by naps in male ultra-endurance cyclists in a 600-km ultra-cycling race</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin J Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>133</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4077/CJP.2012.BAA022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22559737</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Poussel</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laroppe</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hurdiel</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep management strategy and performance in an extreme mountain ultra-marathon</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Res Sports Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>330</fpage>–<lpage>336</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15438627.2015.1040916</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26020095</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Venter</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Potgieter</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barnard</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The use of recovery modalities by elite South African team athletes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">South African J Res Sport, Phy Edu Recreation</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4314/sajrs.v32i1.54106</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arnal</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoffman</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep habits and strategies of ultramarathon runners</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e0194705</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0194705</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29742118</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Caia</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scott</surname>
<given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Halson</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Do players and staff sleep more during the pre- or competitive season of elite rugby league?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Sport Sci</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>964</fpage>–<lpage>972</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17461391.2017.1335348</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28585467</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Carter</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gervais</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adomeit</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Subjective and objective sleep differ in male and female collegiate athletes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>623</fpage>–<lpage>628</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleh.2020.01.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32147360</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hurdiel</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Riedy</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Millet</surname>
<given-names>GP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cognitive performance and self-reported sleepiness are modulated by time-of-day during a mountain ultramarathon</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Res Sports Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>482</fpage>–<lpage>489</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15438627.2018.1492401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29973086</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dawson</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gucciardi</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Evening electronic device use and sleep patterns in athletes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sports Sci</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>864</fpage>–<lpage>870</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02640414.2018.1531499</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30326782</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kölling</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wiewelhove</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raeder</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep monitoring of a six-day microcycle in strength and high-intensity training</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Sport Sci</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>507</fpage>–<lpage>515</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17461391.2015.1041062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26062597</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mah</surname>
<given-names>CD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kezirian</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marcello</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Poor sleep quality and insufficient sleep of a collegiate student-athlete population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Health</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>257</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleh.2018.02.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29776619</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Romyn</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Robey</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dimmock</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep, anxiety and electronic device use by athletes in the training and competition environments</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Sport Sci</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>301</fpage>–<lpage>308</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17461391.2015.1023221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25790844</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sargent</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Halson</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roach</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep or swim? Early-morning training severely restricts the amount of sleep obtained by elite swimmers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Sport Sci</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>Suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>S310</fpage>–<lpage>S315</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17461391.2012.696711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24444223</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stevens</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thornton</surname>
<given-names>HR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fowler</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Long-haul northeast travel disrupts sleep and induces perceived fatigue in endurance athletes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1826</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphys.2018.01826</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30618835</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Thornton</surname>
<given-names>HR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duthie</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pitchford</surname>
<given-names>NW</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of a 2-week high-intensity training camp on sleep activity of professional rugby league athletes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Sports Physiol Perform</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>928</fpage>–<lpage>933</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/ijspp.2016-0414</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27918662</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Walsh</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sanders</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hamilton</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep profiles of elite swimmers during different training phases</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Strength Cond Res</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>811</fpage>–<lpage>818</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1519/jsc.0000000000002866</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30289871</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ajjimaporn</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramyarangsi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Siripornpanich</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of a 20-min nap after sleep deprivation on brain activity and soccer performance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Sports Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>1009</fpage>–<lpage>1016</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/a-1192-6187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32629506</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Blanchfield</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lewis-Jones</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wignall</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The influence of an afternoon nap on the endurance performance of trained runners</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Sport Sci</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1177</fpage>–<lpage>1184</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17461391.2018.1477180</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29851569</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Boukhris</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trabelsi</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ammar</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A 90 min daytime nap opportunity is better than 40 min for cognitive and physical performance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>4650</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph17134650</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Brotherton</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moseley</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Langan-Evans</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of two nights partial sleep deprivation on an evening submaximal weightlifting performance; are 1 h powernaps useful on the day of competition?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Chronobiol Int</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>407</fpage>–<lpage>426</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07420528.2018.1552702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30626222</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Daaloul</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Souissi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davenne</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of napping on alertness, cognitive, and physical outcomes of karate athletes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Med Sci Sports Exerc</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>338</fpage>–<lpage>345</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/MSS.0000000000001786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30239491</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Davies</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Graham</surname>
<given-names>KS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chow</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effect of prior endurance training on nap sleep patterns</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Sports Physiol Perform</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/ijspp.5.1.87</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20308699</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Driller</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Argus</surname>
<given-names>CK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Flotation restricted environmental stimulation therapy and napping on mood state and muscle soreness in elite athletes: a novel recovery strategy?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Perform Enhanc Health</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>60</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.peh.2016.08.002</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hammouda</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Romdhani</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chaabouni</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Diurnal napping after partial sleep deprivation affected hematological and biochemical responses during repeated sprint</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biol Rhythm Res</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>927</fpage>–<lpage>939</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09291016.2018.1429553</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pelka</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferrauti</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meyer</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>How does a short, interrupted recovery break affect performance and how is it assessed? A study on acute effects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Sports Physiol Perform</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>S114</fpage>–<lpage>S1121</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/ijspp.2016-0399</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pelka</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kölling</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferrauti</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Acute effects of psychological relaxation techniques between two physical tasks</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sports Sci</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>216</fpage>–<lpage>223</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02640414.2016.1161208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26999625</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Petit</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bourdin</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tio</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of a 20-min nap post normal and jet lag conditions on P300 components in athletes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Sports Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>508</fpage>–<lpage>516</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/a-0599-0888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29758571</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Petit</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mougin</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bourdin</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A 20-min nap in athletes changes subsequent sleep architecture but does not alter physical performances after normal sleep or 5-h phase-advance conditions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Appl Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>114</volume>:<fpage>305</fpage>–<lpage>315</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00421-013-2776-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24276580</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Romdhani</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Souissi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chaabouni</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Improved physical performance and decreased muscular and oxidative damage with postlunch napping after partial sleep deprivation in athletes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Sports Physiol Perform</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>874</fpage>–<lpage>883</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/ijspp.2019-0308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32023544</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0055">
        <label>55.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Romyn</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lastella</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Daytime naps can be used to supplement night-time sleep in athletes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chronobiol Int</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>865</fpage>–<lpage>868</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07420528.2018.1466795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30024323</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0056">
        <label>56.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Suppiah</surname>
<given-names>HT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Low</surname>
<given-names>CY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Choong</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of a short daytime nap on shooting and sprint performance in high-level adolescent athletes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Sports Physiol Perform</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/ijspp.2018-0107</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0057">
        <label>57.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>O’Donnell</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beaven</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Driller</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The influence of match-day napping in elite female netball athletes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Sports Physiol Perform</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1143</fpage>–<lpage>1148</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/ijspp.2017-0793</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29543074</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0058">
        <label>58.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Thornton</surname>
<given-names>HR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Delaney</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duthie</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of preseason training on the sleep characteristics of professional rugby league players</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Sports Physiol Perform</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>176</fpage>–<lpage>182</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/ijspp.2017-0119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28530487</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0059">
        <label>59.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Steyer</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schwenkmezger</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Notz</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Testtheoretische analysen des mehrdimensionalen befindlichkeitsfragebogens (MDBF) [In German: theoretical analysis of a multidimensional mood questionnaire (MDBF)]</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diagnostica</italic></source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>320</fpage>–<lpage>328</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0060">
        <label>60.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kölling</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duffield</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Erlacher</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep-related issues for recovery and performance in athletes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Sports Physiol Perform</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>144</fpage>–<lpage>148</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/ijspp.2017-0746</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29651858</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0061">
        <label>61.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Draper</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whyte</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Here’s a new running based test of anaerobic performance for which you need only a stopwatch and a calculator</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Peak Performance</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0062">
        <label>62.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hatta</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yoshizaki</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ito</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Reliability and validity of the digit cancellation test, a brief screen of attention</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychologia</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>246</fpage>–<lpage>256</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2117/psysoc.2012.246</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0063">
        <label>63.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baron</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Strengths and limitations of ipsative measurement</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Occup Organ Psychol</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.2044-8325.1996.tb00599.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0064">
        <label>64.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dierking</surname>
<given-names>JK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bemben</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bemben</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Validity of diagnostic ultrasound as a measure of delayed onset muscle soreness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Orthop Sports Phys Ther</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>116</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2519/jospt.2000.30.3.116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10721507</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0065">
        <label>65.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Laurent</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Green</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bishop</surname>
<given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A practical approach to monitoring recovery: development of a perceived recovery status scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Strength Cond Res</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>620</fpage>–<lpage>628</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1519/JSC.0b013e3181c69ec6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20581704</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0066">
        <label>66.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Boukhris</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abdessalem</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ammar</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Nap opportunity during the daytime affects performance and perceived exertion in 5-m shuttle run test</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>779</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphys.2019.00779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31281263</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0067">
        <label>67.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Borg</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Psychophysical scaling with applications in physical work and the perception of exertion</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Scand J Work Environ Health</italic></source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>Suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>S55</fpage>–<lpage>S58</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5271/sjweh.1815</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0068">
        <label>68.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Haddad</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chaouachi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Castagna</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Validity and psychometric evaluation of the French version of RPE scale in young fit males when monitoring training loads</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Sports</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e29</fpage>–<lpage>e35</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scispo.2012.07.008</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0069">
        <label>69.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Johns</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A new method for measuring daytime sleepiness: the Epworth Sleepiness Scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>540</fpage>–<lpage>545</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/14.6.540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1798888</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0070">
        <label>70.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Santhi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Groeger</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Archer</surname>
<given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Morning sleep inertia in alertness and performance: effect of cognitive domain and white light conditions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e79688</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0079688</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24260280</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0071">
        <label>71.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hoddes</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zarcone</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smythe</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Quantification of sleepiness: a new approach</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychophysiology</italic></source>. <year>1973</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>431</fpage>–<lpage>436</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8986.1973.tb00801.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4719486</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0072">
        <label>72.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cayrou</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dickès</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dolbeault</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Version française du profile of mood states (POMS-f) [In French: French version of the Profile Of Mood States (POMS-f)]</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J de Thérapie Comportementale et Cognitive</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0073">
        <label>73.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>McNair</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Droppleman</surname>
<given-names>LF</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Manual for the Profile of Mood States</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>San Diego, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Educational and Industrial Testing Service</publisher-name>; <year>1971</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0074">
        <label>74.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tietzel</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lack</surname>
<given-names>LC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The short-term benefits of brief and long naps following nocturnal sleep restriction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>293</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/24.3.293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11322712</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0075">
        <label>75.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ji</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Midday napping in children: associations between nap frequency and duration across cognitive, positive psychological well-being, behavioral, and metabolic health outcomes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>zsz126</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsz126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31135911</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0076">
        <label>76.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hayashi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Watanabe</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hori</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effects of a 20 min nap in the mid-afternoon on mood, performance and EEG activity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Neurophysiol</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>110</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>272</fpage>–<lpage>279</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s1388-2457(98)00003-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10210616</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0077">
        <label>77.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Halson</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Nutrition, sleep and recovery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Sport Sci</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>119</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17461390801954794</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0078">
        <label>78.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lastella</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roach</surname>
<given-names>GD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Athletes underestimate sleep quantity during daytime nap opportunities</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chronobiol Int</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>869</fpage>–<lpage>871</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07420528.2018.1466787</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29842816</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0079">
        <label>79.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Harrison</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Horne</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>“High sleepability without sleepiness”. The ability to fall asleep rapidly without other signs of sleepiness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurophysiol Clin</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0987-7053(96)81530-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8657094</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0080">
        <label>80.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Folkard</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Åkerstedt</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <chapter-title>A three process model of the regulation of alertness and sleepiness</chapter-title>. In: <string-name><surname>Ogilvie</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Broughton</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, editors. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep, Arousal, and Performance: Problems and Promises</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Boston</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Birkhiiuser</publisher-name>; <year>1991</year>:<fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0081">
        <label>81.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lack</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lushington</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The rhythms of human sleep propensity and core body temperature</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2869.1996.00005.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0082">
        <label>82.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Naitoh</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Angus</surname>
<given-names>RG</given-names></string-name>. <chapter-title>Napping and human functioning during prolonged work</chapter-title>. In: <string-name><surname>Dinges</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Broughton</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, editors. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep and Alertness: Chronobiological, Behavioral and Medical Aspects of Napping</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Raven Press</publisher-name>; <year>1989</year>:<fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>246</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0083">
        <label>83.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Taub</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hawkins</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Van de Castle R. Temporal relationships of napping behavior to performance, mood states and sleep physiology</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>1978</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>164</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0084">
        <label>84.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lastella</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roach</surname>
<given-names>GD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Halson</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep/wake behaviour of endurance cyclists before and during competition</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sports Sci</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>293</fpage>–<lpage>299</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02640414.2014.942690</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25105558</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0085">
        <label>85.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vitale</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weydahl</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Chronotype, physical activity, and sport performance: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sports Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1859</fpage>–<lpage>1868</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40279-017-0741-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28493061</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0086">
        <label>86.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lastella</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roach</surname>
<given-names>GD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Halson</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The chronotype of elite athletes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Hum Kinet</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>225</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/hukin-2016-0049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28031772</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0087">
        <label>87.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vitale</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bonato</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Galasso</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep quality and high intensity interval training at two different times of day: a crossover study on the influence of the chronotype in male collegiate soccer players</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chronobiol Int</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>260</fpage>–<lpage>268</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07420528.2016.1256301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27906554</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0088">
        <label>88.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Belenky</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wesensten</surname>
<given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thorne</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Patterns of performance degradation and restoration during sleep restriction and subsequent recovery: a sleep dose-response study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2869.2003.00337.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12603781</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0089">
        <label>89.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Van Dongen</surname>
<given-names>HPA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maislin</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mullington</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The cumulative cost of additional wakefulness: dose-response effects on neurobehavioral functions and sleep physiology from chronic sleep restriction and total sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/26.2.117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12683469</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0090">
        <label>90.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Milner</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cote</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Benefits of napping in healthy adults: impact of nap length, time of day, age, and experience with napping</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>272</fpage>–<lpage>281</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.2008.00718.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19645971</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0091">
        <label>91.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Trotti</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Waking up is the hardest thing I do all day: sleep inertia and sleep drunkenness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2016.08.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27692973</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0092">
        <label>92.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jewett</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wyatt</surname>
<given-names>JK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ritz-de Cecco</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Time course of sleep inertia dissipation in human performance and alertness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.1999.00128.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0093">
        <label>93.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tassi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bonnefond</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Engasser</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>EEG spectral power and cognitive performance during sleep inertia: the effect of normal sleep duration and partial sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiol Behav</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>87</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>184</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.physbeh.2005.09.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16303153</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0094">
        <label>94.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Matchock</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mordkoff</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of sleep stage and sleep episode length on the alerting, orienting, and conflict components of attention</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Exp Brain Res</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>232</volume>:<fpage>811</fpage>–<lpage>820</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00221-013-3790-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24337231</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0095">
        <label>95.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Groeger</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lo</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burns</surname>
<given-names>CG</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of sleep inertia after daytime naps vary with executive load and time of day</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>125</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>252</fpage>–<lpage>260</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0022692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21463024</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0096">
        <label>96.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kovac</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferguson</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paterson</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Exercising caution upon waking–can exercise reduce sleep inertia?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Front Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>254</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphys.2020.00254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32317980</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0097">
        <label>97.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dawson</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferguson</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vincent</surname>
<given-names>GE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Safety implications of fatigue and sleep inertia for emergency services personnel</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>101386</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2020.101386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33027747</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0098">
        <label>98.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vincent</surname>
<given-names>GE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sargent</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roach</surname>
<given-names>GD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Exercise before bed does not impact sleep inertia in young healthy males</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e12903</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12903</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31621995</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
