<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34466044</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">8397827</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">319917</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S319917</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Sporadic Creutzfeldt–Jakob Disease Appears to Be Sporadic Fatal Insomnia: A Case Report and Review of the Literature</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Sun et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Sun et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>Qingqing</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shen</surname>
            <given-names>Pingping</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tang</surname>
            <given-names>Jiayi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Meng</surname>
            <given-names>Hongmei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Feng</surname>
            <given-names>Jiachun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Zan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cui</surname>
            <given-names>Li</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Neurology and Neuroscience Center, The First Hospital of Jilin University</institution>, <addr-line>Changchun</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Zan Wang; Li Cui Email wangzan@jlu.edu.cn; wangzanprof@163.com; lcui@jlu.edu.cn</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>23</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>13</volume>
      <fpage>1441</fpage>
      <lpage>1448</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>03</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2021 Sun et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Sun et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <p>Creutzfeldt–Jakob disease (CJD) subtypes are difficult to identify due to the heterogeneity of the clinical phenotype, and early accurate identification of sporadic CJD (sCJD) subtypes aids prognosis prediction. Currently, the diagnosis of sCJD subtypes is mainly based on brain tissue biopsy or autopsy. In this report, we present a case of confirmed sCJD initially presenting as insomnia. We described detailed information including clinical, electroencephalographic, polysomnographic, positron emission tomography-computed tomographic and other neuroimaging findings, cerebrospinal fluid biomarkers, skin tissue biopsy and whole blood <italic>PRNP</italic> gene sequencing in this patient. An extensive literature search was performed in order to better understand the diagnosis of various sCJD subtypes, particularly the thalamic form, sCJDMM2 (also known as sporadic fatal insomnia). Our study highlights sporadic fatal insomnia as a differential diagnosis of sCJD.</p>
      </abstract>
      <abstract abstract-type="video">
        <title>Video abstract</title>
        <p>
<fig id="UF0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-1441-g0001"/></fig>
</p>
        <p>Point your SmartPhone at the code above. If you have a QR code reader the video abstract will appear. Or use:</p>
        <p>
<underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://youtu.be/jCqVlf1vqVU">https://youtu.be/jCqVlf1vqVU</ext-link></underline>
</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>sporadic Creutzfeldt–Jakob disease</kwd>
        <kwd>sporadic fatal insomnia</kwd>
        <kwd>sCJDMM</kwd>
        <kwd>polysomnography</kwd>
        <kwd>PET</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="4"/>
        <table-count count="4"/>
        <ref-count count="19"/>
        <page-count count="8"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Prion disease, also known as transmissible spongiform encephalopathy, comprises a group of rare and fatal neurodegenerative diseases caused by misfolded prion proteins (PrP<sup>Sc</sup>). They may present as sporadic, genetic or acquired disorders.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Sporadic Creutzfeldt–Jakob disease (sCJD), the most common type of human prion disease, accounts for 85–90% of prion disease cases.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Based on the genotype of <italic>PRNP</italic> alleles at codon 129, different fragment sizes of PrP<sup>Sc</sup> after proteinase K cleavage (type 1 and 2), the disease phenotypes of sCJD can be divided into five subtypes: sCJDMM(V)1, sCJDMM(V)2C, sCJDVV1, sCJDVV2, sCJDMV2K and sporadic fatal insomnia (sFI, or sCJDMM2T).<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> sFI is considered as the thalamic form of sCJDMM2.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Different phenotypes of sCJD are defined by the polymorphism (Met and Val) at codon 129 of the prion protein gene (<italic>PRNP</italic>) and by the molecular mass of PrP<sup>Sc</sup> (type 1 and 2).<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> sFI is a rare subtype, accounting for 0.9% of sporadic human prion disease cases.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> We herein present a confirmed sCJD case initially presenting as insomnia.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Case Presentation</title>
      <p>A 47-year-old woman who had an unremarkable medical and family history (no previous blood transfusion and surgery) presented with a chief complaint of insomnia. One month after onset, she developed visual and auditory hallucinations, experienced psychotic and worsening hallucinations and agitation at night. A diagnosis of mania was originally considered by a psychiatrist. High blood pressure, excessive sweating, tachycardia, irregular breathing and other symptoms of autonomic hyperactivity were evident. Brain diffusion-weighted imaging (DWI) imaging showed hyperintense lesions in the bilateral basal ganglia and frontal cortical lobes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1A</xref>). Unfortunately, the patient’s symptoms progressively worsened. Repeated brain magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) revealed a wider distribution of abnormal high signals on DWI (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1B</xref>). Electroencephalography (EEG) showed a slow activity background θ-δ with atypical periodic sharp-wave complexes (PSWCs) in the right temporal regions. Specifically, the first phase of typical PSWCs is a negative-phase sharp wave with a low amplitude, the second phase is a positive-phase sharp wave with a high amplitude and wide time frame, and the third phase is a slow wave with a high amplitude than the first phase. In our case, the whole PSWCs were approximately 1 Hz and the sleep staging was inconclusive (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">B</xref>). To further understand the patient’s sleep structure, 24-hour polysomnography (PSG) was performed. The results demonstrated an evident abnormal sleep structure, with a significant reduction in sleep spindles and K-complexes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3</xref>). The total sleep time was 655.0 min, with a total sleep time in the N1 stage of being 91.9%, and N2 stage of being 8.1%, and the N3 stage and rapid eye movement stages of sleep being absent. The sleep efficiency was 48.8% and sleep apnea hypoventilation index (average number of occurrences per hour) was 5.7. The periodic leg movement index was 5.8 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3</xref>). As the symptoms worsened, the patient’s EEG voltage was gradually decreased, suggesting a reduced whole-brain function. The PSWCs remained atypical with the disappearance of sleep staging and periodic synchronous discharge (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2B</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">D</xref>). Three months after disease onset, the patient developed cognitive impairment, aphasia and intermittent bilateral lower limb myoclonus. Four months later, she developed laryngeal stridor. To further clarify the diagnosis, the positron emission tomography-computed tomography (PET-CT) was performed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1C</xref>), showing heterogeneous hypometabolism in the whole brain parenchyma with pronounced hypometabolism being noted in bilateral frontal, temporal lobes, basal ganglia and thalamus. Her routine cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) tests including color, clarity, cell count, protein, and other routine biochemical markers were normal. Tests were also negative for autoimmune encephalitis antibodies (NMDAR, AMPA1, AMPA2, LGI1, CASPR2, GABA, and GAD), and negative for paraneoplastic antibodies (Hu, Yo, Ri, MA2, CV2 and amphiphysin). For further detection of CSF 14-3-3 protein, real-time quaking-induced conversion (RT-QuIC) assay of CSF, skin biopsy and whole blood <italic>PRNP</italic> gene sequencing were performed, and the skin tissue biopsy, whole blood samples, and remaining CSF samples were sent to the China Center for Disease Control and Prevention. The CSF 14-3-3 protein was negative using Western blot. The whole blood <italic>PRNP</italic> gene sequence was compared to the standard sequence (NCBI: NM-183079.1) and no homozygous or heterozygous mutations were found. The biopsied skin and CSF samples were positive according to RT-QuIC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">B</xref>). Therefore, this patient was diagnosed with sCJD. Six months after disease onset, repeated brain MRI was performed. However, due to patient’s tolerance, only an apparent diffusion coefficient sequence was completed, and the results showed slight hypointensities in the left temporal and parietal lobes, and ventricular enlargement compared to the previous brain MRI (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1D</xref>).<fig id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Brain imaging features of this patient. (<bold>A</bold>) Restricted diffusion in bilateral caudate nucleus, putamen nucleus and frontal cortical areas on DWI, obtained at one month, (<bold>B</bold>) wider distribution of abnormal high signal on DWI, “cortical ribboning” of frontal, temporal, parietal and cingulate cortex, obtained at one and a half months, (<bold>C</bold>) Brain PET-CT images showed uneven hypometabolism of the whole brain parenchyma most evident in the bilateral frontotemporal lobes, bilateral basal ganglia and bilateral thalamus, obtained at four months. (<bold>D</bold>) Brain ADC images showed significant ventricular enlargement, obtained at six months after disease onset.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-1441-g0002"/></fig><fig id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>EEG showed generalized slowing without typical PSWCs, obtained at (<bold>A</bold>) three months, (<bold>B</bold>) three and a half months, (<bold>C</bold>) four months (<bold>D</bold>) four and a half months after disease onset.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-1441-g0003"/></fig><fig id="f0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>PSG trend graph of abnormal sleep structures obtained three months after onset. Recording Duration (min) 1342.1, from 11:01:45 to 09:23:52 the next day.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-1441-g0004"/></fig><fig id="f0004" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Positive skin biopsy tissue (<bold>A</bold>) and CSF samples (<bold>B</bold>) RT-QuIC results at four months after onset (Updated diagnostic guidelines for sCJD have incorporated RT-QuIC for early diagnosis of disease, surveillance, evaluation of PrP<sup>sc</sup> inoculation in different tissues, and in trial monitoring).<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-1441-g0005"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In this report, we presented a rare case of sCJD with persistent insomnia. Sporadic prion disease with codon 129 polymorphism MM was confirmed by skin, CSF RT-QuIC, and genetic testing 4 months after disease onset. As the patient’s family members refused brain tissue biopsy or autopsy, we could not determine whether the patient’s PrP<sup>Sc</sup> was type 1, type 2 or both. MM2 can be divided into cortical and thalamic types. Clinical features of the thalamic type overlap with those of fatal familial insomnia (FFI). Thus, it is also referred to sFI by some researchers.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Clinical findings of our case were consistent with the sFI subtype. Therefore, this case can be used to expand our understanding of the characteristics of the sCJDMM2T/sFI, sCJDMM2C, and sCJDMM1 subtypes (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Sleep disorders are not uncommon in sCJD, while have not received extensive attention in other disease subtypes. This patient’s PSG is different from our previous study<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> of PSG in patients with sCJD. We propose that PSG in patients may be useful in the diagnosis of clinical subtypes of sCJD. The various subtypes are discussed as below:<table-wrap id="t0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of sCJDMM2T/sFI, sCJDMM2C, sCJDMM1 and Our Case</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">sCJDMM2T/sFI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">sCJDMM2C</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">sCJDMM1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">This Case</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age of onset (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (13–74)<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (56–88)<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66(59–73)<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">First symptoms</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterogeneity, early stage sleep abnormalities are often not reported by the patient or family<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterogeneity, symptoms in the early stages include cognitive impairment, psychiatric symptoms, visual symptoms, extrapyramidal signs<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterogeneity, visual impairment or unilat-eral signs at onset in 40% of cases<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Persistent insomnia</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Typical symptoms</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychiatric symptoms, autonomic dysfunction and sleep abnormalities<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slow progression, cognitive impairment, few neurological symptoms<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dementia, myoclonus, and PSWCs on EEG<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insomnia, psychomotor hyperactivity, autonomic hyperactivity, laryngeal stridor</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disease duration (months)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (10–73)<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (13–30)<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6(2.0–3.4)<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Still alive (18 months since the onset of the disease)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain MRI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hyperintensity on DWI typically absent, but has been reported in some cases<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hyperintensity lesions mainly confined to the cerebral cortex on DWI<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Striatum and asymmetric lesions are the key lesions of the sCJDMM1 subtype<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hyperintensity on DWI in the caudate nucleus, the nucleus accumbens of bilateral basal ganglia region and bilateral frontal cortical areas</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain PET-CT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Early thalamic hypometabolism or hypoperfusion that may spread to other areas of the brain as disease progresses<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No reports were found in PubMed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No reports were found in PubMed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PET-CT showed thalamic hypometabolism, milder involvement of the cortex.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EEG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Generalized slowing without PSWCs<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">frequency of PSWCs in the patients with sCJDMM2C was 44.4%, lower<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">frequency of PSWCs in the patients with sCJDMM1/MV1 was 80% within the first 3 months of disease<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Generalized slowing without typical PSWCs.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reduction in sleep spindles, K-complexes, slow-wave sleep, REM sleep, and total sleep time<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No reports were found in PubMed.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No reports were found in PubMed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abnormal sleep architecture, sleep inefficiency, Reduction in sleep spindles, K-complexes, N3 sleep and REM sleep absence, sleep apnea hypoventilation, periodic leg movements</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CSF biomarkers</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensitivity of RT-QuIC was 100%,<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> specificity of RT-QuIC was 99–100%<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensitivity of RT-QuIC was 100%,<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> specificity of RT-QuIC was 99–100%.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensitivity of RT-QuIC was 96.8%,<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> specificity of RT-QuIC was 99–100%.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14-3-3 protein was negative, RT-QuIC was positive.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pathological finfdings</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe atrophy of the medial thalamus and inferior olivary nucleus with little pathology in other areas; spongiform change may be absent or focal<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Large confluent vacuole, cerebellum is relatively spared<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Typical fine vacuole<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not done</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PrP<sup>Sc</sup> deposition</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lesser deposition than in the other variants<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perivacuolar type<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Synaptic type<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not done</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> MRI, magnetic resonance imaging; DWI, diffusion-weighted imaging; PET-CT, positron emission tomography-computed tomography; EEG, Electroencephalography; PSWCs, periodic sharp-wave complexes; PSG, Polysomnography; REM, rapid eye movement.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>sCJDMM2T/sFI</title>
        <p>sFI (the thalamic form of CJD) is the most rare type of sporadic prion disease.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> The symptoms of sFI overlap with those of FFI.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> However, insomnia is not evident in most sFI cases, unless the patients and family members are surveyed for sleep disorders<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Neuroimaging findings of sFI are similar to FFI, while most sFI cases do not exhibit typical MRI features of sCJD,<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> with DWI showing hyperintensity in approximately 8% cases.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> A previous study revealed that 71.4% of sFI cases had significant bilateral thalamic hypometabolism and scattered cortical hypometabolic areas using fluorodeoxyglucose-PET.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> The PSG and EEG features of sFI are similar to FFI. The characteristic manifestations of PSG include the reduction of sleep-related EEG activities, such as K complexes and sleep spindles.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> EEG recordings had a slow background activity (or normal), dominated by the θ-δ rhythm. PSWCs were noted in only 7.7% reported cases,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> and elevated level of 14-3-3 protein was rarely found in the CSF of patients with sFI.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></p>
        <p>In patients with rapidly progressing cognitive impairment, behavioral or mood changes associated with ataxic signs, and sleep abnormalities, sFI should be considered as a differential diagnosis. PSG examination, cerebral blood flow single-photon emission CT and/or PET can be used if sFI is suspected. While standard EEG, CSF tests, and MRI are not helpful for diagnosing this disorder, PSG findings including reductions in sleep-related EEG activities (K-complexes and spindles) can be beneficial for a final diagnosis even during an early disease stage. PET examinations have consistently shown thalamic hypometabolism, associated with variable participation in cerebral cortical regions.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Cracco et al<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> proposed clinical diagnostic criteria for sFI by summarizing 32 cases of pathologically confirmed sFI (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). It is thus recommended to complete the PSG examination as early as possible. Additional PSG and PET-CT examinations can also be performed.<table-wrap id="t0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Proposed Clinical Diagnostic Criteria of sCJDMM2T/sFI, sCJDMM2C</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">sCJDMM2T/sFI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">sCJDMM2C</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proposed clinical diagnostic criteria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(must meet A through D)<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><break/>A．Symptoms (must meet 1 through 3) 1. Cognitive impairment<break/>2. Sleep disturbance and/or psychiatric symptoms<break/>3. Two or more typical CJD symptoms:<break/>(a) Ataxia or dysarthri (b) Visual changes<break/>(c) Pyramidal symptoms<break/>(d) Extrapyramidal symptoms<break/>(e) Myoclonus<break/>B. Diagnostic test results (one or more)<break/>1. Reduced sleep architecture (eg, sleep spindles, K-complexes) on PSG<break/>2. Thalamic hypometabolism on brain FDG-PET<break/>3. Thalamic hypoperfusion on brain SPECT<break/>C. Lack of alternative etiology<break/>D. Negative for <italic>PRNP</italic> mutation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A.<break/>Confirmed with neuropathological (large confluent vacuoles) and immunohistochemical (perivacuolar prion protein (PrP) deposits) analysis, genetic analysis of PrP gene (no mutation and methionine homozygote at codon 129 of the PrP gene) and Western blotting of the PrP (type 2)<break/>B.<break/>1.Progressive dementia.<break/>2.No mutation and methionine homozygote at codon 129 of the PrP gene. 3.Hyperintensity lesions confined to the cerebral cortex on a diffusion-weighted image of brain MRI.<break/>4.Only one or none out of the following four clinical features within 6 months post-onset: (1) myoclonus, (2) pyramidal or extrapyramidal signs, (3) cerebellar ataxia or visual impairment, and (4) akinetic mutism.<break/>Definite: A; probable: B, 1–4; possible: B, 1–3. ‘Probable’ and ‘possible’ cases are in the absence of an alternative diagnosis from a routine investigation.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> CJD, Creutzfeldt–Jakob disease; PrP, Prion protein; FDG-PET, fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography; SPECT, single photon emission computed tomography; MRI, magnetic resonance imaging.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>sCJDMM2C</title>
        <p>Compared to other sCJD subtypes, patients with sCJDMM2C experience slower disease progression and a higher frequency of high-intensity lesions on DWI.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Of note, parietal lobes were abnormal in 96% of patients with sCJDMM2C.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> The frequency of PSWCs in patients with sCJDMM2C was 44.4%, and the CSF 14-3-3 protein was positive in 62.5% patients.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Pathological features of sCJDMM2C include large confluent vacuoles, cerebellar sparing, and PrP<sup>Sc</sup> perivacuolar deposition.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Hamaguchi et al<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> reviewed 254 patients with pathologically confirmed prion disease in Japan and proposed the clinical diagnostic criteria for sCJDMM2C (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). sCJDMM2C should be included in the differential diagnosis if a patient has a relatively long survival period, few neurological symptoms, and slow progression and the hyperintensity lesions are mainly confined to the cerebral cortex on DWI.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>sCJDMM1</title>
        <p>sCJDMM1 is the most common subtype of sCJD, accounting for 60–70% of sporadic cases. Previously classified as typical CJD, this subtype has a shorter duration of symptoms than other subtypes.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Striatal and asymmetric lesions are frequently noted in sCJDMM1.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> PSWCs were detected in 80% cases within 3 months of disease onset.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Elevated level of 14-3-3 protein is common in the CSF with 95% being sensitive.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> To our knowledge, PSG manifestations are rarely noted in patients with sCJDMM1 subtype. Our previous studies found that sCJD can present with multiple sleep disorders including hypersomnia, insomnia, sleep apnea, and periodic limb movement disorder.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Pathological findings include typical fine vacuoles and PrP<sup>Sc</sup> synaptic deposition.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> The clinical diagnostic criteria has not been established for sCJDMM1 yet. Although sCJD can present with a variety of sleep disorders including insomnia, the PSG of sCJD patients with insomnia symptoms differs from those of patients with sFI.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>Although our patient’s clinical phenotype was consistent with fatal insomnia, the case fulfilled the proposed clinical diagnostic criteria for sFI. Phenotypic variability is one of remarkable features in sCJD. In the absence of brain tissue biopsy or autopsy, the subtype is only highly suspected. sFI is a rare subtype and it should be distinguished from other sCJD subtypes. In individuals with rapidly progressive cognitive impairment, behavioral abnormalities and sleep abnormalities, differential diagnosis of sFI should be considered. Once the sFI subtype is considered. Apart from brain MRI and EEG, PSG, PET and RT-QuIC are also recommended.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We are grateful to Prof. Xiao Kang at China Center for Disease Control and Prevention for his technical help regarding RT-QuIC analysis of skin biopsy tissue and CSF. We thank Prof. Zhou Wei at China Center for Disease Control and Prevention for the detection of 14-3-3 protein in CSF and prion gene in blood. We are grateful to our hospital neurophysiology unit for providing help regarding dynamic EEG examinations and 24-hour PSG.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Ethical Approval</title>
      <p>The present study was approved by ethics committees of the First Hospital of Jilin University.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Informed Consent</title>
      <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient’s relatives for publication of this manuscript and any accompanying images.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007" sec-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors have no conflicts of interest for this work to declare.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Prusiner</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</italic></source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>95</volume>:<fpage>13363</fpage>–<lpage>13383</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.95.23.13363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9811807</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Prusiner</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Human prion diseases</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Neurol</italic></source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>385</fpage>–<lpage>395</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ana.410350404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8154865</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zerr</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parchi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sporadic Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Handb Clin Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>153</volume>:<fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/b978-0-444-63945-5.00009-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29887134</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nemani</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cali</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A novel mechanism of phenotypic heterogeneity in Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Neuropathol Commun</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>85</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40478-020-00966-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32560672</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Parchi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Giese</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Capellari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Classification of sporadic Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease based on molecular and phenotypic analysis of 300 subjects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Neurol</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>224</fpage>–<lpage>233</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1531-8249(199908)46:2&lt;224::AID-ANA12&gt;3.0.CO;2-W</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10443888</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cracco</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Appleby</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gambetti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Fatal familial insomnia and sporadic fatal insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Handb Clin Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>153</volume>:<fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>299</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/b978-0-444-63945-5.00015-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29887141</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Geschwind</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prion diseases</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Continuum (Minneap Minn)</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>1612</fpage>–<lpage>1638</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/con.0000000000000251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26633779</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Clinical manifestations and polysomnography-based analysis in nine cases of probable sporadic Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;Online ahead of print. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10072-021-05102-8</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Puoti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bizzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Forloni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sporadic human prion diseases: molecular insights and diagnosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>618</fpage>–<lpage>628</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s1474-4422(12)70063-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22710755</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Moda</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suardi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Di Fede</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>MM2-thalamic Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease: neuropathological, biochemical and transmission studies identify a distinctive prion strain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Pathol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>662</fpage>–<lpage>669</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1750-3639.2012.00572.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22288561</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hamaguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kitamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Clinical diagnosis of MM2-type sporadic Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>643</fpage>–<lpage>648</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/01.Wnl.0000151847.57956.Fa</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15728285</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Abu-Rumeileh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Redaelli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baiardi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sporadic fatal insomnia in Europe: phenotypic features and diagnostic challenges</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>84</volume>:<fpage>347</fpage>–<lpage>360</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ana.25300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30048013</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gambetti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parchi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Hereditary Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease and fatal familial insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Lab Med</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0272-2712(02)00065-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12733424</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hamaguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sanjo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ae</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>MM2-type sporadic Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease: new diagnostic criteria for MM2-cortical type</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>1158</fpage>–<lpage>1165</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jnnp-2020-323231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32839349</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bizzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pascuzzo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blevins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Subtype diagnosis of sporadic Creutzfeldt–Jakob disease with diffusion magnetic resonance imaging</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>560</fpage>–<lpage>572</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ana.25983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33274461</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Iwasaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropathology</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>174</fpage>–<lpage>188</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/neup.12355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28028861</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wiltfang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cepek</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Tau protein and 14-3-3 protein in the differential diagnosis of Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>192</fpage>–<lpage>197</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/wnl.58.2.192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11805244</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hermann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Appleby</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brandel</surname><given-names>J-P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Biomarkers and diagnostic guidelines for sporadic Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>246</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s1474-4422(20)30477-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33609480</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Abu-Rumeileh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baiardi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Polischi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Diagnostic value of surrogate CSF biomarkers for Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease in the era of RT-QuIC</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>266</volume>:<fpage>3136</fpage>–<lpage>3143</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00415-019-09537-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31541342</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
