<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34557049</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">8455296</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">327110</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S327110</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Deep Learning–Based Assessment of Brain Connectivity Related to Obstructive Sleep Apnea and Daytime Sleepiness</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Lee et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Lee et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1932-9557</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Min-Hee</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5120-5557</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Seung Ku</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Thomas</surname>
            <given-names>Robert J</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2203-2698</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Yoon</surname>
            <given-names>Jee-Eun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2204-8067</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Yun</surname>
            <given-names>Chang-Ho</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0004">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="ft0001">*</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2928-8576</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Shin</surname>
            <given-names>Chol</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0005">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="ft0001">*</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0002"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Institute of Human Genomic Study, College of Medicine, Korea University Ansan Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Ansan</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Medicine, Division of Pulmonary, Critical Care and Sleep Medicine, Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line>Boston</addr-line>, <addr-line>MA</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Neurology, Uijeongbu Eulji Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line>Uijeongbu</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Neurology, Seoul National University Bundang Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Seongnam</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label><institution>Department of Pulmonary Sleep and Critical Care Medicine Disorder Center, College of Medicine, Korea University</institution>, <addr-line>Ansan</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Chang-Ho Yun <institution>Department of Neurology, Bundang Clinical Neuroscience Institute, Seoul National University Bundang Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>82 Gumi-ro 173beon-gil, Bundang-gu</addr-line>, <addr-line>Seongnam</addr-line>, <addr-line>13620</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country><phone>Tel +82 31 787 7469</phone><fax>Fax +82 31 787 4059</fax> Email ych333@gmail.com</corresp>
        <corresp id="an0002">Chol Shin <institution>Division of Pulmonary, Sleep, and Critical Care Medicine, Department of Internal Medicine, Korea University Ansan Hospital and Institute of Human Genomic Study, Korea University Ansan Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>516, Gojan-1-dong, Danwon-gu</addr-line>, <addr-line>Ansan</addr-line>, <addr-line>Gyeonggi-do</addr-line>, <addr-line>15355</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country><phone>Tel +82 31 412 5541</phone><fax>Fax +82 31 412 5604</fax> Email chol-shin@korea.ac.kr</corresp>
        <fn id="ft0001">
          <label>*</label>
          <p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>17</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>13</volume>
      <fpage>1561</fpage>
      <lpage>1572</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>01</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>04</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2021 Lee et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Lee et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p>Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) is associated with altered pairwise connections between brain regions, which might explain cognitive impairment and daytime sleepiness. By adopting a deep learning method, we investigated brain connectivity related to the severity of OSA and daytime sleepiness.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Patients and Methods</title>
          <p>A cross-sectional design applied a deep learning model on structural brain networks obtained from 553 subjects (age, 59.2 ± 7.4 years; men, 35.6%). The model performance was evaluated with the Pearson’s correlation coefficient (<italic>R</italic>) and probability of absolute error less than standard deviation (P<sub>AE&lt;SD</sub>) between the estimated and the actual scores. In addition, we investigated sex effects on deep learning outputs for OSA and daytime sleepiness and examined the differences in brain connectivity related to daytime sleepiness between OSA and non-OSA groups.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>We achieved a meaningful <italic>R</italic> (up to 0.74) and P<sub>AE&lt;SD</sub> (up to 0.92) in a test dataset of whole group and subgroups. Motor, frontal and limbic areas, and default mode network were the prominent hubs of important connectivity to predict OSA severity and daytime sleepiness. Sex affected brain connectivity relevant to OSA severity as well as daytime sleepiness. Brain connectivity associated with daytime sleepiness also differed by the presence vs absence of OSA.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>A deep learning method can assess the association of brain network characteristics with OSA severity and daytime sleepiness and specify the relevant brain connectivity.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>convolutional neural network</kwd>
        <kwd>obstructive sleep apnea</kwd>
        <kwd>daytime sleepiness</kwd>
        <kwd>diffusion tensor imaging</kwd>
        <kwd>structural brain network</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="4"/>
        <table-count count="10"/>
        <ref-count count="48"/>
        <page-count count="12"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Sufficient sleep of good quality is essential for optimal brain health. Nevertheless, sleep problems such as insufficient sleep, insomnia, and obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) are common.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> OSA is characterized by repetitive cessations or reductions in airflow due to upper airway collapse during sleep, resulting in intermittent hypoxia and sleep fragmentation.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> OSA not only causes harmful systemic responses including oxidative stress, inflammation, hypertension, and insulin resistance, but also leads to functional impairment and structural alteration of brain.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> OSA is related to diminished excessive daytime sleepiness by several mechanisms, including blood–brain barrier dysfunction,<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> brain edema,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> amyloid deposition,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> cerebral structure changes,<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> and altered anatomical brain connections.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></p>
      <p>Discrete brain areas communicate with each other for diverse functions through anatomical connections to generate and integrate information from multiple sources.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Structural network properties depend on the integrity of brain structure and connections as well as the efficiency of functional segregation and integration. Altered network properties and their topography can explain neurocognitive defects and symptom diversity in OSA.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> A good example of phenotypic diversity is excessive daytime sleepiness that does not only impair daytime function and quality of life but also determines cardiometabolic outcomes and therapeutic responses.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> For the same degree of OSA, the level of daytime sleepiness varies substantially. Its mechanisms are still elusive.</p>
      <p>Previous neuroimaging studies highlight the need to address OSA and daytime sleepiness as a network disorder underpinned by brain structure or activity that connects heterogeneous regional function. One study analyzed structural brain networks constructed from diffusion tensor imaging (DTI) and found altered anatomical connections driven by white matter injury in OSA.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Another study demonstrated that OSA led to alterations of global topological characteristics in the brain network constructed by statistical associations of cortical volumes.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Functional MRI studies also report that OSA severity is associated with abnormal functional connectivity as well as cognitive dysfunction.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13–16</xref> Although very few studies have examined the relationship between daytime sleepiness and brain connectivity, one study reported that daytime sleepiness is associated with functional connectivity in the default mode network (DMN), which has a crucial role in cognition.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> An increased rate of β-amyloid accumulation particularly in the DMN areas is associated with sleepiness.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Residual sleepiness in treated OSA patients may be partially explained by white matter abnormality on DTI.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> However, it is still unclear which clusters of brain connectivity (ie, pairwise connections between brain regions) specifically correlate with the degree of OSA and daytime sleepiness.</p>
      <p>Prior methods for network analysis have limitations in specifying brain connectivity related to OSA severity and daytime sleepiness since it is a complicated task to solve the relationship between a nonlinear complex system (ie, brain network) and continuous measures (ie, degree of OSA severity and daytime sleepiness scale). Thus, it is necessary to develop novel approaches to estimate linear properties from a nonlinear complex system and to understand which brain connections are linearly associated with OSA severity and daytime sleepiness. The deep learning algorithm is a computational technique to assess complex relationships between input features and target variables.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> The purpose of this algorithm is to learn a mapping function from input features to targets, achieved by adjusting the weights of the neural network in response to the errors between predicted and actual outputs the model makes on the training dataset. The adjusting processes are intended to continually reduce errors until a good enough model is found.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Contributions of individual input features to performance of decision-making by a trained model can be calculated by gradient information associated with the change in weights in relation to the change in errors (eg, input features with a larger gradient can have a greater effect on the predicted output).<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Therefore, deep learning can determine brain connections that are the most susceptible to OSA severity or sleepiness, by maximizing the relationship between predicted and actual scores based on structural network organization while minimizing the errors between the two scores.</p>
      <p>The purpose of this study was to investigate anatomical brain connectivity related to OSA severity and daytime sleepiness in a representative sample from a general population in middle-to-late adulthood by using structural network analysis implemented with a deep learning model referred to as BrainNetCNN, which has been recently described as a powerful prediction model for structural brain networks.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> We also investigated differences in deep learning outputs according to sex and presence of OSA. Our specific hypothesis was that a deep learning analysis can be predictive of OSA severity and daytime sleepiness. Such an analysis could be an effective tool to improve our understanding of the neuroanatomical substrates for OSA and daytime sleepiness in adult populations.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Study Subjects</title>
        <p>Study procedures were approved by the Institutional Review Board of Korea University Ansan Hospital (approval no. 2006AS0045), which is a sub-study of the Korean Genome and Epidemiology Study (KoGES), an ongoing prospective community-based cohort study. In 2001–2002, the original cohort was established in Ansan, South Korea, and consisted of 5012 adults aged 40–69 years. Furthermore, it was performed in accordance with the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki. Written informed consent from all study participants was obtained. Participants in KoGES have been biennially evaluated for demographic characteristics, medical history, health status, and sleep-related factors. As sleep and cognitive aging were adopted as an adjunct research agenda, polysomnography (PSG) and structural MRI were introduced in 2011. In contrast to the core KoGES evaluations performed every 2 years, MRI and PSG was aimed to cover all participants in a 4-year cycle.</p>
        <p>For this cross-sectional analysis, we included 625 participants (age, 59.5 ± 7.6 years; men, 34.7%) who completed both MRI and PSG evaluations in 2011. We excluded subjects with 1) major neurological disorders (stroke, n = 16; major head trauma, n = 4; dementia, n = 1; hydrocephalus, n = 4), 2) incomplete Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS) assessment (n = 7), and 3) loss of MR image slices through the manual review of MRI image quality (n = 40). Finally, 553 participants (age 59.2 ± 7.4 years, men 35.6%) were included in the present study.</p>
        <p>To perform an analysis of brain connectivity related to apnea–hypopnea index (AHI), oxygen desaturation index (ODI), the minimum oxygen saturation (<sub>min</sub>SpO<sub>2</sub>) and ESS scores, all subjects were randomly assigned into one of three data-sets: a training set (n = 398) to perform deep learning of a connectivity matrix, a validation set (n = 100) to confirm convergence of the deep learning model established in the training set, and a test set (n = 55) to evaluate the reliability of the deep learning model. In addition, a sex effect on the relationship of brain connectivity with OSA severity and ESS was examined in the subgroup analysis of men (n = 142/35/20 for training/validation/testing sets) and women (n = 256/64/36). The ESS-associated connectivity was compared between non-OSA (n = 222/55/31 for training/validation/testing sets) and OSA (n = 176/44/25) groups.</p>
        <p>All participants underwent overnight PSG. Apneas and hypopneas were defined according to standard methods.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> The AHI was calculated by averaging the total number of obstructive apneas and hypopneas occurring per hour of sleep. OSA was defined as an AHI ≥ 5/hour of sleep and the non-OSA group had an AHI &lt; 5/hour. Daytime sleepiness was assessed using the ESS.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> The time interval between overnight PSG and brain MRI was within 2 weeks. The characteristics and sleep variables were presented in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Tables 1</xref> and <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Before the analysis, we investigated the relationship between AHI and ESS to determine whether ESS should be regarded as an independent variable and found no significant correlation (<italic>R</italic> = −0.1, <italic>P</italic> = 0.12); therefore, ESS was considered as an independent variable.<table-wrap id="t0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic Data from All Participants</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole (n=553)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men (n=197)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women (n=356)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-OSA (n=308)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSA (n=245)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.2 ± 7.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.0 ± 7.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.7 ± 7.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.0 ± 6.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.9 ± 7.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">197 (35.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90 (29.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107 (43.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.7 ± 3.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.7 ± 2.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.7 ± 3.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.9 ± 2.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.6 ± 3.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;6 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101 (18.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (9.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 (23.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (14.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (23.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7–9 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">113 (20.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (16.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81 (22.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (22.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (18.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 10–12 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">240 (43.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (44.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">153 (43.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">139 (45.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101 (41.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 13–16 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90 (16.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (26.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (10.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (17.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (15.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt; 16 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (1.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (3.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (1.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (2.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current smokers</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (8.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (20.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (1.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (7.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (9.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current drinkers</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">215 (38.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">122 (61.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93 (26.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">114 (37.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101 (41.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">202 (36.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 (42.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">119 (33.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 (26.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">119 (48.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes mellitus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">132 (23.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (26.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 (22.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (14.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (35.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BDI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8 ± 7.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8 ± 6.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0 ± 7.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8 ± 6.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9 ± 8.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Data are presented as n (%) or mean ± SD, unless otherwise stated.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: OSA, obstructive sleep apnea; BMI, body mass index; BDI, Beck Depression Inventory.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="t0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Sleep Variables of All Participants</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole (n=553)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men (n=197)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women (n=356)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-OSA (n=308)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSA (n=245)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI (events/hour)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9 ± 8.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5 ± 10.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 ± 7.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8 ± 1.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.2 ± 9.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mild (5–14)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">175 (31.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (37.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102 (28.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">175 (71.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Moderate (15–29)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (10.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26(13.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (8.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (22.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Severe (≥30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (4.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (1.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (5.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sub>min</sub>SpO<sub>2</sub> (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.8 ± 4.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.8 ± 5.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.4 ± 4.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.4 ± 3.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.6 ± 4.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sub>mean</sub>SpO<sub>2</sub> (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.7 ± 1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.5 ± 1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.9 ± 1.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.2 ± 1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.1 ± 1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TS90 (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7 ± 13.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 ± 5.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 ± 11.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 ± 9.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7 ± 10.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTS90 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5 ± 3.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 ± 1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 ± 3.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2 ± 2.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 ± 2.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ODI (events/hour)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2 ± 8.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6 ± 9.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5 ± 7.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 ± 1.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0 ± 9.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0 ± 3.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6 ± 2.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3 ± 3.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2 ± 3.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9 ± 3.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TST (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">391.4 ± 74.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">384.8 ± 74.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">395.0 ± 74.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">395.1 ± 73.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">386.7 ± 74.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage N1 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 ± 4.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7 ± 5.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5 ± 4.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2 ± 3.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9 ± 6.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage N2 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.9 ± 11.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.3 ± 12.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.4 ± 10.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.1 ± 10.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.7 ± 11.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage N3 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2 ± 4.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4 ± 4.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6 ± 3.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7 ± 3.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3 ± 3.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage R (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.8 ± 6.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.1 ± 6.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.2 ± 6.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.3 ± 7.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.0 ± 6.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Data are presented as n (%) or mean ± SD, unless otherwise stated.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: AHI, apnea–hypopnea index; <sub>min</sub>SpO<sub>2</sub>, minimum oxygen saturation; <sub>mean</sub>SpO<sub>2</sub>, mean oxygen saturation; ODI, oxygen desaturation index; ESS, Epworth Sleepiness Scale; TST, total sleep time; TS90, time spent with oxygen saturation below 90%; PTS90, percentage of time spent with oxygen saturation below 90%.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Data Acquisition and Processing</title>
        <p>DTI data was acquired using a 1.5-Tesla MRI scanner (General Electric, Milwaukee, WI) at TR = 15,000 ms, TE = 93.8 ms, 15 isotropic gradient directions with b = 1000 s/mm<sup>2</sup>, and single b = 0 image acquisition. T1-weighted images were also obtained with the following parameters: TR = 7.7 ms, TE = 3.4 ms, flip angle = 12<sup>°</sup>, slice thickness = 1.6 mm. Artifacts including head motion, noise, physiological artifacts, susceptibility-induced distortion, B1 field inhomogeneity, and eddy current-induced distortion in DTI data were corrected by using the FSL eddy tool.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Whole brain streamlines were then reconstructed using second-order integration over fiber orientation distributions<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> incorporating anatomically constrained tractography<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> with 1000 dynamically randomized seeding points on the gray-matter/white-matter interface.</p>
        <p>A parcellation scheme was applied to whole brain streamlines using an automated anatomical labeling (AAL) atlas,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> segmented into 90 cerebral areas in order to construct a structural brain network. Each AAL region represented a node in the brain network, and an edge in the brain network was defined as the number of white-matter streamlines connecting the nodes normalized by volume of the nodes to stabilize inter-subject variability. Before training by using deep learning model, the strength of brain connections was adjusted for age, sex, education, drink, smoke, hypertension, and diabetes mellitus using a multiple linear regression model. For the subgroup analysis by sex, sex was not included in the model. To reduce the effect of inter-subject variability on the training process, the resulting residuals were used to substitute for the raw connection strength.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Conventional DTI Metrics</title>
        <p>To investigate the correlation of conventional DTI metrics including diffusivity and network properties with OSA severity and daytime sleepiness, we employed fractional anisotropy (FA) and three network parameters including node strength, nodal efficiency, and node betweenness centrality. FA measures the microstructural integrity of white matter.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Node strength is the sum of connection weights connecting neighbor nodes, assessing the ability of information interactions with these nodes.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> Nodal efficiency reflects the importance of the node for reciprocal communication within the brain network, estimated by the average path length between any node and other nodes.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> Node betweenness centrality is defined as the fraction of shortest paths between any two nodes that pass through a given node, and indicates the relative importance of a node on information flow in a complex network.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Convolutional Neural Network Architecture</title>
        <p>Before applying the deep learning algorithm to connectivity matrices, as overfitting which corresponds exactly or closely to target variables in the analysis model was expected due to the relatively small size of the training dataset (n = 398/142/256/222/176 for whole/men/women/non-OSA/OSA group), we employed the synthetic minority over-sampling technique<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> based on a randomly interpolated resampling procedure across the nearest neighbors, which enlarges the training dataset by triple augmentations for each subject.</p>
        <p>Prior neural network techniques have a limitation when applied to brain network data to determine the relationship between anatomical brain connectivity related to OSA severity and daytime sleepiness. Fully connected neural networks may ignore the topological relationships between edges or nodes by treating the input connection weights as a vector of features.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Conventional convolutional neural networks (CNNs) use traditional convolutional filters (ie, square filters) designed to capture the spatial 2D grid locality of images, which treat connectivity matrix as an image.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> It also cannot capture topological relationships in the brain network. Therefore, in the present study, we applied the BrainNetCNN,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> which is a novel type of CNN optimized for the connectivity matrix. It consists of three types of layers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref>): an Edge-to-Node (E2N) layer, which works by assigning weights to the edges of the network, a node-to-graph (N2G) layer, which reduces the dimensionality of the input by taking a weighted combination of nodes to output a single response and a final fully connected (FC) layer. The E2N layer takes a 90×90 connectivity matrix derived from DTI and uses a 256×1 × 90 filter, which allows to extract topological features in the brain network. It gives a unique output value for each node i as it takes the average of weights of each edge connected to node i. The outputs of the E2N layer, 1×90 × 256 feature maps, are the inputs to N2G layer which acts as a 1D convolution to compress the node information. Finally, the number of features is reduced to the number of target variables through an FC layer with 1×1 × 64 feature maps. To avoid overfitting on the training set, we engaged an additional measure, adopting a dropout layer of 0.5 before the FC layer and to prevent vanishing gradient a leaky rectified linear unit with a negative slope of 0.2 was employed. Furthermore, we empirically set the number of training iterations as 30,000 for the whole group and 20,000 for other groups. To minimize the Euclidean distance loss with a weighted L2 regularization term between the predicted and actual scores on the training set, BrainNetCNN was trained using a stochastic gradient descent algorithm, which updates the weights by a linear combination of the negative gradient and the previous weight update at the learning rate of 0.01.<fig id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Schematic overview of the convolutional neural network architecture used to estimate the sleep variables. The convolutional neural network consists of an Edge-to-Node (E2N) layer, a node-to-graph (N2G) layer and fully connected (FC) layer. The E2N layer takes a 90×90 connectivity matrix and works by assigning weights to the edges of the network, a node-to-graph (N2G) layer reduces the dimensionality of the input by taking a weighted combination of nodes to output a single response and a final fully connected (FC) layer reduces the number of features for estimating a target variable. The saliency map is obtained by computing the partial derivatives of the output with respect to the input connectivity matrix for every input edge. Edges with a larger partial derivative were determined to be more predictive of the target variable.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-1561-g0001"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>The general characteristics are reported as means and standard deviations and proportions with group comparisons using <italic>t</italic>-tests and standard chi-squared test for continuous and categorical variables, respectively. The statistical significance was set at p&lt;0.05. For the conventional DTI metrics analyses, statistical significance was set at p&lt;0.05, after false discovery rate controlled for multiple comparisons.</p>
        <p>To evaluate consistency and performance of the BrainNetCNN model, we performed Three-fold Cross-Validation on the training and validation sets, and calculated the mean absolute error (MAE), the Pearson’s correlation coefficient (<italic>R</italic>) and the probability of absolute error less than standard deviation (P<sub>AE&lt;SD</sub>) between the predicted and the actual scores. In the present study, we report average and standard deviation of MAE, <italic>R</italic> and P<sub>AE&lt;SD</sub> over cross-validation folds. The statistical significance for <italic>R</italic> was set at p&lt;0.05 in all cross-validations. When the <italic>R</italic> between the predicted and actual scores met the statistical significance (p&lt;0.05) in all cross-validations, the deep learning model was accepted as a meaningful prediction model. To determine which pairwise connections were learned by BrainNetCNN to be predictive of AHI, ODI, <sub>min</sub>SpO<sub>2</sub> and ESS, we used the method of saliency visualization<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> that computes the partial derivatives of the output (ie, predicted score) with respect to the input connectivity matrix for every input edge.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Edges with a larger partial derivative were determined to be more predictive of the actual score, which have higher pairwise connections contributing to better prediction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref>). The BrainNetCNN was implemented with deep a learning framework (Caffe, <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://caffe.berkeleyvision.org/">https://caffe.berkeleyvision.org/</ext-link></underline>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Conventional DTI Metrics</title>
        <p>There were no meaningful correlations (<italic>R</italic> &lt; 0.3 and <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05) between any conventional DTI metrics including FA, node strength, regional efficiency, and node betweenness centrality and OSA severity and daytime sleepiness in the whole dataset, and in all the subgroups. This suggests that conventional DTI metrics may not be a proper predictor of OSA severity and daytime sleepiness although they were different by group comparisons between non-OSA and OSA groups as reported in previous studies including our own, based on the same population.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Prediction of OSA Severity</title>
        <p>The results of using the BrainNetCNN model to predict AHI, ODI and <sub>min</sub>SpO<sub>2</sub> scores are summarized in <xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. We achieved meaningful Pearson’s correlation coefficients and P<sub>AE&lt;SD</sub> for AHI, ODI and <sub>min</sub>SpO<sub>2</sub> in the test dataset of whole group and the subgroups, suggesting that the deep learning method is better than conventional DTI at predicting the degree of OSA severity indicated by AHI, ODI, and <sub>min</sub>SpO<sub>2.</sub><table-wrap id="t0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Pearson’s Correlation Coefficient (<italic>R</italic>), Mean Absolute Error (MAE), and Probability of Absolute Error Less Than Standard Deviation (P<sub>AE&lt;SD</sub>) Between Measured and Predicted Apnea–Hypopnea Index (AHI), Oxygen Desaturation Index (ODI), and Minimum Oxygen Saturation (<sub>min</sub>SpO<sub>2</sub>) Scores with Three-fold Cross-Validation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">AHI</th><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">ODI</th><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1"><sub>min</sub>SpO<sub>2</sub></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>R</italic>*</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAE</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>AE&lt;SD</sub></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>R</italic>*</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAE</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>AE&lt;SD</sub></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>R</italic>*</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAE</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>AE&lt;SD</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Whole group</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Train</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.37 ± 0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.09 ± 0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.95 ± 0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 ± 0.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60 ± 0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.01 ± 0.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61 ± 0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.66 ± 0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.42 ± 0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 ± 0.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.10 ± 0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.59 ± 0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.61 ± 0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 ± 0.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Men group</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Train</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.60 ± 0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.13 ± 0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.10 ± 0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 ± 0.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77 ± 0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.05 ± 1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 ± 0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76 ± 0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.52 ± 1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 ± 0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73 ± 0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.85 ± 0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 ± 0.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.01 ± 0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 ± 0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.59 ± 0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.60 ± 0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73 ± 0.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Women group</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Train</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.93 ± 1.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 ± 0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.87 ± 0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 ± 0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.32 ± 0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 ± 0.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.47 ± 0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.32 ± 0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60 ± 0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.86 ± 0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 ± 0.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73 ± 0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.22 ± 1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 ± 0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 ± 0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.21 ± 0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 ± 0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 ± 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.04 ± 0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 ± 0.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: *All Pearson’s correlation coefficients (<italic>R</italic>) were statistically significant at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01. Values are Listed for Three Different Groups/Subgroups: Whole Dataset (n = 553), Men Group (n = 197) and Women Group (n = 356).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Anatomical Brain Connectivity Related to OSA Severity</title>
        <p>The partial derivatives predictive of AHI, ODI and <sub>min</sub>SpO<sub>2</sub> scores are plotted with edges connecting nodes of AAL atlas regions (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">3</xref>). In the whole group, we could delineate the prominent hubs of important connections such as the left motor area, left fusiform gyrus, and the limbic system, for predicting OSA severity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2</xref>). In the subgroup analysis, anatomical connections related to OSA severity differed by sex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3</xref>). AHI and ODI were predicted by the connections of hubs located in left occipital and right prefrontal areas for men, and in left occipital, prefrontal areas and the limbic system for women. The lowest value of oxygen saturation, <sub>min</sub>SpO<sub>2,</sub> was closely related to left occipital areas and the limbic system in men, and to left occipital, temporal areas and limbic system in women.<fig id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The brain connectivity most predictive of the apnea–hypopnea index (AHI), oxygen desaturation index (ODI), and minimum oxygen saturation (<sub>min</sub>SpO<sub>2</sub>) scores in the whole group. The brain connectivity with the top 20 derivative magnitudes were chosen for clarity. On the 3D surface images, the thickness of individual edge (red) indicates the partial derivative magnitude and the size of each sphere (blue) indicates the sum of the partial derivative magnitude, with respect to AHI, ODI, <sub>min</sub>SpO<sub>2</sub> scores, respectively. A complete list of the region labels is available in <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=327110.docx">Table S1.</ext-link></underline></p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-1561-g0002"/></fig><fig id="f0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The brain connectivity to be most predictive of apnea–hypopnea index (AHI), oxygen desaturation index (ODI), and minimum oxygen saturation (<sub>min</sub>SpO<sub>2</sub>) score for two different subgroups: men and women. The brain connections with the top 20 derivative magnitudes were chosen for clarity. On the 3D surface images, the thickness of individual edge (red) indicates the partial derivative magnitude and the size of each sphere (blue) indicates the sum of the partial derivative magnitude, with respect to AHI, ODI, <sub>min</sub>SpO<sub>2</sub> scores, respectively. A complete list of region names corresponding to the region labels is available in <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=327110.docx">Table S1</ext-link></underline>.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-1561-g0003"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Prediction of Degree of Daytime Sleepiness</title>
        <p>The performance of the BrainNetCNN model to predict daytime sleepiness is summarized in <xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. The deep learning method predicted ESS in the whole group analysis as well as in the subgroup analysis by sex and presence of OSA.<table-wrap id="t0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Pearson’s Correlation Coefficient (<italic>R</italic>), Mean Absolute Error (MAE), and Probability of Absolute Error Less Than Standard Deviation (P<sub>AE&lt;SD</sub>) Between Measured and Predicted Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS) Scores with Three-fold Cross-Validation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Train Set</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valid Set</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Set</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Whole group</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>R</italic>*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75±0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60±0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54±0.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.93±0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.39±0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.13±0.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>AE&lt;SD</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82±0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72±0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76±0.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Men group</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>R</italic>*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92±0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70±0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68±0.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.73±0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94±0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.39±0.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>AE&lt;SD</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78±0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77±0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60±0.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Women group</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>R</italic>*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85±0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67±0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60±0.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85±0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.37±0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.43±0.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>AE&lt;SD</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85±0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77±0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74±0.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Non-OSA group</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>R</italic>*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87±0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74±0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73±0.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55±0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.03±0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.70±0.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>AE&lt;SD</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92±0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81±0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72±0.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">OSA group</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>R</italic>*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91±0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73±0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74±0.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25±0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.91±0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.35±0.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>AE&lt;SD</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95±0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79±0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72±0.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0006"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: *All Pearson’s correlation coefficients (<italic>R</italic>) were statistically significant at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01. Values are Listed for Five Different Groups/Subgroups: Whole Dataset (n = 553), Men Group (n = 197), Women Group (n = 356), Non-Obstructive Sleep Apnea (OSA) Group (n = 308) and OSA Group (n = 245).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2005">
        <title>Anatomical Brain Connectivity Related to Daytime Sleepiness</title>
        <p>The partial derivatives to be predictive of ESS scores are plotted with edges connecting nodes of the AAL atlas regions (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4</xref>). In the whole group, prominent hubs were the left superior frontal areas, the cingulate, precuneus, angular, occipital temporal, prefrontal, hippocampal, and posterior inferior parietal areas known as components of the right DMN in a previous study.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> In the subgroup analysis, sex differences were found in brain connectivity related to daytime sleepiness. The right DMN appeared to be a prominent hub of important connectivity in men. In contrast, the right prefrontal areas and the left DMN were important in women. The presence of OSA also influenced the characteristics of anatomical connections. Important connectivity related to sleepiness were in the right DMN and the left limbic system in the OSA group, but in bilateral prefrontal areas and the right limbic system in the non-OSA group.<fig id="f0004" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>The brain connectivity maps to be most predictive of the Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS) scores for five different groups/subgroups: whole dataset, Men group, Women group, non-OSA group and obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) group. The brain connectivity with the top 20 derivative magnitudes were chosen for clarity. On the 3D surface images, the thickness of individual edges (red) indicates the partial magnitude and the size of each sphere (blue) indicates the sum of the partial derivative magnitude, with respect to ESS scores, respectively. A complete list of region names corresponding to the region labels is available in <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=327110.docx">Table S1.</ext-link></underline></p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-1561-g0004"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>This study was motivated by a desire to overcome the limitations of conventional approaches to brain network analyses, which could not readily estimate a continuous property (ie, OSA severity and daytime sleepiness) in relation to a nonlinear complex system (ie, structural brain network). For this goal, we applied a novel deep learning algorithm that can effectively discriminate subtle differences in the strength of anatomical brain connections. Three major findings in the present study support our hypothesis. First, while conventional DTI metrics did not predict OSA severity and daytime sleepiness (<italic>R</italic> &lt; 0.3 and <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05), the deep learning technique accurately predicted AHI (<italic>R</italic> = 0.69 ± 0.1, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01), ODI (<italic>R</italic> = 0.66 ± 0.1, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01), <sub>min</sub>SpO<sub>2</sub> (<italic>R</italic> = 0.62 ± 0.1, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01), and ESS (<italic>R</italic> = 0.70 ± 0.0, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01) for test datasets of all group/subgroup analyses. The high correlation as well as the high probability of absolute error within 1 standard deviation (up to 92%) indicate that the predicted OSA severity and daytime sleepiness is a close proxy of the actual OSA severity and daytime sleepiness. Second, the deep learning technique can determine anatomical brain connectivity associated with OSA and daytime sleepiness. Finally, our approach revealed the effects of sex and OSA on the relationship of anatomical brain connectivity with daytime sleepiness. Sex also influenced network connectivity related to OSA severity. Although previous studies showed group differences, OSA vs non-OSA, in white matter integrity and network properties,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> we could not find any topographic features of FA values and network properties that explained incremental changes in OSA severity and daytime sleepiness with conventional network analysis in this study. The present findings suggest that deep learning techniques are promising tools to provide neuroimaging biomarkers of OSA severity and daytime sleepiness and to explain the phenotypic diversity in OSA.</p>
      <p>OSA affects a wide range of brain areas related to medullary respiratory regulatory, cognitive and autonomic function.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> In the present study, OSA severity was related to brain connectivity including the left motor system that consists of the precentral gyrus, the supplementary area, and its connections and the left limbic system that includes amygdala, caudate, cingulate, putamen and its neighboring connections. These brain systems are susceptible to OSA and related to breathing control, mood, cognition, and cardiovascular regulation.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> These findings suggest that the neural substrates for common clinical manifestations of OSA such as cardiovascular dysregulation, cognitive dysfunction, and affective change can be better identified. Chronic exposure to repetitive hypoxia in OSA results in myelin and axonal damage as well as alterations in the cellular space that lead to changes in structural network properties in these brain areas.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> In addition, we found that excessive daytime sleepiness is associated with brain connectivity in the left superior frontal areas and right DMN that consists of cingulate, prefrontal, angular, temporal, and parahippocampus areas. The DMN is closely tied to memory performance<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> and the prefrontal cortex sub-serves several cognitive domains.<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> DMN areas are vulnerable to increased amyloid accumulation in older adults who experience daytime sleepiness.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> These findings can be interpreted as one of the mechanisms for cognitive impairment in subjects with daytime sleepiness, especially in the elderly population.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></p>
      <p>The men and women brains show anatomical, functional and biochemical differences across the whole life span.<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> In the present study, we investigated sex differences in brain connectivity related to OSA severity and daytime sleepiness. Men and women had different patterns of brain connectivity related to AHI, ODI, <sub>min</sub>SpO<sub>2</sub> and ESS. AHI and ODI was associated with prefrontal area-related connectivity, left side in women but right side in men. The prefrontal area is involved in decision-making and associated with sex differences in its response to stress.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> Prefrontal lesions impair decision-making by right-sided lesions in men but by left-sided lesion in women.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> In the women, but not in men, AHI and ODI were related to left limbic system-related connectivity. Women have a larger deep limbic system, which has been proposed as one explanation for sex differences in the susceptibility to depression.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> Our findings may help explain why depression is reported more frequently as a presenting symptom in women than men with OSA.<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></p>
      <p>The range of excessive daytime sleepiness across severities of sleep apnea or pathological sleep in general remains a mystery. In our analysis, daytime sleepiness was associated with right prefrontal areas and left DMN-related connectivity in women, but with right DMN-related connectivity in men. Daytime sleepiness contributes to memory and mood impairment in OSA.<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> Interestingly, left and right DMNs are associated with verbal and spatial memory performance, respectively.<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> In women, right prefrontal areas that play a key role in working memory and executive functioning were also associated with excessive daytime sleepiness, and might be related to the decline in OSA-related attention and executive function.<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> Sex effects need to be considered when interpreting neuroimaging studies in OSA.</p>
      <p>In both groups, anterior cingulate-, parietal-, and orbitofrontal-related connections were common brain connections susceptible to daytime sleepiness. These areas are known to be vulnerable to daytime sleepiness and are associated with increasing amyloid accumulation.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Besides these areas, ESS was related to right limbic system and bilateral prefrontal areas-related connectivity in the non-OSA group, but to right DMN and left limbic system-related connectivity in the OSA group. Affected brain connections were more widely distributed in the OSA group. In particular, the hippocampus-related connections were susceptible to daytime sleepiness in the OSA group. Hippocampus damage caused by OSA may lead to worsening daytime sleepiness as well as cognitive impairments.<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></p>
      <p>The present study has several limitations. The DTI data had a limited number of isotropic gradient directions (n = 15) and were measured at a relatively low diffusion weight (b = 1000 s/mm<sup>2</sup>). Thus, the tractography analysis may not be fully resolved in voxels with crossing, kissing, fanning, and curving fiber configurations although we utilized state-of-the-art algorithms.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> This may lead to incorrect and ambiguous estimates of fiber orientation.<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> The sample size (n = 553) in this retrospective and observational study is not large enough to determine the heterogeneity of high dimensional structural brain network data by using the present deep learning technique. To minimize this limitation, we applied data augmentation. Since this approach may also cause model overfitting for the training dataset, our approach needs to be tested and refined in a larger independent sample including other institutional data sets. It is likely that different severities and clinical vs population-based differences exist, which our results do not address, nor the dynamics of network connectivity over time. Racial differences in connectivity and OSA impact will need assessments in a diverse population. Our subjects were a non-clinical population, mostly diagnosed with milder OSA (71.4%). Although our trained model successfully predicted OSA severity and found OSA severity-related brain connections, the number of severe OSA was quite small during the training process. Therefore, since there might be the probability of large absolute error for severe OSA, additional validation is needed for severe OSA. In addition, only 6.2% of our subjects experienced excessive daytime sleepiness (ESS &gt; 10), which may result from underestimation in ESS domains in older adults.<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> Therefore, although our trained model successfully predicted ESS, the number of severe ESS was relatively small during the training process; additional validation is needed for severe subjective sleepiness. Finally, in the present study, we did not compare cognitive performance between groups. Although most brain connections susceptible to OSA severity and daytime sleepiness determined by deep learning model are related to cognitive performance, decline associated with OSA and sleepiness could not be quantitatively explained. It remains an important line of inquiry for future research.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>In summary, the present study provides a novel approach to determine the anatomical blueprint underlying OSA and daytime sleepiness-related brain connectivity in middle and late adulthood. This approach has clinical implications to delineate the mechanism of functional impairment and daytime sleepiness, and to predict the risk of subsequent cognitive impairment in OSA.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>This research is supported by the grants from the Korea Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (2011-E71004-00), from the Basic Science Research Program (NRF-2019R1A2C2086705), and from the Brain Pool Program (NRF-2020H1D3A1A04105299) through the National Research Foundation of Korea, funded by the Ministry of Science and ICT.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006" sec-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>Dr R. J. Thomas reports personal consulting fees from GLG Councils, Guidepoint Global, and Jazz Pharmaceuticals, outside the submitted work. In addition, RJT has a patent ECG-spectrogram with royalties paid by MyCardio, LLC, a patent PAPGAM issued, and a patent Auto CPAP licensed to DeVilbiss-Drive. All other authors declare no potential conflict of interest.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Grandner</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep, health, and society</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Clin</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28159089</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Veasey</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea in adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>380</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>1442</fpage>–<lpage>1449</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMcp1816152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30970189</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lévy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kohler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mcnicholas</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnoea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Dis Primers</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Palomares</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tummala</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Water exchange across the blood-brain barrier in obstructive sleep apnea: an MRI diffusion-weighted pseudo-continuous arterial spin labeling study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neuroimaging</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>900</fpage>–<lpage>905</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jon.12288</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26333175</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baril</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gagnon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Descoteaux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cerebral white matter diffusion properties and free-water with obstructive sleep apnea severity in older adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hum Brain Mapp</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2686</fpage>–<lpage>2701</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.24971</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32166865</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Amyloid burden in obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Alzheimers Dis</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/JAD-161047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28550245</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baril</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gagnon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brayet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Gray matter hypertrophy and thickening with obstructive sleep apnea in middle-aged and older adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>195</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1509</fpage>–<lpage>1518</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201606-1271OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28060546</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Altered structural brain network resulting from white matter injury in obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>zsz120</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsz120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31260533</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Brain structure network analysis in patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e0139055</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0139055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26413809</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sporns</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tononi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kötter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The human connectome: a structural description of the human brain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS Comput Biol</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e42</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.0010042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16201007</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Houston</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Worsnop</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A randomized controlled trial of continuous positive airway pressure in mild obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>165</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>773</fpage>–<lpage>780</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/ajrccm.165.6.2003166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11897643</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mancini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maislin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Continuous positive airway pressure treatment of sleepy patients with milder obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>186</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>677</fpage>–<lpage>683</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201202-0200OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22837377</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Resting-state functional magnetic resonance imaging of high altitude patients with obstructive sleep apnoea hypopnoea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>15546</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-72339-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32968086</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Palomares</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Disrupted functional brain network organization in patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Behav</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e00441</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/brb3.441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27099802</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Topological reorganization of the default mode network in severe male obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>363</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fneur.2018.00363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29951028</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Canessa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Castronovo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cappa</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep apnea: altered brain connectivity underlying a working-memory challenge</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroimage Clin</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>56</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nicl.2018.03.036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30035002</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McLaren</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Daytime sleepiness is associated with decreased default mode network connectivity in both young and cognitively intact elderly subjects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1609</fpage>–<lpage>1615</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.3108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24179292</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Carvallho</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knopman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Excessive daytime sleepiness predicts increased β-amyloid accumulation in non-demented elderly: a longitudinal PiB-PET study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>88</volume>:<page-range>S14.004</page-range>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>White matter structural differences in OSA patients experiencing residual daytime sleepiness with high CPAP use: a non-Gaussian diffusion MRI study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2018.09.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30445240</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nisi</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Brain white matter changes in CPAP-treated obstructive sleep apnea patients with residual sleepiness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Magn Reson Imaging</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1371</fpage>–<lpage>1378</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmri.25463</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27625326</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lecun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bengio</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hinton</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Deep learning</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nature</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>521</volume>(<issue>7553</issue>):<fpage>436</fpage>–<lpage>444</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature14539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26017442</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Simonyan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vedaldi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zisserman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Deep inside convolutional networks: visualising image classification models and saliency maps</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">arXiv Preprint arXiv</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>. Available form: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1312.6034.pdf">https://arxiv.org/pdf/1312.6034.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed September 14,2021.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kawahara</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>BrainNetCNN: convolutional neural networks for brain networks; towards predicting neurodevelopment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroimage</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>146</volume>:<fpage>1038</fpage>–<lpage>1049</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2016.09.046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27693612</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Iber</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ancoli-Israel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chesson</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">The AASM Manual for the Scoring of Sleep and Associated Events: Rules, Terminology and Technical Specifications</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</publisher-name>; <year>2007</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Johns</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A new method for measuring daytime sleepiness: the Epworth sleepiness scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>540</fpage>–<lpage>545</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/14.6.540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1798888</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>JLR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drobnjak</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Towards a comprehensive framework for movement and distortion correction of diffusion MR images: within volume movement</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroimage</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>152</volume>:<fpage>450</fpage>–<lpage>466</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2017.02.085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28284799</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tournier</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Calamante</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Connelly</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Improved probabilistic streamlines tractography by 2nd order integration over fibre orientation distributions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Int Soc Magn Reson Med</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>1670</volume>. Available from:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cds.ismrm.org/protected/10MProceedings/PDFfiles/1670_4298.pdf">https://cds.ismrm.org/protected/10MProceedings/PDFfiles/1670_4298.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed September 14,2021.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tournier</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Calamante</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Connelly</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Anatomically-constrained tractography: improved diffusion MRI streamlines tractography through effective use of anatomical information</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroimage</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>62</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1924</fpage>–<lpage>1938</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2012.06.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22705374</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tzourio-Mazoyer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Landeau</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Papathanassiou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Automated anatomical labeling of activations in SPM using a macroscopic anatomical parcellation of the MNI MRI single-subject brain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroimage</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>289</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/nimg.2001.0978</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11771995</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rubinov</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sporns</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Complex network measures of brain connectivity: uses and interpretations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroimage</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1059</fpage>–<lpage>1069</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2009.10.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19819337</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Achard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bullmore</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Efficiency and cost of economical brain functional networks</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS Comput Biol</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e17</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17274684</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A set of measures of centrality based on betweenness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sociometry</italic></source>. <year>1977</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3033543</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chawla</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bowyer</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>LO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kegelmeyer</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>SMOTE: synthetic minority over-sampling technique</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Artif Intell Res</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>321</fpage>–<lpage>357</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1613/jair.953</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mars</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Neubert</surname><given-names>FX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Noonan</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sallet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Toni</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rushworth</surname><given-names>MFS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>On the relationship between the “default mode network” and the “social brain”</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Hum Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>189</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnhum.2012.00189</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22737119</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macey</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yan-Go</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Abnormal myelin and axonal integrity in recently diagnosed patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>723</fpage>–<lpage>732</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.3578</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24899761</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Anticevic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Repovs</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shulman</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barch</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>When less is more: TPJ and default network deactivation during encoding predicts working memory performance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroimage</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>2638</fpage>–<lpage>2648</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2009.11.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19913622</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Greicius</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krasnow</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reiss</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Menon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Functional connectivity in the resting brain: a network analysis of the default mode hypothesis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>100</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>258</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0135058100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12506194</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>It is not all hormones: alternative explanations for sexual differentiation of the brain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Res</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>1126</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainres.2006.09.105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17101121</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bland</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Der-avakian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Expression of C-Fos and BDNF mRNA in subregions of the prefrontal cortex of male and female rats after acute uncontrollable stress</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Res</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>1051</volume>(<issue>1–2</issue>):<fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainres.2005.05.065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15993862</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tranel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Damasio</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Denburg</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bechara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Does gender play a role in functional asymmetry of ventromedial prefrontal cortex?</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Brain</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>128</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2872</fpage>–<lpage>2881</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awh643</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16195242</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zaidi</surname><given-names>ZF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Gender differences in human brain: a review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Open Anat J</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1877609401002010037</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yaffe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laffan</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep-disordered breathing, hypoxia, and risk of mild cognitive impairment and dementia in older women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Med Assoc</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>306</volume>:<fpage>613</fpage>–<lpage>619</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Guilleminault</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Excessive daytime sleepiness: a challenge for the practising neurologist</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>124</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1482</fpage>–<lpage>1491</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/124.8.1482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11459741</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bayram</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Default mode network lateralization and memory in healthy aging and alzheimer’s disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Alzheimers Dis</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1223</fpage>–<lpage>1234</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/JAD-180541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30412488</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hishikawa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fukui</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cognitive and affective functions associated with insomnia: a population-based study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurol Res</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>331</fpage>–<lpage>336</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01616412.2017.1281200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28181457</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Strohl</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Excessive daytime sleepiness in obstructive sleep apnea. Mechanisms and clinical management</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Am Thorac Soc</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>757</fpage>–<lpage>768</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1513/AnnalsATS.202006-696FR</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33621163</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>FQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Irfanoglu</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Anatomical accuracy of brain connections derived from diffusion MRI tractography is inherently limited</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>111</volume>(<issue>46</issue>):<fpage>16574</fpage>–<lpage>16579</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1405672111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25368179</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Onen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gooneratne</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petit</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Falissard</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Onen</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Limits of the Epworth sleepiness scale in older adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>343</fpage>–<lpage>350</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-012-0700-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22467194</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
