<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34611453</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">8486008</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">329894</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S329894</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Associations of Sleep Insufficiency and Chronotype with Inflammatory Cytokines in College Students</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Zhai et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Zhai et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhai</surname>
            <given-names>Shuang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tao</surname>
            <given-names>Shuman</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>Xiaoyan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zou</surname>
            <given-names>Liwei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Yajuan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0004">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xie</surname>
            <given-names>Yang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Tingting</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Dan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Qu</surname>
            <given-names>Yang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tao</surname>
            <given-names>Fangbiao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Maternal, Child &amp; Adolescent Health, School of Public Health, Anhui Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Hefei</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Nephrology, The Second Hospital of Anhui Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Hefei</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>MOE Key Laboratory of Population Health Across Life Cycle/NHC Key Laboratory of Study on Abnormal Gametes and Reproductive Tract</institution>, <addr-line>Hefei</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>School of Nursing, Anhui Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Hefei</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Shuman Tao <institution>Department of Nephrology, The Second Hospital of Anhui Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Hefei</addr-line>, <addr-line>230601</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country><phone>Tel +86 15077927106</phone> Email shumantao@126.com</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>27</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>13</volume>
      <fpage>1675</fpage>
      <lpage>1685</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2021 Zhai et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Zhai et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p>Sleep insufficiency and circadian rhythm disturbances in college students have become prominent. Current findings show that sleep insufficiency is closely related to inflammation. Studies on the correlation between chronotype and inflammatory factors are still lacking. Therefore, this research intended to examine the relationships between sleep duration, chronotype and inflammatory cytokines in young adults, and to estimate the correlation between chronotype and inflammatory cytokines stratified by sleep duration.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Patients and Methods</title>
          <p>We conducted a cross-sectional study in April and May 2019. Participants were recruited from two colleges located in central China. The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) and the Morning and Evening Questionnaire-5 (MEQ-5) were administered to assess sleep duration and chronotype. Sleep duration less than 7 hours was defined as insufficient sleep. Fasting venous blood was collected to measure plasma levels of inflammatory markers including IL-1β, IL-6, TNF-α and IL-10.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>A total of 723 participants were included in this study, with a mean age of 18.68 years (standard deviation=0.99). After adjusting for confounding factors, the results of generalized linear model showed that sleep insufficiency was positively correlated with IL-1β, TNF-α and IL-10; and evening-types (E-types) were positively associated with the levels of IL-1β and IL-6 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05). Compared to the control group (sleep sufficiency and M-types), there were positive interaction effects of sleep insufficiency and neutral-types (N-types) on the levels of IL-1β, IL-6, TNF-α and IL-10 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05). The hierarchical regression model showed that N-types and E-types were positively correlated to the levels of IL-1β, IL-6, TNF-α and IL-10 among college students with sleep insufficiency (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>The levels of inflammatory markers were higher among college students with sleep insufficiency and E-types. N-types and E-types were positively correlated with IL-1β, IL-6, TNF-α and IL-10 among college students with sleep insufficiency.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>sleep duration</kwd>
        <kwd>circadian rhythm</kwd>
        <kwd>chronic inflammation</kwd>
        <kwd>young adults</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
            <institution-wrap>
              <institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution>
              <institution-id institution-id-type="open-funder-registry">10.13039/501100001809</institution-id>
            </institution-wrap>
          </funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
            <institution-wrap>
              <institution>Anhui Medical University</institution>
              <institution-id institution-id-type="open-funder-registry">10.13039/501100002947</institution-id>
            </institution-wrap>
          </funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
            <institution-wrap>
              <institution>MOE Key Laboratory of Population Health Across Life Cycle</institution>
            </institution-wrap>
          </funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>This study was supported by National Natural Science Foundation of China (81803257, 81773455), Scientific Research of BSKY from Anhui Medical University (XJ201824), and Open Project Program of MOE Key Laboratory of Population Health Across Life Cycle (JK20205).</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="2"/>
        <table-count count="6"/>
        <ref-count count="52"/>
        <page-count count="11"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>College life represents an important transition period for young adults characterized by increased social involvement. During this critical period, lifestyles acquired will affect the future life of young college students.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Insufficient sleep is a serious public health problem in college students.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> It is generally considered that chronotype is one of an expression of circadian rhythm.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> The most common methods of classification used in chronotype is morning-types (M-types), neutral-types (N-types) and evening-types (E-types).<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> M-types prefer to sleep and get up early, and it is most efficient to perform physical and intellectual activities in the morning; E-types prefer to sleep and get up late, and feel and perform better in the afternoon or evening; N-types display between these two types.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Changes in chronotype are primarily characterized by delayed sleep phase syndrome in late adolescence.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Several studies have demonstrated that circadian rhythm disorder also exists at surprising levels in the college students.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Circadian rhythm regulation or adequate sleep is evidently essential for normal metabolic health.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> It has been found that unhealthy sleep habits adversely affect physical, cognitive, emotional and academic well-being.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Specifically, sleep problems affect circadian hormonal profiles and inflammatory markers, and may damage executive function, attention and decision-making capacity.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></p>
      <p>Like many biological processes, sleep is associated with immunity and inflammation and changes in circulating immune cells.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Inflammation is a process by which the body responds to injury or infection.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Cytokines are proved to be biomarkers of chronic low-grade inflammation which transmitting information from the immune system, regulating the inflammatory processes and mediating local and systemic reactions.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Interleukin-10 (IL-10),<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> interleukin-1β (IL-1β),<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> interleukin-6 (IL-6),<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> and tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α)<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> are important cytokines involved in chronic inflammation. IL-10 is generally considered to be an anti-inflammatory cytokine, which can inhibit the production of pro-inflammatory markers.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Sleep duration has been suggested to be related to an increased risk of cardiovascular morbidity, neurocognitive impairment, diabetes and mortality. Inflammation is considered to be one of the main associations between sleep duration or sleep disorders and these illnesses.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> Unfortunately, there are currently rare research on the relationship between chronotype and inflammatory factors.</p>
      <p>Rarely, investigation on the interaction between sleep duration and chronotype, and limited substantive evidence on the interaction effects of them on inflammation in college students. Research reported that daytime sleepiness and E-types were related to self-regulation.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Investigation has revealed that in adolescents with insomnia, shorter sleep duration was associated with increased levels of inflammation.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> What is more, a survey in the United States showed that the combined effects of adolescents’ sleep duration and quality were predictors of adolescents’ social mood adjustment.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> On the contrary, a Swedish study showed that there was no interaction between adolescents’ sleep duration and sleep problems on health.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></p>
      <p>To be sure, it is imperative to examine the interaction between sleep duration and chronotype, which can promote the health and function of the entire life process. Therefore, a cross-sectional study was conducted to make inquiries about the relationships between sleep duration, chronotype and its interaction effects on inflammatory cytokines among college students in China.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants and Procedure</title>
        <p>Participants were enrolled in the College Student Behavior and Health Cohort Study, which is an ongoing cohort designed to track behaviors, physical and mental health in college students from the first year to the third year in China. Baseline data was analyzed in the present study. Participants were selected from a medical university located in Hefei, Anhui Province and a distinguished federated university situated in Shangrao, Jiangxi Province between April and May 2019. Cluster random sampling was used, with the faculty as the primary sampling unit. The baseline survey consisted of electronic questionnaires scanned with smartphones and physical examination. We received a total of 1135 valid questionnaires that collected baseline information on sociodemographic and health-related factors, and the response rate was 98.6%. Blood samples were collected in 771 students. Finally, a total of 723 valid respondents both have survey data and blood samples were analyzed. The study protocol was approved by the Ethics Committee of Anhui Medical University (No. 20170291). Written informed consents were obtained from all participants before completing the survey, which was conducted in accordance with the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Measures</title>
        <sec id="s0002-s2002-s3001">
          <title>Demographic Factors</title>
          <p>Sociodemographic data were collected by questionnaire, including gender, age, height, weight, residential area (rural or urban), any siblings (yes or no), self-reported family economy (low, medium or high), self-rated health (high, medium or low), parental education level (primary school and below, middle school or senior high school and above).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2002-s3002">
          <title>Sleep Duration and Chronotype</title>
          <p>Sleep duration during the past month was assessed by a question in the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI): “During the past month, how many hours of actual sleep did you get at night?”.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> According to sleep time duration recommendations proposed by National Sleep Foundation of America, the appropriate sleep duration for young adults (18–25 years) is between 7 and 9 hours. Therefore, responses were categorized into two groups: less than 7 hours (sleep insufficiency) and 7 hours or more (sleep sufficiency).<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> The Morning and Evening Questionnaire-5 (MEQ-5) was well validated and used as a self-reported measurement of chronotype.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> The MEQ-5 questionnaire comprised five items, which evaluated the habit of sleep among participants. In accordance with total scores (4 to 25 points), chronotype could be parted into three groups including evening-types (4 to 11 points), neutral-types (12 to 17 points), and morning-types (18 to 25 points).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2002-s3003">
          <title>Inflammatory Cytokines</title>
          <p>Laboratory analyses were performed on blood samples to evaluate IL-1β, IL-6, TNF-α and IL-10, as systemic inflammatory markers. During the physical examination, 5 mL of fasting venous blood samples were collected on 6:00 to 8:00 in the morning using vacuum blood collection tube with anticoagulant (EDTA). The blood samples were centrifuged for 10 min at a set speed of 3000 revolutions per minute within 2 hours. The upper plasma samples were stored at −80°C. Liquid-phase protein suspension chip (Luminex) was used in the detection process. Plasma inflammatory markers were detected by multi-bead enzyme-free analyzer MILLIPLEX <sup>®</sup> MAP instrument (Merck Millipore). Within the analysis of variation, the intra-assay coefficient of variation of IL-1β, IL-6, TNF-α and IL-10 were all &lt;5%, and the inter-assay coefficient of variation were &lt;15%, &lt;20%, &lt;15%, &lt;20%, respectively. The assay had a lower detection limit of IL-1β, IL-6, TNF-α and IL-10 of 0.14 pg/mL, 0.11 pg/mL, 0.16 pg/mL, 0.56 pg/mL, respectively. All inflammatory markers were log transformed to settle skewness.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2002-s3004">
          <title>Covariates</title>
          <p>Health behaviors included cigarette use, alcohol use, physical activity, afternoon napping and symptoms of depression. Two questions from the Young Risk Behavior Surveillance System questionnaire were modified to measure current cigarette and alcohol use.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Cigarette use was measured by “How many days did you smoke during the past month?” Alcohol use was measured by “How many days did you have at least one drink during the past month?” The answers are recoded into “yes” or “no”. Physical activity was assessed using International Physical Activity Questionnaire Short Form (IPAQ-SF) was used to measure physical activity.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> Physical activity level was divided into 3 categories: low, moderate and high. Afternoon napping was measured by “Are you in the habit of taking afternoon napping?” and answers are recoded into “yes” or “no”.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Symptoms of depression were measured by the Patient Health Questionnaire 9 (PHQ-9).<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> PHQ-9 was used to screen for depressive symptoms during the last 2 weeks, which contains 9 items. The total score (0 to 27 points) was divided into a dichotomous variable with a critical value of 4 points.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2002-s3005">
          <title>Statistical Analyses</title>
          <p>All statistical analyzes were conducted using SPSS version 23.0 (SPSS, Chicago, IL, USA). Continuous variables of the normal distribution in present study were represented as mean and standard deviation (SD), while categorical variables were summarized using frequencies (n) and percentages (%). Two independent sample <italic>t</italic>-test, and Chi-square tests were used to assess the demographic characteristics stratified by sleep duration. ANOVA was performed to assess the differences in levels of inflammatory factors between chronotype. The generalized linear models we performed were to investigate the relationships between sleep duration, chronotype and inflammatory factors. We also introduced the interactive terms of sleep duration * chronotype. Regression coefficients were measured for the explanatory factors, adjusting for age, self-rated health, physical activity, afternoon napping and depressive symptoms. Existing findings showed that E-types were characterized by late bedtimes and greater physical and mental activity in the evening and cause more sleep problems, worse sleep quality, and more behavioral problems compared to M-types. Therefore, the healthier group, M-types were recognized as the control group.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> All statistical tests were two-sided and significance was set at <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Participant Characteristics</title>
        <p><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> manifests the demographic descriptive information of 723 participants (32.9% males and 67.1% females) aged 16–26 years old (M=18.68, SD=0.99). Of the 723 participants, the proportion of sleep insufficiency were 56.2%. The proportions of M-types, N-types and E-types were 14.8%, 74.8% and 10.4% among college students. Nevertheless, no sex-based difference was found in sleep duration (<italic>p</italic>=0.955). There were no significant differences on BMI (<italic>p</italic>=0.080), residential area (<italic>p</italic>=0.202), any siblings (<italic>p</italic>=0.717), self-reported family economy (<italic>p</italic>=0.361), parental educational level (<italic>p</italic>=0.944; <italic>p</italic>=0.464), cigarette use (<italic>p</italic>=0.185) and alcohol use (<italic>p</italic>=0.942) between different groups of sleep duration. College students with higher age, lower self-rated health status, having a nap habit, lower level of physical activity or suffering from depressive symptoms were more likely to experience sleep insufficiency (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05). The mean level of IL-1β, IL-6, TNF-α and IL-10 were 0.32±0.26 pg/mL, 0.72±0.32 pg/mL, 0.77±0.21 pg/mL and 1.92±0.31 pg/mL, respectively. There were statistical differences in the levels of all inflammatory cytokines in this study among sleep duration.<table-wrap id="t0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of the Study Sample</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Sample (n=723)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Sufficiency (n=317)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Insufficiency (n=406)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>χ</italic><sup>2/</sup><italic>t</italic> value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">238 (32.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104 (43.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">134 (56.3)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.003</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.955</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">485 (67.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">213 (43.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">272 (56.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Age, mean±SE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.68±0.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.81±1.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.57±0.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.257</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> BMI, mean±SE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.73±2.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.54±2.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.84±2.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.752</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.080</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Residential area</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Rural</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">407 (56.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">170 (41.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">237 (58.2)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">1.630</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.202</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Urban</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">316 (43.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">147 (46.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">169 (53.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any siblings</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">185 (25.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79 (42.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106 (57.3)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.132</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.717</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">538 (74.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">238 (44.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">300 (55.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported family economy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">160 (22.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (46.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (53.1)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">2.040</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.361</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Medium</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">525 (72.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">229 (43.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">296 (56.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> High</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (5.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-rated health</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> High</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">435 (60.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">208 (47.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">227 (52.2)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">11.242</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Medium</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">265 (36.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105 (39.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">160 (60.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (3.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (17.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (82.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Father’s education level</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Primary school and below</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">160 (22.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (45.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88 (55.0)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.114</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.944</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Middle school</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">350 (48.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">152 (43.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">198 (56.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Senior high school and above</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">213 (29.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93 (43.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120 (56.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mother’s education level</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Primary school and below</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">322 (44.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">140 (43.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">182 (56.5)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">1.534</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.464</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Middle school</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">249 (34.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104 (41.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">145 (58.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Senior high school and above</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">152 (21.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (48.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79 (52.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cigarette use</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">678 (93.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">293 (43.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">385 (56.8)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">1.755</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.185</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (6.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (53.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (46.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol use</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">567 (78.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">249 (43.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">318 (56.1)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.005</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.942</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">156 (21.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (43.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88 (56.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical activity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> High</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">212 (29.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (42.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (57.8)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">16.263</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Medium</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">395 (54.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">151 (38.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">244 (61.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">116 (16.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">117 (55.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95 (44.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Afternoon napping</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">631 (87.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">263 (41.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">368 (58.3)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">9.442</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (12.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (58.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (41.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depressive symptoms</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">433 (59.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">208 (48.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">225 (52.0)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">7.704</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">290 (40.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109 (37.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">181 (62.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronotype</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> M-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107 (14.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (60.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (39.3)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">20.353</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> N-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">541 (74.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">231 (42.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">310 (57.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> E-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (10.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (28.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (72.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inflammatory cytokines, mean±SE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> IL-1β</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32±0.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27±0.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36±0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.418</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> IL-6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72±0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70±0.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74±0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.997</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> TNF-α</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77±0.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74±0.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79±0.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.549</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> IL-10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.92±0.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.86±0.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.97±0.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.742</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Note</bold>: Inflammatory factors were log-transformed before analysis.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: SE, Standard Error; BMI, body mass index; M-types, Morning-types; N-types, Neutral -types; E-types, Evening-types; IL-1β, interleukin-1β; IL-6, interleukin-6; TNF-α, tumor necrosis factor-α; IL-10, interleukin-10.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>The Comparison of Inflammatory Cytokines Among Different Groups of Sleep Duration or Chronotype</title>
        <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref> shows the comparison of inflammatory cytokines among different groups of sleep duration or chronotype. There were statistical differences in the levels of IL-1β, IL-6, TNF-α and IL-10 in this study among different groups of sleep duration or chronotype (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05). Further, the levels of IL-1β, IL-6 and TNF-α and IL-10 were significant higher in sleep insufficiency and E-types group.<fig id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The comparison of inflammatory cytokines among different groups of sleep duration or chronotype.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-1675-g0001"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: Results are presented as mean and standard deviation, (<bold>A</bold>–<bold>D</bold>) show the difference in the levels of IL-1β, IL-6, TNF-α and IL-10 between sufficient sleep group and insufficient sleep group, (<bold>E</bold>–<bold>H</bold>) show the difference in the levels of IL-1β, IL-6, TNF-α and IL-10 among different chrontype; inflammatory cytokines were log-transformed before analysis; *<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05, **<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.01.</attrib><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: IL-1β, interleukin-1β; IL-6, interleukin-6; TNF-α, tumor necrosis factor-α; IL-10, interleukin-10; M-types, Morning-types; N-types, Neutral-types; E-types, Evening-types.</attrib></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Generalized Linear Model Analysis of Sleep Duration, Chronotype and Inflammatory Cytokines</title>
        <p><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> describes the results of sleep duration, chronotype and inflammatory cytokines analysis using the generalized linear model. The results indicated that inflammatory cytokines were statistically positively correlated with sleep duration or chronotype. After controlling for age, self-rated health, physical activity, afternoon napping, and depressive symptoms, the level of inflammatory cytokines were higher in sleep insufficiency group (IL-1β: B=0.064, <italic>p</italic>=0.001; TNF-α: B=0.042, <italic>p</italic>=0.008; IL-10: B=0.089, <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001). The levels of inflammatory cytokines were higher in E-types (IL-1β: B=0.096, <italic>p</italic>=0.013; IL-6: B=0.125, <italic>p</italic>=0.009).<table-wrap id="t0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Generalized Linear Models of Sleep Duration, Chronotype and Inflammatory Cytokines</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Inflammatory Cytokines</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Crude Model</th><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Adjusted Model</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>B</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>B</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="10" colspan="1">IL-1β</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Duration</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥ 7 h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt; 7 h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.085</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.048–0.123</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.064</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026–0.102</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronotype</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> M-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> N-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.072</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019–0.126</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.007–0.100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.091</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> E-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.131</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.055–0.208</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020–0.173</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Duration * Chronotype</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sleep insufficiency* N-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.150</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.043–0.258</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.144</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038–0.250</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sleep insufficiency* E-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.113</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.049–0.274</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.173</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.092</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.067–0.251</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.257</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="10" colspan="1">IL-6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥ 7 h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt; 7 h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.048</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001–0.094</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.023–0.071</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.316</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronotype</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> M-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> N-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.079</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014–0.145</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.054</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.012–0.120</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.110</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> E-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.158</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.065–0.251</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031–0.220</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Duration * Chronotype</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sleep insufficiency* N-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.201</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.068–0.334</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.197</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.065–0.328</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sleep insufficiency* E-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.132</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.067–0.331</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.194</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.113</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.083–0.310</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.258</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="10" colspan="1">TNF-α</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Duration</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥ 7 h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt; 7 h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.055</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025–0.086</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011–0.073</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronotype</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> M-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> N-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.050</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007–0.093</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.011–0.076</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.142</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> E-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.079</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017–0.140</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.055</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.007–0.117</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.084</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Duration * Chronotype</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sleep insufficiency* N-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.141</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.054–0.228</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.140</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.054–0.226</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sleep insufficiency* E-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.141</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011–0.272</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.001–0.258</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.052</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="10" colspan="1">IL-10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥ 7 h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt; 7 h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.110</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.065–0.156</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.089</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.043–0.135</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronotype</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> M-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> N-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.074</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009–0.138</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.026–0.104</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.240</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> E-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.112</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020–0.204</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.066</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.027–0.159</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.162</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration * Chronotype</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sleep insufficiency* N-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.194</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.064–0.324</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.190</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.062–0.318</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sleep insufficiency* E-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.198</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003–0.394</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.184</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.008–0.376</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Crude model was not adjusted by any variables, adjusted model was adjusted by age, self-rated health, physical activity, afternoon napping, and depressive symptoms; Sleep duration * Chronotype indicated the multiplicative interaction between sleep duration and chronotype; inflammatory factors were log-transformed before analysis.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: B, regression coefficient; CI, confidence interval; IL-1β, interleukin-1β; IL-6, interleukin-6; TNF-α, tumor necrosis factor-α; IL-10, interleukin-10; M-types, Morning-types; N-types, Neutral -types; E-types, Evening-types.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
        <p>The interaction effects of sleep duration and chronotype on inflammatory cytokines are shown in <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Crude and adjusted models showed that among college students sleep duration and chronotype had a positive multiplicative interaction effect on inflammatory cytokines. Compared to the reference group (sleep sufficiency and M-types), students with sleep insufficiency and N-types were more likely to be with higher levels of inflammatory markers including IL-1β (B=0.144, <italic>p</italic>=0.008), IL-6 (B=0.197, <italic>p</italic>=0.003), TNF-α (B=0.140, <italic>p</italic>=0.001) and IL-10 (B=0.190, <italic>p</italic>=0.004).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Generalized Linear Models of the Associations Between Chronotype and Inflammatory Cytokines Stratified by Sleep Duration</title>
        <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2</xref> shows the results of the generalized linear models of the connections between chronotype and inflammatory cytokines stratified by sleep duration. E-types were statistically positively correlated with the levels of inflammatory markers in students with sleep insufficiency. After controlling for age, self-rated health, physical activity, afternoon napping, and depressive symptoms, N-types (IL-1β: B=0.117, <italic>p</italic>=0.004; IL-6: B=0.161, <italic>p</italic>=0.001; TNF-α: B=0.107, <italic>p</italic>=0.001; IL-10: B=0.135, <italic>p</italic>=0.003) and E-types (IL-1β: B=0.139, <italic>p</italic>=0.006; IL-6: B=0.201, <italic>p</italic>=0.001; TNF-α: B=0.119, <italic>p</italic>=0.003; IL-10: B=0.146, <italic>p</italic>=0.012) were statistically positively correlated with the level of inflammatory markers in college students reported sleep insufficiency.<fig id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Generalized linear models of the associations between chronotype and inflammatory cytokines stratified by sleep duration.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-1675-g0002"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: The black icon indicated the sufficient sleep group (≥7 h), the gray icon indicated the insufficient sleep group (&lt;7 h); crude model was not adjusted by any variables, adjusted model was adjusted by age, self-rated health, physical activity, afternoon napping, and depression; inflammatory factors were log-transformed before analysis.</attrib><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: CI, confidence interval; IL-1β, interleukin-1β; IL-6, interleukin-6; TNF-α, tumor necrosis factor-α; IL-10, interleukin-10; M-types, Morning-types; N-types, Neutral-types; E-types, Evening-types.</attrib></fig></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>As far as we know, this is the first study to investigate the independent effects of sleep duration, chronotype and combination of them in relation to inflammation in college students’ crowd. The findings suggested that sleep insufficiency and E-types were positively related to the level of inflammatory markers. Furthermore, we confirmed the interaction effects of sleep insufficiency and E-types on the level of inflammatory markers among Chinese college students. The paradox is that sleep duration and chronotype were positively associated with IL-10, which is considered an anti-inflammatory cytokine under most circumstances.</p>
      <p>We observed that 56.2% of participants reported sleep insufficiency, which was lower than in previous studies.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> Furthermore, the proportion of M-types, N-types and E-types among college students was 14.8%, 74.8% and 10.4%, respectively. Similarly, in another investigation of 1st-year college students, the distribution of chronotype also got consistent results.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Moreover, the percentage of sleep insufficiency in E-types students was 72.0%, which was higher than that of M-types (39.7%) and N-types (57.3%). The current results were compatible with formerly covered in Korean adolescents as well.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></p>
      <p>College students should represent a specially and huge group in society. The lifestyles developed during college period could have a broad and profound impact on health such as immune system.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Inflammation underlies widely various physiological and pathological processes.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> Inflammation mechanism is an important defense mechanism for the body to restore homeostasis and tissue function and exists in most non-communicable chronic diseases.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> The present study indicated that sleep insufficiency was related to higher levels of inflammatory factors including IL-1β, TNF-α and IL-10, which is consistent with other studies.<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> In addition, we also found that E-types were statistically related to higher levels of IL-1β and IL-6. Yet little research has examined the effect of chronotype on inflammation in college students. Recently, there was a pilot study on the role of inflammatory factors in sleep, circadian preference, and health found that in adolescents with higher CRP, shorter sleep duration was associated with greater emotional health risks; however, among adolescents with higher IL-6, small effect size simple slopes were observed between evening preference and behavior.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></p>
      <p>A major finding of this present research was that N-types and E-types were only associated with elevated levels of inflammatory factors in college students with insufficient sleep. Short sleep duration has been proved to be with systemic Inflammation in young adults.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> Sleep duration and chronotype are interconnected. A large school-based study showed that none of the chronotype met the minimum recommended amount of sleep duration on school nights; and E-types had shorter school day sleep duration than M-types, with N-types displaying a moderate sleep duration between these two extremes.<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> Perhaps this is why compare to M-types, N-types and E-types were only associated with elevated levels of inflammatory factors, and the correlation sizes of N-types on inflammatory factors were lower than those of E-types. Insufficient sleep is strongly associated with sympathetic activation, and elevated levels of epinephrine and norepinephrine could be served as its evidence.<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> The changes in the levels of these two nerve mediators may be caused in part by stimulation of leukocyte adrenergic receptors and activation of nuclear factor (NF)-κB-mediated NLRP3 inflammasome inflammatory signaling pathways.<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> Likewise, it has been posited that circadian rhythm disorder triggers an immune cascade that eventually activates inflammatory factors, which are general markers of systemic inflammation.<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> For this reason, the results of this study further support the proposal that sleep is related to inflammation. Future research should explore the associations of sleep insufficiency and chronotype with activation of the sympathetic nervous system.</p>
      <p>In the present investigation, it was extraordinary that insufficient sleep or E-types was associated with higher levels of IL10, and IL-10 was considered to be an anti-inflammatory cytokine in most instances. Nevertheless, some studies have also found contradictory results for IL-10.<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> However, similar results were obtained when the circadian rhythm was disturbed. IL-10 was decreased due to circadian misalignment in a randomized controlled trial of adults in the United States.<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> One potential explanation is that IL-10 may require cofactors to function as an anti-inflammatory mediator.<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> Moreover, IL-10 has different signaling mechanism pathways for each subset of immune cells.<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> Recently, the possibility of pro-inflammation of IL-10 has been reported. For example, when used during cancer treatment, it may be pro-inflammatory.<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref> Thus, additional rigorous scientific research is needed to better clarify the potential and vital role of IL-10 in the relationship between sleep and immune system.</p>
      <p>One of the advantages of the present study was a multitude of sample of Chinese college students as participants, which may cause our findings more compelling. Moreover, we explored the interactions between sleep duration and chronotype on the level of inflammation, and further stratified by sleep duration, which more accurately estimate the relationship of them. Last but not least, we analyzed the relationships between a variety of inflammatory biomarkers, not just one, sleep duration and chronotype that make the results more convincing. Nonetheless, the following restrictions were recognized in this research. Firstly, our research was not a longitudinal study that has limitation in determining the causal relationship of sleep duration, chronotype and inflammation among college students. Our research is still ongoing and further longitudinal analysis will be performed in the future. Secondly, data of sleep pattern were based on subjective responses of college students, which were not able to avoid recall bias. Further studies should be undertaken, including more objective measures of sleep patterns such as polysomnography and actigraphy.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Our findings suggested that sleep insufficiency, N-types and E-types were positively associated with inflammation. In addition, N-types and E-types were particularly related to inflammation factors among Chinese college students with sleep insufficiency. Inflammation may be an intermediate mechanism between sleep and health in college students. The present findings should be replicated in longitudinal studies to determine the direction of this association. Our study provides evidence that maintaining a healthy sleep pattern, such as getting enough sleep duration and maintaining a healthy routine, are advantageous to healthy development in college students.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>The authors sincerely thank the consent of data access from College Student Behavior and Health Cohort Study, carried out by the Institute of Anhui Medical University, and all participants involved in this study for their full support.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <p>BMI, body mass index; B, regression coefficient; CI, confidence interval; IL-10, interleukin-10; IL-1β, interleukin-1β; IL-6, interleukin-6; TNF-α, tumor necrosis factor-α; M-types, Morning-types; N-types, Neutral-types; E-types, Evening-types.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007" sec-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of physical activity, sedentary time, and sleep duration on the health-related quality of life of college students in Northeast China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Health Qual Life Outcomes</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>124</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12955-019-1194-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31311564</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Glavin</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matthew</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spaeth</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Gender differences in the relationship between exercise, sleep, and mood in young adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Health Educ Behav</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1090198120986782</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1090198120986782</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Horne</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ostberg</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A self-assessment questionnaire to determine morningness-eveningness in human circadian rhythms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Chronobiol</italic></source>. <year>1976</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>110</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1027738</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vitale</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roveda</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Montaruli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Chronotype influences activity circadian rhythm and sleep: differences in sleep quality between weekdays and weekend</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chronobiol Int</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>405</fpage>–<lpage>415</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/07420528.2014.986273</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25469597</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Haraden</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mullin</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hankin</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The relationship between depression and chronotype: a longitudinal assessment during childhood and adolescence</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Depress Anxiety</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>967</fpage>–<lpage>976</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/da.22682</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28884932</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Carskadon</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Acebo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between puberty and delayed phase preference</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>258</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/16.3.258</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8506460</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reider</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whiting</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Prichard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep patterns and predictors of disturbed sleep in a large population of college students</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Adolesc Health</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>124</fpage>–<lpage>132</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jadohealth.2009.06.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20113918</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Christian</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Polivka</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep behaviors in traditional-age college students: a state of the science review with implications for practice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Assoc Nurse Pract</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>695</fpage>–<lpage>703</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/2327-6924.12520</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28981991</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Depner</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stothard</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Metabolic consequences of sleep and circadian disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Diab Rep</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>507</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11892-014-0507-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24816752</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Humphries</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bath</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dysfunctional beliefs, sleep hygiene and sleep quality in university students</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Health Promot J Austr</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hpja.471</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Choshen-Hillel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ishqer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mahameed</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Acute and chronic sleep deprivation in residents: cognition and stress biomarkers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Med Educ</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>174</fpage>–<lpage>184</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/medu.14296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32697336</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Immunity and inflammation in atherosclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circ Res</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>124</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>315</fpage>–<lpage>327</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.118.313591</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30653442</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Besedovsky</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haack</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The sleep-immune crosstalk in health and disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiol Rev</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1325</fpage>–<lpage>1380</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physrev.00010.2018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30920354</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dimitrov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Born</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of sleep and circadian rhythm on the human immune system</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann N Y Acad Sci</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>1193</volume>:<fpage>48</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1749-6632.2009.05300.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20398008</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rethorst</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Toups</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carmody</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trivedi</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>IL-1β and BDNF are associated with improvement in hypersomnia but not insomnia following exercise in major depressive disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Transl Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e611</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/tp.2015.104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26241349</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rohleder</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aringer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boentert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Role of interleukin-6 in stress, sleep, and fatigue</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann N Y Acad Sci</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>1261</volume>:<fpage>88</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1749-6632.2012.06634.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22823398</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rockstrom</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taishi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Tumor necrosis factor alpha in sleep regulation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2017.10.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29153862</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Garra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>IL-10 family cytokines IL-10 and IL-22: from basic science to clinical translation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Immunity</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>871</fpage>–<lpage>891</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2019.03.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30995504</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Why sleep is important for health: a psychoneuroimmunology perspective</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Annu Rev Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>172</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-psych-010213-115205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25061767</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dearth-Wesley</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lewin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gioia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whitaker</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Self-regulation and sleep duration, sleepiness, and chronotype in adolescents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatrics</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>138</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e20161406</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2016-1406</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27940688</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fernandez-Mendoza</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vgontzas</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gaines</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bixler</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia symptoms with objective short sleep duration are associated with systemic inflammation in adolescents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Behav Immun</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>110</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2016.12.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28041986</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>El-Sheikh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saini</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gillis</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Interactions between sleep duration and quality as predictors of adolescents’ adjustment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Health</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>180</fpage>–<lpage>186</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleh.2018.11.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30928119</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Norell-Clarke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hagquist</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Child and adolescent sleep duration recommendations in relation to psychological and somatic complaints based on data between 1985 and 2013 from 11 to 15 year-olds</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Adolesc</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>68</volume>:<fpage>12</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.adolescence.2018.07.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30007217</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buysse</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monk</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kupfer</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0165-1781(89)90047-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2748771</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hirshkowitz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whiton</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>National Sleep Foundation’s sleep time duration recommendations: methodology and results summary</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Health</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleh.2014.12.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29073412</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kanagarajan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Antinora</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Morningness-Eveningness questionnaire in bipolar disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>262</volume>:<fpage>102</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2018.02.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29427910</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McManus</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Youth risk behavior surveillance - United States, 2015</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">MMWR Surveill Summ</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.ss6506a1</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nolan</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raynor</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>May</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Self-reported physical activity using the international physical activity questionnaire (IPAQ) in Australian adults with type 2 diabetes, with and without peripheral neuropathy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Can J Diabetes</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>576</fpage>–<lpage>579</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcjd.2016.05.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27658764</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kroenke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spitzer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The PHQ-9 validity of a brief depression severity measure</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Gen Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>606</fpage>–<lpage>613</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1525-1497.2001.016009606.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11556941</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep patterns and their association with depression and behavior problems among Chinese adolescents in different grades</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psych J</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pchj.189</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29278311</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Chronotype, sleep, and depressive symptoms among Chinese college students: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>592825</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fneur.2020.592825</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33391156</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration and sleep patterns in Chinese university students: a comprehensive meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1153</fpage>–<lpage>1162</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.6760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28859718</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Chronotype and depressive symptoms: a moderated mediation model of sleep quality and resilience in the 1st-year college students</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>77</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>340</fpage>–<lpage>355</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jclp.23037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32761628</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yim</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hwangbo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between eveningness preference, socio-behavioral factors, and insomnia symptoms in Korean adolescents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>82</volume>:<fpage>144</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2021.03.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33915430</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Medzhitov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Origin and physiological roles of inflammation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nature</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>454</volume>(<issue>7203</issue>):<fpage>428</fpage>–<lpage>435</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature07201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18650913</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Arulselvan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fard</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Role of antioxidants and natural products in inflammation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Oxid Med Cell Longev</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>2016</volume>:<fpage>5276130</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2016/5276130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27803762</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Clinton</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zielinski</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jewett</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Biochemical regulation of sleep and sleep biomarkers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>5 Suppl</issue>):<fpage>S38</fpage>–<lpage>S42</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/JCSM.1360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22003330</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Taraz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khatami</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hajiseyedjavadi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association between antiinflammatory cytokine, IL-10, and sleep quality in patients on maintenance hemodialysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hemodial Int</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>382</fpage>–<lpage>390</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/hdi.12035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23490309</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dolsen</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>IL-6, sTNF-R2, and CRP in the context of sleep, circadian preference, and health in adolescents with eveningness chronotype: cross-sectional and longitudinal treatment effects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychoneuroendocrinology</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>129</volume>:<fpage>105241</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psyneuen.2021.105241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33932814</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bakour</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Rourke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration trajectories and systemic inflammation in young adults: results from the national longitudinal study of adolescent to adult health (add health)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>zsx156</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsx156</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bower</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep and inflammation during adolescents’ transition to young adulthood</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Adolesc Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>821</fpage>–<lpage>828</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jadohealth.2020.04.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32586679</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Saxvig</surname><given-names>IW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Evanger</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pallesen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Circadian typology and implications for adolescent sleep health. Results from a large, cross-sectional, school-based study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>83</volume>:<fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2021.04.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33990068</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Floam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nemeth</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scott-Sutherland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gautam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haack</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep characteristics as predictor variables of stress systems markers in insomnia disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>296</fpage>–<lpage>304</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25524529</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fernandez-Mendoza</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vgontzas</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia symptoms, objective sleep duration and hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal activity in children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Clin Invest</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>493</fpage>–<lpage>500</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/eci.12263</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24635035</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep loss activates cellular inflammatory signaling</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biol Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>538</fpage>–<lpage>540</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2008.05.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18561896</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jeltema</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The NLRP3 inflammasome: an overview of mechanisms of activation and regulation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Mol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>3328</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms20133328</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Scheiermann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kunisaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frenette</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Circadian control of the immune system</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Immunol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>190</fpage>–<lpage>198</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nri3386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23391992</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Figueiredo-Braga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cornaby</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cortez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Influence of biological therapeutics, cytokines, and disease activity on depression in rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Immunol Res</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>2018</volume>:<fpage>5954897</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2018/5954897</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30148175</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drake</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Influence of sleep deprivation and circadian misalignment on cortisol, inflammatory markers, and cytokine balance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Behav Immun</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>24</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2015.01.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25640603</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Anti-inflammatory effects of IL-4 and IL-10 on human polymorphonuclear leukocytes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Korean Med Sci</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3346/jkms.2002.17.1.7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11850581</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sanjabi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zenewicz</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kamanaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Flavell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Anti-inflammatory and pro-inflammatory roles of TGF-β, IL-10, and IL-22 in immunity and autoimmunity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Opin Pharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>447</fpage>–<lpage>453</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coph.2009.04.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19481975</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mocellin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Panelli</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nagorsen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marincola</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The dual role of IL-10</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Trends Immunol</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s1471-4906(02)00009-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12495723</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
