<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34675725</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">8517637</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">327478</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S327478</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>The Association of Obstructive Sleep Apnea and Nocturnal Hypoxemia with Lipid Profiles in a Population-Based Study of Community-Dwelling Australian Men</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Guscoth et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Guscoth et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4917-0425</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Guscoth</surname>
            <given-names>Layla B</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7292-9714</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Appleton</surname>
            <given-names>Sarah L</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Martin</surname>
            <given-names>Sean A</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7572-0796</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Adams</surname>
            <given-names>Robert J</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3051-7313</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Melaku</surname>
            <given-names>Yohannes A</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wittert</surname>
            <given-names>Gary A</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Freemasons Centre for Male Health and Well-Being, South Australian Health and Medical Research Institute and Faculty of Health and Medical Sciences, University of Adelaide</institution>, <addr-line>Adelaide</addr-line>, <addr-line>South Australia</addr-line>, <addr-line>5000</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Flinders Health and Medical Research Institute (Sleep Health, Formerly the Adelaide Institute for Sleep Health) A Flinders Centre of Research Excellence, Flinders University</institution>, <addr-line>Adelaide</addr-line>, <addr-line>South Australia</addr-line>, <addr-line>5042</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Sarah L Appleton <institution>Flinders Health and Medical Research Institute (Sleep Health, formerly the Adelaide Institute for Sleep Health) A Flinders Centre of Research Excellence, Flinders University</institution>, <addr-line>Bedford Park</addr-line>, <addr-line>Adelaide</addr-line>, <addr-line>South Australia</addr-line>, <addr-line>5042</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country> Email sarah.appleton@flinders.edu.au</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>08</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>13</volume>
      <fpage>1771</fpage>
      <lpage>1782</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>06</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2021 Guscoth et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Guscoth et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Objective</title>
          <p>To determine the association of obstructive sleep apnea and nocturnal hypoxemia with serum lipid profiles in unselected community-dwelling men.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>Cross-sectional data from participants of the Men Androgen Inflammation Lifestyle Environment and Stress (MAILES) study (n=753) who underwent full in-home polysomnography (Embletta X100) was used. Triglycerides, high- (HDL), low-density lipoprotein (LDL), and total cholesterol were assessed on a fasting morning blood sample. Multivariable linear regression analyses assessed associations between lipids and continuous measures of nocturnal hypoxemia (oxygen desaturation index (3%) (ODI), apnea–hypopnea index (AHI), and rapid eye movement sleep apnea–hypopnea index (REM-AHI)), adjusted for chronic conditions, risk behavior and sociodemographic factors. Sensitivity analyses examined the effect of lipid lowering therapies on reported estimates. Effect modification was examined through stratification by waist circumference groups.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>In 753 participants with mean (SD) age of 60.8 (10.9) years and waist circumference: 99.3 (11.6) cm, the prevalence of OSA (AHI≥10) was 52.6%. Overall, no significant associations between OSA metrics and lipid measures were found. Similarly, sensitivity analysis excluding lipid lowering therapies showed no significant associations. In analysis stratified by waist circumference (&lt;95cm, 95–100cm, &gt;100cm), ODI (3%, unstandardized B: 0.027, 95% CI: 0.015–0.040), AHI (0.023, 0.012–0.033) and AHI<sub>REM</sub> (0.012, 0.001–0.022) were positively associated with serum triglycerides in participants with a normal waist circumference (&lt;95cm).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>Obstructive sleep apnea metrics were positively associated with serum triglyceride levels in men with a normal waist circumference. Healthy weight individuals with OSA require clinical attention to improve cardiometabolic risk profiles.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>obstructive sleep apnea</kwd>
        <kwd>triglycerides</kwd>
        <kwd>hypoxemia</kwd>
        <kwd>cohort studies</kwd>
        <kwd>men</kwd>
        <kwd>visceral obesity</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Health and Medical Research Council of Australia Project</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Hospital Research Foundation and ResMed Foundation</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported by a National Health and Medical Research Council of Australia Project Grant (627227), the Hospital Research Foundation and ResMed Foundation.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="2"/>
        <table-count count="9"/>
        <ref-count count="64"/>
        <page-count count="12"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) is a syndrome characterized by partial or complete obstruction of the upper airways, resulting in intermittent hypoxia, variably accompanied by sleep fragmentation and daytime sleepiness.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> In male participants of the Swiss HypnoLaus cohort, the prevalence of moderate-to-severe OSA was 49.7%,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> with 74.7% men aged 40 or over having OSA syndrome according to ICD-3 criteria.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> However, OSA is often underdiagnosed and unrecognized in clinical settings.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> OSA has been implicated in the development of cardiovascular conditions,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> however OSA during rapid eye movement (REM) sleep and the resultant nocturnal hypoxemia are also longitudinally associated with cardiovascular disease<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> and associated risk factors such as hypertension,<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> insulin resistance,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> metabolic syndrome,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> and carotid atherosclerosis.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Animal models suggest that this increased cardiovascular risk is the result of intermittent hypoxemia<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> leading to activation of the sympathetic nervous system, increased oxidative stress<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> and systemic inflammation.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Furthermore, chronic intermittent hypoxia (CIH) reduced clearance of triglyceride-rich lipoproteins and inhibited adipose tissue lipoprotein lipase activity.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></p>
      <p>Current studies investigating an association between OSA and dyslipidemia have shown inconsistent results.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16–18</xref> This variation may be due to differences in study populations, the use of polygraphy rather than polysomnography, which may underestimate OSA, and studies largely conducted in the clinical setting which may not be generalizable to community-based, non-clinical samples. In a large clinical sample of adults being investigated for OSA, Trzepizur et al<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> showed a relationship between oxygen desaturation index (ODI) with higher triglycerides and lower HDL. In the European Sleep Apnea Database Cohort (ESADA), hyperlipidemia was independently associated with ODI<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> and a positive relationship between triglyceride concentration and both ODI and AHI were shown.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> A recent study also showed an independent association between severe OSA (AHI ≥30/h) with dyslipidemia, total cholesterol and LDL cholesterol, with ODI shown to be an independent determinant of triglyceride levels.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> In a general population sample, HypnoLaus Study investigators found that OSA was an independent risk factor for incident metabolic syndrome mediated through increased nocturnal hypoxemia, however no associations with incident metabolic syndrome components including high triglyceride or low HDL levels were seen.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></p>
      <p>Given the paucity of community-based studies, we aimed to determine the association between polysomnography-measured OSA parameters and nocturnal hypoxemia with serum lipid concentrations in a community dwelling cohort (n=753) of adult males. Community-based studies are required which can identify atypical/asymptomatic OSA in individuals perceived to be at low risk of OSA and its associated cardiometabolic sequelae in those who are less likely to be referred for a sleep study. We hypothesize that given that central obesity is a strong risk factor for both OSA<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> and dyslipidemia, it may overwhelm any contribution of nocturnal hypoxemia to dyslipidemia. A few small clinical studies report lipid alterations in patients with OSA free of generalized obesity<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> or with both normal BMI and normal waist circumference levels.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Supporting this, a recent study using early morning 3-T-<sup>1</sup>H-magnetic resonance spectroscopy of the vastus lateralis muscle in men reported substantial and most likely transient increases of intramyocellular and extramyocellular lipids in non-obese men with OSA compared to participants without OSA.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Consequently, we conducted analyses stratified by waist circumference to observe an obesity-independent association between OSA metrics and dyslipidemia.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Study Participants</title>
        <p>Participants were from the Men Androgens Inflammation Lifestyle Environment and Stress Study (MAILES study, n=2563 at baseline), a longitudinal study of community-dwelling men participating in the North West Adelaide Health Study (NWAHS) and Florey Adelaide Male Aging Study (FAMAS). Participants were aged at least 35 years at baseline (2002–2006) and are of predominantly European or Australian descent (96%) as previously described.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> MAILES participants underwent a computer-assisted telephone health interview (CATI) in 2010 (n=1629), and men who did not report a previous diagnosis of OSA on a sleep study (n=1445) were invited to take part in a sub-study including polysomnography with 75.2% agreeing. In 2010–11, 837 men successfully completed eight-channel in-home unattended polysomnography (PSG, Embletta X100, Embla Systems, Broomfield, CO, USA) which measured EEG, EOG, EMG, nasal pressure, thoracic and abdominal effort, oximetry, and body position. Trained staff visited study participants in their homes to set up the PSG equipment. The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> and the Epworth Sleepiness Scale<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> were administered, and all current medications were recorded. Sleep study participants showed minor healthy volunteer bias but did not differ in sleep symptoms compared to non-sleep study participants.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></p>
        <p>Sleep studies were manually scored by a single, trained sleep technician according to American Academy of Sleep Medicine 2007 alternate criteria (hypopnea defined by a &gt; 50% decrease in nasal pressure (or in both thoracic and abdominal excursions) with an associated 3% oxygen desaturation or an EEG arousal) and recommended for use in prospective epidemiological studies by the AASM and by an expert panel of the Australasian Sleep Association.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> Independent variables included the apnea–hypopnea index (AHI), rapid eye movement sleep AHI (AHI<sub>REM</sub>, in participants recording at least 30 minutes of REM sleep),<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> AHI<sub>REM</sub> if AHI<sub>NREM</sub> &lt;10, and oxygen desaturation index (ODI, 3%). OSA was defined as AHI≥10/h of sleep, with further categorization into mild (AHI 10–19/h sleep), moderate (20–29/h sleep) or severe (≥30/h sleep) as defined by the alternate 2007 AASM definition.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> The cut-offs for classification were chosen because Ruehland et al<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> have shown that an AHI of 5/h of sleep used to define sleep-disordered breathing scored by the 2007 recommended AASM criteria is equivalent to an AHI of 10/h of sleep using the alternate AASM definition, and 15/h using the older 1999 Chicago criteria. In order to maintain comparability with previous work a cut-off of 10/h was chosen.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></p>
        <p>The study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. Study approval was provided by the research ethics committees at the Royal Adelaide Hospital and North West Adelaide Health Service (approval numbers: 2010054, 02305H). Written, informed consent was obtained from all participants.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Dependent Variables</title>
        <p>Lipid measurements were obtained at clinical assessments between 2007 and 2010 on a fasting blood sample taken between 8am and 11am after a 12 hour fast. Total cholesterol, triglycerides, HDL (high-density lipoprotein), LDL (low-density lipoprotein), glucose and HbA1c were quantified by an Olympus AU5400 automated chemistry analyzer<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> in two laboratories of the South Australian Department of Health pathology service.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Cardiovascular Risk Factors</title>
        <p>Clinic assessment (as previously described)<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> included anthropometry and blood pressure. Body mass index (BMI, Kg/m<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>) was categorized by World Health Organization criteria of underweight/normal &lt;24.9, overweight 25.0–29.9 and obese ≥30.0. Systolic and diastolic blood pressures were taken using a standard calibrated sphygmomanometer, with two measurements taken 5 to 10 minutes apart and the mean result calculated. A definition of systolic blood pressure &gt;140 mmHg and diastolic blood pressure &gt;90 mmHg or the use of anti-hypertensive medication was used to define hypertension. The presence of cardiovascular disease (including myocardial infarction, stroke, transient ischemic attack, angina) was identified via self-reported questionnaire. The presence of diabetes was defined by a doctor's diagnosis, HbA1c ≥6.5%, fasting glucose ≥7.0mmol/l or use of anti-diabetic medications.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Other Covariates</title>
        <p>Socioeconomic factors including age, gender, marital status, country of birth, highest education level and gross household income were obtained by CATI or self-completed questionnaire. Behavioral risk factors including smoking status and alcohol consumption were identified using a self-reported questionnaire and physical activity was assessed with the Active Australia questionnaire.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Current use of psychotropic agents (benzodiazepines, opiates, anti-psychotics, anti-depressants) and other sleep disrupting medications (nicotine replacement therapy) was identified on the night of the sleep study by staff.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> Lipid lowering therapies were classified using the ATC classification system<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> C10A included plain lipid modifying agents (HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors, fibrates, bile acid sequestrants, nicotinic acid and derivatives, other lipid modifying agents) and C10B combinations of lipid modifying agents (HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors in combination with other lipid modifying agents). Depression was assessed using the 20-point Centre for Epidemiological Studies Depression Scale (CES-D) for NWAHS participants<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> and the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI-1A) for FAMAS participants.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></p>
        <p>Principal component analysis was used to identify dietary patterns using data collected by a validated food frequency questionnaire. We identified two dietary patterns – western and prudent dietary patterns.<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> A prudent dietary pattern is based on high dietary intake of vegetables, fruit, fish, whole grains, legumes. A western dietary pattern is based on high intake of red meat, processed meat, refined grains.<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> We then used a single diet construct, derived by subtracting factor scores of prudent patterns from western pattern. A higher diet score represents higher adherence to a healthy diet.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>Statistical analysis was conducted using SPSS version 24 (IBM corporation, Armonk, NY USA). The analytical sample is described as mean ± SD or median and interquartile range (IQR) for continuous variables and n(%) for categorical variables and tests for differences across waist circumference categories included Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test, independent samples Kruskal–Wallis test and Pearson chi-square tests, respectively. Statistical significance was set at p&lt;0.05. Those using psychotropic agents (benzodiazepines, opiates, anti-psychotics, anti-depressants) and other medications that disrupt sleep (nicotine replacement therapy) were excluded (n=84) from the analysis. The selection of the analytical sample (n=753) is shown in a CONSORT diagram (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>).<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Flow diagram of the MAILES study participants. <italic toggle="yes">*</italic>Sleep-disrupting medications include benzodiazepines, opiates, nicotine replacement therapy, anti-psychotics, anti-depressants.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-1771-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
        <p>Linear regression analysis identified unadjusted, and covariate adjusted relationships between sleep parameters including AHI, AHI<sub>REM</sub> (in participants recording at least 30 minutes of REM sleep), AHI<sub>REM</sub> if AHI<sub>NREM</sub>&lt;10, ODI (3%) and lipid measures (Model 1). Separate models determined the association between sleep parameters and lipid measures, adjusted for age, waist circumference, smoking (non/former compared with current), alcohol (non-low risk compared with moderate-very high risk), total sleep time, diet, depressive symptoms (none compared with at least mild depression) and HbA1c (Model 2). We checked for collinearity and homoscedastic assumptions. Waist circumference was used rather than BMI due to evidence that it is a better predictor of cardiovascular risk compared to BMI.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></p>
        <p>We further conducted a sensitivity analysis to exclude participants on lipid-lowering therapies. Given the effects of obesity on OSA and lipid levels, we further explored the relationship between triglycerides and AHI, AHI<sub>REM</sub>, AHI<sub>REM</sub> if AHI<sub>NREM</sub>&lt;10, and ODI (3%), stratified by waist circumference &lt;95cm, 95–100cm and over 100 cm. Triglycerides were specifically analyzed due to a strong relationship between waist circumference and triglycerides, likely mediated through insulin resistance<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> and due to the minimal effects of lipid lowering therapies compared to other lipid measures. We further conducted binary logistic regression to determine associations between clinical categories of OSA [no OSA &lt;10/hr, mild (10–19/hr), moderate (20–29/hr) and severe (≥30/hr) (27)] and the categorized dependent variable – triglyceride (≥ 1.7mmol/L). Covariates were the same as for the linear regression models.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Participant Characteristics and Sleep Measures</title>
        <p>The sociodemographic and sleep characteristics of the analyzed sample overall and by OSA severity category are shown in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The mean (SD) age was 60.8 (10.9) years and waist circumference 99.3 (11.6) cm. The prevalence of diabetes was 17.1% and hypertension was 55.4%. Undiagnosed OSA (AHI≥ 10/hr) was determined in 52.6% of participants, with severe OSA (AHI ≥30/h) present in 12.4%. The characteristics of the sample in relation to waist circumference levels are shown in <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=327478.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link></underline>.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic, Socioeconomic, Cardiometabolic Conditions, and Sleep Parameters of Study Sample</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Participant Characteristics (n=753), Mean ± SD</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI&lt;10/hr n=357</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI 10–19/hr n=196</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI 20–29/hr n=107</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI ≥30/hr n=93</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.8 ± 10.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.9 ± 10.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.1 ± 10.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.9 ± 10.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.9 ± 11.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.6 ± 4.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.7 ± 3.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5 ± 4.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.4 ± 4.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.5 ± 5.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Waist Circumference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.3± 11.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.0 ± 11.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.2 ± 11.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102.1± 11.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106.1 ± 12.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triglycerides</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.73± 1.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68 ± 0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.77 ± 2.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76 ± 0.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.77 ± 0.89</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Cholesterol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.22± 1.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.25 ± 1.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.21 ± 1.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.21 ± 1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.06 ± 1.13</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32± 0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32 ± 0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36 ± 0.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 ± 0.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26 ± 0.30</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.15± 0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.21 ± 0.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.20 ± 0.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.15 ± 0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.04 ± 0.96</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HbA1c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9± 0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8 ± 0.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9 ± 0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9 ± 0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 ± 1.0</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Household Income, n (%)</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up to $40,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">210 (28.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 (23.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (30.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (35.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (36.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">$40,001-$80,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256 (34.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">124 (35.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (34.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (29.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (39.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Over $80,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">234 (31.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">123 (35.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (31.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (31.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (20.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not stated</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (4.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (5.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (4.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (3.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3.4)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Cardiometabolic Risk Factors and Conditions, n (%)</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current Smoking (n=736)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">112(15.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (17.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (10.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (20.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (10.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol Risk: Intermediate- High</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (4.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (8.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (5.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiovascular Disease*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62(8.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (6.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (7.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (15.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (10.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical activity level: Sedentary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">561(77.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 (22.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (21.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (22.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (28.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">403(55.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">164 (46.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111 (58.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (68.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (67.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">127(17.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (12.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (21.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (15.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (28.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI&gt;30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">252(33.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (23.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (32.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (44.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (59.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Waist circumference &gt;102cm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">291(39.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76 (21.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (38.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (53.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (66.3)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Polysomnography Measures, Median (IQR)</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apnoea-Hypopnea Index (AHI)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.4 (5.7, 20.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5 (3.2, 7.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.2 (119, 16.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.2 (21.9–26.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.9 (35.2, 50.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI<sub>NREM</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6 (4.6, 20.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3 (2.2, 6.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.6 (10.6, 16.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.3 (20.7, 27.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.4 (35.5, 53.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI<sub>REM</sub><sup>‡</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0 (6.3, 25.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1 (4.9, 15.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.5 (9.0, 26.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.5 (11.5–35.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.7 (24.8, 58.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxygen Desaturation Index</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0 (3.7, 16.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7 (2.1, 6.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.5 (8.4, 14.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.5 (16.1, 23.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.3 (28.3, 45.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean oxygen saturation (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.0 (92.9, 95.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.4 (93.2, 95.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.8 (92.9, 94.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.4 (92.4, 94.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.4 (92.2, 94.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lowest oxygen saturation (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.0 (82.0, 89.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.0 (85.0, 90.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.0 (82.0, 88.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.0 (78.0, 86.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.0 (74.0, 85.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Time spent with Oxygen Saturation &lt;90%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (0.0, 3.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 (0.0, 1.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 (0.2, 3.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 (0.4, 6.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7 (1.1, 11.4)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>NREM Sleep Period (%)</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.9 (10.2, 18.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.6 (9.8, 16.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.1 (9.4, 16.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.2 (11.7, 20.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.6 (12.4, 23.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.6 (49.5, 60.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.7 (50.7, 61.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.6 (49.1, 59.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.6 (47.5, 59.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.6 (46.5, 60.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4 (9.2, 20.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.8 (8.5, 19.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.0 (12.1, 22.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.3 (9.6, 19.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.7 (6.8, 21.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM sleep period (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.6 (11.4, 18.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.8 (11.6, 17.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.9 (11.8, 17.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.6 (11.2, 18.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7 (8.7, 17.5)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index, Mean +/ SD</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8 ± 3.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8 ± 3.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4 ±3.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 ± 4.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3 ± 3.6</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: The analytical sample (n=753) excludes 84 participants on sleep disrupting medications recorded on the night of the sleep study including benzodiazepines, opiates, nicotine replacement therapy, anti-psychotics, anti-depressants. Values represent mean ± standard deviation or number (percentage) for categorical variables. Total numbers for each demographic may not correspond to reported number due to small missing values. Units are displayed in brackets. *Myocardial Infarction, Angina, Stroke, Transient Ischemic Attack. ‡AHI<sub>REM</sub>: Rapid eye movement sleep (REM) AHI is calculated for participants with at least 30 minutes of REM sleep.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviation</bold>: AHI<sub>NREM</sub>, non-rapid eye movement sleep AHI.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Relationship Between Sleep Study Metrics and Lipids</title>
        <p>Covariate unadjusted and adjusted analyses showed no significant associations of AHI, AHI<sub>REM</sub>, REM sleep predominant AHI (AHI<sub>REM</sub> if AHI<sub>NREM</sub>&lt;10), or ODI with lipid measures (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Multiple Linear Regression Analyses of the Association Between Measures of Nocturnal Hypoxemia and Lipid Profiles in Men (n=728<sup>§</sup>)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Unadjusted Model n=728</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Covariate Adjusted Model* n=663</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">B (SE)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">B (SE)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apnea–Hypopnea Index</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triglycerides</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004(0.004)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.001(0.001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000(0.001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.002(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Cholesterol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.002(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ODI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triglycerides</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004(0.005)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.001(0.001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001(0.001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.001(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Cholesterol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI<sub>REM</sub><sup>‡</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triglycerides</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.002(0.004)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.002(0.002)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.001(0.001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001(0.001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.001(0.002)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Cholesterol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.002(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI<sub>REM</sub> if AHI<sub>NREM</sub> &lt;10/hr</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triglycerides</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000 (0.005)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.002 (0.005)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.001 (0.002)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000 (0.002)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.004 (0.005)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.003 (0.006)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Cholesterol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.004 (0.006)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.003 (0.007)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: *Adjusted for age, smoking, depression, alcohol risk, total sleep time, HbA1c, diet quality, waist circumference. <sup>§</sup>Analyses excluded participants using sleep disrupting medications recorded on the night of the PSG study include benzodiazepines, opiates, nicotine replacement therapy, anti-psychotics, anti-depressants. <sup>‡</sup>AHI<sub>REM</sub>: Rapid eye movement sleep (REM) AHI is calculated for participants with at least 30 minutes of REM sleep. In models excluding participants with AHI<sub>NREM</sub>&lt;10, unadjusted models n=339; adjusted model n=312.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: AHI<sub>NREM</sub>, non-rapid eye movement sleep AHI.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Relationship Between Sleep Study Metrics and Lipids in Sample Free from Lipid Lowering Therapies</title>
        <p>In a sensitivity analysis (n=566), excluding participants using lipid lowering therapies (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>), there was no associations between ODI, AHI, AHI<sub>REM</sub>, or REM sleep predominant AHI (AHI<sub>REM</sub> if AHI<sub>NREM</sub>&lt;10) with lipid measures in co-variate unadjusted or adjusted analyses.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Multiple Linear Regression Analyses of the Association Between Nocturnal Hypoxemia Measures and Lipid Profiles in Men without Use of Lipid Lowering Therapies or Sleep Disrupting Medications<sup>§</sup> (n=566)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Unadjusted Model n=566</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Covariate Adjusted Model* n=517</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">B (SE)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">B (SE)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apnea–Hypopnea Index (AHI)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triglycerides</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.001(0.001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000(0.001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Cholesterol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ODI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triglycerides</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.069</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.002(0.001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000(0.001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Cholesterol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002(0.004)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI<sub>REM</sub><sup>‡</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triglycerides</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.004(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000(0.001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002(0.001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.081</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001(0.002)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Cholesterol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000(0.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI<sub>REM</sub> if AHI<sub>NREM</sub> &lt;10/hr</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triglycerides</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.001 (0.006)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.002 (0.006)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001 (0.002)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001 (0.002)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000 (0.005)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000 (0.006)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Cholesterol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000 (0.006)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.001 (0.007)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: *Adjusted for age, smoking, depression, alcohol risk, total sleep time, HbA1c, diet quality, waist circumference. <sup>§</sup>Sleep disrupting medications recorded on the night of the PSG study included benzodiazepines, opiates, nicotine replacement therapy, anti-psychotics, anti-depressants. <sup>‡</sup>AHI<sub>REM</sub>: Rapid eye movement sleep (REM) AHI is calculated for participants with at least 30 minutes of REM sleep. In models excluding participants with AHI<sub>NREM</sub>&lt;10 unadjusted models n=277; adjusted model n=255.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0006"><p><bold>Abbreviation</bold>: AHI<sub>NREM</sub>, non-rapid eye movement sleep AHI.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Relationship Between Sleep Study Metrics and Triglycerides, Stratified by Waist Circumference</title>
        <p>In analysis stratified by waist circumference to minimize the contribution of obesity to hypertriglyceridemia, triglyceride levels were positively associated with AHI, ODI and REM-AHI in participants with a waist circumference of &lt;95cm (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>) in co-variate adjusted analyses (p&lt;0.05). Associations were not observed in participants with a waist circumference of 95–100cm or &gt;100cm. When we considered AHI<sub>REM</sub> in participants with AHI<sub>NREM</sub> &lt;10, the association with triglyceride levels did not persist in men with waist circumference &lt;95cm [unstandardized B (SE) =0.004 (0.008), p=0.60, n=147]. The results remained unchanged in men with waist circumference 95–100cm [−0.029 (0.016), p=0.076, n=47] and waist circumference &gt;100cm [0.003 (0.009), p=0.75, n=118].<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Forest plots for the association between triglycerides and AHI, REM-AHI and ODI in males separated into groups by waist circumference (&lt;95cm, 95–100cm, &gt;100cm). Coefficients are unstandardized with 95% confidence intervals. Model adjusted for age, smoking, depression, alcohol risk, total sleep time, HbA1c, diet quality. Sleep disrupting medications include benzodiazepines, opiates, nicotine replacement therapy, anti-psychotics, anti-depressants.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-1771-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
        <p>In analyses based on clinical categories of OSA and triglycerides, in males with a waist circumference &lt;95cm, severe OSA was significantly associated with an increased likelihood of triglyceride levels ≥1.7 mmol/L [OR=4.1 (95% CI: 1.1–15.5, p=0.039)]. For men with moderate OSA, there was an increased likelihood that did not reach statistical significance [OR=2.1 (95% CI: 0.7–5.9, p=0.17)]. Consistent with the findings of the linear regression analysis, there were no associations of severe OSA with triglyceride ≥1.7 mmol/L in men with waist circumference levels of 95–100cm [OR=0.9 (95% CI: 0.2–4.1, p=0.84)] and &gt;100cm [OR=0.7 (95% CI: 0.4–1.5, p=0.40)].</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>These data show that in a large, extensively characterized cohort of community dwelling men with a mean age of 61 years, after adjustment for covariates, there was no overall significant relationship between any measure of OSA metrics and serum lipid profiles. However, after stratification by waist circumference, AHI, ODI and AHI<sub>REM</sub> were significantly and positively associated with serum triglyceride concentrations only in men without central adiposity.</p>
      <p>OSA during REM sleep is characterized by longer obstructive events, with greater oxygen desaturations<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> and there is an increasing body of evidence<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> suggesting that compared to obstructive events during non-REM sleep, events during REM sleep may be more harmful. REM-predominant OSA has been associated with incident hypertension,<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> cardiovascular disease,<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> and glycemic control in type 2 diabetes.<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> In the current study, we were unable to demonstrate a separate contribution of AHI<sub>REM</sub> independent of AHI<sub>NREM</sub> to triglyceride levels. There may be a few reasons for this; REM sleep comprised only 15% of the sleep time in our study, there may be insufficient hypoxic burden present overall if significant OSA is not present in NREM sleep. Furthermore, to allow adequate observation of REM sleep, we excluded subjects with less than 30 min of REM sleep from AHI<sub>REM</sub> analyses. This may have excluded participants most at risk of chronic intermittent hypoxia-related lipid abnormalities given that severe OSA, or a high frequency of OSA arousals during the REM period will result in very short REM sleep.</p>
      <p>Our findings regarding AHI<sub>REM</sub> are consistent with a recent clinical cohort study by Xu et al,<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> showing that associations of AHI<sub>REM</sub> with increasing serum triglyceride concentration were not independent of AHI<sub>NREM</sub>. A small study (15 participants) undertaken in Hungary showed that serum lipid profiles were not adversely affected by the presence of REM predominant OSA.<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></p>
      <p>Our findings also support other small clinic-based patient samples where OSA has been shown to be independently associated with serum triglyceride concentrations in individuals with BMI &lt;30 Kg/m<sup>2</sup>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> and in patients with both normal BMI and normal waist circumference levels),<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> but not with obesity.<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> Of lean patients assessed as having OSA (AHI &gt;5/hr and relevant symptoms), 39.6% had multiple metabolic abnormalities, including serum triglycerides ≥1.7 mmol/L.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> In studies of lean participants<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref> with varying severities of OSA ranging from mostly mild,<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> to mild to severe OSA,<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> compared to the control patients without OSA, those with OSA were significantly more likely to demonstrate impaired glucose metabolism and insulin resistance.</p>
      <p>Animal studies provide evidence for a mechanism linking CIH and lipid abnormalities. In mice, CIH, as occurs in OSA, has been shown to have adverse effects on lipid metabolism including increasing hepatic triglyceride production, decreasing plasma triglyceride clearance by lipase activity inhibition and increased free fatty acid mobilization from adipose tissue.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref> Li et al found that lean, but not obese mice, with pre-existing abnormalities of lipid metabolism, exposed to intermittent hypoxia exhibited upregulation of key transcription factors involved in triglyceride biosynthesis (SREBP – sterol regulatory element-binding protein, SCD-1- SREBP-1 regulated enzyme for lipid biosynthesis).<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> Insulin inhibits hepatic triglyceride production and animal studies have also demonstrated a link between intermittent hypoxia and insulin resistance in lean mice.<xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref> In human studies, Koenig et al<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> recently reported large overnight CIH-related increases in plasma triglycerides that occurred in non-obese participants with OSA compared to participants with obesity and OSA (214.7 ±40.9 <italic toggle="yes">cf</italic> 95.6 ± 12.6 mg/100mL), and speculate that muscle or liver free fatty acid uptake capacity may be exceeded by overnight increases in circulating FFAs and may therefore be associated with re-esterification of FFAs. In a small clinical study of 15 “healthy” men with severe OSA (mean WC: 97cm, BMI: 28.4 kg/m<sup>2</sup>; free of significant comorbidities), Drager et al<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref> reported disturbances in triglyceride-rich lipoprotein metabolism, with correction of delayed fractional clearance rates (FCR) of radiolabeled triglycerides and cholesteryl ester by 3 months of CPAP therapy supporting their earlier work.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> That disrupted sleep that occurs in OSA is linked to dyslipidemia is further supported by a recent multi-ancestry genome-wide sleep-by-single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) analyses on three lipid traits (HDL, LDL, and triglycerides) which identified gene-short sleep interactions that explained 4.25% of the variance in triglyceride levels.<xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></p>
      <p>We therefore suggest based upon our data and the results of animal and mechanistic studies that intermittent hypoxia due to OSA may induce metabolic derangements associated with insulin resistance that cannot be separated from the predominant effect of visceral obesity and therefore results are observed in lean participants where obesity does not have a dominant effect. Supporting this, CPAP therapy has resulted in an improvement in insulin resistance in non-obese participants to a greater effect than in obese participants.<xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></p>
      <p>The current study has several strengths. The participants were randomly recruited, community-dwelling men with extensive phenotypic, clinical, and biochemical assessments. They were broadly representative of the Australian male population aged 40 and over. The sleep subgroup was randomly selected from the whole study population, had similar socio-demographic and health-related characteristics to the full sample and gold standard polysomnography was performed in-home.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> We adjusted for co-founders that were clinically relevant or showed strong significance in univariate analysis, and we performed sensitivity analysis excluding the use of lipid lowering agents. The cross-sectional nature of the study limits any inferences about causality, and the findings cannot be generalized to younger men or women. Sex-specific relationships between OSA and serum lipid profiles have previously been reported.<xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref> Furthermore, our findings from a cohort of community-dwelling men with many reporting few symptoms may not be generalizable to patients in the clinical setting. However, the advantage of population-based studies is the ability to identify healthy weight, asymptomatic individuals with OSA and cardiometabolic risk who would otherwise be unlikely to be referred for a sleep study.</p>
      <p>Our findings have potential clinical implications. OSA has been shown to occur in approximately 5–14% of lean men<xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref> who may be perceived as being at low risk of OSA and its related cardiometabolic sequelae. The presence of obstructive sleep apnea should be considered in the workup for elevated serum triglycerides in lean men. A recent clinical study reported high prevalence rates of metabolic risk in lean patients with OSA (AHI &gt;5/hr, BMI &lt;25 kg/m<sup>2</sup> and waist &lt;80cm in females; &lt;90 cm in males), with dyslipidemia demonstrated in 61%, and two of three metabolic syndrome components in 64%.<xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref> Despite this high metabolic risk, treatment of hyperlipidemia in clinical populations with OSA is not high [eg 12% in the European Sleep Apnea Database Cohort (ESADA) cohort].<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></p>
      <p>OSA treatment with continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) therapy, however, may not yield desired reductions in lipid levels and mainstay therapy with HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors and fibrates will be required. As reviewed recently,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="cit0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref> observational studies and randomized controlled trials (often limited by small sample sizes and short follow-up times) have reported inconsistent effects of CPAP therapy on lipid parameters. In the ESADA Cohort, where higher ODI and AHI were associated with lipid parameters,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> an observational study of at least 3 months of PAP therapy (n=1564) in the cohort yielded a mean decrease in total cholesterol of 4.9 mg/dl (0.13 mmol/L) after ≥3 months therapy, with no effect on triglyceride levels.<xref rid="cit0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref> Compliance with CPAP therapy may have influenced the inconsistent benefits on lipid parameters reported in studies to date as CPAP use less than 4hrs per night is unlikely to treat REM sleep OSA demonstrated in our study and others to be relevant for lipid measures.<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></p>
      <p>In conclusion, we have shown that in a population of community-dwelling male adults, severe obstructive sleep apnea is a risk factor for raised serum triglyceride concentrations in those without central adiposity. This is likely the direct consequence of chronic intermittent hypoxia on triglyceride metabolism. Good CPAP compliance over the entire night including REM sleep may be beneficial. Further studies are required to evaluate the relationships between OSA and dyslipidemia in lean women and in younger men and to determine the effects of CPAP on triglycerides.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>This work was conducted at the University of Adelaide. The authors wish to acknowledge the participants of the study for their ongoing contributions to the project.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0005">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>Dr Sarah L Appleton reports grants from NH&amp;MRC of Australia and The Hospital Research Foundation Group, during the conduct of the study; personal fees from Dove Press, outside the submitted work. Professor Robert J Adams reports grants from National Health and Medical Research Council, The Hospital Research Foundation, ResMed Foundation, and National Heart Foundation, during the conduct of the study; grants from Philips, outside the submitted work. The authors report no other conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Maspero</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Giannini</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Galbiati</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosso</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Farronato</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea syndrome: a literature review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Minerva Stomatol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25747430</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Heinzer</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vat</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marques-Vidal</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence of sleep-disordered breathing in the general population: the HypnoLaus study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Respir Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>310</fpage>–<lpage>318</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(15)00043-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25682233</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Heinzer</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marti-Soler</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haba-Rubio</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalence of sleep apnoea syndrome in the middle to old age general population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Respir Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e5</fpage>–<lpage>e6</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(16)00006-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26868630</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Costa</surname>
<given-names>LE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Uchôa</surname>
<given-names>CHG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harmon</surname>
<given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bortolotto</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lorenzi-Filho</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drager</surname>
<given-names>LF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Potential underdiagnosis of obstructive sleep apnoea in the cardiology outpatient setting</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Heart</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>101</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>1288</fpage>–<lpage>1292</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/heartjnl-2014-307276</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25897039</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Javaheri</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barbe</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Campos-Rodriguez</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep apnea: types, mechanisms, and clinical cardiovascular consequences</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>841</fpage>–<lpage>858</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2016.11.069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28209226</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gonzaga</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bertolami</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bertolami</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amodeo</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Calhoun</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea, hypertension and cardiovascular diseases</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Hum Hypertens</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>705</fpage>–<lpage>712</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jhh.2015.15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25761667</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Appleton</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vakulin</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Hypertension is associated with undiagnosed OSA during rapid eye movement sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>150</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>495</fpage>–<lpage>505</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chest.2016.03.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27001264</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chami</surname>
<given-names>HA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gottlieb</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Redline</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Punjabi</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between glucose metabolism and sleep-disordered breathing during REM sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>192</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1118</fpage>–<lpage>1126</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201501-0046OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26200994</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hirotsu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haba-Rubio</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Togeiro</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnoea as a risk factor for incident metabolic syndrome: a joined Episono and HypnoLaus prospective cohorts study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Respir J</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.01150-2018</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>YY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Javaheri</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Associations between sleep apnea and subclinical carotid atherosclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Stroke</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>3340</fpage>–<lpage>3346</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/STROKEAHA.118.022184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31610764</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dematteis</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Julien</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guillermet</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Intermittent hypoxia induces early functional cardiovascular remodeling in mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>177</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>227</fpage>–<lpage>235</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.200702-238OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17962641</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lavie</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnoea syndrome–an oxidative stress disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/smrv.2002.0261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12586529</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Arnaud</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bochaton</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pépin</surname>
<given-names>J-L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Belaidi</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnoea and cardiovascular consequences: pathophysiological mechanisms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Cardiovasc Dis</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>113</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>350</fpage>–<lpage>358</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.acvd.2020.01.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32224049</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lévy</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ryan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oldenburg</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parati</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep apnoea and the heart</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Respir Rev</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>129</issue>):<fpage>333</fpage>–<lpage>352</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09059180.00004513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23997061</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Drager</surname>
<given-names>LF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shin</surname>
<given-names>M-K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Intermittent hypoxia inhibits clearance of triglyceride-rich lipoproteins and inactivates adipose lipoprotein lipase in a mouse model of sleep apnoea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Heart J</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>783</fpage>–<lpage>790</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehr097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21478490</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Drager</surname>
<given-names>LF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jun</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Polotsky</surname>
<given-names>VY</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea and dyslipidemia: implications for atherosclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Opin Endocrinol Diabetes Obes</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>165</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MED.0b013e3283373624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20125003</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Adedayo</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olafiranye</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea and dyslipidemia: evidence and underlying mechanism</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-012-0760-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22903801</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Barros</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>García-Río</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea and dyslipidemia: from animal models to clinical evidence</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsy236</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Trzepizur</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Le Vaillant</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meslier</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Independent association between nocturnal intermittent hypoxemia and metabolic dyslipidemia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>143</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1584</fpage>–<lpage>1589</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.12-1652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23699812</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gunduz</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Basoglu</surname>
<given-names>OK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hedner</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Hyperlipidaemia prevalence and cholesterol control in obstructive sleep apnoea: data from the European sleep apnea database (ESADA)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>286</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>676</fpage>–<lpage>688</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/joim.12952</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31260567</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gündüz</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Basoglu</surname>
<given-names>OK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hedner</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnoea independently predicts lipid levels: data from the European Sleep Apnea Database</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Respirology</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1180</fpage>–<lpage>1189</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/resp.13372</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30133061</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Martínez-Cerón</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Casitas</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Galera</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Contribution of sleep characteristics to the association between obstructive sleep apnea and dyslipidemia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>84</volume>:<fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2021.05.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34111805</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Karkinski</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Georgievski</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dzekova-Vidimliski</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Milenkovic</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dokic</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea and lipid abnormalities</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Open Access Maced J Med Sci</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3889/oamjms.2017.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28293310</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schwartz</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patil</surname>
<given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laffan</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Polotsky</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schneider</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>PL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obesity and obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Am Thorac Soc</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>185</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1513/pats.200708-137MG</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18250211</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>Q-C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>X-B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>G-P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>D-Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Din</surname>
<given-names>H-B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>A-Z</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea syndrome is associated with some components of metabolic syndrome in nonobese adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>571</fpage>–<lpage>578</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-011-0544-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21681412</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Akahoshi</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Uematsu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Akashiba</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnoea is associated with risk factors comprising the metabolic syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Respirology</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1122</fpage>–<lpage>1126</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1843.2010.01818.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20723141</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Koenig</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koehler</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hildebrandt</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The effect of obstructive sleep apnea and continuous positive airway pressure therapy on skeletal muscle lipid content in obese and nonobese men</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Endocr Soc</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>bvab082</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jendso/bvab082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34268461</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Grant</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cohort profile: the Men Androgen Inflammation Lifestyle Environment and Stress (MAILES) Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1040</fpage>–<lpage>1053</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyt064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23785097</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>CF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monk</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berman</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kupfer</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2748771</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Johns</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A New Method for measuring daytime sleepiness: the Epworth Sleepiness Scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>540</fpage>–<lpage>545</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/14.6.540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1798888</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name><surname>Thornton</surname>
<given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruehland</surname>
<given-names>WR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duce</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>ASTA/ASA. Commentary on AASM manual for the scoring of sleep and associated events</article-title>; <year>2010</year>. <comment>Available from:</comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://sleep.org.au/Public/Resource-Centre/F-Sleep-docs/ASTA-ASA-comm.aspx" ext-link-type="uri">https://sleep.org.au/Public/Resource-Centre/F-Sleep-docs/ASTA-ASA-comm.aspx</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>September</month>
<day>24</day>, 2021</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ruehland</surname>
<given-names>WR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rochford</surname>
<given-names>PD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Donoghue</surname>
<given-names>FJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pierce</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Singh</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thornton</surname>
<given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The new AASM criteria for scoring hypopneas: impact on the apnea hypopnea index</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>150</fpage>–<lpage>157</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/32.2.150</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19238801</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Australian Institute of Health and Welfare (AIHW)</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">The Active Australia Survey: A Guide and Manual for Implementation, Analysis and Reporting</italic></source>; <year>2003</year>:<fpage>55</fpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>WHO Collaborating Centre for Drug Statistics Methodology</collab>. <article-title>Guidelines for ATC Classification and DDD Assignment, 2021</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Oslo</publisher-loc>; <year>2020</year>. <comment>Available from:</comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://scholar.google.com/scholar_lookup?title=Guidelines%20for%20ATC%20classification%20and%20DDD%20assignment%202010&amp;publication_year=2009" ext-link-type="uri">https://scholar.google.com/scholar_lookup?title=Guidelines%20for%20ATC%20classification%20and%20DDD%20assignment%202010&amp;publication_year=2009</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>June</month>
<day>7</day>, 2021</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lewinsohn</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seeley</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roberts</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>NB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale (CES-D) as a screening instrument for depression among community-residing older adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Aging</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>277</fpage>–<lpage>287</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0882-7974.12.2.277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9189988</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Steer</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clark</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beck</surname>
<given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ranieri</surname>
<given-names>WF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Common and specific dimensions of self-reported anxiety and depression: the BDI-II versus the BDI-IA</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Res Ther</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>183</fpage>–<lpage>190</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0005-7967(98)00087-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9990749</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wittert</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adams</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dietary patterns and sleep parameters in a cohort of community dwelling Australian men</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Asian Pac J Clin Nutr</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1158</fpage>–<lpage>1169</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6133/apjcn.122016.03</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hodge</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patterson</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ireland</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Giles</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Anti Cancer Council of Victoria FFQ: relative validity of nutrient intakes compared with weighed food records in young to middle-aged women in a study of iron supplementation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Aust N Z J Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>576</fpage>–<lpage>583</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-842x.2000.tb00520.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11215004</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marchand</surname>
<given-names>NE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Driban</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McAlindon</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eaton</surname>
<given-names>CB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dietary patterns and progression of knee osteoarthritis: data from the osteoarthritis initiative</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Clin Nutr</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>111</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>667</fpage>–<lpage>676</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ajcn/nqz333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31912140</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Czernichow</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kengne</surname>
<given-names>A-P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huxley</surname>
<given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Comparison of waist-to-hip ratio and other obesity indices as predictors of cardiovascular disease risk in people with type-2 diabetes: a prospective cohort study from ADVANCE</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Cardiovasc Prev Rehabil</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>312</fpage>–<lpage>319</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/HJR.0b013e32833c1aa3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20628304</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lemieux</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pascot</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Couillard</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Hypertriglyceridemic waist</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circulation</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>102</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>184</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.CIR.102.2.179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10889128</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Findley</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilhoit</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suratt</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Apnea duration and hypoxemia during REM sleep in patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>1985</year>;<volume>87</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>432</fpage>–<lpage>436</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.87.4.432</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3979129</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mokhlesi</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Varga</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea and cardiovascular disease. REM sleep matters!</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>197</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>554</fpage>–<lpage>556</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201710-2147ED</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29141154</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Varga</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mokhlesi</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>REM obstructive sleep apnea: risk for adverse health outcomes and novel treatments</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>413</fpage>–<lpage>423</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-018-1727-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30232681</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mokhlesi</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Finn</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hagen</surname>
<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea during REM sleep and hypertension. results of the Wisconsin Sleep Cohort</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>190</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1158</fpage>–<lpage>1167</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201406-1136OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25295854</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aurora</surname>
<given-names>RN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crainiceanu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gottlieb</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Punjabi</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea during REM sleep and cardiovascular disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>197</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>653</fpage>–<lpage>660</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201706-1112OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29112823</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ljunggren</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lindberg</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Franklin</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea during rapid eye movement sleep is associated with early signs of atherosclerosis in women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsy099</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Grimaldi</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beccuti</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Touma</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Cauter</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mokhlesi</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association of obstructive sleep apnea in rapid eye movement sleep with reduced glycemic control in type 2 diabetes: therapeutic implications</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes Care</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>363</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc13-0933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24101701</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xia</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association between obstructive sleep apnea and lipid metabolism during REM and NREM sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>475</fpage>–<lpage>482</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.8242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32003732</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bikov</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lazar</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Horvath</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association between serum lipid profile and obstructive respiratory events during REM and non-REM sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lung</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>197</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>443</fpage>–<lpage>450</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00408-019-00195-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30712133</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sharma</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kumpawat</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goel</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Banga</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramakrishnan</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chaturvedi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obesity, and not obstructive sleep apnea, is responsible for metabolic abnormalities in a cohort with sleep-disordered breathing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>12</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2006.06.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17157064</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pamidi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wroblewski</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Broussard</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea in young lean men: impact on insulin sensitivity and secretion</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes Care</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2384</fpage>–<lpage>2389</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc12-0841</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22912423</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jun</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shin</surname>
<given-names>M-K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yao</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Acute hypoxia induces hypertriglyceridemia by decreasing plasma triglyceride clearance in mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>303</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>E377</fpage>–<lpage>E388</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpendo.00641.2011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22621867</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thorne</surname>
<given-names>LN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Punjabi</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Intermittent hypoxia induces hyperlipidemia in lean mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circ Res</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>97</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>698</fpage>–<lpage>706</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.RES.0000183879.60089.a9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16123334</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0055">
        <label>55.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Iiyori</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alonso</surname>
<given-names>LC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Intermittent hypoxia causes insulin resistance in lean mice independent of autonomic activity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>175</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>851</fpage>–<lpage>857</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.200610-1527OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17272786</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0056">
        <label>56.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Prabhakar</surname>
<given-names>NR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nanduri</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Impairment of pancreatic β-cell function by chronic intermittent hypoxia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Exp Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>98</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1376</fpage>–<lpage>1385</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/expphysiol.2013.072454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23709585</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0057">
        <label>57.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Drager</surname>
<given-names>LF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tavoni</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Silva</surname>
<given-names>VM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea and effects of continuous positive airway pressure on triglyceride-rich lipoprotein metabolism</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Lipid Res</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1027</fpage>–<lpage>1033</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1194/jlr.M083436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29628442</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0058">
        <label>58.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Noordam</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bos</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Multi-ancestry sleep-by-SNP interaction analysis in 126,926 individuals reveals lipid loci stratified by sleep duration</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Commun</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-019-12958-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30602773</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0059">
        <label>59.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Harsch</surname>
<given-names>IA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schahin</surname>
<given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Radespiel-Tröger</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Continuous positive airway pressure treatment rapidly improves insulin sensitivity in patients with obstructive sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>169</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>156</fpage>–<lpage>162</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.200302-206OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14512265</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0060">
        <label>60.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Newman</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nieto</surname>
<given-names>FJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guidry</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Relation of sleep-disordered breathing to cardiovascular disease risk factors the sleep heart health study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>154</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>50</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/154.1.50</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11434366</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0061">
        <label>61.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Peppard</surname>
<given-names>PE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Young</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barnet</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Palta</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hagen</surname>
<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hla</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Increased prevalence of sleep-disordered breathing in adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>177</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1006</fpage>–<lpage>1014</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kws342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23589584</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0062">
        <label>62.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chaudhary</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goyal</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pakhare</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Metabolic syndrome in non-obese patients with OSA: learning points of a cross-sectional study from a tertiary care hospital in Central India</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-021-02401-4</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0063">
        <label>63.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jullian-Desayes</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Joyeux-Faure</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tamisier</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impact of obstructive sleep apnea treatment by continuous positive airway pressure on cardiometabolic biomarkers: a systematic review from sham CPAP randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2014.07.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25220580</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0064">
        <label>64.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gunduz</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Basoglu</surname>
<given-names>OK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kvamme</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Long-term positive airway pressure therapy is associated with reduced total cholesterol levels in patients with obstructive sleep apnea: data from the European Sleep Apnea Database (ESADA)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>75</volume>:<fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>209</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.02.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32858361</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
