<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34675728</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">8519353</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">326762</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S326762</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Clinical Trial Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Impact of Acupuncture on Sleep and Comorbid Symptoms for Chronic Insomnia: A Randomized Clinical Trial</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Wang et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Wang et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Cong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>Wen-lin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Guan-wu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Fu</surname>
            <given-names>Cong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Jin-jin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3791-5741</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Jing</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Xin-yu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Zhen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Yun-fei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Acupuncture and Moxibustion, Yueyang Hospital of Integrated Traditional Chinese and Western Medicine, Shanghai University of Traditional Chinese Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Radiology, Yueyang Hospital of Integrated Traditional Chinese and Western Medicine, Shanghai University of Traditional Chinese Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Acupuncture and Tuina Academy, Beijing University of Chinese Medicine Dongfang College</institution>, <addr-line>Hebei</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Yun-fei Chen; Zhen Liu <institution>Department of Acupuncture and Moxibustion, Yueyang Hospital of Integrated Traditional Chinese and Western Medicine, Shanghai University of Traditional Chinese Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>No. 110 Ganhe Road, Hongkou District</addr-line>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <addr-line>200437</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>
<phone>Tel/Fax +86-21-65162628</phone> Email icyf1968@163.com; liuzhen8918@163.com</corresp>
        <fn id="ft0001">
          <label>*</label>
          <p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>10</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>13</volume>
      <fpage>1807</fpage>
      <lpage>1822</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2021 Wang et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Wang et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Study Objectives</title>
          <p>To evaluate the efficacy and safety of acupuncture at HT 7 (Shenmen) and KI 7 (Fuliu) on sleep and comorbid symptoms for chronic insomnia.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Methods and Design</title>
          <p>A randomized, single-blind, parallel and sham-controlled trial consisted of an acupuncture group (n = 41) and a sham acupuncture group (n = 41). Setting: a tertiary hospital of integrated Chinese and Western medicine. Participants: 82 subjects with chronic insomnia based on the International Classification of Sleep Disorders, Third Edition (ICSD-3). Interventions: a 10-session acupuncture treatment at bilateral HT 7 and KI 7 or sham acupoints with shallow needling was performed over 3 weeks. Measurements: the Pittsburgh sleep quality index (PSQI) and insomnia severity index (ISI) were evaluated at baseline, posttreatment, and at two follow-ups as the primary outcome measures. Polysomnography (PSG) on two consecutive nights, the Beck anxiety inventory (BAI), the Beck depression inventory (BDI) fatigue severity scale (FSS) and the Epworth sleepiness scale (ESS) were evaluated at baseline and posttreatment as the secondary outcome measures.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>After the treatments, PSQI scores decreased by 5.04 in the acupuncture group and 2.92 in the sham acupuncture group. ISI scores decreased by 7.65 in the acupuncture group and 5.05 in the sham acupuncture group. The between-group differences in the primary outcome measures posttreatment were statistically significant. However, no differences were found between the two groups during the two follow-ups. Regarding the PSG data, there were significantly lower levels of sleep onset latency (SOL), a lower percentage of sleep stage N1 and a higher percentage of sleep stage N3 in the acupuncture group than in the sham acupuncture group. After treatment, there were lower levels of comorbid symptoms (BAI, BDI, FSS and ESS) in both groups. However, no significant differences were observed between the groups.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>Acupuncture at HT 7 and KI 7 is an effective and safe nonpharmacologic intervention option for chronic insomnia.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2005">
          <title>Clinical Trial Registration</title>
          <p>The study was registered at the Chinese Clinical Trial Registry, registration ID: ChiCTR1900023787, China.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>acupuncture</kwd>
        <kwd>chronic insomnia</kwd>
        <kwd>sleep and comorbid symptoms</kwd>
        <kwd>randomized clinical trial</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Shanghai Clinical Research Centre for Acupuncture and Moxibustion</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>The National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>The Shanghai Science and Technology Commission</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>The Construction of Chinese Medicine Heritage Innovation Platform</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>The Shanghai Municipal Commission of Health and Family Planning</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>Shanghai Clinical Research Centre for Acupuncture and Moxibustion (Grant No. 20MC1920500);The National Natural Science Foundation of China (Grant No. 81904300);The Shanghai Science and Technology Commission (Grant No. 18401971000);The Construction of Chinese Medicine Heritage Innovation Platform (Grant No. ZY (2018-2020)-CCCX-2004-03);The Shanghai Municipal Commission of Health and Family Planning (Grant No. ZYKC201703006).</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="4"/>
        <table-count count="14"/>
        <ref-count count="75"/>
        <page-count count="16"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s0001">
      <title>Plain Language Summary</title>
      <p>Acupuncture has been used to treat chronic insomnia for years, but no study has focused on the comprehensive evaluation of acupuncture on sleep (subjective and objective) and comorbid symptoms. This was the first randomized controlled clinical trial to study the therapeutic effect of acupuncture at a pair of acupoints on insomnia. This randomized controlled clinical study showed that, compared with sham acupuncture, the streamlined and optimized acupuncture programme could improve subjective and objective sleep measurements of subjects with chronic insomnia, but there was no significant improvement in comorbid symptoms. This study led to a more comprehensive understanding of this nonpharmaceutical intervention. However, the optimal plan and mechanism of acupuncture treatment for chronic insomnia need to be further determined.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0002">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Insomnia is a frequently occurring clinical disease that affects people’s lives in our society. The incidence of chronic insomnia has increased year by year.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> According to the diagnostic criteria of the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders-4th (DSM-IV), the incidence rate of chronic insomnia in Chinese adults is 19.6%.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Long-term chronic insomnia can cause serious health problems and many other chronic diseases such as diabetes,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> obesity,<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> cardiovascular disease,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> chronic kidney disease,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> and hypertension.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> The most direct harm is effects on quality of life.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Furthermore, patients with chronic insomnia usually have mood disorders,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> and chronic insomnia is often accompanied by daytime dysfunction.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> All these factors can deteriorate the severity of chronic insomnia and contribute to the difficulty of treatment, which requires clinical attention and a search for simpler and faster treatment options.</p>
      <p>At present, cognitive behavioural therapy for insomnia (CBT-I) and other psychotherapeutic approaches are generally accepted internationally as the primary recommended treatment for chronic insomnia disorder.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> However, due to its time-intensive nature and because physicians need much professional training to conduct them,<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> these methods are not fully implemented in China. Although pharmacologic treatments have the advantages of being effective and fast, there are many side effects of sedative-hypnotic medicine, such as cognitive impairment, hangover effects, and drug addiction.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Therefore, more patients with chronic insomnia seek complementary and alternative therapies, such as acupuncture, especially among Chinese people.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> Studies have shown that acupuncture can improve sleep quality and psychological health.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> An earlier Cochrane review showed that, when compared with untreated subjects and those receiving placebo acupuncture, acupuncture can significantly improve sleep quality among subjects with insomnia.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Our previous study also indicated that acupuncture has better clinical efficacy and safety in perimenopausal insomnia than sham acupuncture.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></p>
      <p>However, most of the previous studies on acupuncture for insomnia have some general disadvantages, such as an unreasonable control group, no randomization, no blinding method, and no objective indicators for sleep evaluation.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22–24</xref> In addition, the existing studies generally lack the guidance of traditional Chinese medicine (TCM) theory,<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> and the selection of acupoints is highly variable,<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> which increases the difficulty of implementation and increases subject pain. Most of the studies on acupuncture for insomnia did not use comprehensive indicators to evaluate sleep and related symptoms. However, the Recommendations for a Standard Research Assessment of Insomnia highlight that evaluating and reporting the diagnosis of insomnia and its comorbid symptoms, sleep symptoms, and waking correlates and consequences of insomnia (ie, fatigue, depression, anxiety, quality of life and function) are the basic elements for treatment efficacy and effectiveness studies.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> More studies are needed to investigate the subjective and objective indicators of acupuncture for improving sleep and explore the secondary benefits of treating insomnia, such as reductions in depression, anxiety, fatigue, and daytime sleepiness.</p>
      <p>According to TCM theory, the main causes of chronic insomnia are Yin deficiency leading to heart fire and dysregulated coordination between the heart and the kidney.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> Therefore, we chose acupoints based on disease differentiation and special acupoint combinations to nourish Yin, calm the mind, and regulate mental activity. HT 7 (Shenmen) and KI 7 (Fuliu) are adopted as the points to nourish Yin, and they are especially used to nourish Yin of the liver and kidney and decrease heart fire.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> According to the theory of TCM, acupuncture at this pair of acupoints can solve sleep problems and related symptoms of insomnia. There are no reports on the treatment of insomnia through these two acupoints in the existing literature. This was the first randomized controlled clinical trial to study the therapeutic effect of acupuncture at HT 7 and KI 7 on insomnia. The objective was to explore the efficacy and safety of acupuncture at HT 7 and KI 7 on sleep and comorbid symptoms for chronic insomnia in sham-controlled, subject- and assessor-blind, randomized controlled trials.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Study Design</title>
        <p>This was a randomized, single-blind, parallel and sham-controlled trial. This study followed the Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials (CONSORT)<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> and Standards for Reporting Interventions in Clinical Trials of Acupuncture (STRICTA)<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> guidelines for designing and reporting controlled trials. The trial was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki and was approved by the Institutional Review Board of Yueyang Hospital of Integrated Traditional Chinese and Western Medicine, Shanghai University of Traditional Chinese Medicine (Shanghai, China).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p>The participants were patients with chronic insomnia who came from the outpatient department of the Department of Acupuncture and Moxibustion, Yueyang Hospital of Integrated Traditional Chinese and Western Medicine, from June 2019 to January 2020. In addition, the study recruited subjects through community lectures and recruitment advertisements. This study followed the principle of voluntary participation and required the signing of an informed consent document before enrolment. All those who wanted to participate in the study called the study coordinator, and we conducted a preliminary clinical interview.</p>
        <p>The diagnosis of chronic insomnia was made with clinical interviews according to the American Academy of Sleep Medicine International Classification of Sleep Disorders, Third Edition (ICSD-3).<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> The inclusion criteria were as follows: (1) 18 to 75 years old. (2) In compliance with the diagnostic criteria for chronic insomnia in ICSD-3. (3) In compliance with the TCM diagnostic criteria for insomnia, TCM syndrome of dysregulated coordination between the heart and the kidney. (4) Consistent administration of sedative-hypnotic drugs for more than 3 months before entering the study or not taking such drugs. (5) A total score higher than five on the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) questionnaire.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> (6) Patients voluntarily participated in the study and signed informed consent forms.</p>
        <p>All subjects who wanted to participate were given an outpatient interview to determine whether they met the inclusion criteria. The interviews were conducted by experienced clinicians in the form of semistructured interview questionnaires. The interview questionnaire included the cause of insomnia, the onset process, the main sleep complaints at the current time, the treatment process, the state before going to bed, the sleep-wake cycle, other sleep-related symptoms, mental states, and daytime symptoms.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> Individuals on stable doses of sedative-hypnotic medications were allowed to remain on them during the study. In addition, all subjects completed a one-week sleep diary to establish sleep patterns before the clinical interview.<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></p>
        <p>The exclusion criteria were as follows: (1) severe hepatic or renal function damage, haematological disease, respiratory disease, or diagnosis of one or more mental disorders according to the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-V).<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> (2) semistructured interviews determined that subjects had sleep disorders other than chronic insomnia. (3) Infectious diseases such as infectious hepatitis, tuberculosis, AIDS and syphilis. (4) Severe digestive system diseases or severe malnutrition. (5) Pregnant or lactating. (6) Severe trauma with no cure or other contraindications to acupuncture, such as allergic constitution or severe dermatosis. (7) An Apnoea–Hypopnea Index &gt;10 or periodic limb movements index during sleep associated with &gt;15 arousals per hour on diagnostic PSG.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> (8) Participation in other clinical trials in the last 3 months.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Intervention</title>
        <p>The acupuncturist had received a master’s degree in acupuncture and tui na, had a doctor qualification certificate, and had more than 3 years of acupuncture clinical work experience. All the research assistants received 3 days of training before the start of the study.</p>
        <p>Subjects in the acupuncture group were placed in a supine position. The acupuncturist selected two acupoints, HT 7 and KI 7. These acupoints were selected based on a previous systematic review<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> and our clinical experience summary and because the use of only two points can streamline the treatment and alleviate patient pain. The needles used were disposable, sterile, stainless-steel acupuncture needles with a length of 40 mm and a diameter of 0.25 mm (Andy, Guizhou, China). The acupuncturist treated each acupoint bilaterally, and the depth of insertion was 10–20 mm. The acupuncturist selected the depth according to the subject’s body type (high, short, fat and thin). After penetration, the acupuncturist lifted and twisted the needles to induce the subject’s sensation of “De qi”, and the needle was left for 20 minutes.<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> “De qi” refers to manipulation of the needle by the acupuncturist (extract, intercalate, twist, and rotate) after the needle has been inserted into the acupoints to a certain depth so that the acupoints can be induced by the meridians. The patient has a conscious response, such as soreness, numbness, or tenderness. According to TCM, this is the key to the curative effect of acupuncture.<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></p>
        <p>Subjects in the sham acupuncture group were treated with shallow needling of sham acupoints. Due to its convenience, this control group setting method has been widely used in acupuncture clinical research, especially for the purpose of exploring acupoint-specific effects among the Chinese population.<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> Sham HT 7 was 2 cun (≈40 mm) lateral to HT 7, and sham KI 7 was 2 cun (≈40 mm) lateral to KI 7 (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). The purpose of choosing the sham points in this way is explained in previous similar clinical studies;<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> this approach avoids the true acupoints and meridian routes. Choosing sham points close to the true acupoints was conducive to blinding. The acupuncturist took the sham points on both sides and performed needling at a depth of 2–4 mm, sufficient only to penetrate the skin. The acupuncturist did not manipulate the needles and did not cause “De qi”. The parameters of the acupuncture needles were identical to those used in the acupuncture group. Subjects in the two groups received the same treatment, which included 3 times a week for a total of 10 treatments. Each subject experienced screening, treatment, and a follow-up period of approximately 8 weeks, and the treatment phase lasted approximately 3.5 weeks. All subjects were treated equally to prevent them from perceiving differences. They were told about the methods of acupuncture as follows:
<disp-quote><p>In our study, different types of acupuncture treatments will be compared. One is ordinary acupuncture, and the other is related to the positive results in previous clinical studies.<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></p></disp-quote><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Acupoints for the acupuncture and sham acupuncture groups.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-1807-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Measures</title>
        <sec id="s0003-s2004-s3001">
          <title>Primary Outcome Measures</title>
          <p>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI): The PSQI contains 19 self-assessed items and 5 other-rated items. The self-assessed items evaluate duration of sleep, sleep onset latency, sleep efficiency, sleep disturbance, need for medications to sleep, daytime dysfunction, and overall sleep quality. The total score is 0–21. A higher score indicates a worse quality of sleep.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> The PSQI is widely used to evaluate sleep dysfunction,<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> and it is more inclined to evaluate the subject’s sleep state during the workday.<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> A total score &gt;5 indicates that the subjects have poor sleep quality and has significance for clinical treatment.<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> The Chinese version of the PSQI has high reliability and validity for the Chinese population and has been used as an effective tool for sleep screening in clinical and scientific research.<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> This study evaluated the PSQI at baseline, posttreatment, one-week follow-up and one-month follow-up.</p>
          <p>Insomnia Severity Scale (ISI): The ISI mainly evaluates the nature and severity of insomnia and its impact on daytime function. The scale consists of 7 evaluation items, and the total score ranges from 0–28 points. A higher score indicates more severe insomnia.<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref> The ISI is mainly used to screen for insomnia and to evaluate treatment effects in clinical research.<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref> A total score of 8–14 indicates subclinical insomnia, and a total score &gt;14 indicates clinically significant insomnia. A reduction in the ISI score by 8 points or more reflects a significant treatment effect in clinical evaluations. ISI has good reliability and validity.<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> The Chinese version has high reliability and validity for evaluating insomnia among the Chinese population.<xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref> This study evaluated ISI at baseline, posttreatment, one-week follow-up and one-month follow-up.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2004-s3002">
          <title>Secondary Outcome Measures</title>
          <p>Polysomnography (PSG): PSG was used as the objective sleep evaluation index. The PSG (NIHON KOHDEN, Japan) used in this study was composed of multiple quantitative parameters. The collection indicators included electroencephalogram (EEG), mentalis electromyography (EMG), bilateral electrooculography (ECoG), oral/nasal airflow, and bilateral anterior tibial EMG. In this study, PSG was used for two consecutive nights to eliminate the “first night effect”.<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref> PSG monitoring started from the usual bedtime to the next morning, and a total of 8.0 hours were recorded. The efficacy evaluation of this study was based on EEG. The sleep stages and parameters were manually scored based on the American Academy of Sleep Medicine Manual for the Scoring of Sleep and Associated Events.<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref> The objective sleep evaluation parameters used in this study included the following: total sleep duration (TST); sleep onset latency (lights out to first epoch of any sleep, SOL); REM sleep latency (REM-sl); wake after sleep onset (WASO, SOL minus TST); sleep efficiency (SE, TST/total recording time × 100%); arousal index (Arl; number of arousals ×60/TST); and percent time in each stage (length of each sleep stage/TST×100%). In this study, during the screening period and at posttreatment, two consecutive monitorings were performed, but only the second result for each timepoint was used as the efficacy evaluation index.</p>
          <p>Beck Anxiety Inventory (BAI): The BAI was developed by Beck et al in 1988<xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref> and contains a total of 21 anxiety symptom items. It has been used as an evaluation index to evaluate the anxiety state of the subject within the past week. Higher scores correspond to more serious anxiety. Generally, BAI≥45 is used as the criterion to indicate anxiety. The scale is simple in content, easy to administer, and easily understood. The Chinese version has good reliability and validity and is commonly used for the evaluation of anxiety symptoms in China.<xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,<xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref> This study evaluated it at baseline and posttreatment.</p>
          <p>Beck Depression Inventory (BDI): The BDI was developed by Beck et al according to the diagnostic criteria for depression in the DSM-IV.<xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref> Beck et al formulated the first version of the BDI in 1961 and restructured it for the second version, which is now generally used. The BDI has a total of 21 self-evaluated depression-related items that can evaluate depression in the past 7 days. The higher the total score, the more severe the depression. A total score of 0–13 indicates no depression, 14–19 indicates mild depression, and 29–63 indicates severe depression. The Chinese version of the BDI has good validity and reliability.<xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,<xref rid="cit0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref> This study evaluated it at baseline and posttreatment.</p>
          <p>Fatigue Severity Scale (FSS): FSS was proposed and formulated by Krupp et al in 1989.<xref rid="cit0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref> The FSS scale is simple and clear. It consists of only 9 self-evaluation items. Subjects scored themselves on the corresponding symptoms. Higher total scores indicate more fatigue. Studies have shown that the FSS score of patients with insomnia is higher than 5.5, which means that there is a high level of daytime fatigue among patients with insomnia.<xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref> The Chinese version of the FSS has good validity and reliability.<xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref> This study evaluated the FSS at baseline and posttreatment.</p>
          <p>Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS): The ESS is a relatively simple and internationally recognized sleepiness assessment scale.<xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref> It has a total score of 24 points. The higher the score is, the more severe the daytime sleepiness. This scale is generally used to screen and evaluate the hypopnea status of patients with obstructive sleep apnoea-hypopnea syndrome (OSAHS), but studies have shown that the ESS scale can be used to screen and diagnose other sleep disorders.<xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref> The Chinese version of the ESS has good validity and reliability.<xref rid="cit0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref> This study used the ESS to assess the daytime sleepiness of subjects at baseline and posttreatment.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2005">
        <title>Safety Assessments</title>
        <p>Two types of safety assessments were performed: evaluation of changes in routine blood tests, liver function, and kidney function after the 10 intervention sessions and records of adverse events during the entire study. The record of adverse events in this study was conducted using the Adverse Event Record Form. Subjects were required to fill in the list of adverse events during the study, including the time point, severity, measures taken, whether the event was related to the treatment and prognosis. During the assessment phase, researchers assessed the possible relationship between adverse events and the study treatment, as well as medications taken concurrently. Adverse events include all adverse reactions that are definitely related to treatment, most likely related to treatment, and likely related to treatment.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2006">
        <title>Sample Size</title>
        <p>The required sample size was estimated based on the change in PSQI scores. According to previous research by our team,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> sham acupuncture can reduce the PSQI to 14.76 after 10 interventions, with an SD of 3.35. This study hypothesized that acupuncture at HT 7 and KI 7 for insomnia would reduce the PSQI by 2.70 points more than sham acupuncture. According to the needs of this study, we made α=0.05 and 1-β=0.90, according to the formula:<xref rid="cit0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>
<disp-formula-group><disp-formula id="um0001"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-1807-e0001.jpg" position="float"/><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$${\rm{ n}} = {\rm{ }}2{\left[{{{{\rm{ }}\left({{u_\alpha } + {u_\beta }} \right){\rm{ }}} \over {\delta/\sigma }}} \right]^2} + {1 \over 4}{u_\alpha }^2$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></disp-formula></disp-formula-group></p>
        <p>A two-sided test was performed. Through the query, <inline-formula id="ilm0001"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-1807-e0002.jpg"/><tex-math id="M2">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$${u_{0.05/2}}$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula>=1.96, <inline-formula id="ilm0002"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-1807-e0003.jpg"/><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$${u_{0.1}}$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula>=1.282, and calculated n=33.32≈34. In addition, considering the loss factor (according to a 20% loss rate), the final sample size was 41 subjects in each group, for 82 subjects in total.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2007">
        <title>Randomization and Blinding</title>
        <p>Specialized statisticians who were independent of the research group generated 82 random numbers in SPSS 25.0 and then arranged these numbers in order from small to large. Numbers 1–41 were artificially specified as the acupuncture group, and 42–82 were specified as the sham acupuncture group. The random numbers are reproducible (random seed number: 20190520). Subjects entered the acupuncture group or the sham acupuncture group according to randomly assigned numbers at a ratio of 1:1 after signing the informed consent form. The random number and treatment plan corresponding to each subject were printed on a card and stored in an opaque envelope. Each subject who signed the informed consent form was given an envelope with their name, which was handed over to the acupuncturist during the treatment. The acupuncturist checked the envelope and removed the treatment card to view the treatment plan.</p>
        <p>During the study, the generation of the random numbers list, subject recruitment, acupuncture treatment, outcome measure assessment and follow-up were performed independently by different researchers. Only the outside assistant and the acupuncturist were aware of the allocation. Participants and other relevant researchers were blinded to the allocation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2008">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>The statistics and analysis of all data were performed by two analytical researchers independent of the trial. Intention-to-treat (ITT) was used as the evaluation method to evaluate the results of the study. Statistical analysis of the data was performed using SPSS 25.0. The measurement data conformed to a normal distribution, and homogeneous variances were determined using the mean ± standard deviation to describe the central tendency and the degree of dispersion. The primary outcome assessments were analysed using a mixed-effect model for repeated measures (MMRM) with patients as a random-effect factor, treatment group, age, gender, time and comorbidities as the fixed variable, patients as the random variable, random effects including intercept, baseline as a covariable, age*group, gender*group, time*group and comorbidities*group as interaction effect using a first-order ante dependence covariance matrix. The comparison between groups used the independent sample <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test, and the comparison of multiple time points within groups used repeated measurement data combined with multivariate variance analysis. For measurement data that did not conform to the normal distribution, the median, minimum, and maximum were given. The between-group comparisons used the Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test, and the within-group comparisons used the Friedman (F) test. Enumeration data were expressed as frequency and composition rate. For binary or multicategory nonranked data, comparisons between groups were performed by the χ2 test. If the data were ranked as ordinal data, the comparison between groups was performed by the Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test.</p>
        <p>All statistical analyses used two-sided tests, and P values of ≤.05 were considered statistically significant.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0004-s2001">
        <title>Subject Characteristics</title>
        <p>A total of 91 subjects were recruited, of whom 9 were excluded during screening. Eighty-two subjects with chronic insomnia meeting the criteria were included in this study and were randomly assigned to the acupuncture group or the sham acupuncture group. Among the subjects, 4 withdrew for personal reasons; 1 withdrew due to poor results; 1 withdrew due to adverse reactions; and 1 completed the treatment but did not undergo posttreatment evaluation. Therefore, a total of 75 eligible subjects completed the treatment and follow-up stage, including 37 in the acupuncture group and 38 in the sham acupuncture group (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Flow of subjects randomized to acupuncture or sham acupuncture.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-1807-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
        <p><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> presents the demographic characteristics of the subjects. Subjects’ ages ranged from 25 to 73 (median 58 years), 23 (28.0%) were male, and 59 (72.0%) were female. The majority of the subjects were normal weight (n = 68, 82.9%). The subjects had a longer course of insomnia (median 9.5 years). Approximately 53.7% of the subjects were taking sedative-hypnotic drugs. There were no differences in the demographics between the two groups. Baseline clinical characteristics were also balanced between the two groups (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Tables 2</xref> and <xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">3</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic Characteristics of Subjects</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Sample (n = 82)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acupuncture (n = 41)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sham Acupuncture (n = 41)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Z</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">χ</italic><sup>2</sup> Value<sup>a</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58(25, 73)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57(25, 72)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58(25, 73)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.264</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.791</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.544</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.461</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23(28.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13(31.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10(24.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59(72.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28(69.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31(75.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, kg/m<sup>2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">−1.106</td><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">0.269</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Under weight</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(2.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(2.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(2.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Normal weight</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68(82.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36(87.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32(78.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Overweight</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10(12.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3(7.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7(17.2%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Obesity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(2.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(2.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(2.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="6" colspan="1">1.352</td><td rowspan="6" colspan="1">0.853</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Primary school</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3(3.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(2.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(4.9%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Junior high school</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11(13.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7(17.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4(9.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> High school</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20(24.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9(21.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11(27.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> College degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40(48.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20(48.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20(48.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Graduate degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8(9.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4(9.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4(9.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insomnia duration, y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5(0.3, 40.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0(0.3, 40.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0(0.5, 40.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.297</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.195</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Concomitant diseases</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35(42.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18(43.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17(41.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.050</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.823</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug allergy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20(24.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12(29.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8(19.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.058</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.304</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current hypnotics</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">−0.603</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.546</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Never</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38(46.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18(43.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20(48.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Taking one or more</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44(53.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23(56.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21(51.2%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Data are presented as either M (Min, Max) or number (%). <sup>a</sup>The measurement data did not conform to normality after the Shapiro–Wilk test. Comparison between the acupuncture and sham acupuncture groups by Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test or <italic toggle="yes">χ</italic><sup>2</sup> test.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The Mixed Effect Model Analysis of Primary Outcome Measures</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comorbidity</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age Group*</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender Group*</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time Group *</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comorbidity Group*</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">PSQI</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.129</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.486</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.178</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.261</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.832</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.406</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.756</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.058</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.145</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.860</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.609</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.362</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.236</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.304</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">ISI</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.440</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.222</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.264</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.901</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.682</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.130</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.534</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.507</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.946</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.845</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.195</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.465</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Data were analyzed using a mixed-effect model for repeated measures (MMRM). *Interaction.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: PSQI, Pittsburgh sleep quality index; ISI, insomnia severity index.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Primary Outcome Measures from Baseline to 4-Week Follow-Up</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Assessments</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Group</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-Treatment</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow-Up 1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow-Up 2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">PSQI score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acupuncture (n=41)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula id="ilm0003"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-1807-e0004.jpg"/><tex-math id="M4">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$$\bar x\pm s$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.78±2.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.74±3.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.66±3.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.51±3.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.694</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sham-acupuncture (n=41)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula id="ilm0004"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-1807-e0005.jpg"/><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$$\bar x\pm s$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.61±3.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.69±3.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.03±3.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.59±3.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.217</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Between-group</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.265</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.537</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.472</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.075</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.791</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.638</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.940</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">ISI score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acupuncture (n=41)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula id="ilm0005"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-1807-e0006.jpg"/><tex-math id="M6">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$$\bar x\pm s$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.78±4.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.13±3.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.05±5.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.14±5.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.048</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sham-acupuncture (n=41)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula id="ilm0006"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-1807-e0007.jpg"/><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$$\bar x\pm s$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.49±4.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.44±5.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.49±7.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.42±6.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Between-group</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.657</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.796</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.624</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.949</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.101</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.109</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.346</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Data are presented as the mean ± SD. Comparison within-group and between-group by repeated-measures ANOVA.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: PSQI, Pittsburgh sleep quality index; ISI, insomnia severity index.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2002">
        <title>Efficacy</title>
        <sec id="s0004-s2002-s3001">
          <title>Primary Outcome Assessments</title>
          <p>The mixed-effect model analysis revealed that there were significant effects for the time × treatment interaction on the PSQI (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>=4.756, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.004) (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and <xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>), which means that the change trend of the PSQI over time was different due to the different groups. The mixed-effect model analysis also showed significant effects for the time × treatment interaction on the ISI (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>=4.130, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.008) (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and <xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>), which means that the change trend of the ISI over time was different due to different groups. There were improvements in PSQI and ISI scores after either acupuncture or sham acupuncture treatment (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). PSQI scores decreased from 14.78 to 9.74 in the acupuncture group and from 14.61 to 11.69 in the sham acupuncture group. After treatment, the difference between groups was statistically significant (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>=−2.537, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.013). ISI scores at baseline were 18.78 for the acupuncture group and 20.49 for the sham acupuncture group. The scores decreased to 11.13 for the acupuncture group and 15.44 for the sham acupuncture group. After treatment, the difference between groups was statistically significant (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>=−3.796, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001). Although the PSQI and ISI scores were lower than at baseline at the one-week follow-up and one-month follow-up, no differences were observed between groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&gt;0.05 for all comparisons).<fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Mean PSQI scores of the two groups during the study period.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-1807-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Note</bold>: *P&lt;0.05 vs sham-acupuncture group.</attrib></fig><fig position="float" id="f0004" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Mean ISI scores of the two groups during the study period.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-1807-g0004" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Note</bold>: *P&lt;0.05 vs sham-acupuncture group.</attrib></fig></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0004-s2002-s3002">
          <title>Secondary Outcome Assessments</title>
          <sec id="s0004-s2002-s3002-s4001">
            <title>PSG Assessments</title>
            <p>The results of PSG measurements are summarized in <xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. After treatment, there were significantly lower levels of SOL [15.5 (10.0, 18.5) vs 18.5 (11.5, 31.0), <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.039) in the acupuncture group than in the sham acupuncture group. In terms of sleep architecture, the percentage of sleep stage N1 (19.65±5.06% vs 24.99±4.60%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.015) was decreased and that of stage N3 (25.22±5.31 vs 17.88±4.84, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.002) was increased significantly in the acupuncture group compared with the sham acupuncture group. However, no significant differences in the percentage of stages N2 or R were noted between the groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>PSG Measures from Baseline to Post-Treatment</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">PSG Assessments</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Acupuncture</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Sham-Acupuncture</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula id="ilm0007"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-1807-e0008.jpg"/><tex-math id="M8">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$$\bar x\pm s$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula>/ M(Min, Max)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Z/F</italic><sup>a</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula id="ilm0008"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-1807-e0009.jpg"/><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$$\bar x\pm s$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula>/ M(Min, Max)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Z/F</italic><sup>a</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Z/F</italic><sup>b</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOL(minutes)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.0(5.0, 78.0)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">2.273</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.132</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.0(5.0, 100.0)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.333</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.564</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.141</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.254</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5(10.0, 18.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5(11.5, 31.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.065</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TST (minutes)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">384.5(226.5, 452.5)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">7.364</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">353.0(214.5, 443.0)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">8.333</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.310</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">404.0(318.5, 458.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">394.0(219.0, 475.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.046</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.295</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WASO (minutes)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.5(13.0, 242.5)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">7.364</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.5(12.0, 259.0)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">5.333</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.037</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.300</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.5(9.5, 109.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.25(1.5, 258.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.416</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.157</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.66±13.63</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">2.836</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.018</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.82±12.64</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">3.399</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.006</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.321</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.93±9.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.70±12.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.147</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.264</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.38±8.96</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">−1.789</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.104</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.69±7.72</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">1.157</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.272</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.224</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.824</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.38±6.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.57±6.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.984</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.060</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N1 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.61±10.38</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">−4.737</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.52±9.68</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">−1.735</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.111</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.844</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.406</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.65±5.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.99±4.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.654</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N2 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.73±10.82</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">−1.919</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.084</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.96±11.18</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">−1.695</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.118</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.056</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.955</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.13±9.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.83±8.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.035</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.312</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N3 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.37±5.58</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">6.846</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.55±8.34</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.812</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.434</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.228</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.230</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.22±5.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.88±4.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.467</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.30±5.50</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">4.856</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.97±5.16</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">4.407</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.168</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.868</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.01±3.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.26±5.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.914</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.371</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0006"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Data are presented as the mean ± SD or median (minimum, maximum). <sup>a</sup>Comparison within groups by repeated-measures ANOVA or nonparametric test. <sup>b</sup>Post-treatment comparison between groups by repeated-measures ANOVA or nonparametric test.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0007"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: PSG, polysomnography; SOL, sleep onset latency; TST, total sleep time; WASO, wake after sleep onset; SE, sleep efficiency; ArI, arousal index; R, rapid eye movement.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="s0004-s2002-s3002-s4002">
            <title>Assessment of Comorbid Symptoms</title>
            <p>The results of comorbid symptom assessments are summarized in <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>. After treatment, there were lower levels of comorbid symptoms (BAI, BDI, FSS and ESS) in both the acupuncture group and the sham acupuncture group. However, no significant differences were noted between the groups after treatment (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Comorbid Symptom Measurements from Baseline to Post-Treatment</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Comorbid Assessments</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Acupuncture</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Sham-Acupuncture</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula id="ilm0009"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-1807-e0010.jpg"/><tex-math id="M10">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$$\bar x\pm s$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula>/ M(Min, Max)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Z/F</italic><sup>a</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula id="ilm0010"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-1807-e0011.jpg"/><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$$\bar x\pm s$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula>/ M(Min, Max)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Z/F</italic><sup>a</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Z/F</italic><sup>b</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BAI score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (24, 71)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">19.882</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (24, 74)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">8.257</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.427</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.669</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (24, 59)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (24, 65)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.552</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.581</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BDI score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (2, 34)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">15.114</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (1, 37)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.317</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.251</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.802</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.5 (0, 39)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (0, 31)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.031</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.303</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FSS score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.59±14.46</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.685</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.497</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.98±13.40</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">1.414</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.166</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.101</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.274</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.13±13.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.54±13.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.115</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.269</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESS score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (0, 19)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (0, 21)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">1.400</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.237</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.985</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5 (1, 24)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (0, 18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.729</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.084</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0008"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Data are presented as the mean ± SD or median (minimum, maximum). <sup>a</sup>Comparison within groups by repeated-measures ANOVA or nonparametric test. <sup>b</sup>Post-treatment comparison between groups by repeated-measures ANOVA or nonparametric test.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0009"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: BAI, Beck anxiety inventory; BDI, Beck depression inventory; FSS, fatigue severity scale; ESS, Epworth sleepiness scale.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="s0004-s2002-s3002-s4003">
            <title>Safety Assessments</title>
            <p>The main observation and recording indicators in this study were WBC, RBC, Hb, and PLT as routine blood tests; AST, ALT, and ALP for liver function; and UREA, CRE, and UA for kidney function. The blood indicators of the subjects were divided into three levels: normal range, abnormalities with no clinical significance, and abnormalities with clinical significance. The results showed that the blood indicators of the two groups had no abnormal changes from baseline to posttreatment.</p>
            <p>During the implementation of this study, one subject in the sham acupuncture group withdrew due to foot swelling. The research leader judged that the relationship with intervention was “may not be relevant”. Some subjects experienced local subcutaneous bleeding symptoms after the needles were removed, but the bleeding time did not exceed 1 minute, and there was no other discomfort. During the study period, no subjects experienced adverse reactions such as needle syncope, needle sticking, or subcutaneous haematoma, and no subjects experienced pain for longer than 30 minutes due to the intervention.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>This study is consistent with our team’s previous research<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> and other similar clinical studies of acupuncture for insomnia.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>,<xref rid="cit0072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref> The current study found that acupuncture can improve subjective and objective sleep indicators in patients with chronic insomnia. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study to evaluate the efficacy and safety of using acupuncture at HT 7 and KI 7 to improve sleep and comorbid symptoms in chronic insomnia through subjective and objective measurements. On the basis of our previous research,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> we reduced the pain of subjects by streamlining the acupoints, improved compliance (drop-out rate 8.54%), introduced more efficacy evaluation indicators, and extended the follow-ups to one month.</p>
      <p>This study used the PSQI and ISI as the main outcome measures. We found that in the acupuncture group, PSQI and ISI scores decreased by 5.04 and 7.65 points, respectively, after 10 sessions of acupuncture treatment. Similarly, improvements were also found in other studies of acupuncture for insomnia.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Previous research by our team has shown that for patients with perimenopausal insomnia, 10 sessions of acupuncture significantly reduced PSQI and ISI scores by 8.03 and 11.35 points, respectively. This study did not achieve the same effect. The reasons may be as follows: First, the acupoints were simplified in this study, and the effect of the treatment was reduced accordingly. Second, the previous study was aimed at people with perimenopausal insomnia, and appropriate acupoints can reduce perimenopausal symptoms and indirectly improve sleep symptoms. Third, compared with the previous study, the subjects recruited in this study had a lower severity of insomnia at the baseline analysis. In addition, there are some clinical studies on acupuncture for insomnia that have not achieved such a significant effect in subjective measurements. Xua Yin and colleagues<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> found that the ISI score decreased 6.6 points after 4 weeks of acupuncture among subjects with insomnia. The study by Wing-Fai Yeung et al<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> found no significant differences between groups in ISI or other outcome measures. The inconsistencies may be caused by differences in the choice of acupuncture points (number and attributes), acupuncture manipulation, and study populations. In this study, we provided direct evidence for the benefits of acupuncture at HT 7 and KI 7 in treating chronic insomnia among the Chinese population.</p>
      <p>Among the factors that could affect acupuncture treatment for insomnia, the selection of acupoints is the most important. According to TCM theory, the selection for acupoints is based on three main strategies, ie, acupoints of the corresponding meridian, experience points, and special acupoint combinations. Therefore, each clinical study has different acupuncture point selections according to different TCM theories. In previous studies, acupoints used for insomnia with high frequency were GV20 (Baihui), PC 6 (Neiguan), SP 6 (Sanyinjiao), HT 7 (Shenmen), GV24 (Shenting), and Ex-HN1 (Sishencong),<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="cit0073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref> which are experience acupoints for insomnia. Previous studies selected acupoints based on experience but lacked the guidance of TCM theory. We believe that these studies did not fully represent TCM acupoints. The disadvantage of empirical acupoints is that logic suggests that the more acupuncture points are selected for the treatment, the better the effect will be; however, that is not what is observed. Therefore, many studies have used a total of 10 or more acupoints according to the empirical acupoint principle, which not only fails to achieve the expected effect,<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> but also increases the subjects’ suffering. Therefore, this study abandoned the principle of empirical acupoints and selected acupoints based on TCM and meridian theory. According to the theory of TCM, the comorbidity of the heart and kidney is an important factor in the occurrence of insomnia. Heart belongs to fire, and kidney belongs to water. The relationship between the heart and kidney is one of interaction and restriction. The rise of Yang in the kidney can warm the heart fire, and the heart fire can drop to the kidney, which can nourish the Yin in the kidney. If the functional relationship between the heart and kidney is imbalanced, pathological changes will occur. In addition to insomnia, the symptoms of this imbalance include anxiety, depression and other unhealthy emotions. This study used the theory of harmony between the heart and kidney to treat insomnia. The selected acupoints HT 7 and KI 7 belong to the Hand Shaoyin Heart Meridian and Foot Shaoyin Kidney Meridian, respectively, which satisfy the attributes of meridians and Zang-Fu in the treatment of insomnia according to TCM. The selected points on the meridians with the same name have an appropriate relationship for the mother-son reinforcing-reducing method. The results showed that acupuncture at HT 7 and KI 7 for insomnia had a benign effect based on the theory of harmony between the heart and kidney.</p>
      <p>In terms of objective sleep measures, this study found that acupuncture can improve SOL and sleep architecture. Compared with the sham acupuncture group, the acupuncture group showed a statistically significant decrease in SOL. With respect to sleep architecture, less time in stage N1 and more time in stage N3 were found in the acupuncture group. Other studies on acupuncture for insomnia have rarely explored sleep architecture, although some have used PSG as an objective measure. Some similar studies suggest that acupuncture can improve sleep architecture by increasing the percentage of slow wave sleep (SWS), thereby improving sleep quality,<xref rid="cit0074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref> which was consistent with our study. However, regarding the effects of acupuncture on sleep maintenance and SE, the results of our study are inconsistent with those of similar studies. Studies have suggested that acupuncture can improve TST and SE.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> This study found that although the acupuncture group showed increases in TST and SE, there was no significant difference between the groups. This may be due to the use of data from only the second consecutive night of PSG monitoring for statistical analysis in this study to exclude the “first night effect”. Therefore, this result was more objective than previous studies, but due to the “first night effect”, subjects might have been prone to compensatory sleep on the second night; that is, they may have slept better than usual. That is why the baseline analysis of the study showed that the mean TST was &gt;6 hours, and the room for improvement was small. There are different conclusions about the impact of acupuncture for insomnia on objective sleep measures, and it is limited by many factors. In the future, acupuncture researchers may pay more attention to the recovery and stability of the sleep architecture.</p>
      <p>It is worth noting that acupuncture could improve comorbid symptoms, but the difference was not statistically significant compared with sham acupuncture. The reasons may be as follows: First, this study only selected two acupoints (HT 7 and KI 7) to treat insomnia and comorbid symptoms. When selecting the acupoints, we mainly considered that HT 7 and KI 7 can improve insomnia symptoms. Although HT 7 has the effect of improving depression and anxiety symptoms and KI 7 has the effect of improving fatigue symptoms, the effect of a single acupoint may not be sufficient. Second, this study only adopted ten acupuncture treatments. However, chronic insomnia is a long-term disease. Our course of treatment may be relatively short and fail to achieve the expected clinical effect. Finally, this study mainly recruited subjects diagnosed with chronic insomnia and excluded patients with mental illnesses such as anxiety and depression disorders. Although the subjects generally had symptoms of anxiety and depression, they did not meet the relevant diagnostic criteria. Because of the “floor effect”, the indicators improved, but the difference was not significant.</p>
      <p>In addition, the results of this study showed that sham acupuncture had a benign effect on subjective and objective measurements. The results were similar to those of other clinical studies, suggesting that sham acupuncture has a certain clinical effect.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> A possible reason for this discrepancy may be that the participants we recruited had a positive attitude towards acupuncture treatment, and this high expectation might overoptimize the responses. The other reason may be that we used the true needle through, did not manipulate needles, and did not induce “De qi” but rather produced a shallow puncture through the skin.<xref rid="cit0075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref> According to the theory of TCM, this sham acupuncture method belongs to the categories of “burr needling” and “shallow needling” in the Canon of Internal Medicine. It can exert curative effects by stimulating the twelve skin zones (superficial parts of human skin). In future research, we would expand the scope of recruitment and adopt more reasonable sham acupuncture methods.</p>
      <p>Overall, acupuncture at HT 7 and KI 7 can significantly improve subjective and objective sleep indicators in subjects with chronic insomnia. While the subjects’ anxiety and depression were reduced, no significant difference compared with sham acupuncture was observed. Acupuncture at HT 7 and KI 7 failed to significantly improve the subjects’ daytime fatigue and sleepiness. Acupuncture at HT 7 and KI 7 for insomnia had short-term effects, and there was no significant difference between the groups during the follow-ups. This kind of acupuncture method has high safety and no obvious adverse effects and thus has value for further clinical exploration.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Limitations</title>
      <p>This study has some limitations. First, the acupuncturist could not be blinded to the treatment group, and the measure of treatment fidelity was not established. Second, due to limited time and insufficient equipment, only some of the subjects were selected for PSG monitoring. The results may be not accurate. Finally, there was no difference between the two groups during the follow-up period. The precise effect duration of acupuncture at HT 7 and KI 7 needs more exploration.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>The results of the current trial provide supportive evidence that acupuncture at HT 7 and KI 7 can be an effective, safe, and well-tolerated nonpharmacological intervention for insomnia using both subjective questionnaires and objective sleep measures. However, acupuncture at HT 7 and KI 7 can only provide a short-term effect, and a better combination of acupuncture points needs further exploration.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>The authors thank Xiao-peng Ma from Shanghai Research Institute of Acupuncture and Meridian for her comments and suggestions on the study. We also thank Pin-xian Huang from Shanghai University of Traditional Chinese Medicine for her guidance on statistical methods. We also thank Wen-jia Yang, Xin-tong Yu and Na Zhao from Yueyang Hospital of Integrated Traditional Chinese and Western Medicine, Shanghai University of Traditional Chinese Medicine.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0008">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p>The data that support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author (Yun-fei Chen) upon reasonable request. Additionally, the individual deidentified participant data are available after contacting the corresponding author via email (<email xlink:href="mailto:icyf1968@163.com">icyf1968@163.com</email>). The data will be available immediately following publication without an end date.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0009">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Suh</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cho</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sex differences in insomnia: from epidemiology and etiology to intervention</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Psychiatry Rep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>69</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11920-018-0940-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30094679</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>KF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yeung</surname>
<given-names>WF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>YM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ho</surname>
<given-names>FY</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A population-based 2-year longitudinal study of insomnia disorder in a Chinese population in Hong Kong</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Health Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>505</fpage>–<lpage>510</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13548506.2017.1363397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28786296</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Brouwer</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van Raalte</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rutters</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep and HbA (1c) in patients with type 2 diabetes: which sleep characteristics matter most?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes Care</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>243</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc19-0550</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31719053</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cai</surname>
<given-names>G-H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Theorell-Haglöw</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Janson</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia symptoms and sleep duration and their combined effects in relation to associations with obesity and central obesity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2018.03.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29773216</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tobaldini</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fiorelli</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Solbiati</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Costantino</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nobili</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Montano</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Short sleep duration and cardiometabolic risk: from pathophysiology to clinical evidence</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41569-018-0109-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30410106</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hou</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep and CKD in Chinese adults: a Cross-Sectional Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">CJASN</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>885</fpage>–<lpage>892</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2215/CJN.09270816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28389618</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hein</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lanquart</surname>
<given-names>J-P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Loas</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hubain</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Linkowski</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Objective sleep alterations and long-term use of short or intermediate half-life benzodiazepine receptor agonists are risk factors for high blood pressure in individuals with insomnia: a study in 1272 individuals referred for sleep examinations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2018.08.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30508779</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>L-J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guan</surname>
<given-names>B-Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia is associated with increased mortality in patients with first-ever stroke: a 6-year follow-up in a Chinese cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Stroke Vasc Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>202</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/svn-2017-000136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30637124</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lichstein</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Durrence</surname>
<given-names>HH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reidel</surname>
<given-names>BW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bush</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Epidemiology of insomnia, depression, and anxiety</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1457</fpage>–<lpage>1464</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/28.11.1457</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16335332</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mallory</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lichstein</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Durrence</surname>
<given-names>HH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Riedel</surname>
<given-names>BW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bush</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Comorbidity of chronic insomnia with medical problems</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>218</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/30.2.213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17326547</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Francesmonneris</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pincus</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>First</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders: DSM-V</italic></source>. <publisher-name>American Psychiatric Association</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Riemann</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baglioni</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bassetti</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>European guideline for the diagnosis and treatment of insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>675</fpage>–<lpage>700</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12594</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28875581</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Qaseem</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kansagara</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Forciea</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cooke</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Denberg</surname>
<given-names>TD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Management of chronic insomnia disorder in adults: a clinical practice guideline from the American College of Physicians</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>165</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>133</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M15-2175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27136449</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Krystal</surname>
<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The changing perspective on chronic insomnia management</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>Suppl 8</issue>):<fpage>20</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buscemi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vandermeer</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Friesen</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The efficacy and safety of drug treatments for chronic insomnia in adults: a meta-analysis of RCTs</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Gen Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1335</fpage>–<lpage>1350</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-007-0251-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17619935</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Miyata</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Iwamoto</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kawano</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The effects of acute treatment with ramelteon, triazolam, and placebo on driving performance, cognitive function, and equilibrium function in healthy volunteers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychopharmacology</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>232</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2127</fpage>–<lpage>2137</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00213-014-3843-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25533998</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Interpretation of “Guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of insomnia disorder in China”</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin J Contemp Neurol Neurosurg</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3969/j.issn.1672-6731.2017.09.002</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yin</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gou</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Efficacy and safety of acupuncture treatment on primary insomnia: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2017.02.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28899535</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sarris</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Byrne</surname>
<given-names>GJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A systematic review of insomnia and complementary medicine</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2010.04.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20965131</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cheuk</surname>
<given-names>DKL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yeung</surname>
<given-names>W-F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>KF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Acupuncture for insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cochrane Database Syst Rev</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>CD005472</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD005472.pub3</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Acupuncture improves peri-menopausal insomnia: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep.</italic></source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>11</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsx153</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>XF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>XN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>[Acupuncture at acupoints along the meridians for primary insomnia: a multi-center randomized controlled trial]</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Zhongguo Zhen Jiu</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>465</fpage>–<lpage>471</lpage>. <comment>Chinese</comment>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.13703/j.0255-2930.20190430-k0001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32394651</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hui</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The effects of active acupuncture and placebo acupuncture on insomnia patients: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Health Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1201</fpage>–<lpage>1215</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13548506.2020.1738015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32167794</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xuan</surname>
<given-names>LH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Acupoint catgut embedding alleviates insomnia in different Chinese medicine syndrome types: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin J Integr Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>543</fpage>–<lpage>549</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11655-018-2770-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30484016</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Garland</surname>
<given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>SX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>DuHamel</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Acupuncture versus cognitive behavioral therapy for insomnia in cancer survivors: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Natl Cancer Inst</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>111</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1323</fpage>–<lpage>1331</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jnci/djz050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31081899</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>KF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yeung</surname>
<given-names>WF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>BY</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Acupuncture with or without combined auricular acupuncture for insomnia: a randomised, waitlist-controlled trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acupunct Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/acupmed-2017-011371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29229613</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Foroughinia</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hessami</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Asadi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of acupuncture on pregnancy-related insomnia and melatonin: a single-blinded, randomized, placebo-controlled trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Sci Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>278</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S247628</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32494210</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ancoli-Israel</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Edinger</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lichstein</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morin</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Recommendations for a standard research assessment of insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1155</fpage>–<lpage>1173</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/29.9.1155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17040003</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Theory</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Traditional Chinese Medicine</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Shanghai Medical University</publisher-name>; <year>1985</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>S-W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zeng</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ren</surname>
<given-names>Y-L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liang</surname>
<given-names>F-R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>[Discussion on disease spectrum treated with acupuncture at shenmen (HT 7) and its compatibility based on bibliometrics]</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Zhongguo Zhen Jiu</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>561</fpage>–<lpage>564</lpage>. <comment>Chinese</comment>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25112089</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>R-D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Q-L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>[Rustic opinions on the theory of the therapeutic method of sweating disease by using Hegu (LI 4) and Fuliu (KI 7)]</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Zhongguo Zhen Jiu</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>781</fpage>–<lpage>782</lpage>. <comment>Chinese</comment>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25335258</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schulz</surname>
<given-names>KF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Altman</surname>
<given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moher</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>; <collab>for the CONSORT Group</collab>. <article-title>CONSORT 2010 Statement: updated guidelines for reporting parallel group randomised trials</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>340</volume>(<issue>mar23 1</issue>):<fpage>c332</fpage>–<lpage>c332</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.c332</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20332509</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>MacPherson</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Altman</surname>
<given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hammerschlag</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Revised STandards for Reporting Interventions in Clinical Trials of Acupuncture (STRICTA): extending the CONSORT statement</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Altern Complementary Med</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<page-range>ST–1–ST-14</page-range>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/acm.2010.1610</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sateia</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>International classification of sleep disorders-third edition</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>146</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1387</fpage>–<lpage>1394</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.14-0970</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25367475</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>CF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monk</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berman</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kupfer</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Pittsburgh sleep quality index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0165-1781(89)90047-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2748771</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schutte-Rodin</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Broch</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dorsey</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sateia</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Clinical guideline for the evaluation and management of chronic insomnia in adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>04</volume>(<issue>05</issue>):<fpage>487</fpage>–<lpage>504</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.27286</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ibáñez</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Silva</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cauli</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A survey on sleep questionnaires and diaries</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2017.08.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29458752</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Francesmonneris</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pincus</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>First</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders: DSM-V</italic></source>. <publisher-name>American Psychiatric Association</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year>. <comment>Available from:</comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.researchgate.net/publication/236017807_Diagnos" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.researchgate.net/publication/236017807_Diagnos</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>November</month>
<day>5</day>, 2020</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yeung</surname>
<given-names>W-F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>K-F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>S-P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yap</surname>
<given-names>T-G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Law</surname>
<given-names>ACK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Electroacupuncture for primary insomnia: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1039</fpage>–<lpage>1047</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/32.8.1039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19725255</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kutner</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bliwise</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A systematic review of the effects of acupuncture in treating insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2008.04.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19097814</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>[Law of acupoint selection in acupuncture treatment for insomnia based on data mining method]</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Zhongguo Zhen Jiu</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>960</fpage>–<lpage>963</lpage>. <comment>Chinese</comment>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26721161</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>White</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Filshie</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cummings</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Clinical trials of acupuncture: consensus recommendations for optimal treatment, sham controls and blinding</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Complement Ther Med</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>245</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1054/ctim.2001.0489</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12184353</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benharash</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Significance of “Deqi” response in acupuncture treatment: myth or reality</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Acupunct Meridian Stud</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>186</fpage>–<lpage>189</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jams.2014.02.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25151451</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Acupuncture as adjunctive therapy for chronic stable angina: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>179</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1388</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2019.2407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31355870</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of electroacupuncture on urinary leakage among women with stress urinary incontinence: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>317</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>2493</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2017.7220</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28655016</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Brinkhaus</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Witt</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jena</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Interventions and physician characteristics in a randomized multicenter trial of acupuncture in patients with low-back pain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Altern Complementary Med</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>649</fpage>–<lpage>657</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/acm.2006.12.649</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mollayeva</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thurairajah</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burton</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mollayeva</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shapiro</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Colantonio</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Pittsburgh sleep quality index as a screening tool for sleep dysfunction in clinical and non-clinical samples: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>52</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2015.01.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26163057</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pilz</surname>
<given-names>LK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Keller</surname>
<given-names>LK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lenssen</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roenneberg</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Time to rethink sleep quality: PSQI scores reflect sleep quality on workdays</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>5</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsy029</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Backhaus</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Junghanns</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Broocks</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Riemann</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hohagen</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Test–retest reliability and validity of the Pittsburgh sleep quality index in primary insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychosom Res</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>737</fpage>–<lpage>740</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-3999(02)00330-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12217446</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lv</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>[Analysis of the reliability and validity of the Chinese version of Pittsburgh sleep quality index among medical college students]</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Beijing Da Xue Xue Bao Yi Xue Ban</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>424</fpage>–<lpage>428</lpage>. <comment>Chinese</comment>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27318902</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>XC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>MQ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Reliability and validity of the Pittsburgh sleep quality index</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin J Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bastien</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Validation of the insomnia severity index as an outcome measure for insomnia research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>307</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1389-9457(00)00065-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11438246</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>P-Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>C-M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morin</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Validating the cross-cultural factor structure and invariance property of the insomnia severity index: evidence based on ordinal EFA and CFA</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>598</fpage>–<lpage>603</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2014.11.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25863811</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Morin</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Belleville</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bélanger</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ivers</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The insomnia severity index: psychometric indicators to detect insomnia cases and evaluate treatment response</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>601</fpage>–<lpage>608</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/34.5.601</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21532953</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0055">
        <label>55.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>DSF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia severity index: psychometric properties with Chinese community-dwelling older people: insomnia severity index</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Adv Nurs</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2350</fpage>–<lpage>2359</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2648.2010.05394.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20722803</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0056">
        <label>56.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Miettinen</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Myllymaa</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hukkanen</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Töyräs</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sipilä</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Myllymaa</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Home polysomnography reveals a first-night effect in patients with low sleep bruxism activity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>08</issue>):<fpage>1377</fpage>–<lpage>1386</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.7278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30092900</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0057">
        <label>57.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Berry</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brooks</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gamaldo</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">The AASM Manual for the Scoring of Sleep and Associated Events (Version 2.3)</italic></source>. <publisher-name>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</publisher-name>; <year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0058">
        <label>58.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Beck</surname>
<given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Epstein</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Steer</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>An inventory for measuring clinical anxiety: psychometric properties</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Consult Clin Psychol</italic></source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>893</fpage>–<lpage>897</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0022-006X.56.6.893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3204199</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0059">
        <label>59.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kin-Wing</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chee-Wing</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kit-Ching</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heung-Chun</surname>
<given-names>GC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A study of psychometric properties, normative scores and factor structure of beck anxiety inventory Chinese version</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin J Clin Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>4</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0060">
        <label>60.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Factor structure and psychometric properties of Chinese version of beck anxiety inventory in Chinese doctors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Health Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>657</fpage>–<lpage>666</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1359105316658971</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27484090</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0061">
        <label>61.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Beck</surname>
<given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Steer</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ball</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ranieri</surname>
<given-names>WF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Comparison of beck depression inventories-IA and-II in psychiatric outpatients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Pers Assess</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>588</fpage>–<lpage>597</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1207/s15327752jpa6703_13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8991972</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0062">
        <label>62.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yeung</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Howarth</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sonawalla</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nierenberg</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fava</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Use of the Chinese version of the beck depression inventory for screening depression in primary care</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Nerv Ment Dis</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>190</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>94</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005053-200202000-00005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11889362</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0063">
        <label>63.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>P-C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>T-W</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Gender-related invariance of the beck depression inventory II for Taiwanese adolescent samples</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Assessment</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>218</fpage>–<lpage>226</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1073191112441243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22517921</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0064">
        <label>64.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Krupp</surname>
<given-names>LB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The fatigue severity scale: application to patients with multiple sclerosis and systemic lupus erythematosus</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Neurol</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1121</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archneur.1989.00520460115022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2803071</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0065">
        <label>65.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Scullin</surname>
<given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bliwise</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep, cognition, and normal aging: integrating a half century of multidisciplinary research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Perspect Psychol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>137</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1745691614556680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25620997</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0066">
        <label>66.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>M-Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>I-C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chiu</surname>
<given-names>C-H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsai</surname>
<given-names>P-S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cultural adaptation and validation of the Chinese version of the fatigue severity scale in patients with major depressive disorder and nondepressive people</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Qual Life Res</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11136-015-1056-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26115873</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0067">
        <label>67.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chervin</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Epworth sleepiness scale?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s1389-9457(03)00030-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14592318</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0068">
        <label>68.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Omobomi</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quan</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A requiem for the clinical use of the Epworth sleepiness scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>711</fpage>–<lpage>712</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.7086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29734996</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0069">
        <label>69.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li-li</surname>
<given-names>PENG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jin-rang</surname>
<given-names>LI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jian-jun</surname>
<given-names>SUN</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Reliability and validity of the simplified Chinese version of Epworth sleepiness scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin J Otorhinolaryngol Head Neck Surg</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>44</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0070">
        <label>70.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sakpal</surname>
<given-names>TV</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sample size estimation in clinical trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Perspect Clin Res</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21829786</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0071">
        <label>71.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Guerreiro da Silva</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nakamura</surname>
<given-names>MU</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cordeiro</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kulay</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Acupuncture for insomnia in pregnancy – a Prospective, Quasi-Randomised, Controlled Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acupunct Med</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/aim.23.2.47</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16025784</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0072">
        <label>72.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zollman</surname>
<given-names>FS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Larson</surname>
<given-names>EB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wasek-Throm</surname>
<given-names>LK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cyborski</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bode</surname>
<given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Acupuncture for treatment of insomnia in patients with traumatic brain injury: a Pilot Intervention Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Head Trauma Rehabil</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/HTR.0b013e3182051397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21386714</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0073">
        <label>73.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <part-title>Acupuncture for the treatment of insomnia</part-title>. In: <source><italic toggle="yes">International Review of Neurobiology</italic></source>. Vol. <volume>111</volume>. <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>;<year>2013</year>:<fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>234</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-411545-3.00011-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24215925</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0074">
        <label>74.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hachul</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garcia</surname>
<given-names>TKP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maciel</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yagihara</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tufik</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bittencourt</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Acupuncture improves sleep in postmenopause in a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Climacteric</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/13697137.2012.698432</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22943846</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0075">
        <label>75.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cummings</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Electroacupuncture is effective for control of myeloablative chemotherapy-induced emesis (N=104)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acupunct Med</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>54</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/aim.19.1.54</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11471587</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
