<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35023978</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">8747786</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">341400</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S341400</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Effect of Continuous Positive Airway Pressure on Chronic Cough in Patients with Obstructive Sleep Apnea and Concomitant Gastroesophageal Reflux</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Su et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Su et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6925-9430</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Su</surname>
            <given-names>Jiao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Fang</surname>
            <given-names>Yifei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Meng</surname>
            <given-names>Yang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
            <given-names>Chunling</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Yanjun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>Linge</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Mengge</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dai</surname>
            <given-names>Liping</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ouyang</surname>
            <given-names>Songyun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Respiratory and Sleep Medicine, First Affiliated Hospital of Zhengzhou University</institution>, <addr-line>Zhengzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Henan</addr-line>, <addr-line>450052</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Henan Institute of Medical and Pharmaceutical Sciences, Zhengzhou University</institution>, <addr-line>Zhengzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Henan</addr-line>, <addr-line>450052</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Songyun Ouyang <institution>Department of Respiratory and Sleep Medicine, First Affiliated Hospital of Zhengzhou University</institution>, <addr-line>Zhengzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Henan</addr-line>, <addr-line>450052</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>
<phone>Tel +86 371-6629 5091</phone> Email ouyangsy@163.com</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>06</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <fpage>13</fpage>
      <lpage>23</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>29</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2022 Su et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Su et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) and/or gastroesophageal reflux (GER) may be the contributors to chronic cough in patients with OSA and concomitant GER. This study aimed to explore whether continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP), antireflux treatment and lifestyle modifications improve chronic cough in patients with OSA and concomitant GER.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>Patients with OSA and concomitant GER who also experienced chronic cough were enrolled, and were divided into two groups. Patients who were treated with general treatment (antireflux treatment and lifestyle modifications) as the control group, and patients who were treated with CPAP and general treatment as the treatment group. Effects of different treatments on chronic cough were assessed, and the association among chronic cough, GER and OSA was evaluated by Pearson’s correlation analysis.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index and Epworth Sleepiness Scale were better in the treatment group after 1 week of treatment; further, the improvement became stronger with the duration of therapy. The gastroesophageal reflux disease questionnaire, visual analog scale (VAS) for cough, and daytime and nighttime cough symptom scores significantly improved in both groups after treatment, whereas this improvement was more significant in the treatment group. Significant associations between the apnea-hypopnea index (AHI) and VAS, weak acid reflux and VAS, and weak acid reflux and AHI were observed.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>CPAP improved the symptoms of chronic cough and GER in patients with OSA and concomitant GER. AHI and weak acid reflux may be important factors affecting the therapeutic effect of chronic cough in patients with OSA and concomitant GER.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>obstructive sleep apnea</kwd>
        <kwd>gastroesophageal reflux</kwd>
        <kwd>chronic cough</kwd>
        <kwd>continuous positive airway pressure</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="open-funder-registry">10.13039/501100001809</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>Supported by grants No. 81800091 and U1804195 from National Natural Science Foundation of China.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="5"/>
        <table-count count="3"/>
        <ref-count count="48"/>
        <page-count count="11"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Chronic cough affects 2.3–33% of adults<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> and is a common complaint in respiratory outpatient clinic visits. Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) could cause a variety of complications, such as chronic cough, gastroesophageal reflux (GER), cardiovascular and cerebrovascular diseases.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3–6</xref> A cross-sectional study found that the incidence of chronic cough was up to 33% in patients with sleep-disordered breathing.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Shi et al have found that OSA can induce cough hypersensitivity.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> OSA is increasingly thought to be the cause of chronic cough.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> However, the pathogenesis of chronic cough in patients with OSA is multifactorial.</p>
      <p>The incidence of GER is high in patients with OSA,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> and GER may be a contributor to chronic cough in patients with OSA and GER. A multivariate population-level analysis suggested that there was a significant correlation between GER and OSA after the exclusion of other confounders.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> The CHEST Guideline and Expert Panel Report published in Chest has suggested that general treatment, including lifestyle modifications and weight reduction, alleviates the symptom of chronic cough in patients with GER.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Tamanna et al have found that continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) can improve the events of nocturnal GER in OSA patients.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> A retrospective study has demonstrated that GER is present in 42% of patients with OSA, and CPAP can significantly improve GER events.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> A Randomized Controlled Pilot Study found that CPAP treatment could relieve the symptom of chronic cough in OSA patients.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></p>
      <p>Unfortunately, as far as OSA and GER-related cough are concerned, the therapeutic management of chronic cough remains largely empirical. This study aimed to explore effects of different treatments on chronic cough in patients with OSA and concomitant GER and the possible mechanism of this association.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p>This retrospective study enrolled patients aged ≥18 years with chronic cough who visited the Respiratory and Sleep Medicine Department of First Affiliated Hospital of Zhengzhou University between March 2017 and November 2020. Informed consent was waived owing to the retrospective nature of the study. The patient data accessed was maintained with confidentiality. This study was conducted in accordance with the World Medical Association Declaration of Helsinki and approved by the grass-roots ethics committee of the First Affiliated Hospital of Zhengzhou University.</p>
        <p>The inclusion criteria were: (1) cough more than 8 weeks; (2) normal spirometry and provocation test; (3) normal chest radiographs and/or computed tomography scans of the chest; (4) normal acidophilic granulocyte count of induced sputum; (5) normal skin prick test; (6) Tests for the diagnosis of upper airway disease were normal;<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> (7) no history of angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor drug use.</p>
        <p>The exclusion criteria were: (1) the unstable haemodynamics patients, acute stage of cardiovascular and cerebrovascular diseases, uncontrollable arrhythmia, congestive heart failure; (2) giant bullous emphysema; (3) a history of hypertension, poor blood pressure control; (4) esophagus cancer, or erosive esophagitis; (5) heavy smoker;<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> (6) alcohol dependence and alcohol abuse;<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> (7) pregnancy.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index</title>
        <p>The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) was used to assess the subjective sleep quality of the participants within the past 1 month.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> It consists of 19 self-assessment items and 5 other-assessment items, in which 18 self-assessment items were scored. The 18 self-assessment items were divided into 7 aspects, and each answer is graded on a scale of 0 to 3. The total score ranges from 0 to 21, with higher score indicating poorer sleep quality.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Epworth Sleepiness Scale</title>
        <p>The Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS) score was used to assess daytime sleepiness.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> It consists of 8 questions regarding how often an individual dozes during daily activities. In this study, a Chinese version of the ESS score was used to assess daytime sleepiness of patients in both groups. Each answer is scored on a scale of 0 to 3. The ESS score ranges from 0 (never dozed) to 24 (high chance of dozing), with higher values indicating greater sleep propensity during the day.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease Questionnaire</title>
        <p>The gastroesophageal reflux disease questionnaire (GERD-Q) can be used to assess the severity of reflux symptoms.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> It consists of six questions that are divided into the following three aspects: heartburn, reflux, epigastric pain, nausea, sleep disorder and antireflux treatment use within the past 1 week. In this study, a Chinese version of the GERD-Q was used to assess GER symptoms of patients in both groups. A total score of ≥8 was considered indicative of GER disease.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Visual Analog Scale for Cough</title>
        <p>The visual analog scale (VAS) for cough<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> is used to assess cough severity by the linear integral method. It ranges from 0 to 100, with 0 indicating asymptomatic and 100 indicating the most severe cough. It can be used for the longitudinal comparison of cough severity before and after the treatment.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2006">
        <title>Cough Symptom Score</title>
        <p>The Chinese version of the cough symptom score was used to evaluate daytime cough symptoms and nighttime cough symptoms separately according to the 2015 Chinese Cough Diagnosis and Treatment Guidelines.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Each score is rated on a scale of 0 (no cough) to 3 (most severe cough), with higher values indicating more severe cough symptoms.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2007">
        <title>24-h Esophageal Multichannel Intraluminal Impedance-pH</title>
        <p>24-h esophageal multichannel intraluminal impedance-pH (24-h MII-pH) (Medtronic Inc, USA) monitoring was used to diagnose GER. No antacid treatment was administered during the examination and 8 weeks prior to the examination. An abnormal GER was defined by a DeMeester score of ≥14.72<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> and/or meeting the criteria of Lyon Consensus.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Acid reflux was defined as nadir pH&lt;4, weak acid reflux was define as nadir pH between 4 and 7, and non-acid reflux was define as nadir pH&gt;7.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2008">
        <title>Polysomnography</title>
        <p>Overnight polysomnography monitoring was performed using a Compumedics system (E-series compumedics, Australia). Sleep stages and respiratory events were classified according to the American Academy of Sleep Medicine standards (version 2.4).<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> The apnea-hypopnea index (AHI) was used to define the severity of OSA.</p>
        <p>24 h MII-pH combined with polysomnography monitoring were performed for each patient at the baseline. Synchronous pH signals were recorded in the reflux monitoring and Compumedics systems to accurately analyze the temporal association between apnea and reflux events.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2009">
        <title>Lifestyle Modifications</title>
        <p>Lifestyle modifications included diet control, aerobic exercises, tongue exercises, soft palate exercises, exercises for the cheeks, throat, and neck, exercises for lips and jaw, sleeping on one’s side, and quit smoking and alcohol.</p>
        <sec id="s0002-s2009-s3001">
          <title>Diet Control</title>
          <p>Diet control referred to calorie intake and dietary pattern changes.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Low-carbohydrate diets come in several forms, including moderate to very low-carbohydrate diets. The moderate carbohydrate intake provided about 26~45% of total calories. The term “low-fat diet” mainly referred to a diet low in triglycerides and cholesterol. This study considered the moderate carbohydrate and low-fat diet patterns, with daily caloric intake ranging from 1200 to 1500 kcal for women and 1500 to 1800 kcal for men.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2009-s3002">
          <title>Aerobic Exercises</title>
          <p>Aerobic exercises<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> included walking, jogging, gymnastics, and treadmill exercise. The aerobic exercises intensity was recommended to be 60%~85% of heart rate reserve, 4 times per week, 150 min per time, and the exercise intensity was adjusted based on the patients’ cardiopulmonary exercise test results.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2009-s3003">
          <title>Tongue Exercises</title>
          <p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Keep the chin open throughout the exercise. Press the front of the tongue against the hard palate for 5 s, then relax for 8 s, 10 times a cycle, 3 cycles daily.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Open the mouth and try to touch the chin with the tip of the tongue. Hold for 5 s, relax for 8 s, 10 times a cycle, 3 times daily.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Open the mouth, try to touch the tip of the nose with the tip of the tongue, and relax for 8 s, 10 times a cycle, 3 cycles daily.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></p></list-item></list>
</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2009-s3004">
          <title>Soft Palate Exercises</title>
          <p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Pronounce “A, E, I, O, U” 5 times daily.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Inhale through the nose and exhale through the mouth, keeping the lips together while exhaling for 5 s. Repeat 5 times, 3 times daily.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></p></list-item></list>
</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2009-s3005">
          <title>Cheeks, Throat, and Neck Exercises</title>
          <p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Tilt the head back and stick out the tongue as far as possible with the tip of the tongue. Hold for 5s, return the head to the starting position, and relax the tongue for 8s. Repeat the process 5 times daily.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Tilt the head back and gently bite the tongue. Attempt swallowing once. Then, stand the head upright and relax the tongue for 8s. Repeat the process 5 times daily.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Facial muscle training used the facial expression simulation method to exercise orbicularis oris muscle, buccinator muscle, as well as lateral and medial pterygoid muscles.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></p></list-item></list>
</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2009-s3006">
          <title>Lips and Jaw Exercises</title>
          <p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Shrink lips for 10 s, then relax for 12 s repeat 10 times once daily.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Open mouth wide while shrinking the lips. Hold for 5s and then relax for 8s. Repeat this 5 times daily.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Place one hand under the chin, then open the mouth as wide as possible. Hold for 5 s, then relax for 8 s. Repeat this 10 times a day.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></p></list-item></list>
</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2009-s3007">
          <title>Smoking</title>
          <p>The World Health Organization<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> define smoking as continuous or cumulative smoking for 6 months or more. Smokers were further classified as regular smoker (smoking more than one cigarette daily for consecutive or cumulative six months), occasional smoker (smoking more than four times per week, but less than one cigarette per day), and non-smoker. Passive smoking is defined as inhaling smoke from a smoker at least 15 min/day for more than one day per week.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2010">
        <title>Protocol</title>
        <p>According to the above inclusion and exclusion criteria, patients with chronic cough who met the criteria were enrolled. After relevant auxiliary examinations, patients with OSA and concomitant GER were further collected. General treatment included antireflux treatment (proton pump inhibitor ± mosapride) and lifestyle modifications. Average CPAP use ≥ 4 h per night was considered as good compliance, average CPAP use &lt; 2 h per night was considered as poor compliance.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> Patients with poor CPAP compliance but received general treatment as the control group, patients with good CPAP compliance and received general treatment as the treatment group. Patients kept a daily treatment log and, under the supervision of physicians, through regular outpatient visits to ensure the completion of treatment. The study protocol is presented in <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>.<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The protocol of the study.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-13-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2011">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>Data are presented as mean±SD. First, a Chi-square test was used to assess whether the variables of sex, smoking, and alcohol consumption had differences between the treatment and control groups. Second, as the overnight polysomnography and 24-h MII-pH monitoring were performed only before the treatment, an independent sample <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test was used to analyze AHI, the longest time of apnea, the lowest oxygen saturation, DeMeester score, reflux measures between the treatment and control groups. It could be used to assess whether there were significant differences in relevant indicators between the treatment and control groups, and to ensure the homogeneity of the patients of the two groups before treatment. Third, a analysis of variance of repeated measurement data were used to assess of the improvement of PSQI, ESS, GERD-Q, VAS and cough symptom scores. Forth, because of the collinearity between independent variables which entered in the model, the regression model was not developed. Pearson’s correlation analysis was used to explore the association between VAS for cough and age, BMI, PSQI, ESS, GERD-Q, objective sleep and reflux-related indicators. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant. All statistical analyses were performed using the Statistics Package for Social Science version 16.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Baseline Characteristics</title>
        <p>Of the 86 patients who met the criteria, 40 patients in the control group and 46 patients in the treatment group. The pre-treatment data of this study are presented in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Patients in both groups had poor sleep quality, severe daytime sleepiness, sleep structural disorder, decreased sleep efficiency, moderate-severe sleep apnea, significant weak acid reflux, and moderate coughing events. These parameters did not differ statistically between the control and treatment groups at the baseline (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&gt;0.05).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The Baseline Data of This Study</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment Group (n=46)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control Group (n=40)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value*</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.91±5.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.52±5.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex (Male/Female)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26/20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24/16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.48±4.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.38±4.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking:</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (56.52%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (62.50%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Regular smoker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Occasional smoker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (41.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (50.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Passive smoking</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (15.22%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (12.50%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Non-smoker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (43.48%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (37.50%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol consumption:</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (60.87%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (67.50%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (39.13%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (32.50%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.09±2.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.63±2.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.33±2.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.08±2.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GERD-Q</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.09±2.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.43±2.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TST/min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">398.33±23.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">404.18±23.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep efficiency (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.15±5.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.18±4.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep structure:</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N1 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.04±2.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.15±2.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N2 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.28±5.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.53±2.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N3 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.56±2.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.05±2.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.89±3.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.03±3.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.24±5.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.73±4.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longest time of apnea (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.12±8.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.26±4.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSaO<sub>2</sub>(%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.09±3.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.08±4.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demeester score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.23±7.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.71±5.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acid reflux</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.33±11.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.77±13.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weak acid reflux</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.60±9.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.89±7.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-acid reflux</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14±1.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12±1.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAS for cough</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.76±10.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.38±8.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daytime cough symptom</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.13±0.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.03±0.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nighttime cough symptom</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.83±0.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.73±0.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56<sup>a</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>a</sup><italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test; <sup>b</sup>Chi-square test; *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Comparisons of Sleep, GER and Cough-Related Parameters Between the Treatment Group and Control Group</title>
        <p>PSQI and ESS scores improved in the treatment group after 1-week treatment compared with baseline (improved by 15.14% for PSQI, <xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>; improved by 24.63% for ESS score, <xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), and compared with those in the control group at the same measurement time (improved by 9.20% for PSQI, <xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>; improved by 21.91% for ESS score, <xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05); and the improvement became stronger with the duration of therapy in the treatment group (improved by 45.16% after three months’ intervention for PSQI, <xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>; improved by 62.39% after three months’ intervention for ESS score, <xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Compared with pre-treatment data, GERD-Q (improved by 97.80% after three months’ intervention in the treatment group, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05; improved by 48.53% after three months’ intervention in the control group, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05; <xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>), VAS (improved by 81.87% after three months’ intervention in the treatment group, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05; improved by 22.91% after three months’ intervention in the control group, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05; <xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref>), daytime cough symptom scores (improved by 89.67% after three months’ intervention in the treatment group, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05; improved by 48.28% after three months’ intervention in the control group, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05; <xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4B</xref>) and night cough symptom scores (improved by 92.90% after three months’ intervention in the treatment group, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05; improved by 62.43% after three months’ intervention in the control group, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05; <xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4C</xref>) improved after treatment in both groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), the improvement being more significant in the treatment group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Comparisons of PSQI (<bold>A</bold>) and ESS score (<bold>B</bold>) between the treatment and control groups. *Indicates a significant difference between the treatment and control groups at the same measurement time (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). <italic toggle="yes">#</italic>Indicates a significant improvement in the treatment group when compared with the data of baseline (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-13-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Comparisons of GERD-Q between the treatment and control groups. *Indicates a significant difference between the treatment and control groups at the same measurement time (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). #Indicates a significant improvement in the treatment group when compared with the data of baseline (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). &amp;Indicates a significant improvement in the control group when compared with the data of baseline (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-13-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="f0004" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Comparisons of VAS for cough (A), Daytime cough symptom score (B) and Nighttime cough symptom score (C) between the treatment and control groups. *Indicates a significant difference between the treatment and control groups at the same measurement time (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). #Indicates a significant improvement in the treatment group when compared with the data of baseline (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). &amp;Indicates a significant improvement in the control group when compared with the data of baseline (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-13-g0004" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
        <p>Significant associations between AHI and VAS scores (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5A</xref>, r = 0.612, P &lt; 0.05) and between weak acid reflux and VAS score (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5B</xref>, r = 0.429, P &lt; 0.05) were observed. Further, a significant correlation was found between weak acid reflux and AHI (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5C</xref>, r = 0.366, P &lt; 0.05). VAS for cough had no significant relationship with age, BMI, PSQI, ESS, GERD-Q or the other objective sleep and reflux-related indicators (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The Correlation Between VAS and Other Quantitative Data</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESS</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GERD-Q</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longest Time of Apnea</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSaO<sub>2</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demeester</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acid Reflux</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Acid Reflux</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.098</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.126</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.090</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.064</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.127</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.084</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.082</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.166</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.083</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.369</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.248</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.409</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.555</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.244</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.444</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.455</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.862</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.127</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.447</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
<fig position="float" id="f0005" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Correlation between AHI and VAS score (<bold>A</bold>), weak acid reflux and VAS score (<bold>B</bold>), weak acid reflux and AHI (<bold>C</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-13-g0005" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The present study yielded two major findings. First, antireflux treatment and lifestyle modifications provided partial relief of chronic cough and reflux symptoms which were further resolved by CPAP in patients with OSA and concomitant GER. Second, AHI and weak acid reflux were significantly correlated with chronic cough, and AHI also showed a relationship with weak acid reflux. These findings are consistent with those of other studies showing that CPAP treatment can improve GER<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> and daytime sleepiness.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Previous studies have explored the effects of CPAP on GER and OSA, but there had been no analysis focused on the effect of CPAP on chronic cough in patients with OSA and concomitant GER. The present study investigated the effects of different treatment modalities on chronic cough in patients with OSA and concomitant GER, allowing clinicians to provide CPAP therapy after determining its effect on chronic cough in these patients.</p>
      <p>Orr et al suggested that proton pump inhibitor could improve GER symptoms, but it was not statistically significant in patients with OSA and concomitant GER.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> The CHEST Guideline and Expert Panel Report published in Chest pointed out that lifestyle modifications, weight loss, and proton pump inhibitor treatment could alleviate cough symptoms in patients with GER.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> In our study, we found that antireflux treatment and lifestyle modifications could partially relief the symptoms of cough and GER; but, it had no effect on sleep quality and daytime sleepiness in patients with OSA and concomitant GER. These results suggested that GER may be one of contributors of chronic cough, rather than the primary cause since refractory GER, such as gastrointestinal motility disorder, has been excluded. Tawk et al have found that GER improved after 1-week CPAP treatment in patients with OSA and concomitant GER.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Furthermore, Tamanna et al discovered that GER and daytime sleepiness improved after 6 months of CPAP treatment in patients with OSA and concomitant GER.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> We assessed the association among chronic cough, GER, and treatment response in patients with OSA and concomitant GER, and found that sleep parameters (such as sleep quality and daytime sleepiness), symptoms of chronic cough and GER were all markedly improved after 3-month CPAP treatment in present study. A meta-analysis has demonstrated that GER is involved in the pathogenesis of OSA in patients with OSA and concomitant GER.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> Radovanovic et al believed that although OSA and GER might not be causally related, the two disorders probably interact.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> Our data suggested that antireflux treatment and lifestyle modifications provided partial relief of cough and GER symptoms which were further resolved by CPAP. We speculated that OSA might be the primary cause of chronic cough, and GER might only play a role of contributor in patients with OSA and concomitant GER.</p>
      <p>We discovered the associations between AHI and VAS, weak acid reflux and VAS, and AHI and weak acid reflux, and found there was no significant correlation between cough and age, BMI, PSQI, ESS, GERD-Q and the other objective sleep and reflux-related indicators in this study. These findings are consistent with those of several previous studies, but not entirely.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> Previous studies have reported the association between AHI and GER using symptoms,<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> responses to anti-GER medication,<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> 24-h esophageal pH monitoring,<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> or endoscopic findings<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> to define GER, rather than 24-h MII-pH as in the present study. The 24-h MII-pH monitoring can accurately distinguish and analyze several forms of reflux (such as acid reflux, weak acid reflux, and non-acid reflux).<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> The wide use of 24-h MII-pH monitoring has shown that not all forms of reflux can cause symptoms in patients with GER, and the 24-h esophageal pH monitoring may be far from perfect for the diagnosis of patients with extra-esophageal symptoms. Compared to patients with GER without cough, the frequency of weak acid reflux was significantly higher in patients with cough.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> This probably reveals why some reflux episodes in patients with GER cause cough while others do not. Our findings suggested that both AHI and weak acid reflux play important roles in the development of chronic cough in patients with OSA and concomitant GER.</p>
      <p>Several studies have suggested that OSA causes GER, rather than the reverse, while there are no objective parameters to assess AHI and reflux episodes in these studies.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> The mechanism by which CPAP relieve the symptom of chronic cough in patients with OSA and concomitant GER is not fully understood. Chronic cough is multifactorial and etiologies includes pharyngeal and laryngeal hypersensitivity. This could occur due to a variety of irritants including acid. Several studies have demonstrated that CPAP can make the lower esophageal sphincter (LES) less prone to reflux via increasing barrier pressure to reflux and reducing LES relaxation time.<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> We speculated that CPAP determines chronic cough resolution probably by improving upper airway collapse, and reducing the effect of intrathoracic and abdominal pressure, and further promoting the barrier function of LES, and then alleviating weak acid reflux in patients with OSA.</p>
      <p>Additionally, there are still several issues to be addressed. First, patient population was young with mean age about 36–37 years in present study. This is not typical of most moderate-severe OSA study populations. What was the reason for this? This may be related to the interaction between OSA and GER. Shepherd et al found that the severity of GER symptom was correlated with the severity of AHI,<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> that is, the higher the AHI index, the more severe the reflux symptom. Further fundamental study is necessary to elucidate this mechanism in the future. Second, the baseline of GERD-Q in this study was less than 8 in both groups, while the GERD-Q should be more than 8 to be GER disease. The possible reasons for this are as follows: (1) the GER symptoms were divided into two parts, esophageal and extra-esophageal symptoms. GERD-Q consists of six questions: heartburn, reflux, epigastric pain, nausea, sleep disorder, and anti-reflux treatment use within the past 1 week; 5/6 of the questions were related to esophageal symptoms. It indicates that GERD-Q tends to diagnose patients with typical esophageal symptoms more than those with atypical esophageal symptoms. And cough is one of the extra-esophageal symptoms of GER. (2)24-h MII-pH monitoring further discovered that the significant abnormalities were weak acid reflux in OSA patients with GER in present study. GER esophageal symptoms are atypical in patients with OSA and concomitant GER, which might explain why both groups’ baseline GERD-Q was less than 8. Further, it also indicated that the GERD-Q score alone could not diagnose GER in patients with OSA and concomitant GER. Patients with probable OSA and GER should have their MII-pH level monitored for 24 hours. Third, previous studies have found a sex difference in the incidence of OSA.<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> However, sex did not affect the therapeutic effect of cough in patients with OSA and concomitant GER in present study. It suggested that sex could affect the incidence of OSA, but CPAP therapy was equally important for cough in male and female patients with OSA and concomitant GER.</p>
      <p>This study had several limitations. First, this was a single-center retrospective study. Further fundamental studies and large-scale prospective studies are necessary to reach a more definitive conclusion in the future. Second, there was no blank control group. However, it would be unethical to withhold therapy from patients. Third, the subjective parameters, such as sleep quality, daytime sleepiness, GER-related questionnaire, and cough-related questionnaires, could be influenced by patients’ judgment. However, these questionnaires are simple and practical to perform, and there is no objective cough-related monitoring up till now. Moreover, professional technicians use these questionnaires strictly and accurately according to the instructions in our study.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>In summary, our results indicate that CPAP improved the symptoms of chronic cough and GER in patients with OSA and concomitant GER. Meanwhile, AHI and weak acid reflux may be important factors affecting the therapeutic effect of chronic cough in patients with OSA and concomitant GER. The probable mechanism of cough resolution with CPAP is the improvement of upper airway collapse, and reducing the effect of intrathoracic and abdominal pressure, further promoting the barrier function of LES and then alleviating weak acid reflux in patients with OSA. Further fundamental studies and large-scale prospective studies are necessary to reach a more definitive conclusion in the future.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We thank Jiao Su’s classmates, the statisticians (Xin Chen, Dalian Medical University, Dalian, China; Bing Huang, Dalian Runsheng Kangtai Medical Lab Co. Ltd., Dalian, China), for their help in the statistical analysis.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <p>24-h MII-pH, 24-h esophageal multichannel intraluminal impedance-pH; AHI, apnea-hypopnea index; CPAP, continuous positive airway pressure; ESS, Epworth Sleepiness Scale; GER, gastroesophageal reflux; GERD-Q, Gastroesophageal reflux disease questionnaire; LES, Lower esophageal sphincter; OSA, obstructive sleep apnea; PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index; VAS, Visual analog scale.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Ethics Approval and Informed Consent</title>
      <p>Informed consent was waived owing to the retrospective nature of the study. The patient data accessed was maintained with confidentiality. This study was conducted in accordance with the World Medical Association Declaration of Helsinki and approved by the grass-roots ethics committee of the First Affiliated Hospital of Zhengzhou University.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0008">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation, or in all these areas; took part in drafting, revising or critically reviewing the article; gave final approval of the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0009">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>All authors declared that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest and reported no conflicts of interest for this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>KF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pavord</surname>
<given-names>ID</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Chronic cough prevalence, pathogenesis, and causes of chronic cough</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>371</volume>(<issue>9621</issue>):<fpage>1364</fpage>–<lpage>1374</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(08)60595-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18424325</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>YS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Faruqi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The global epidemiology of chronic cough in adults: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Respir J</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1479</fpage>–<lpage>1481</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.00218714</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25657027</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Michaudet</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malaty</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Chronic cough: evaluation and management</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am Fam Physician</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>96</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>575</fpage>–<lpage>580</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29094873</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gouveia</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yalamanchili</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghadersohi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Are chronic cough and laryngopharyngeal reflux more common in obstructive sleep apnea patients?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Laryngoscope</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>129</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1244</fpage>–<lpage>1249</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lary.27557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30443914</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Javaheri</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barbe</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Campos-Rodriguez</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep apnea: types, mechanisms, and clinical cardiovascular consequences</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>841</fpage>–<lpage>858</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2016.11.069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28209226</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dong</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dong</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence, risk factors, outcomes, and treatment of obstructive sleep apnea in patients with cerebrovascular disease: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Stroke Cerebrovasc Dis</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1471</fpage>–<lpage>1480</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jstrokecerebrovasdis.2017.12.048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29555400</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>KK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ing</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laks</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Chronic cough in patients with sleep-disordered breathing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Respir J</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>368</fpage>–<lpage>372</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.00110409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20123846</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cough hypersensitivity in patients with obstructive sleep apnea hypopnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-018-1641-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29453637</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sabaté</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jouët</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Merrouche</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Gastroesophageal reflux in patients with morbid obesity: a role of obstructive sleep apnea syndrome?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Obes Surg</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1479</fpage>–<lpage>1484</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11695-008-9508-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18418659</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>YJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Associations between obstructive sleep apnea severity and endoscopically proven gastroesophageal reflux disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-017-1533-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28687968</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gilani</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quan</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pynnonen</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea and gastroesophageal reflux: a multivariate population-level analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>154</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>390</fpage>–<lpage>395</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0194599815621557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26645532</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kahrilas</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Altman</surname>
<given-names>KW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Chronic cough due to gastroesophageal reflux in adults: CHEST guideline and expert panel report</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>150</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1341</fpage>–<lpage>1360</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chest.2016.08.1458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27614002</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tamanna</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Warren</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of CPAP therapy on symptoms of nocturnal gastroesophageal reflux among patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1257</fpage>–<lpage>1261</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.6126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27306392</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Relationship between reflux diseases and obstructive sleep apnea together with continuous positive airway pressure treatment efficiency analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>75</volume>:<fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>155</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.07.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32858354</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sundar</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Willis</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A Randomized, Controlled, Pilot Study of CPAP for patients with chronic cough and obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lung</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>198</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>449</fpage>–<lpage>457</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00408-020-00354-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32356074</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>The asthma group of Chinese Thoracic Society</collab>. <article-title>Guideline for the diagnosis and treatment of cough (2015)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin J Tuberc Respir Dis</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>323</fpage>–<lpage>354</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>World Health Organisation</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Guidelines for Controlling and Monitoring the Tobacco Epidemic</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Tobacco or Heahh Programme, WHO</publisher-name>; <year>1997</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>World Health Organisation</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">ICD-10 Classification of Mental and Behavioural Disorders: Clinical Descriptions and Diagnostic Guidelines</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Geneva, Switzerland</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>; <year>1992</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mollayeva</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thurairajah</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burton</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The Pittsburgh sleep quality index as a screening tool for sleep dysfunction in clinical and non-clinical samples: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>52</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2015.01.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26163057</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Johns</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A new method for measuring daytime sleepiness: the Epworth sleepiness scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>540</fpage>–<lpage>545</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/14.6.540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1798888</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Teklu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gouveia</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yalamanchili</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Predicting obstructive sleep apnea status with the reflux symptom index in a sleep study population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Laryngoscope</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>130</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>E952</fpage>–<lpage>E957</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lary.28592</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32119130</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Neto</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Herbella</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schlottmann</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Does DeMeester score still define GERD?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Dis Esophagus</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>doy118</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/dote/doy118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30561585</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gyawali</surname>
<given-names>CP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kahrilas</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Savarino</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Modern diagnosis of GERD: the Lyon consensus</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Gut</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1351</fpage>–<lpage>1362</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gutjnl-2017-314722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29437910</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sifrim</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Castell</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dent</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kahrilas</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Gastro-oesophageal reflux monitoring: review and consensus report on detection and definitions of acid, non-acid, and gas reflux</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Gut</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1024</fpage>–<lpage>1031</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gut.2003.033290</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15194656</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Berry</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brooks</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gamaldo</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, et al; <collab>for the American Academy of Sleep Medicine</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">The AASM Manual for the Scoring of Sleep and Associated Events: Rules, Terminology, and Technical Specifications. Version 2.4</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Darien, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</publisher-name>; <year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chawla</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tessarolo Silva</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amaral Medeiros</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mekary</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Radenkovic</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effect of low-fat and low-carbohydrate diets on weight loss and lipid levels: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nutrients</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>3774</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu12123774</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Clifton</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Condo</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Keogh</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Long term weight maintenance after advice to consume low carbohydrate, higher protein diets–a systematic review and meta analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nutr Metab Cardiovasc Dis</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>224</fpage>–<lpage>235</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.numecd.2013.11.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24472635</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kline</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crowley</surname>
<given-names>EP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ewing</surname>
<given-names>GB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The effect of exercise training on obstructive sleep apnea and sleep quality: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1631</fpage>–<lpage>1640</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.1422</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22131599</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mei</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of 12 weeks of regular aerobic exercises on autonomic nervous system in obstructive sleep apnea syndrome patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1189</fpage>–<lpage>1195</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-018-1736-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30328014</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Neumannova</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hobzova</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sova</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Prasko</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pulmonary rehabilitation and oropharyngeal exercises as an adjunct therapy in obstructive sleep apnea: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>92</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2018.03.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30292081</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sawyer</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gooneratne</surname>
<given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marcus</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ofer</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Richards</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weaver</surname>
<given-names>TE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A systematic review of CPAP adherence across age groups: clinical and empiric insights for developing CPAP adherence interventions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>343</fpage>–<lpage>356</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2011.01.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21652236</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bakker</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weaver</surname>
<given-names>TE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parthasarathy</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aloia</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Adherence to CPAP: what should we be aiming for, and how can we get there?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>155</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1272</fpage>–<lpage>1287</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chest.2019.01.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30684472</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tawk</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goodrich</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kinasewitz</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The effect of 1 week of continuous positive airway pressure treatment in obstructive sleep apnea patients with concomitant gastroesophageal reflux</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>130</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1003</fpage>–<lpage>1008</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.130.4.1003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17035431</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Orr</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Robert</surname>
<given-names>JJT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Houck</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The effect of acid suppression on upper airway anatomy and obstruction in patients with sleep apnea and gastroesophageal reflux disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>330</fpage>–<lpage>334</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.27543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19968010</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>ZH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>XP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Niu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The relationship between obstructive sleep apnea hypopnea syndrome and gastroesophageal reflux disease: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>389</fpage>–<lpage>397</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-018-1691-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29987514</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Radovanovic</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pini</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rizzi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence and influence of gastroesophageal reflux symptoms on sleep apnea and sleepiness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>84</volume>:<fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejim.2020.11.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33281054</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vela</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kramer</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Richardson</surname>
<given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Poor sleep quality and obstructive sleep apnea in patients with GERD and barrett’s esophagus</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurogastroenterol Motil</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>346</fpage>–<lpage>352</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nmo.12265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24460751</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ju</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yoon</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Relationships between sleep disturbances and gastroesophageal reflux disease in Asian sleep clinic referrals</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychosom Res</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>551</fpage>–<lpage>555</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychores.2013.10.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24290045</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Faruqi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fahim</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morice</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Chronic cough and obstructive sleep apnoea: reflux-associated cough hypersensitivity?</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Respir J</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1049</fpage>–<lpage>1050</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.00025012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23024327</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Boeckxstaens</surname>
<given-names>GE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smout</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Systematic review: role of acid, weakly acidic and weakly alkaline reflux in gastro-oesophageal reflux disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Aliment Pharmacol Ther</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>332</fpage>–<lpage>343</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2036.2010.04358.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liao</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The characteristics of high-resolution esophageal manometry and multichannel intraluminal esophageal impedance and pH monitoring in gastroesophageal reflux cough</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin J Gastroenterol Hepatol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1196</fpage>–<lpage>1999</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Xavier</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moraes</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eckley</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalence of signs and symptoms of laryngopharyngeal reflux in snorers with suspected obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Braz J Otorhinolaryngol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>589</fpage>–<lpage>593</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5935/1808-8694.20130105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24141673</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Laohasiriwong</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnston</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Woodson</surname>
<given-names>BT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Extra-esophageal reflux, nose score, and sleep quality in an adult clinic population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Laryngoscope</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>123</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>3233</fpage>–<lpage>3238</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lary.24236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23754257</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shepherd</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holloway</surname>
<given-names>RH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hillman</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The impact of continuous positive airway pressure on the lower esophageal sphincter</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>292</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>G1200</fpage>–<lpage>G1205</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpgi.00476.2006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17234890</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shepherd</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hillman</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holloway</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Mechanisms of nocturnal gastroesophageal reflux events in obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>561</fpage>–<lpage>570</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-010-0404-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20711680</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shepherd</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>James</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Musk</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hunter</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hillman</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eastwood</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Gastro-oesophageal reflux symptoms are related to the presence and severity of obstructive sleep apnoea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1pt2</issue>):<fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>249</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.2010.00843.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20545839</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fietze</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laharnar</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Obst</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence and association analysis of obstructive sleep apnea with gender and age differences - results of SHIP-trend</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e12770</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12770</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30272383</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wächter</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kantelhardt</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bonsignore</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Unique sleep-stage transitions determined by obstructive sleep apnea severity, age and gender</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e12895</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31347213</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
