<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35422668</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">9005082</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">347630</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S347630</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Altered Salivary Microbiota in Patients with Obstructive Sleep Apnea Comorbid Hypertension</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Chen et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Chen et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Xuehui</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9934-5241</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Yanlong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Feng</surname>
            <given-names>Mengqi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <given-names>Xin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Changtao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0364-8457</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Han</surname>
            <given-names>Fang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2448-6597</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Qian</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5690-9385</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Gao</surname>
            <given-names>Xuemei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref>
          <xref rid="an0002" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Orthodontics, Peking University School and Hospital of Stomatology</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <addr-line>100081</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Orthodontics, Beijing Haidian Hospital, Haidian Section of Peking University Third Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <addr-line>100080</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Sleep Medicine Center, Department of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine, Peking University People’s Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <addr-line>100044</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Central Laboratory, Peking University School and Hospital of Stomatology</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <addr-line>100081</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label><institution>National Engineering Laboratory for Digital and Material Technology of Stomatology &amp; Beijing Key Laboratory of Digital Stomatology</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <addr-line>100081</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Qian Zhang, <institution>Central Laboratory, Peking University School and Hospital of Stomatology</institution>, <addr-line>22 Zhongguancun South Ave</addr-line>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <addr-line>100081</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, <phone>Tel +861082195773</phone>, Email zhangqian860203@163.com</corresp>
        <corresp id="an0002">Xuemei Gao, <institution>Department of Orthodontics, Peking University School and Hospital of Stomatology</institution>, <addr-line>22 Zhongguancun South Ave</addr-line>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <addr-line>100081</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, <phone>Tel +861082195350</phone>, Email xmgao@263.net</corresp>
        <fn id="ft0001">
          <label>*</label>
          <p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>08</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <fpage>593</fpage>
      <lpage>607</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>03</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2022 Chen et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Chen et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p>Microorganisms contribute to the pathogenesis of obstructive sleep apnea (OSA)-associated hypertension (HTN), while more studies focus on intestinal microbiome. However, the relationship between oral microbiota and OSA-associated HTN has yet to be elucidated. This study aimed to identify differences in salivary microbiota between patients with OSA comorbid HTN compared with OSA patients, and furthermore evaluate the relationship between oral microbiome changes and increased blood pressure in patients with OSA.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Patients and Methods</title>
          <p>This study collected salivary samples from 103 participants, including 27 healthy controls, 27 patients with OSA, 23 patients with HTN, and 26 patients with OSA comorbid HTN, to explore alterations of the oral microbiome using 16S rRNA gene V3-V4 high-throughput sequencing. And ultra-high-performance liquid chromatography was used for metabolomic analysis.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>Alpha- and beta-diversity analyses revealed a substantial difference in community structure and diversity in patients with OSA comorbid HTN compared with patients with OSA or HTN. The relative abundance of the genus <italic toggle="yes">Actinomyces</italic> was significantly decreased in patients with HTN compared with healthy controls, and those with OSA concomitant HTN compared with the patients in OSA, but was not significantly different between patients with OSA and healthy controls. Linear discriminant analysis effect size and variance analysis also indicated that the genera <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus, Neisseria</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Lautropia</italic> were enriched in HTN. In addition, <italic toggle="yes">Oribacterium</italic> was an unique taxa in the OSA comorbid HTN group compared with the control group. Metabolomic analysis of saliva identified compounds associated with cardiovascular disease in patients with OSA comorbid HTN.2-hydroxyadenine, was significantly increased in the group of patients with OSA compared with controls, and L-carnitine was significantly decreased in patients with OSA comorbid HTN compared with OSA patients.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>This study highlighted noninvasive biomarkers for patients with OSA comorbid HTN. As the first study to find alterations of the salivary microbiome in patients with OSA comorbid HTN, it may provide a theoretical foundation for clinical diagnosis and treatment of this condition.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>OSA</kwd>
        <kwd>hypertension</kwd>
        <kwd>oral microbiome</kwd>
        <kwd>16S rRNA</kwd>
        <kwd>metabolomics</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Program for Multidisciplinary Cooperative Treatment on Major Diseases</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="open-funder-registry">10.13039/501100001809</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Science Foundation of HaiDian Hospital</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported partly by National Program for Multidisciplinary Cooperative Treatment on Major Diseases (PKUSSNMP-201902), National Natural Science Foundation of China (82170102), and Science Foundation of HaiDian Hospital (KYM2017014).</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="6"/>
        <table-count count="3"/>
        <ref-count count="51"/>
        <page-count count="15"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Systemic hypertension, a very common chronic disease, is a leading risk factor for stroke, heart failure, atrial fibrillation, chronic kidney disease, and other life-threatening diseases.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> It also coexists with obstructive sleep apnea (OSA), which is characterized by intermittent and repeated collapse of the upper airway, resulting in intermittent hypoxia (IH), hypercapnia, daytime sleepiness, and other consequences such as hypertension (HTN).<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Approximately 50% of adult patients with OSA have underlying HTN, and OSA is thought to be the cause of 75% of cases of treatment-resistant HTN.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Daytime systolic blood pressure and diastolic blood pressure values have been proven to be significantly positively related to AHI and significantly negatively related to nadir nocturnal oxygen saturation.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Furthermore, a study conducted in Iceland in 2014<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> was the first to apply cluster study analysis to identify subtypes of patients with OSA associated with different comorbidities. Since then, several studies have utilized subtype analysis and revealed that HTN is an important predictive value for subtype identification.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Vavougious et al also found that comorbidities were the hallmarks of moderate and severe OSA phenotypes, and HTN was associated with the comorbidities subtype independently.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> The underlying mechanisms of OSA regulating HTN include increased chemosensory sensitivity leading to daytime sympathetic vasoconstriction, resistance to vascular inflammation, and excessive production of superoxide ions.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></p>
      <p>Individuals harbor distinct microbial communities, with microorganisms affecting the host through synthesis or catabolism and direct host-microbial interactions and signals. Moreover, the imbalance of structures or functions of microbiota is related to various diseases,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> such as breast cancer,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> obesity,<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Sjogren’s syndrome,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> and so on. This provides a new thought for the diagnosis and treatment of diseases. Numerous studies have proposed that microbiota participate in the pathogenesis of HTN. <italic toggle="yes">Veillonella, Actinomyces, Haemophilus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Neisseria</italic> are the most copious taxa among the nitrate-reducing bacteria of the dorsal tongue.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Pamela et al found the concentration of <italic toggle="yes">Neisseria subflava</italic> was significantly higher in subgingival samples of normotensive subjects compared with patients with HTN.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Also, recent studies demonstrated an important link between OSA and microbiomes.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> The nasal microbiome of subjects with severe OSA was rich in <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus, Prevotella</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Veillonella</italic>, and these taxa were associated with inflammatory markers.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Other research revealed a significant decrease of species diversity and abundance in the oropharyngeal microbiota of middle-aged men with OSA compared with subjects without OSA, but concurrently, the proportion of <italic toggle="yes">Neisseria</italic> was higher in the group with severe OSA.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></p>
      <p>Some studies have reported that microbiota may participate in the pathogenesis of OSA-related HTN, with most of these studies focusing on gut microbes. A rat model of OSA verified that the blood pressure effect of a high-fat diet on rats could be reproduced by intestinal flora transplantation.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Probiotics <italic toggle="yes">C. butyricum</italic> and HylonVII reduced gut dysbiosis, loss of epithelial goblet cells, and thinning of the mucus barrier caused by OSA,<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> and prebiotics, probiotics, and transplantation of fecal microbiota may have antihypertensive effects on OSA-related HTN.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> OSA combined with a high-salt diet increased blood pressure through increasing the concentration of blood trimethylamine oxide (TMAO) and depleting <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> in the gut microbiome of rats.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></p>
      <p>As the beginning of the digestive tract, the oral cavity is also rich in microorganisms and variable due to changes of the host microecological environment. Oral microbes are linked to some diseases such as diabetes, systemic sclerosis, and cancer.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Furthermore, research has shown that oral microbiota play important roles in various pathways, including direct invasion, platelet aggregation, oxidative stress response, and inflammatory responses, resulting in cardiovascular disease (CVD) of patients.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> Oral bacteria were recently reported to reduce Th17 cells and increase the M1/M2 macrophage ratio in the small intestine, thereby promoting chronic inflammation.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Ko et al collected oral mucosal samples (including tongue, buccal mucosa, palate) to analyze oral microbiota in patients with OSA-associated HTN.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> And saliva samples have been routinely taken as a representative average of the entire ecosystem of the oral cavity.</p>
      <p>Based on the above, the current study aimed to investigate the association of salivary microbiota with the distinct subtype of OSA combined with HTN, which might indicate new guidance or directions for the treatment of OSA-related HTN.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants, Study Design, and Clinical Assessment</title>
        <p>The study was designed as cross-section study research and was approved by the Institutional Review Board of Peking University Hospital of Stomatology (PKUSSIRB - 201950155). Written informed consent was obtained from all participants. Research conducted in this study adhered to the tenets of the Declaration of Helsinki.</p>
        <p>A total of 103 consecutive participants were recruited to the study from two co-operation general hospitals between June 2019 and November 2020. Inclusion criteria were: &gt;18 years old, male, volunteered in the projects, and met the requirements of each group. Exclusion criteria for the study were: a) inappropriate disease history or serious disease(s)/conditions of all systems other than HTN—for example, serious cardiovascular disease (myocardial infarction, etc.), respiratory disease (chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, COVID-19, etc.), other sleep conditions (insomnia, etc.), serious neuropsychiatric diseases, serious endocrine system conditions (diabetes, etc.) or the presence of a malignant tumor; b) inappropriate oral signs, such as severe periodontitis, Sjogren’s syndrome, oral ulcer, presence of a dental prosthesis in the mouth, or other oral diseases; c) inappropriate lifestyle habits and medical history, including vegan diet, periodontal treatment in the past 6 months, and use of antibiotics within the last 3 months.</p>
        <p>OSA was defined by standard American Academy of Sleep Medicine criteria: AHI≥5 was defined as OSA.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> HTN was diagnosed by ambulatory blood pressure monitoring, defined as 24-hour systolic blood pressure (SBP) ≥130 mmHg or diastolic blood pressure (DBP) ≥80 mmHg or use of medications for HTN, which is equal to clinic SBP ≥140 mmHg or DBP ≥90 mmHg. The measurement of blood pressure accorded with guidelines. Participants sat in a chair relax for at least 5 min, avoided caffeine, exercise and did not smoke for at least 30 min.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></p>
        <p>Four groups were included in the study. There were 27 patients in OSA group who went through full-night hospitalization of polysomnography (PSG) in Sleep Center of Peking University People’s Hospital. The blood pressure of these participants remained at normal levels. The complication group comprised 26 patients who had both OSA and HTN. The control group included 27 patients that did not exhibit positive findings by PSG or blood pressure monitoring. Finally, the HTN group contained 23 patients who came from the Cardiology Department of Beijing Haidian Hospital having been diagnosed by 24-h ambulatory blood pressure monitoring; subjects were recruited to this group when their clinic blood pressure was ≥140/90 mmHg and measured their real-time blood pressure and recorded the data as their blood pressure before saliva collection. Home sleep test indicated that they did not meet the diagnostic conditions of OSA.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Saliva Sample Collection and DNA Extraction</title>
        <p>All subjects did not eat, drink, or brush their teeth for at least 2 h prior to saliva collection at 7:00–9:00 a.m., then rinsed their mouth with pure water, and rested for at least 10 min before saliva collection. A minimum of 3 mL unstimulated whole saliva samples were collected into sterile centrifugal tubes, then immediately placed on ice and processed within 2 h. Saliva samples were centrifuged at 12,000 g for 30 min at 4°C, and the resulting precipitate and supernatant were stored separately at −80°C. Genomic DNA was extracted using a QIAamp DNA mini kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. The purity and concentration of extracted DNA was tested by a NanoDrop 8000 spectrophotometer (NanoDrop Technologies, Wilmington, DE, USA), and the molecular size of the DNA was estimated by 1% agarose gel electrophoresis. DNA samples were stored at −80°C until further use.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>16S rRNA Gene Amplification and Sequencing, and Processing of Sequence Data</title>
        <p>Extracted DNA was used as template to amplify the V3-V4 variable region of bacterial 16S rRNA genes. The forward primer was 5′-ACTCCTACGGGAGGCAGCA-3′ and the reverse primer was 5′-GGACTACHVGGGTWTCTAAT-3′. The thermal cycle consisted of an initial denaturation at 98°C for 5 min, followed by 25 cycles of denaturation at 98°C for 30s, annealing at 53°C for 30s, and extension at 72°C for 45s, then a final extension for 5 min at 72°C. After purification using Vazyme VAHTSTM DNA Clean Beads (Vazyme, Nanjing, China) and quantification by the Quant-iT PicoGreen dsDNA Assay Kit (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA), amplicons were pooled in equal amounts, and paired-end (2×250 bp) sequencing was performed using an Illumina Novaseq<sup>TM</sup> 6000 platform (Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA) at Shanghai Personal Biotechnology Co., Ltd (Shanghai, China). After trimming off the barcodes and primers, the raw sequence data were filtered, denoised, merged, and chimeras removed using the DADA2 plugin. Amplicon sequence variants (ASVs) were classified taxonomically according to the Human Oral Microbiome Database (HOMD) (V15.2).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Metabolomic Analysis of Saliva</title>
        <p>Metabolomic analysis was performed on random samples from each group, including six samples from the control group, six from the HTN group, six from the OSA group, and seven samples from the complication group. The supernatant of the salivary samples was thawed at 4°C and mixed in equal portions of 100 μL with 400 μL cold methanol/acetonitrile (1:1, V/V) to remove protein. The mixture was centrifuged for 15 min (14,000 g, 4°C) and the resulting supernatant was dried in a vacuum centrifuge. For liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry (LC-MS) analysis, the samples were re-dissolved in 100 μL acetonitrile/water (1:1, V/V) solvent. Analyses were performed using an ultra-high-performance liquid chromatography (UHPLC) system (1290 Infinity LC, Agilent Technologies) coupled to a quadrupole time-of-flight mass spectrometer (AB Sciex TripleTOF 6600). The samples were separated on the Agilent 1290 Infinity LC by hydrophilic interaction liquid chromatography (HILIC) column with a column temperature of 25°C, flow rate of 0.5 mL/min, injection volume of 2 μL, and mobile phase composition of 25 mM ammonium acetate, 25 mM ammonia, water, and acetonitrile. QC samples were inserted into the sample queue to monitor and evaluate the stability of the system and the reliability of the experimental data.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) in SPSS 22.0 (IBM, Armonk, NY, USA) was used to evaluate the differences of clinical indicators among the four experimental groups. Sequence data analyses were mainly performed using QIIME2 (2019.4)<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> and R packages (v3.2.0). Multivariate linear regression was performed to test associations between clinical covariates (age, BMI) and the salivary microbiome, with a q-value &lt;0.10 used as significance cut-off. (MaAsLin, Galaxy Version 1.0.1).<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Alpha diversity was measured with the indices of Chao1, Shannon, and Richness, respectively. Beta diversity analysis was performed to investigate the structural variation of microbial communities across samples using Bray-Curtis metrics and was visualized using principal coordinates analysis (PCoA). Comparisons of the similarities between different groups were conducted using Analysis of similarities (Anosim) based on Bray-Curtis metrics. Kruskal–Wallis tests in SPSS 22.0 were used to analyze the different taxa at the genus level, with p&lt;0.05 considered statistically significant. Linear discriminant analysis (LDA) effect size (LEfSe) analysis was used to determine the organisms most likely to explain differences among the groups. A nested cross-validation based on the random forest model was conducted to illustrate the diagnostic value of the salivary microbiome, using a receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve to evaluate the diagnostic value of the salivary microbiome. Microbial functions were predicted by PICRUSt2 with the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) database, and STAMP software was used to identify the difference of pathways by White nonparametric <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test, with p&lt;0.05 considered statistically significant. For metabolomic analyses, after normalizing the total peak intensity to processed data, the R package was used for multivariate data analysis, including Pareto-scaled principal component analysis (PCA) and orthogonal partial least-squares discriminant analysis (OPLS-DA). When VIP value &gt;1, metabolites were further tested at the univariate level by Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test to measure the significance of each metabolite; p&lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Demographic and Clinical Characteristics of the Study Participants</title>
        <p>A total of 103 subjects were recruited to the study. There were 27 patients in the control group, 27 in the OSA group, 23 in the HTN group, and 26 in the complication group (OSA+HTN). General information for the different groups is shown in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. No significant differences were observed in terms of age, body mass index (BMI), and AHI between the OSA group and the complication group, However, SBP and DBP were significantly increased in the complication group compared with the OSA group (p&lt;0.001 and p=0.002 for SBP and DBP, respectively). In addition, compared with the HTN group, the complication group had a considerably higher BMI and AHI (p=0.031 and p=0.001, respectively), despite no significant differences in age, SBP, or DBP. In consideration of age and BMI, were significantly differences among groups, multivariate linear regression analysis revealed that age and BMI did not affect the difference in salivary microbiomes among groups (q &gt;0.10).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic and Clinical Characteristics of the Study Participants</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Item</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HTN</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complication</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value<sup>a</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (y)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.50±5.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.11±11.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.22±10.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.17±9.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001<sup>bd</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.60±3.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.08±2.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.63±3.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.53±3.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001<sup>bcdf</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI (events/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70±1.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.12±23.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.60±0.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.49±23.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001<sup>bdf</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBP (mmHg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">118.07±12.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120.44±10.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">139.04±16.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">137.27±12.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001<sup>cde</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DBP (mmHg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.15±11.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.56±7.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.87±12.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.38±10.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001<sup>cde</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>a</sup>Unadjusted P value for comparison among groups. <sup>b</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 when comparing control vs OSA. <sup>c</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 when comparing control vs HTN. <sup>d</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 when comparing control vs complication. <sup>e</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 when comparing OSA vs complication. <sup>f</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 when comparing HTN vs complication.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: N, number; BMI, body mass index; AHI, apnea hypopnea index; SBP, systolic blood pressure; DBP, diastolic blood pressure; OSA, obstructive sleep apnea; HTN, hypertension; Complication, OSA comorbid HTN.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Diversity and Variation of Salivary Microbiome</title>
        <p>A total of 12,732,407 raw reads were generated from 103 samples, with an average of 123,616 (range from 99,143 to 161,937) sequences per sample. The DADA2 plug-in of QIIME2 was used to select representative sequences, and after filtering, there were 8,683,851 clean reads in total, with an average of 83,402 (range from 57,599 to 119,679) reads per sample. Finally, 51,186 ASVs were detected among the 103 samples. According to the Human Oral Microbiome Database (HOMD) (V15.2), all sequences were classified into taxa. In total, there were 15 phyla, 35 classes, 64 orders, 119 families, and 247 genera detected in the saliva of the 103 patients.</p>
        <p>The shape of the rarefaction curve (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=347630.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 1</ext-link></underline>) demonstrated that the plateauing stage had been reached, indicating that the sequencing depth of all samples was reasonable and the sequencing results could reflect the microbial information in the saliva samples. Alpha diversity among the groups was described by evenness, richness, and diversity. The Chao1 index of the HTN group was considerably lower than that of the control group (p&lt;0.001), whereas there was no significant change in Chao1 index in the OSA and complication groups compared with the control group (p=0.15 and p=0.42, respectively). The Chao1 index was substantially lower in the HTN group compared with the complication group (p=0.014), whereas the Richness index was significantly lower in HTN group compared with control and complication groups (p=0.001 and p=0.0087, respectively). The Shannon index did not reveal a significant variation in alpha diversity among the four groups (p=0.43) (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A–C</xref>). Variation of salivary microbial community structure was investigated using PCoA based on the Bray-Curtis distance (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1D</xref> and <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">E</xref>). Samples obtained from patients in the OSA and complication groups clearly clustered away from those obtained from the control group, highlighting a significant difference in the phylogenetic structures of the salivary microbial communities (Anosim, p=0.026 for control vs OSA group; p=0.014 for control vs complication group, respectively). In addition, there were significant differences among the control, HTN, and complication groups (Anosim, p=0.001 for control vs HTN group; p=0.021 for HTN vs complication group, respectively).<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The Alpha and Beta diversity. The Alpha diversity was estimated by Chao1 index (<bold>A</bold>), Shannon index (<bold>B</bold>) and Richness index (<bold>C</bold>). Both Chao1 index and Richness index was significantly decreased in HTN group (p&lt;0.001) compared with control group. Compared with complication group (OSA+HTN), Chao1 index and Richness index was significantly decreased in HTN group (p=0.014, p=0.0087, respectively). Alpha diversity by Shannon index did not show a significant difference among these 4 groups (p=0.43). Beta diversity was calculated using bray_curties distance by PCoA to analyze the variation of salivary microbial community structure (<bold>D</bold> and <bold>E</bold>). *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-593-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: OSA, obstructive sleep apnea; HTN, hypertension.</attrib></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Taxa Composition of Salivary Microbiome</title>
        <p>The top 10 phyla in terms of abundance are presented in <xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>. <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes, Actinobacteria, Proteobacteria</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic> were four components in the saliva microbiome with a relative abundance greater than 10%. At the genus level, <xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref> shows the top 20 most abundant taxa. The genera with highest abundance in the HTN group were <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus, Lautropia, Neisseria, Fusobacterium</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Aggregatibacter</italic> based on the heatmap. The genera <italic toggle="yes">Peptostreptococcaceae_[XI][G-1], Actinomyces, Absconditabacteria_(SR1)_[G-1], Granulicatella, Corynebacterium</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Peptostreptococcus</italic> had the highest abundance in the OSA group, while <italic toggle="yes">Porphyromonas, Leptotrichia</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Treponema</italic> exhibited a higher abundance in the complication group (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2C</xref>).<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic profile of salivary microbes among patients with OSA (n=27), HTN (n=23), OSA with HTN (n=26) and healthy controls (n=27). Composition of Salivary microbiota at the phylum level (<bold>A</bold>) and genus level (<bold>B</bold>). The heatmap shows relative abundance of microbiota at the genus level in each group (<bold>C</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-593-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: OSA, obstructive sleep apnea; HTN, hypertension.</attrib></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Comparison of Bacterial Flora Characteristics Among Different Groups</title>
        <p>Compared with the control group, the abundances of <italic toggle="yes">Rothia, Granulicatella</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Peptostreptococcus</italic> in the OSA group were significantly increased (p=0.027, p=0.013, and p=0.014, respectively), while that of the genus <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus</italic> was decreased (p=0.032). Correspondingly, <italic toggle="yes">Rothia</italic> was also increased in the complication group (p=0.014 vs the control group), and <italic toggle="yes">Absconditabacteria_(SR1)_[G-1]</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Oribacterium</italic> were significantly decreased (p=0.033 and p=0.016, respectively), compared with controls. While the other three genera <italic toggle="yes">Granulicatella, Peptostreptococcus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus</italic> had no significant difference in the complication group compared with the control group. Moreover, the abundances of <italic toggle="yes">Actinomyces, Absconditabacteria_(SR1)_[G-1]</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Peptostreptococcaceae_[XI][G-1]</italic> were significantly decreased (p=0.029, p=0.009, and p=0.02, respectively) in the complication group compared with the OSA group.</p>
        <p>Compared with the control group, three genera, including <italic toggle="yes">Rothia, Neisseria</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Lautropia</italic>, were significantly increased in the HTN group (p=0.004, p=0.043, and p&lt;0.001, respectively), while <italic toggle="yes">Actinomyces</italic> was significantly decreased (p=0.044). Furthermore, compared with the HTN group, the abundances of <italic toggle="yes">Lautropia</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus</italic> were significantly decreased in the complication group (p=0.01 and p=0.003, respectively) and that of <italic toggle="yes">Peptostreptococcus</italic> was significantly increased (p=0.019) (<xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). Detailed statistics represented in <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=347630.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link></underline>.<fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Comparison of the relative abundance of the top 20 genera with changes in relative abundance. *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-593-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: OSA, obstructive sleep apnea; HTN, hypertension.</attrib></fig></p>
        <p>The LEfSe method was applied to analyze more specific differences in microflora composition and look for potential biomarkers of the four experimental groups. A cladogram representative of salivary microbial structure and predominant bacteria showing the greatest differences in taxa among the four groups was produced based on an LDA threshold of 2 (<xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). At the genus level, the predominant bacteria of the OSA group were <italic toggle="yes">Peptostreptococcaceae__XI__G_1_, Peptostreptococcus, Parvimonas, Mogibacterium, Pseudopropionibacterium</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Peptidiphaga</italic>, while <italic toggle="yes">Neisseria, Rothia, Haemophilus, Lautropia, Campylobacter, Kingella, Cardiobacterium, Ralstonia, Flavitalea</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Anaeroglobus</italic> were enriched in the HTN group. In addition, the genus <italic toggle="yes">Johnsonella</italic> occupied an important position in the complication group.<fig position="float" id="f0004" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Predicted salivary microbiome taxa by linear discriminant analysis effect size (LEfSe), of OSA group (n=27), HTN group (n=23), OSA with HTN group (n=26) and healthy controls (n=27). (<bold>A</bold>) Histogram of taxonomic. (<bold>B</bold>) Cladogram of taxonomic. Each dot represents a taxonomic hierarchy, from inner to outer circles represented taxa from phylum to genus level. Linear discriminant analysis (LDA) score&gt;2 indicates significant bacterial differences among four groups. Prefix p_phylum, c_class, o_order, f_family and g_genus.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-593-g0004" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: OSA, obstructive sleep apnea; HTN, hypertension.</attrib></fig></p>
        <p>Microbial functions were predicted by PICRUSt2 using the KEGG database and indicated that pathways of nitrogen metabolism, citrate cycle, bacterial secretion system, toluene degradation, phenylalanine metabolism, lipopolysaccharide biosynthesis, and fatty acid metabolism had significantly higher abundance in the HTN group compared with the control group. In addition, compared with control group, the pathways of metabolism of xenobiotics by cytochrome P450, polyketide sugar unit biosynthesis, phosphonate and phosphinate metabolism, and proteasome exhibited significantly higher abundance in the OSA group. Furthermore, the KEGG pathways of vasopressin-regulated water reabsorption, steroid biosynthesis, inositol phosphate metabolism, and lipoic acid metabolism presented significantly lower abundance in the complication group compared with the OSA group (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=347630.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figures 2</ext-link></underline>–<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=347630.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">6</ext-link></underline>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2005">
        <title>Identification of Genus-Based Microbial Markers</title>
        <p>To illustrate the diagnostic value of the salivary microbiome for the OSA and complication groups, random forest classifier models were constructed to identify OSA samples from control samples (model 1), complication samples from HTN samples (model 2), and complication samples from OSA samples (model 3), and a nested cross-validation was then conducted on these random forest models. In model 1, all patients with OSA were included, that is, patients with OSA in the model included both those from the OSA group and those from the complication group, and this combined grouping was renamed all-OSA group. The model was shown by ROC curve analysis, and the area under the ROC curve (AUC) value was 91.9% (95% CI, 85.35–98.51%). In model 2, five genera were selected as the optimal marker set and achieved an AUC value of 94.7% (95% CI, 86.57–100%). These five genera were <italic toggle="yes">Cronobacter, Escherichia, Kingella, Oribacterium</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Peptostreptococcus</italic>. Moreover, in model 3, <italic toggle="yes">Anaeroglobus, Bacteroides, Fretibacterium, Solobacterium</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Veillonella</italic> were selected as optimal marker genera and the AUC value was 78.5% (95% CI, 65.85–91.13%) (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5A–C</xref>).<fig position="float" id="f0005" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) for ASVs-based markers identified by random forest models. (<bold>A</bold>) Prediction of the key genera for all-OSA (OSA+complication) group from control group, area under the parametric curve (AUC)=91.9% (95% CI, 85.35–98.51%). (<bold>B</bold>) AUC value achieved 94.7% (95% CI, 86.57–100%) between HTN group and complication (OSA+HTN) group. (<bold>C</bold>) AUC value achieved 78.5% (95% CI, 65.85–91.13%) between OSA group and complication (OSA+HTN) group.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-593-g0005" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: OSA, obstructive sleep apnea; HTN, hypertension.</attrib></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2006">
        <title>Salivary Metabolomics</title>
        <p>PCA of the metabolomics samples revealed that the QC samples were closely clustered in the positive mode, indicating that the experimental results were reproducible. In addition, there was a tendency of separation among the groups. Data were interrogated based on the orthogonal partial least-squares discrimination analysis (OPLS-DA), which established intergroup separation between the OSA group and the control group (<xref rid="f0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6A</xref>), and between the complication and control groups (<xref rid="f0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6B</xref>). The discriminant metabolites that account for the intergroup separation, between the complication and HTN groups, and between the complication group and the OSA group, were also identified by OPLS-DA (<xref rid="f0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6C</xref> and <xref rid="f0006" ref-type="fig">D</xref>). Four discriminant metabolites were measured in the OSA group relative to the control group, (2-hydroxyadenine, erucic acid, 7-methylxanthine, and pyruvaldehyde), while 26 discriminant metabolites were measured in the HTN group relative to the control group. The levels of 2-hydroxyadenine and 7-methylxanthine were significantly increased in the patients with OSA (p=0.004 and p=0.04, respectively) compared with the control group. Furthermore, there were 6 metabolites that were altered in the complication group compared with the OSA group, while four discriminant metabolites (L-carnitine, Tyr-Gln, N-(omega)-hydroxyarginine, and His-Ala) were measured in the complication group compared with the HTN group; all four of these metabolites were significantly increased in the complication group compared with HTN group.(p=0.038, p=0.039, p=0.045, and p=0.048, respectively). The changes in metabolites are shown in <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=347630.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 2</ext-link></underline> and <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=347630.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figures 7</ext-link></underline>–<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=347630.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">11</ext-link></underline>.<fig position="float" id="f0006" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Score plots of the orthogonal partial least-squares discriminant analysis (OPLS-DA) model for saliva samples. (<bold>A</bold>) OPLS-DA model for OSA and control group, the model parameters were: R<sup>2</sup>X=0.344 R<sup>2</sup>Y=0.949 Q<sup>2</sup>=0.352. (<bold>B</bold>) OPLS-DA model for complication (OSA+HTN) and control group, the model parameters were R<sup>2</sup>X=0.619 R<sup>2</sup>Y=0.998 Q<sup>2</sup>=0.772. (<bold>C</bold>) OPLS-DA model for complication (OSA+ HTN) and HTN group, the model parameters were: R<sup>2</sup>X=0.609 R<sup>2</sup>Y=0.993 Q<sup>2</sup>=0.587. (<bold>D</bold>) OPLS-DA model for complication (OSA+HTN) and OSA group, the model parameters were: R<sup>2</sup>X=0.378 R<sup>2</sup>Y=0.881 Q<sup>2</sup>=−0.0792.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-593-g0006" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: OSA, obstructive sleep apnea; HTN, hypertension.</attrib></fig></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In recent years, attention has increased towards OSA combined with HTN.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> This subtype of OSA is common and greatly impacts health. However, these patients have fewer typical OSA symptoms such as sleep disturbance and daytime sleepiness, so it may not be easily detected in clinical practice, and it is also somewhat inconvenient to identify in the case of troublesome polysomnography. Therefore, the identification of biomarkers for this subtype of OSA is desirable and may facilitate a more targeted treatment approach. Studies of the gut microbiome of patients with OSA have revealed that the microbiome is associated with OSA-related HTN, but there are limited studies examining oral microbiomes in patients with OSA.</p>
      <p>Saliva samples have been routinely taken as a representative average of the entire ecosystem of the oral cavity, therefore, the current study conducted salivary microbiome analysis in patients with OSA combined with HTN to confirm the hypothesis that oral microbiomes might be associated with the distinct subtype of OSA combined with HTN. Alpha diversity of patients with OSA or HTN decreased compared with the control group, indicating a decrease in the richness of the microflora, which was similar to the results of previous studies.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> Simultaneously, beta-diversity analysis suggested there was significantly different community evolution structures among the different groups of patients. Ko et al found the abundance of the <italic toggle="yes">Porphyromonas</italic> was significantly higher in oral mucosal samples of OSA patients with or without HTN compared with controls. Furthermore, the abundance of the <italic toggle="yes">Syntrophomonas</italic> was significantly higher in patients with mild OSA plus HTN compared with that in patients with mild OSA without HTN.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> We did not find <italic toggle="yes">Porphyromonas</italic> has significant different among groups probably because saliva samples were taken in our study. Moreover, individuals with HTN but without OSA were recruited in our study to verify whether the microbiological alterations were caused by HTN or OSA.</p>
      <p>In the current study, some taxa correlated with OSA-related HTN were defined. <italic toggle="yes">Rothia</italic> was relatively more abundant in all three disease groups (OSA, HTN, and complication) compared with the control group. A previous study reported that <italic toggle="yes">Rothia</italic> was correlated with apnea-hypopnea of patients with severe OSA,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> while another study showed that <italic toggle="yes">Rothia</italic> was present at a high level in the gut microbiome of people with HTN,<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> which was congruent with the current study. Therefore, <italic toggle="yes">Rothia</italic> may indicate the emergence of a disease state or unhealthy outcomes. In addition, in most of the oral microbial studies on diseases, an increased abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Oribacterium</italic> is associated with oral lesions.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> In the current study, <italic toggle="yes">Oribacterium</italic> was a specific taxa in the complication group compared with control group, and while the underlying mechanism for the OSA-related HTN was not identified, it might be that <italic toggle="yes">Oribacterium</italic> can be used as a biomarker of the complication group as it was proved in random forest model 2 to distinguish patients of the complication group from those in the HTN group. Furthermore, in the current study, the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Actinomyces</italic> was significantly lower in the complication group compared with the OSA group, and as one of the most copious taxa among the nitrate-reducing bacteria, it was also decreased in the HTN group. Nitrate-reducing bacteria such as <italic toggle="yes">Actinomyces</italic> were found on the dorsum of the tongue, cleaning of the tongue and the use of chlorhexidine mouthwash prevents increased proportion of nitrate reducing species.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> However, there was no significant difference between the OSA and control groups. Therefore, we speculate that the decrease of <italic toggle="yes">Actinomyces</italic> in patients with OSA is associated with a potential mechanism of OSA-related hypertension, and it may be possible to predict the tendency to develop HTN in patients with OSA by the reduction of Actinomyces in the salivary microbiome of these individuals.</p>
      <p>As the second largest biobank in the human body, microbes have attracted increasing attention regarding the occurrence and development of diseases. Various microorganisms exist in human tissues and organs, including the skin, digestive tract, oral cavity, and so on. The oral microbiome is related to nitrate metabolism and cardiovascular health. Approximately 1/4 of the nitrate intake returns to the mouth via an entero-salivary nitrate-nitrite-nitric oxide (NO) pathway.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Nitrate-reducing bacteria in oral cavity can reduce nitrate to nitrite, which is absorbed into the bloodstream through the digestive tract and converted into NO,<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> a multifunctional signaling molecule involved in cardiovascular homeostasis and an effective endogenous vasodilator. Blockage of the nitrate-nitrite-NO pathway by the use of antimicrobial mouthwash was paralleled by a small increase in SBP in treated men and women with HTN.<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> Findings from the current study are consistent with this theory, hence the development of the hypothesis that the decrease of <italic toggle="yes">Actinomyces</italic>, which leads to the decrease of NO production, is associated with the increase of blood pressure in patients in the HTN and complication groups. The relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Absconditabacteria_(SR1)</italic> in the oral flora of patients with inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) was higher than normal, and was positively correlated with the levels of inflammatory cytokines such as fecal calprotectin.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>
<italic toggle="yes">Absconditabacteria_(SR1)</italic> may be related to the inflammatory state caused by OSA, but there was no evidence of a possible mechanism of OSA-related HTN associated with <italic toggle="yes">Absconditabacteria_(SR1)_[G-1]</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Peptostreptococcaceae_[XI][G-1]</italic> in the previous literature, therefore we regarded these taxa more likely as outcome indicators. <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic> are known to be related to the production of acetate, one of the short-chain fatty acids (SCFAs) that result from anaerobic fermentation of dietary fibers by gut microbiota and which has an important vasodilator effect.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> However, no significant differences of <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic> were identified among the four groups in the current study.</p>
      <p>In addition, <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus, Neisseria</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Lautropia</italic> were speculated to be biomarkers of HTN. <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus</italic>, another nitrate-reducing bacteria,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> had a significantly lower abundance in the complication group compared with the HTN group, while simultaneously presented a significantly lower level in the OSA group compared with the control group. Consequently, we speculate that OSA might cause HTN by reducing the production of <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus</italic>. Furthermore, the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Neisseria</italic> in the HTN group was significantly higher than that in the control group, which was consistent with previous studies on intestinal microorganisms in patients with HTN.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Concurrently, in a study of oral microorganisms and salivary NO, <italic toggle="yes">Neisseria</italic> was more abundant in subjects with HTN compared with normal subjects, suggesting that the concentration of this bacteria was a biomarker for the development of HTN.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Moreover, <italic toggle="yes">Lautropia</italic> exhibited a significantly higher relative abundance in the HTN group compared with the control group in the current study. This was consistent with a previous study showing that <italic toggle="yes">Lautropia</italic> was higher in abundance in pharyngeal swabs from patients with pulmonary HTN that from control samples.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> In OSCC cell lines, <italic toggle="yes">Lautropia mirabilis</italic> upregulated IL-6 and TNF-α, which are cytokines related to the inflammatory response.<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> All these genera were verified in LEfSe analysis in the current study.</p>
      <p>Bacterial metabolites may also be responsible for OSA-related HTN. Oral microorganisms may contribute to the occurrence of cardiovascular disease through direct invasion, immune responses, promotion of platelet aggregation, inflammatory responses, and oxidative stress responses.<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> OSA may induce related inflammatory factors such as C-reactive protein, TNF-α, and IL-6,<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> through oral bacterial pathogens, like <italic toggle="yes">Rothia, Haemophilus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Actinomyces</italic>, which can promote the occurrence and development of HTN. DNA and lipopolysaccharide from oral bacterial pathogens activate nuclear factor-κB (NF-κB) and activator protein 1 (AP1), which lead to increased production of inflammatory factors and activation of neutrophils, leading to the production of numerous reactive oxygen species (ROS).<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> Intermittent hypoxia induced by OSA induces systemic inflammation and sympathetic hyperactivity by enhancing the production of ROS. The ROS-HIF-1-endothelium signaling pathway and the ROS-TLR-NF-κB signaling pathway are responsible for hypertension and cardiovascular dysfunction in patients with OSA.<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> In addition, hypoxia induced by OSA can lead to mitochondrial dysfunction, which affects related enzyme systems, such as endothelial NO synthase production.<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></p>
      <p>Previous study compared clinical chemistry measurements of enzymes, metabolites between patients with HTN and controls,<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> few studies used metabolomic to analysis metabolites in patients with HTN, especially OSA related HTN. Ultra-high-performance liquid chromatography was used for metabolomic analysis to screen for differential metabolites in our study, including indicators that are not routinely used in clinical. Metabolomic analysis found evidence of cardiovascular damage associated with OSA. As previously stated, OSA enhances ROS production. 2-Hydroxyadenine, a purine produced in cells by reactive oxygen,<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> was significantly increased in the group of patients with OSA in the current study. Meanwhile, L-carnitine was significantly decreased in the complication group compared with the OSA group, and this metabolite triggers cardioprotective effects through reduced inflammation, oxidative stress, and necrosis of cardiac myocytes, and can also reduce HTN.<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> The decrease of L-carnitine in the complication group may be responsible for the increase of blood pressure in these patients.</p>
      <p>This study does have some limitations. OSA may have an impact on multiple systems of the whole body. In the study, HTN was confirmed with 24-h ambulatory blood pressure monitoring, OSA was confirmed with full-night hospitalization PSG, and the medical history and complications of all subjects were carefully taken in the study. However, it is inevitable that other complications, although very minor, might also interfere with the data. Such as age and BMI, thought they were proved no influence on the comparison among groups they should be better matched in the future study. Moreover, salivary flora has the advantage of easy collection and may induce changes in the gut microbiome through swallowing, but the performance of bacteria in the mouth is not necessarily identical to their role(s) in the intestine. This study allows the screening different flora, but causal relationships between salivary flora and disease require further study by verification of CPAP therapy intervention or through in vivo experiments. In addition, this study does not represent the performance of other genders, ages, and regional races.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>This study demonstrates the characteristic changes in salivary microbiota of patients with OSA, patients with HTN, and patients with both OSA and HTN. Findings from the study led to the hypothesis that the decrease of <italic toggle="yes">Actinomyces</italic> may be associated with OSA-related HTN. To identify specific microbial markers for the different groups of patients, models were constructed to distinguish all-OSA patients from control subjects, patients with OSA and HTN (complication group) from patients with OSA, and patients with OSA and HTN (complication group) from patients with HTN. The diagnostic efficacy of these models was validated and highlights potential noninvasive diagnostic biomarkers for the subtype of OSA that is associated with HTN. Moreover, bacterial metabolites may also be responsible for OSA-related hypertension. OSA produced ROS can increased 2-hydroxyadenine indirectly. And the decrease of L-Carnitine may be associated with the hypertension in OSA patients.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We thank Dr Bing Zhou, Yuhua Zuo, Xueli Zhang, Long Zhao, Jing Li (Sleep Center of Peking University People’s Hospital), Dr Qingchun Ma (Cardiology Department of Peking University People’s Hospital), Dr Liping Song, and Ping Han (Cardiology Department of Beijing Haidian Hospital) for help in sample collection and generous volunteer subjects who recruited in this study. We also thank all the participants in the trial.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <p>OSA, obstructive sleep apnea; HTN, hypertension; BMI, body mass index; AHI, apnea hypopnea index; SBP, systolic blood pressure; DBP, diastolic blood pressure.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p>The sequencing data from this study have been deposited in Genome Sequence Archive in National Genomics Data Center, China National Center for Bioinformation/Beijing Institute of Genomics, Chinese Academy of Sciences (GSA: CRA006039) that are publicly accessible at <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://ngdc.cncb.ac.cn/gsa" ext-link-type="uri">https://ngdc.cncb.ac.cn/gsa</ext-link></underline>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0008">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation, or in all these areas: took part in drafting, revising or critically reviewing the article; gave final approval of the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0009">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fuchs</surname>
<given-names>FD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whelton</surname>
<given-names>PK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>High blood pressure and cardiovascular disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>285</fpage>–<lpage>292</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/hypertensionaha.119.14240</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31865786</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Veasey</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosen</surname>
<given-names>IM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea in adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>380</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>1442</fpage>–<lpage>1449</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMcp1816152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30970189</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pedrosa</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drager</surname>
<given-names>LF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gonzaga</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea: the most common secondary cause of hypertension associated with resistant hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>811</fpage>–<lpage>817</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/hypertensionaha.111.179788</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21968750</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>QY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>XL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Relationship of daytime blood pressure and severity of obstructive sleep apnea among Chinese: a multi-center investigation in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin Med J</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>123</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>18</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20137569</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ye</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pien</surname>
<given-names>GW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ratcliffe</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The different clinical faces of obstructive sleep apnoea: a cluster analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Respir J</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1600</fpage>–<lpage>1607</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.00032314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25186268</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vavougios</surname>
<given-names>GD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>George</surname>
<given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pastaka</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zarogiannis</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gourgoulianis</surname>
<given-names>KI</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Phenotypes of comorbidity in OSAS patients: combining categorical principal component analysis with cluster analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26365653</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dempsey</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Veasey</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morgan</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Donnell</surname>
<given-names>CP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pathophysiology of sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiol Rev</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>90</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>112</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physrev.00043.2008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20086074</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Young</surname>
<given-names>VB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The role of the microbiome in human health and disease: an introduction for clinicians</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>356</volume>:<fpage>j831</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.j831</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28298355</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Douglass</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Prasath</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The microbiome and breast cancer: a review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Breast Cancer Res Treat</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>178</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>493</fpage>–<lpage>496</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10549-019-05407-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31456069</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gopalakrishnan</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Helmink</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spencer</surname>
<given-names>CN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reuben</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wargo</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The influence of the gut microbiome on cancer, immunity, and cancer immunotherapy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cancer Cell</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>570</fpage>–<lpage>580</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccell.2018.03.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29634945</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Maruvada</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leone</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaplan</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>EB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The human microbiome and obesity: moving beyond associations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cell Host Microbe</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>589</fpage>–<lpage>599</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2017.10.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29120742</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tsigalou</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stavropoulou</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bezirtzoglou</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Current insights in microbiome shifts in Sjogren’s syndrome and possible therapeutic interventions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Immunol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1106</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2018.01106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29881381</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pignatelli</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fabietti</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ricci</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Piattelli</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Curia</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>How periodontal disease and presence of nitric oxide reducing oral bacteria can affect blood pressure</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Mol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>7538</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms21207538</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Barbadoro</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ponzio</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coccia</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association between hypertension, oral microbiome and salivary nitric oxide: a case-control study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biol Chem</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>106</volume>:<fpage>66</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.niox.2020.11.002</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cai</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Juszczak</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cope</surname>
<given-names>EK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goldberg</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The microbiome in obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>8</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsab061</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>BG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sulaiman</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Severe obstructive sleep apnea is associated with alterations in the nasal microbiome and an increase in inflammation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Criti Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>199</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201801-0119OC</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shao</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heizhati</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Oropharyngeal microbiome in obstructive sleep apnea: decreased diversity and abundance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1777</fpage>–<lpage>1788</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.8084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31855163</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Durgan</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ganesh</surname>
<given-names>BP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cope</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Role of the gut microbiome in obstructive sleep apnea-induced hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>469</fpage>–<lpage>474</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/hypertensionaha.115.06672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26711739</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ganesh</surname>
<given-names>BP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nelson</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eskew</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prebiotics, probiotics, and acetate supplementation prevent hypertension in a model of obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1141</fpage>–<lpage>1150</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/hypertensionaha.118.11695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30354816</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mashaqi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gozal</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea and systemic hypertension: gut dysbiosis as the mediator?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1517</fpage>–<lpage>1527</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.7990</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31596218</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Lactobacillus rhamnosus GG strain mitigated the development of obstructive sleep apnea-induced hypertension in a high salt diet via regulating TMAO level and CD4(+) T cell induced-type I inflammation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biomed Pharmacother</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>112</volume>:<fpage>108580</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2019.01.041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30784906</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jia</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lai</surname>
<given-names>PFH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The oral microbiota - a mechanistic role for systemic diseases</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Br Dent J</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>224</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>447</fpage>–<lpage>455</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bdj.2018.217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29569607</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Role of the oral microbiota in cancer evolution and progression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cancer Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>6306</fpage>–<lpage>6321</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cam4.3206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32638533</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chistiakov</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Orekhov</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bobryshev</surname>
<given-names>YV</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Links between atherosclerotic and periodontal disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Exp Mol Pathol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>100</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>220</fpage>–<lpage>235</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yexmp.2016.01.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26777261</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>DeSouza</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dengel</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macko</surname>
<given-names>RF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cox</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seals</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Elevated levels of circulating cell adhesion molecules in uncomplicated essential hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Hypertens</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>12 Pt 1</issue>):<fpage>1335</fpage>–<lpage>1341</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0895-7061(97)00268-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9443768</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kobayashi</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ogawa</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hashizume-Takizawa</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kurita-Ochiai</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Oral bacteria affect the gut microbiome and intestinal immunity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pathog Dis</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>78</volume>(<issue>3</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/femspd/ftaa024</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ko</surname>
<given-names>CY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chou</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Analysis of oral microbiota in patients with obstructive sleep apnea-associated hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertens Res</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1692</fpage>–<lpage>1700</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41440-019-0260-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30976074</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Berry</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Budhiraja</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gottlieb</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Rules for scoring respiratory events in sleep: update of the 2007 AASM manual for the scoring of sleep and associated events. deliberations of the sleep apnea definitions task force of the American Academy of Sleep Medicine</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>597</fpage>–<lpage>619</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.2172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23066376</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Whelton</surname>
<given-names>PK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carey</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aronow</surname>
<given-names>WS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>2017 ACC/AHA/AAPA/ABC/ACPM/AGS/APhA/ASH/ASPC/NMA/PCNA Guideline for the prevention, detection, evaluation, and management of high blood pressure in adults: executive summary: a report of the American college of cardiology/American heart association task force on clinical practice guidelines</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1269</fpage>–<lpage>1324</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/hyp.0000000000000066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29133354</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bolyen</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rideout</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dillon</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Reproducible, interactive, scalable and extensible microbiome data science using QIIME 2</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Biotechnol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>852</fpage>–<lpage>857</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41587-019-0209-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31341288</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zinchuk</surname>
<given-names>AV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jeon</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koo</surname>
<given-names>BB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Polysomnographic phenotypes and their cardiovascular implications in obstructive sleep apnoea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Thorax</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>73</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>472</fpage>–<lpage>480</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2017-210431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28935698</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Altered airway microbiota composition in patients with pulmonary hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>76</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1589</fpage>–<lpage>1599</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/hypertensionaha.120.15025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32921193</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dong</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zuo</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Characteristics and variation of fecal bacterial communities and functions in isolated systolic and diastolic hypertensive patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>128</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12866-021-02195-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33902467</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hernandez</surname>
<given-names>BY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goodman</surname>
<given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Betel nut chewing, oral premalignant lesions, and the oral microbiome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e0172196</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0172196</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28225785</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>FY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>QQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Dysbiosis of saliva microbiome in patients with oral lichen planus</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>75</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12866-020-01733-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32245419</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kapil</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Milsom</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Okorie</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Inorganic nitrate supplementation lowers blood pressure in humans: role for nitrite-derived NO</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>274</fpage>–<lpage>281</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/hypertensionaha.110.153536</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20585108</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lundberg</surname>
<given-names>JO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weitzberg</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cole</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benjamin</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Nitrate, bacteria and human health</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>593</fpage>–<lpage>602</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro929</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15197394</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bondonno</surname>
<given-names>CP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Croft</surname>
<given-names>KD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Antibacterial mouthwash blunts oral nitrate reduction and increases blood pressure in treated hypertensive men and women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Hypertens</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>572</fpage>–<lpage>575</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ajh/hpu192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25359409</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Qi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zang</surname>
<given-names>SQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>High-throughput sequencing provides insights into oral microbiota dysbiosis in association with inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Genomics</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>113</volume>(<issue>1 Pt 2</issue>):<fpage>664</fpage>–<lpage>676</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ygeno.2020.09.063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33010388</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rey</surname>
<given-names>FE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Faith</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bain</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Dissecting the in vivo metabolic potential of two human gut acetogens</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Biol Chem</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>285</volume>(<issue>29</issue>):<fpage>22082</fpage>–<lpage>22090</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M110.117713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20444704</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Natarajan</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hori</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Flavahan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Microbial short chain fatty acid metabolites lower blood pressure via endothelial G protein-coupled receptor 41</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiol Genomics</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>826</fpage>–<lpage>834</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physiolgenomics.00089.2016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27664183</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baraniya</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jain</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lucarelli</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Screening of health-associated oral bacteria for anticancer properties in vitro</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Cell Infect Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>575656</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2020.575656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33123499</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zeng</surname>
<given-names>YM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Su</surname>
<given-names>HZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ko</surname>
<given-names>CY</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A review of the association between oral bacterial flora and obstructive sleep apnea-hypopnea syndrome comorbid with cardiovascular disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1261</fpage>–<lpage>1266</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-019-01962-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31758435</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ryan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>CT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McNicholas</surname>
<given-names>WT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Systemic inflammation: a key factor in the pathogenesis of cardiovascular complications in obstructive sleep apnoea syndrome?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Thorax</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>631</fpage>–<lpage>636</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thx.2008.105577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19561283</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>D’Aiuto</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nibali</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parkar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suvan</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Donos</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Oxidative stress, systemic inflammation, and severe periodontitis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Dent Res</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>89</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1241</fpage>–<lpage>1246</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0022034510375830</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20739696</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>YC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Su</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liou</surname>
<given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Co-upregulation of Toll-like receptors 2 and 6 on peripheral blood cells in patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>873</fpage>–<lpage>882</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-014-1116-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25604476</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Janssen</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pathak</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grassi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van de Borne</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Endothelin contributes to the blood pressure rise triggered by hypoxia in severe obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Hypertens</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>118</fpage>–<lpage>124</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/hjh.0000000000001134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27906839</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lavie</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lavie</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Molecular mechanisms of cardiovascular disease in OSAHS: the oxidative stress link</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Respir J</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1467</fpage>–<lpage>1484</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.00086608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19483049</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sohail</surname>
<given-names>MU</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hedin</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Al-Asmakh</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dysbiosis of the salivary microbiome is associated with hypertension and correlated with metabolic syndrome biomarkers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes Metab Syndr Obes</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>4641</fpage>–<lpage>4653</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/dmso.S325073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34858042</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kamiya</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mutagenicities of 8-hydroxyguanine and 2-hydroxyadenine produced by reactive oxygen species</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biol Pharm Bull</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>475</fpage>–<lpage>479</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1248/bpb.27.475</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15056850</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>ZY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>YY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>GH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>HB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mao</surname>
<given-names>CY</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>L-carnitine and heart disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Life Sci</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>194</volume>:<fpage>88</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lfs.2017.12.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29241711</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
