<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35478718</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">9035459</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">359858</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S359858</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Sleep-Related Breathing Disorders in Multiple Sclerosis: Prevalence, Features and Associated Factors</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Sparasci et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Sparasci et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sparasci</surname>
            <given-names>Davide</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8601-423X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Fanfulla</surname>
            <given-names>Francesco</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6937-3065</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Ferri</surname>
            <given-names>Raffaele</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Aricò</surname>
            <given-names>Debora</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Distefano</surname>
            <given-names>Daniela</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5225-2993</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Pravatà</surname>
            <given-names>Emanuele</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Heinzer</surname>
            <given-names>Raphael</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Haba-Rubio</surname>
            <given-names>José</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Berger</surname>
            <given-names>Mathieu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1202-5534</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Riccitelli</surname>
            <given-names>Gianna Carla</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0006" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0007" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0008" ref-type="aff">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gobbi</surname>
            <given-names>Claudio</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0006" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0008" ref-type="aff">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Zecca</surname>
            <given-names>Chiara</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0006" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0008" ref-type="aff">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1849-7196</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Manconi</surname>
            <given-names>Mauro</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0008" ref-type="aff">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Sleep Medicine Unit, Neurocenter of Southern Switzerland</institution>, <addr-line>Lugano</addr-line>, <country>Switzerland</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Sleep Medicine Unit, Istituti Clinici Scientifici Maugeri, IRCCS, Scientific Institute of Pavia</institution>, <addr-line>Pavia</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Sleep Research Centre; Department of Neurology I.C., Oasi Institute for Research on Mental Retardation and Brain Aging (IRCCS)</institution>, <addr-line>Troina</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Neuroradiology Clinic, Ospedale Regionale di Lugano, Neurocenter of Southern Switzerland</institution>, <addr-line>Lugano</addr-line>, <country>Switzerland</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label><institution>Center for Investigation and Research in Sleep (CIRS), Lausanne University Hospital (CHUV) and University of Lausanne</institution>, <addr-line>Lausanne</addr-line>, <country>Switzerland</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0006"><label>6</label><institution>Multiple Sclerosis Center, Neurocenter of Southern Switzerland</institution>, <addr-line>Lugano</addr-line>, <country>Switzerland</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0007"><label>7</label><institution>Neuropsychology and Behavioural Neurology Research Unit, Neurocenter of Southern Switzerland</institution>, <addr-line>Lugano</addr-line>, <country>Switzerland</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0008"><label>8</label><institution>Faculty of Biomedical Sciences, Università della Svizzera Italiana</institution>, <addr-line>Lugano</addr-line>, <country>Switzerland</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Raffaele Ferri, <institution>Sleep Research Centre; Department of Neurology I.C., Oasi Institute for Research on Mental Retardation and Brain Aging (IRCCS)</institution>, <addr-line>Via Conte Ruggero 73</addr-line>, <addr-line>Troina</addr-line>, <addr-line>94018</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country>, Email rferri@oasi.en.it</corresp>
        <fn id="ft0001">
          <label>*</label>
          <p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>20</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <fpage>741</fpage>
      <lpage>750</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2022 Sparasci et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Sparasci et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Multiple sclerosis (MS) represents a risk factor for sleep disorders, but there are conflicting results about the prevalence and severity of sleep-related breathing disorders (SRBD) in MS. Most available data come from self-administered questionnaires.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Objective</title>
          <p>To conduct a polysomnographic study in MS focused on SRBD, compared to a group of healthy controls (HC), also considering the neuroimaging findings. To evaluate the impact of SRBD on vigilance, fatigue and depression in MS.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>In this cross-sectional, observational, instrumental study, 67 MS patients (men/women: 20/47; mean age: 50.6±8.2 years) underwent PSG and maintenance of wakefulness test. Findings were compared to 67 age-, sex-, BMI-matched HC, by using parametric (Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test) and nonparametric statistics (chi-squared test). A subgroup analysis was then performed, evaluating the influence of brainstem (mesencephalic, pontine and medullary) lesions at neuroimaging on instrumental and clinical data: MS patients with at least one brainstem lesion vs MS patients without vs HC.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>The frequency of SRBD was comparable in MS patients and HC. No MS patient had a central apnea index ≥2/h. The respiratory disturbance index (RDI) did not correlate to clinical parameters such as fatigue and depression. Patients with MS were drowsier than HC (47% vs 26%, p = 0.019) and showed a worse sleep pattern, in terms of duration, efficiency and architecture.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2005">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>Our study does not provide evidence of an association between MS-specific symptoms such as fatigue, sleepiness, depression and central or obstructive apneas, even in the presence of brainstem lesions.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>sleep-related breathing disorders</kwd>
        <kwd>multiple sclerosis</kwd>
        <kwd>sleep quality</kwd>
        <kwd>polysomnography</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="2"/>
        <table-count count="6"/>
        <ref-count count="35"/>
        <page-count count="10"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Multiple sclerosis (MS) is an immune-mediated demyelinating and neurodegenerative disease of the central nervous system, which represents the leading cause of nontraumatic neurological disability in young adults. Up to 50% of patients with multiple sclerosis (MS) are at increased risk for sleep disorders.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Insomnia and restless legs syndrome (RLS) represent the most common sleep complaints<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> in MS, with significant impact on quality of life and critical symptoms, such as fatigue.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Despite this, sleep is yet underinvestigated in patients with MS. Although a growing amount of literature on sleep and MS has become available in the past decade, only a few studies have evaluated prospectively sleep by polysomnography (PSG).<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></p>
      <p>MS and sleep-related breathing disorders (SRBD) have shared consequences, such as fatigue, sleepiness, cognitive impairment and depression, which may contribute to increased morbidity. Although some contend that the prevalence and severity of SRBD are higher in persons with MS, the current literature reports conflicting results,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> and most of the available data come from self-administered questionnaires studies.</p>
      <p>Little is known about the pathophysiological mechanisms that contribute to SRBD in people with MS and vice versa. Some speculate that obstructive sleep apnoea syndrome (OSAS) could worsen MS-related disability or progression through its association with local/systemic inflammation.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> On the other hand, MS-related central nervous system lesions, in particular in areas critical for respiration, like the brainstem, might contribute to both obstructive and central sleep apnoea.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></p>
      <p>The primary aim of the current study was to compare prevalence, severity and PSG features of SRBD in patients with MS and healthy controls and their correlations with neuroimaging findings. Secondary aims were to look for clinical determinants of SRBD in MS and to evaluate the impact of SRBD on vigilance, fatigue and depression in MS.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p>A cross-sectional, observational study in a sample of patients older than 18 years old and affected by MS according to McDonald criteria<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> or clinically isolated syndromes (CIS)<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> was carried out. Additional inclusion criteria were an Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS) score &lt;7.0 (range 0–10),<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> and a brain magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) performed within the 12 months preceding the evaluation. MRI exams were performed using 3T Magnetom “Skyra” (Siemens, Erlangen, Germany) scanner with a 20-channel head coil. All participants were examined with a conventional protocol before and after contrast administration (0.1 mmol/Kg of Gadobutrolum). Sagittal 1-mm fluid-attenuated-inversion-recovery (FLAIR) 3D T2-weighted and axial 3 mm dual echo (T2/proton-density weighted) images were acquired and employed to assess the number of T2-visible lesions in the brainstem, subdivided in mesencephalic, pontine and medullary. All images were reviewed by a neuroradiologist (D.D.), blinded to clinical data.</p>
        <p>Exclusion criteria were: Mini Mental Status Examination (MMSE) score lower than 24; clinical MS relapse within the last 3 months; radiologically isolated syndrome (RIS); history of drug and/or alcohol abuse; any serious general medical condition such as decompensated cardiopulmonary disease, cancer or decompensated renal failure, as well as any major neurological condition other than MS that could interfere with the correct execution of the study design. MS was classified as primary progressive, secondary progressive, or relapsing-remitting.</p>
        <p>A group of healthy controls (HC), age-, sex- and body mass index (BMI)-matched with MS patients, was randomly selected by the HypnoLaus Sleep Cohort,<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> which is a large population-based cohort recruited in Lausanne (Switzerland). They had to be in general good health and were excluded if any of the following was present: a diagnosis of any significant sleep disorder(s) other than SRBD, major mental illness including any indications of cognitive problems as determined by history. A full-night home PSG had been previously recorded in the group of controls, in the same standard way adopted for MS patients.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></p>
        <p>All procedures performed in this study were in accordance with the Helsinki declaration and the protocol was approved by the Ethics Committee: Comitato etico cantonale (Ufficio di Sanità, 6501 Bellinzona, Switzerland), Trial No.: EOC.NSI.13.02. All participants signed an informed consent.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Questionnaires</title>
        <p>Patients were interviewed concerning their medical history; received a complete clinical and neurological examination, including the Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS) score assessment. All participants filled in the following questionnaires: Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS) (range: 0–24; cutoff for normality: ≤10), Beck Depression Inventory (BDI) (range: 0–21; cutoff for normality: &lt;9), Multiple Sclerosis Quality of Life (MSQoL) (range: 0–84; cutoff for normality: &lt;38), Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) (range: 0–21; cutoff for normality: &lt;5), Fatigue Severity Scale (FSS) (range: 9–63; cutoff for normality: 36), Modified Fatigue Impact Scale (MFIS) (range: 0–84; cutoff for normality: 38).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Polysomnography and Maintenance of Wakefulness Test</title>
        <p>Within one week from the screening visit, participants underwent a full night PSG by a portable device (Embletta ST + Proxy), and a maintenance of wakefulness test (MWT) the following day (the latter not available for the controls).</p>
        <p>The PSG montage included the following: EEG, electrooculogram, electromyogram (EMG) of chin and both tibialis anterior muscles, electrocardiogram, body position; oro-nasal airflow (nasal pressure cannula), thoracic and abdominal movements, and oxygen saturation.</p>
        <p>Apnea was scored in the presence of a drop in the nasal pressure signal peak amplitude by ≥90% of the pre-event baseline, lasting ≥10 s, while hypopnea when it drop by ≥30% of the pre-event baseline, in association with either ≥3% arterial oxygen desaturation or an arousal.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> The diagnosis of OSAS was established in the presence of: 1) complaints of diurnal sleepiness (ESS ≥10) and an apnea/hypopnea index (AHI) &gt;5/h; or 2) AHI ≥15/h.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></p>
        <p>The MWT quantify, under PSG recording, the ability to stay awake in sleep-promoting environmental conditions.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> Patients were instructed to stay awake during the four sessions, each of 40 min of recording. Sleep latency was assessed in each of the four recordings and then the average of latencies was calculated.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>Descriptive statistics were used, followed by between-group comparisons by means of the Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test. Frequency data were analyzed by means of the chi-squared test. Correlations were assessed by means of the Pearson’s correlation coefficient; following the indications by Cohen,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> we considered correlations 0.10, 0.30, and 0.50 as corresponding to small, medium, and large sizes, respectively. One-way between-groups analysis of variance (ANOVA) was conducted to explore the impact of brainstem lesions on instrumental and clinical parameters.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>Sixty-seven patients with MS (56 (86.3%) relapsing-remitting), whom 47 women (70.1%), with a mean age of 50.6±8.2 years and a mean BMI of 25.4±5.3 kg/m<sup>2</sup>, completed the study. Sixty-seven healthy subjects matched for sex, age and BMI served as a control group (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic and Clinical Parameters</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="2" align="center">MS (n=67)</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="2" align="center">HC (n=67)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age, mean, SD</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">±8.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">±6.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.s.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Male, n, %</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.s.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Female, n, %</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.s.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>BMI (kg/m2), mean, SD</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">±5.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">±4.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.s.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CIS, n, %</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>RR-MS, n, %</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SP-MS, n, %</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PP-MS, n, %</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>EDSS, mean, SD</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">±1.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Patients with:</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mesencephalic lesions, n, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Pontine lesions, n, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Medullary lesions, n, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>DMTs:</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> None, n, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Injectables, n, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Orals, n, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Antibodies, n, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: MS, multiple sclerosis; HC, healthy controls; BMI, body mass index; CIS, clinical isolated syndrome; RR-MS, relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis; SP-MS, secondary progressive multiple sclerosis; PPMS, primary progressive multiple sclerosis; EDSS, expanded disability status scale; DMTs, disease modifying treatments; n.s, not significant.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      <p>Among patients with MS, 64.2% were fatigued, with a mean FSS and MFIS score of, respectively, 41.7±16.9 and 42.7±22.4 points. 11.9% of patients had a severe disability with an EDSS ≥4, and 63.5% of all patients were depressed, according to the BDI score.</p>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>MS Vs Control Group</title>
        <p>As illustrated in <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>, the proportion of MS with a RDI &gt;5/h, &gt;15/h, &gt;30/h was 40.3%, 16.4% and 4.5%, respectively, while corresponding figures were 58.2% (p = 0.057), 29.9% (p = 0.100), 11.9% (p = 0.210) in healthy controls.<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Frequency of sleep-related breathing disorders in patients with multiple sclerosis and in healthy controls.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-741-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: MS, multiple sclerosis; HC, healthy controls; RDI, respiratory disturbance index; OSAS, obstructive sleep apnea syndrome; n.s, not significant.</attrib></fig></p>
        <p>The diagnosis of OSAS was more frequent in healthy controls than in the MS group, without reaching statistical significance (35.9% vs 25.4%, p = 0.262). The percentage of patients with an AHI &gt;15/h in the supine position was 22.4% in the MS group. AHI during REM sleep (AHI-<sub>REM</sub>) did not differ between healthy subjects and patients (p = 0.35). All subjects with an AHI &gt;5/h had obstructive sleep apnea, no patient had a central or mixed AHI &gt;2/h.</p>
        <p>Patients had a higher sleep onset latency (p = 0.001), awakening index (p &lt; 0.001), and a lower sleep efficiency (p &lt; 0.001), total sleep time (p &lt; 0.001), percentage of slow wave sleep (p = 0.07) and REM sleep (p &lt; 0.001), when compared to controls (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Sleep quality impairment was also reflected by PSQI scores (p &lt; 0.001, t = 7.465).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Polysomnographic Parameters</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MS + BS Lesions<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>(n = 31)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MS – BS Lesions<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>(n = 36)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MS (n = 67)<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HC (n = 67)<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> Values</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Total sleep time, min</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">351.3±63.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">368.3±59.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">360.3±61.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">406.1±66.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt; 0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,2,3 vs 4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep latency, min</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.5±33.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.3±33.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.9±34.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.6±22.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,3 vs 4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Awakenings/hour</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1±5.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5±2.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7±4.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.4±9.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt; 0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,2,3 vs.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep efficiency, %</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.0±11.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.9±10.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.1±11.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.6±9.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.032</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 vs 2; 3 vs.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Stage N1, %</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1±4.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3±4.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2±4.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2±6.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.s.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Stage N2, %</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.5±10.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.7±9.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.5±10.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.3±9.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.s.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Stage N3, %</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8±8.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.1±8.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5±8.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.7±9.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,3 vs 4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Stage REM, %</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.3±7.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.0±6.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.2±6.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.9±5.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt; 0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,2,3 vs 4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>WASO, min</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.8±45.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.1±37.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.8±40.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.3±48.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.s.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PLMSI</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.1±19.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5±29.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.8±25.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0±14.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.s.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AHI</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3±16.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8±6.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9±12.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4±14.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.s.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>RDI</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9±16.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8±6.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9±12.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6±15.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.s.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Supine AHI</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.8±20.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9±17.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.7±18.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.a.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.s.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>REM AHI</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8±18.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5±16.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8±17.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.3±17.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.s.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ODI</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9±11.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0±5.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5±8.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5±14.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.s.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>T90</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9±7.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2±3.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6±5.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3±8.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.s.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: MS, multiple sclerosis; BS, brainstem; HC, healthy controls; min, minutes; WASO, wakefulness after sleep onset; PLMSI, periodic limb movements during sleep index; AHI, apnea-hypopnea index; RDI, respiratory disturbance index; ODI, oxygen desaturation index; T90, percentage of sleep time with an SpO2 &lt;90%; n.s, not significant; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values &lt;0.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
        <p>Forty-seven percent of patients reported an ESS score higher than 10, of whom 16.7% and 40% had a pathological MWT, when considering the threshold of 20 and 30 minutes, respectively. The level of drowsiness was significantly lower in the control group: 25.8% had an ESS score &gt;10 (p = 0.019, Phi = 0.23), for which MWT was not available (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Clinical Parameters and MWT</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MS + BS Lesions<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> (n = 31)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MS – BS Lesions<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> (n = 36)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MS (n = 67)<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HC (n = 67)<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> Values</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ESS</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3±5.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5±4.6*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4±4.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0±3.7*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p = 0.011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,3 vs 4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MWT, sleep latency</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.9±9.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.5±8.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.7±9.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.a.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.s.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>FSS</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.2±19.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.7±13.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.7±16.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.a.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.s.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MSQoL54 Ph</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.5±23.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.9±18.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.6±21.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.a.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.s.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSQI</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8±8.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.0±7.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.9±8.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7±2.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p &lt; 0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,2,3 vs 4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>BDI</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.9±11.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.7±12.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.3±11.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.a.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.s.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: MS, multiple sclerosis; BS, brainstem; HC, healthy controls; ESS, Epworth sleepiness scale; MWT, maintenance of wakefulness test; FSS, fatigue severity scale; MSQoL54 M/Ph, multiple sclerosis quality of life – mental/physical; PSQI, Pittsburgh sleep quality index; BDI, Beck depression inventory; n.a., not available; n.s, not significant.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Correlation of SRBD with Clinical/Instrumental Variables in MS Group</title>
        <p>In the MS group, RDI was positively correlated with age (r = 0.39, moderate-to-large size, p =&lt;0.001), BMI (r = 0.47, large size, p = &lt; 0.001), and negatively with sleep efficiency (r = −0.30, moderate size, p = 0.014) and MSQoL54 (r = −0.27, moderate size, p = 0.042). No correlation was found with the disability status (EDSS), fatigue (FSS and MFIS), depression (BDI), and sleep quality (PSQI). AHI<sub>REM</sub> was higher in patients with EDSS ≥4 (t = 2.30; p = 0.025). The oxygen desaturation index (ODI), but not the RDI, correlated with subjective sleepiness (r = 0.27, moderate size, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.034) (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). There was no correlation between mean sleep latency at MWT and respiratory parameters.<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Correlations between sleepiness and respiratory parameters in patients with multiple sclerosis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-741-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: ESS, Epworth sleepiness scale; RDI, respiratory disturbance index; ODI, oxygen desaturation index; T90, percentage of sleep time with an SpO2 &lt;90%; n.s., not significant.</attrib></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Influence of the Symptomatic Treatment</title>
        <p>Excessive daytime sleepiness (EDS) was associated with regular therapy with anti-depressants: 58.7% of patients with EDS received anti-depressants vs 27.3% of those without EDS (<italic toggle="yes">χ</italic><sup>2</sup> 6.2, p = 0.025). A similar association was found with benzodiazepines (t = 2.18, p = 0.03). There was no correlation between anti-depressant/benzodiazepine consumption and respiratory parameters.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>SRBD and MRI Findings in MS</title>
        <p>Fifteen (22.4%) MS patients had lesions in the medulla, 21 (31.3%) in the pons and 12 (17.8%) in the midbrain. Sleep efficiency was significantly lower in MS with brainstem lesions than in MS without (t = −2.196, p = 0.032), while the respiratory variables (RDI, AHI-<sub>REM</sub>, central apnea index, ODI, percentage of sleep time with an SpO2 &lt;90%) did not differ between MS patients with and without brainstem lesions, as well as between healthy controls and MS patients with brainstem plaques (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The number of lesions in the medulla, pons and midbrain (considered both together and individually) did not correlate with RDI.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>This is the largest PSG study focused on sleep-related breathing disorders in MS carried out so far. We did not find a higher RDI and OSAS frequency in MS patients compared to healthy controls and the percentages of subjects with RDI &gt;5/h or &gt;15/h were slightly, but not significantly, higher in the control group. No MS patient had a central apnea index ≥2/h, neither in the subgroup with brainstem lesions. As expected, sleep quality in MS was significantly lower than in healthy controls. However, in the MS group, RDI was not correlated with PSG markers of sleep quality, with the exception of sleep efficiency, neither with clinical parameters such as fatigue, depression, sleepiness, subjective sleep quality, and disability status. The presence of lesions in the brainstem was not correlated with any of the sleep-related parameters.</p>
      <p>According to ESS, patients with MS were drowsier than healthy subjects. Only ODI and pharmacotherapy (benzodiazepines and anti-depressants) were correlated with drowsiness.</p>
      <p>The current literature reports conflicting results concerning the prevalence and severity of SRBD in MS.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Studies based on self-reported questionnaires suggested an elevated risk of OSA in MS patients.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Nevertheless, the STOP-BANG test may not be an accurate tool to identify OSA patients in comorbidity with MS, where the high prevalence of fatigue might represent a confounding factor.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> According to a recent review (2020),<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> there are only five instrumental case-control studies taking into account RDI or AHI, of which only one involved more than 50 patients (sample size = 62). AHI values varied considerably between studies, ranging from normal to moderately increased. Among these five studies, only Braley et al<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> found that the AHI and central apnea index (but not obstructive apnea index) were higher in MS patients than in controls, while the others did not find any differences.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22–25</xref> However, compared to our sample, the patients studied by Braley et al<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> had a higher disease severity, with 30% of patients having progressive MS with an EDSS ≥6, and with brainstem lesions in more than half of the group. A further study considered only obstructive apnea index, finding no difference between MS patients and controls.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></p>
      <p>Another study<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> showed a higher AHI, AHI-<sub>REM</sub> and ODI in patients compared to controls. However, the sample differed from ours in terms of mean age (38.3 years) and sex (56% females). Moreover, the control group consisted of individuals (not affected by MS) who underwent PSG because of sleep complaints.</p>
      <p>Two non-controlled studies partially addressed the relationship between SRBD and fatigue in MS, suggesting a positive correlation that diverge from the findings of our study. Nevertheless, the study by Veauthier et al<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> lacks of statistics due to the small sample size. The second study by Côté et al<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> only focused on the effect of treatment for OSAS (CPAP, positioning devices, weight loss) on fatigue, finding an improvement of fatigue after a successful intervention.</p>
      <p>According to our findings, Veauthier et al<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> showed poor health-related QoL in MS patients with OSA, even if QoL was assessed with a different questionnaire (Nottingham Health Profile). Finally, no instrumental study provides information on the relationship between SRBD and depression in MS patients.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></p>
      <p>Our findings indicate that MS is not associated to an increased risk of SRBD, it seems therefore reasonable considering instrumental screening for SRBD only in MS patients with suspicious symptoms. Notably, RDI and AHI in this study do not account for drowsiness, fatigue and depression in MS patients. This suggests physicians should consider treating depression, MS-related fatigue and other sleep complaints, before assessing a possible underlying SRBD. Patients with an elevated ODI represent an exception, since this correlated to subjective sleepiness. However, it is known that in OSAS oxygen desaturations are more associated to drowsiness than AHI.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></p>
      <p>Patients with MS showed a worse sleep quality, in terms of duration, efficiency, and architecture compared to healthy subjects. As shown by Buratti et al,<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> the course of MS may be influenced by sleep quality, possibly because of the role of sleep in some oligodendrocyte functions, such as myelination. Of consequence, sleep quality assessment could be used to obtain prognostic information. In our study, sleep disruption was not imputable to the respiratory pattern during sleep but likely due to other factors, such as insomnia, RLS, periodic limb movements during sleep,<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> disease modifying treatments.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></p>
      <p>The presence of lesions within the brainstem, which harbors structures playing a critical role in breathing regulation, was not associated with a greater risk of SRBD or central apneas, but with a worse sleep quality. According to our results, the sole presence of either mesencephalic, pontine or medullary lesions in a patient with MS without SRBD-related symptoms should not per se justify the cost of an instrumental screening for SRBD, at least in the range of MS severity considered in our sample. Our results differ from those of another recent study, with a similar sample size (n = 65), which found an association between AHI and the number of lesions in the midbrain and pons, but not medulla.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></p>
      <p>Sleep latency at MWT did not correlate to any sleep respiratory parameter. The discrepancy between MWT and ESS is not surprising and has been described also in other disorders, such as OSAS and narcolepsy.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Limitations</title>
      <p>This study has limitations. The exclusion of subjects with an EDSS ≥7 and the relatively low median EDSS (2.7) in this MS population limits the generalizability of our results to highly disabled MS. Spinal and cerebral magnetic resonance images were not fully evaluated and were used only for the assessment of the presence of brainstem lesions. Additionally, precise brainstem lesion extension and location were not considered. Cervico-thoracic spine dysfunction due to MS might also contribute to both obstructive and central sleep apnea severity.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Finally, the lack of data on oropharyngeal anatomy prevented us from assessing other causes of OSAS not linked to neuroinflammation and obesity.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>Our study did not find evidence of an association between MS and central or obstructive apneas, even in the presence of brainstem lesions. In light of the so far small number of studies on this topic and their limitations, it seems currently reasonable not to screen the MS as well as the general population with PSG for central/obstructive apneas, and limit its use to suspicious cases.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>Grant ABREOC from Ente Ospedaliero Cantonale (EOC); Grant Swiss MS Society (SMSS); Swiss National Science Foundation, grant number: 320030_160250. The authors want to thank all the patients and participants involved in the study. Special thanks are due to Ente Ospedaliero Cantonale (EOC), Swiss MS Society and Swiss National Science Foundation, for the financial support.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <p>AHI, apnea/hypopnea index; BDI, Beck Depression Inventory; BMI, body mass index; CIS, clinically isolated syndrome; CPAP, continuous positive airways pressure; EDS, excessive daytime sleepiness; EDSS, Expanded Disability Status Scale; EMG, electromyogram; ESS, Epworth Sleepiness Scale; FSS, Fatigue Severity Scale; HC, healthy controls; MFIS, Modified Fatigue Impact Scale; MMSE, Mini Mental Status Examination; MRI, magnetic resonance imaging; MS, multiple sclerosis; MSQoL, Multiple Sclerosis Quality of Life; MWT, maintenance of wakefulness test; NS, not significant; ODI, oxygen desaturation index; OSAS, obstructive sleep apnea syndrome; PLMS, periodic limb movements during sleep; PLMSI, periodic limb movements during sleep index; PPMS, primary progressive multiple sclerosis; PSG, polysomnography; PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index; RDI, respiratory disturbance index; RIS, radiologically isolated syndrome; RLS, restless legs syndrome; RR-MS, relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis; SD, standard deviation; SP-MS, secondary progressive multiple sclerosis; SRBD, sleep-related breathing disorders; T90, percentage of sleep time with an SpO2 &lt;90%; WASO, wake after sleep onset.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0008">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p>The data that support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author, upon reasonable request.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0009">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>R.F. was partially supported by a fund of the Italian Ministry of Health (RC2764026). CZ reports grants from Swiss MS Society, during the conduct of the study; grants from Abbvie, Almirall, Biogen Idec, Bristol Meyer Squibb, Genzyme, Lundbeck, Merck, Novartis, Teva Pharma, and Roche, outside the submitted work. The authors report no other conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Barun</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pathophysiological background and clinical characteristics of sleep disorders in multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Neurol Neurosurg</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>115</volume>:<fpage>S82</fpage>–<lpage>S85</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clineuro.2013.09.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24321163</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Melamud</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Golan</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luboshitzky</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lavi</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Melatonin dysregulation, sleep disturbances and fatigue in multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>314</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jns.2011.11.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22137446</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Caminero</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bartolomé</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disturbances in multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>309</volume>:<fpage>86</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jns.2011.07.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21813138</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aldughmi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huisinga</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lynch</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Siengsukon</surname>
<given-names>CF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The relationship between fatigability and sleep quality in people with multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mult Scler J</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2055217316682774</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tanioka</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Castelnovo</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tachibana</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Framing multiple sclerosis under a polysomnographic perspective</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>43</volume>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsz232</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hensen</surname>
<given-names>HA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krishnan</surname>
<given-names>AV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eckert</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep-disordered breathing in people with multiple sclerosis: prevalence, pathophysiological mechanisms, and disease consequences</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>8</volume>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fneur.2017.00740</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Braley</surname>
<given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Segal</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chervin</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep-disordered breathing in multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>929</fpage>–<lpage>936</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0b013e318266fa9d</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22895593</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Polman</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reingold</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Banwell</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Diagnostic criteria for multiple sclerosis: 2010 revisions to the McDonald criteria</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>292</fpage>–<lpage>302</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ana.22366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21387374</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chard</surname>
<given-names>DT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ciccarelli</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Clinically isolated syndromes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>169</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(11)70274-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22265211</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kurtzke</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Rating neurologic impairment in multiple sclerosis: an expanded disability status scale (EDSS)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>1983</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>1444</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/wnl.33.11.1444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6685237</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Haba-Rubio</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marti-Soler</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marques-Vidal</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence and determinants of periodic limb movements in the general population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>464</fpage>–<lpage>474</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ana.24593</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26703954</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Heinzer</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vat</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marques-Vidal</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence of sleep-disordered breathing in the general population: the HypnoLaus study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Respir Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>310</fpage>–<lpage>318</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(15)00043-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25682233</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Berry</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Budhiraja</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gottlieb</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>AA of SM. Rules for scoring respiratory events in sleep: update of the 2007 AASM manual for the scoring of sleep and associated events. deliberations of the sleep apnea definitions task force of the American Academy of Sleep Medicine</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>597</fpage>–<lpage>619</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.2172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23066376</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sateia</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>International classification of sleep disorders-Third Edition</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>146</volume>:<fpage>1387</fpage>–<lpage>1394</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.14-0970</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25367475</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Doghramji</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mitler</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sangal</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A normative study of the maintenance of wakefulness test (MWT)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Electroencephalogr Clin Neurophysiol</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>103</volume>:<fpage>554</fpage>–<lpage>562</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0013-4694(97)00010-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9402886</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Littner</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kushida</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wise</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Practice parameters for clinical use of the multiple sleep latency test and the maintenance of wakefulness test</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>121</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/28.1.113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15700727</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Statistical Power Analysis for the Behavioural Science</italic></source>. <edition>2nd</edition> ed. <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>; <year>1988</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Foschi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rizzo</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liguori</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep-related disorders and their relationship with MRI findings in multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2019.01.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30803830</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Brass</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Auerbach</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The underdiagnosis of sleep disorders in patients with multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1025</fpage>–<lpage>1031</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.4044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25142763</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Braley</surname>
<given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Segal</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chervin</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea and fatigue in patients with multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>162</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.3442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24532998</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sunter</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Omercikoglu Ozden</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vural</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ince Gunal</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Agan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Risk assessment of obstructive sleep apnea syndrome and other sleep disorders in multiple sclerosis patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Neurol Neurosurg</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>207</volume>:<fpage>106749</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clineuro.2021.106749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34126453</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Braley</surname>
<given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chervin</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Segal</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Fatigue, tiredness, lack of energy, and sleepiness in multiple sclerosis patients referred for clinical polysomnography</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mult Scler Int</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>2012</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2012/673936</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kaminska</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kimoff</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benedetti</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea is associated with fatigue in multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mult Scler J</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1159</fpage>–<lpage>1169</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1352458511432328</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kaynak</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Altintaş</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaynak</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Fatigue and sleep disturbance in multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1333</fpage>–<lpage>1339</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1468-1331.2006.01499.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17116216</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>XQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>HY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disorders in multiple sclerosis in China: clinical, polysomnography study, and review of the literature</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Neurophysiol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>375</fpage>–<lpage>381</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/WNP.0000000000000067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25083851</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Saçmacı</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tanık</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Özcan</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Evaluation of sleep-related respiratory disorders in patients with multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Neurol Belg</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>120</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1165</fpage>–<lpage>1171</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13760-020-01358-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32356242</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Veauthier</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Radbru</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gaede</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Fatigue in multiple sclerosis is closely related to sleep disorders: a polysomnographic cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mult Scler J</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>613</fpage>–<lpage>622</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1352458510393772</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Côté</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trojan</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaminska</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impact of sleep disorder treatment on fatigue in multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mult Scler J</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>480</fpage>–<lpage>489</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1352458512455958</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Veauthier</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gaede</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Radbruch</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wernecke</surname>
<given-names>KD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paul</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disorders reduce health-related quality of life in multiple sclerosis (Nottingham health profile data in patients with multiple sclerosis)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Mol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>16514</fpage>–<lpage>16528</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms160716514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26197315</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rashid</surname>
<given-names>NHA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zaghi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scapuccin</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Camacho</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Certal</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Capasso</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The value of oxygen desaturation index for diagnosing obstructive sleep apnea: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Laryngoscope</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>131</volume>:<fpage>440</fpage>–<lpage>447</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lary.28663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32333683</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buratti</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Iacobucci</surname>
<given-names>DE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Viticchi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep quality can influence the outcome of patients with multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>56</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2019.02.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31129524</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sparasci</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferri</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Castelnovo</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Restless legs syndrome and periodic limb movements in 86 patients with multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>44</volume>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsab066</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rocchi</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pulcini</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vesprini</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep in multiple sclerosis patients treated with interferon beta: an actigraphic study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurol Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>744</fpage>–<lpage>748</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01616412.2020.1773629</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32520662</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Levit</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bouley</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baber</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Djonlagic</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sloane</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Brainstem lesions are associated with sleep apnea in multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mult Scler J</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>205521732096795</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2055217320967955</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Erman</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Emsellem</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Black</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mori</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mayer</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Correlation between the Epworth Sleepiness Scale and the Maintenance of Wakefulness Test in patients with narcolepsy participating in two clinical trials of sodium oxybate</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>92</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2017.07.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29031763</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
