<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35698588</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">9188392</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">361925</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S361925</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Both Short and Long Sleep Durations are Risk Factors for Sarcopenia in Suburban-Dwelling Older Chinese Individuals: A 3-Year Longitudinal Study</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Han et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Han et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Han</surname>
            <given-names>Peipei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Hou</surname>
            <given-names>Lin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liang</surname>
            <given-names>Zhenwen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Wuxiong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Junxue</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cheng</surname>
            <given-names>Yazhou</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhou</surname>
            <given-names>Wenjing</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zeng</surname>
            <given-names>Siya</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pan</surname>
            <given-names>Jiangtao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>Lanshan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Yi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Yangyi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0439-8274</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Guo</surname>
            <given-names>Qi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Rehabilitation Medicine, Shanghai University of Medicine and Health Sciences Affiliated Zhoupu Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>College of Rehabilitation Sciences, Shanghai University of Medicine and Health Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Rehabilitation Medicine, TEDA International Cardiovascular Hospital, Cardiovascular Clinical College of Tianjin Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Tianjin</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Child Mental Health and Rehabilitation Center, Shenzhen Maternity &amp; Child Health Care Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Shenzhen</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label><institution>Department of Rehabilitation Medicine, Shanghai Health Rehabilitation Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Qi Guo, <institution>College of Rehabilitation Sciences, Shanghai University of Medicine and Health Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>279 Zhouzhu Highway, Pudong New Area</addr-line>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <addr-line>201318</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, <phone>Tel/Fax +86-22-8333-6977</phone>, Email guoqijp@gmail.com</corresp>
        <fn id="ft0001">
          <label>*</label>
          <p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>07</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <fpage>1089</fpage>
      <lpage>1096</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2022 Han et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Han et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Few longitudinal studies have explored exploring the relationship between sleep duration and sarcopenia. Evidence concerning the relationship between sleep duration and sarcopenia is limited and inconsistent. The purpose of this 3-year prospective study was to explore whether sleep duration was associated with sarcopenia onset in suburb-dwelling older Chinese individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>This was a prospective study that included 754 Chinese suburb-dwelling men and women aged ≥60 years (men n=327, mean age 65.24± 4.87 years) who were not initially diagnosed with sarcopenia. We defined sarcopenia using the diagnostic algorithm recommended by the Asian Working Group for Sarcopenia. Self-reported sleep duration was a component of the interview measured by trained interviewers. Subjects were categorized into 3 groups at baseline [short: &lt;6 h, medium: 6–8 h, and long: &gt;8 h].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>The incidence of sarcopenia during the 3-year follow-up was 12.2%. Multivariate logistic regression analyses showed that after adjustments for potential confounders long sleep duration was independently associated with sarcopenia incidence from baseline through the 3-year follow-up: when using the 6–8 h sleep duration group as a reference, the adjusted ORs for sarcopenia of the groups who slept &lt;6 and &gt;8 hours were 2.74 (95% CI 1.05–7.13) and 1.84 (95% CI 1.07–3.14).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>Both short and long sleep durations were associated with a greater incidence of sarcopenia. Thus, sleep duration should be considered when developing prevention and management strategies for sarcopenia.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>longitudinal study</kwd>
        <kwd>older</kwd>
        <kwd>sarcopenia</kwd>
        <kwd>sleep duration</kwd>
        <kwd>suburb-dwelling</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="1"/>
        <table-count count="5"/>
        <ref-count count="33"/>
        <page-count count="8"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Sarcopenia is a disease that is characterized by a decline in skeletal muscle mass, muscle strength, and physical performance.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> It is associated with the ageing process and is known to be associated with adverse health outcomes, such as physical inactivity, disability, diabetes, metabolic syndrome, poor quality of life, and mortality.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Sarcopenia contributes to current increased health care costs and is becoming a major public health problem.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Because of the debilitating symptoms and increased health care cost burden, it is of great importance to determine the factors related to sarcopenia and to prevent it at an early stage.</p>
      <p>Furthermore, because sarcopenia is difficult to notice in daily life, few people pay attention to it. It is important to observe its risk factors that can be easily avoided, and sleep duration may be a good factor. Sarcopenia is closely related to increased insulin resistance and proinflammatory markers, such as C-reactive protein and interleukin-6.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> It has been reported that long duration sleepers have significantly higher levels of C-reactive protein and interleukin-6, and long sleep duration is closely related to increased insulin resistance.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Therefore, we have reasons to believe that there might be a certain relationship between sleep disorders and sarcopenia. A previous study demonstrated that long sleep duration is related to skeletal muscle loss in postmenopausal women.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Previous studies<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> also found that longer sleep duration is associated with a significantly higher prevalence of sarcopenia. A systematic review<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> showed a U-shaped relationship between sleep duration and sarcopenia. However, the studies used in this meta-analysis were cross-sectional in nature, not longitudinal. The first longitudinal cohort study of sleep duration and sarcopenia revealed that only long sleep duration was associated with sarcopenia.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Hence, the relationship between sleep duration and sarcopenia remains uncertain. Furthermore, most previous studies are cross-sectional studies; there are few longitudinal studies exploring the causal relationship between them. Therefore, it is necessary to conduct longitudinal studies to determine the effect of sleep duration on sarcopenia.</p>
      <p>The aim of this study was to explore whether sleep duration influences sarcopenia in suburb-dwelling older adults. This is a particularly significant study population since in China, more than 70% of elderly individuals live in suburban areas.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Those living in suburban areas often have a relatively low level of medical treatment and poor health. Offering them health guidance is particularly meaningful to them. Furthermore, if sleep duration has an effect on sarcopenia, it can be used as a risk factor allowing for early diagnosis of sarcopenia and consequent prompt interventions.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Study Participants</title>
        <p>All participants were 60 years of age or older and had enrolled in the National Free Physical Examination Program in the Chadian of Hangu area, Tianjin, China, which is a relatively large sample of suburb-dwelling older people living in a rural area. We enrolled 1166 participants from March 2013 to August 2015 at baseline who were invited to participate in a comprehensive geriatric assessment. Participants with the following conditions were excluded from the study: (1) unable to grant informed consent (n=2); (2) unable to perform anthropometric measurements (n=52); and (3) diagnosed with sarcopenia using the AWGS criteria (n=123). The final study population was comprised of 989 subjects without sarcopenia. The cohort was invited to attend repeat questionnaire interviews and physical measurements after 3 years. During the follow-up years, 59 participants died. A total of 176 participants were excluded because they were lost to follow-up. The incidence and risk factors for sarcopenia were therefore assessed in 754 persons (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). This study was carried out according to the Declaration of Helsinki. All participants provided informed consent prior to participation. This study is part of the Adult Physical Fitness and Health Cohort Study, which is a prospective dynamic cohort focusing on the relationship between physical fitness and the health status of a population living in Tianjin, China.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14–16</xref> This study was approved by the Ethics Committee of Tianjin Medical University.<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Participant flow in this study.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-1089-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Covariates</title>
        <p>Data regarding sociodemographic, and behaviour characteristics, and medical conditions were obtained as previously described (via face-to-face questions).<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Sociodemographic variables, including age, gender, marital status, educational level, and occupation, were assessed. Behaviour characteristics included smoking and drinking habits. The daily physical activity and sitting time were evaluated using the short form of the International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ).<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> Depressive symptoms were assessed using the Geriatric Depression Scale. Participants with a score of ≥11 were considered to have depressive symptoms.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> The prevalence of specific medical conditions was established using standardized criteria that combined information from history of physical illness evaluated on the basis of participants’ response (yes or no) to questions, physician diagnosis, and taking corresponding medication or undergoing other treatment now or in the past.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Assessment of Sarcopenia</title>
        <p>Sarcopenia was defined according to the Asian Working Group for Sarcopenia (AWGS) criteria,<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> in which a person who has low muscle mass, low muscle strength and/or low physical performance was identified as having sarcopenia. Low muscle mass was classified as relative skeletal muscle mass index (ASM/ht<sup>2</sup>) less than 7.0 kg/m<sup>2</sup> and 5.7 kg/m<sup>2</sup> in men and women, respectively; low muscle strength was defined as grip strength &lt;28 kg or &lt;18 kg for males and females, respectively; and low physical performance was defined as walking speed &lt;1.0 m/s for both males and females. Details of the measurement methods have been described in our previous study.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Assessment of Sleep Behaviour</title>
        <p>Self-reported sleep duration was measured by trained interviewers as a component of the interview. Participants were asked the time they usually went to bed and got up during the past month, which is the same measure as in some previous studies<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> and our previous study.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> We calculated the time they slept per night. Subjects were categorized into 3 groups: short: &lt; 6 h, medium:6–8 h, and long: &gt; 8 h.</p>
        <p>Sleep quality was assessed by asking the subjects “Do you think you slept enough during the past month?” (The subjects had have 4 choices: 1=very well, 2=good, 3=not enough, 4=very poor). We also asked the subjects whether they took sleep drugs<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>(including Eszopiclone, Zaleplon, Zolpidem, Melatonin, Ramelteon, Benzodiazepine Hypnotics, Antidepressants, Suvorexant et al) before they went to bed.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>Continuous variables (age, ASM/Height2, grip strength, 4-meter walking test, and, BMI) that were normally distributed were expressed as means and standard deviation. Nonnormal distribution parameters (IPAQ, sitting time) are given as medians ± 25–75th percentiles. Additionally, classification variables were reported as percentages. Differences in the characteristics according to sarcopenia status were analysed using <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>–tests, Chi-square tests, and Kruskal–Wallis rank tests. Risk factors for sarcopenia incidence at the follow-up years were analysed individually using logistic regressions. The models considered were Model 1, crude model with adjusted for no variables; Model 2, including age, sex, BMI, sitting time, and depression; and Model 3, including the use of sleep drugs, sleep quality and medical history (diabetes, hypertension, hyperlipidaemia, heart disease, and stroke) along with the covariates of Model 2. All statistical analyses were performed using SPSS version 19.0, and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values less than 0.05 were considered statistically significant.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> presents the characteristics of these participants by sarcopenia status. Of the 754 participants included in this study, there were 327 men (43.3%) and 427 women (56.7%). Between baseline and 3-year follow-up, 92 of the participants without sarcopenia at baseline had developed sarcopenia. The incidence of sarcopenia was 12.2% at the 3-year follow up, representing an incidence of 15.9% men and 9.4% women. The mean ages of the participants without sarcopenia and with sarcopenia were 65.75±5.41 and 69.16±6.18 years, respectively. The incidence of sarcopenia in the &lt; 6-, 6-8-, and &gt; 8- hour groups was 19.5%, 7.1%, and 15.7%, respectively. In the group with no sarcopenia at baseline, subjects with new-onset sarcopenia had a significantly lower BMI than subjects without sarcopenia (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.05). Compared to subjects without sarcopenia, those with new-onset sarcopenia were more likely to be older, and have short or longer sleep durations.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Baseline Characteristics of Study Participants According to the Presence of Sarcopenia</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non Sarcopenia (n=662)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sarcopenia (n=92)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">t, Z or <italic toggle="yes">χ</italic><sup>2</sup> value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (y)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.75±5.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.16±6.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">275(41.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52(56.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">387(58.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40(43.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASM/Height<sup>2</sup> (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.32±2.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.21±0.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.729</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grip strength (kg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.62±9.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.90±8.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.474</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-meter walking test (m/s)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02±0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97±0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.04±3.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.0±3.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IPAQ (Met/wk)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2099.5(939.8,4991.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2079.0(1386.0,4452.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.261</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sitting time (h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0(2.0–6.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0(2.0–5.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.119</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depression, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.139</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">597(90.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79(85.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65(9.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13(14.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration (h/d), n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.5<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≤6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33(5.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8(8.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6–8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">302(45.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23(25.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">327(49.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61(66.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Use of sleep drug, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.380</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">600(90.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82(89.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62(9.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10(10.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep quality, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.349</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Very well</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">304(45.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35(38.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Good</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">205(31.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29(31.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Not enough</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68(10.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14(15.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Very poor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85(12.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14(15.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living alone, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.230</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">586(88.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78(84.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76(11.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14(15.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Illiteracy, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.378</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">421(63.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60(65.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">241(36.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32(34.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Farming, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.369</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109(16.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13(14.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">553(83.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79(85.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drinking, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.226</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">482(72.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63(68.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">180(27.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29(31.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.083</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">459(69.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57(62.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">203(30.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35(38.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diseases</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Diabetes, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.1<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.450</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">582(87.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80(87.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80(12.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12(13.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hypertension, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.366</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">343(51.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50(54.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">319(48.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42(45.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hyperlipidemia, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.097</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">486(73.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61(66.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">176(26.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31(33.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Heart disease, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.401</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">515(77.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70(76.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">147(22.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22(23.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Stroke, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.1<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.545</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">620(93.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86(93.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42(6.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6(6.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Note</bold>: <sup>a</sup>t value, <sup>b</sup><italic toggle="yes">χ</italic><sup>2</sup> value, <sup>c</sup>Z value.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: ASM, appendicular skeletal muscle mass; BMI, body mass index; IPAQ, international physical activity questionnaire; Met/wk, metabolic equivalent task minutes per week.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      <p>The outcomes of the applications of the models that tested the effects of sleep duration on sarcopenia incidence are illustrated in <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Compared to the reference group (6–8 h sleep duration), the ORs of the slept &lt; 6 h and &gt; 8 h groups for Model 1 were 3.18 (95% CI 1.32–7.69) and 2.45 (95% CI 1.48–4.06), respectively, with statistical significance; the results were also statistically significant for Model 2 and Model 3 with added control variables. After adjustments for potential confounders, shorter and longer sleep durations were independently associated with sarcopenia incidence from baseline to the 3-year follow-up in Model 3: the adjusted ORs of the groups who slept &lt; 6 h and &gt; 8 h for sarcopenia were 2.74 (95% CI 1.05–7.13) and 1.84 (95% CI 1.07–3.14), respectively.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Multiple Logistics Regression on Incidence of Sarcopenia During Baseline to 3-Years</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sleep Duration</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 3</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;6 h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.18(1.32–7.69)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.98(1.17–7.55)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.74(1.05–7.13)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6–8 h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">325</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;8 h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">388</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.45(1.48–4.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.89(1.12–3.20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.84(1.07–3.14)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Model 1: unadjusted; Model 2: adjustment for age, gender, BMI, sitting time, and depression; Model 3: Model 2+ adjustment for use of sleep drugs and sleep quality, and medical history of diabetes, hypertension, hyperlipidemia, heart disease, and stroke.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In this study, our results showed that both short and long sleep durations were associated with a greater incidence of sarcopenia during the 3-year study period in older adults. To the best of our knowledge, this study is the first longitudinal study to examine the relationship between sleep duration and sarcopenia.</p>
      <sec id="s0004-s2001">
        <title>Incidence of Sarcopenia</title>
        <p>The incidence of sarcopenia during the period from baseline to the 3-year follow-up was 12.2% (15.9% in men and 9.4% in women). This is consistent with earlier findings,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> which showed that the annual and 4-year incidences of sarcopenia were 4.0%<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> and 11.2%,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> respectively. In our study, the incidence of sarcopenia in men was higher than that in women, which is in line with one earlier study that showed that males were more commonly affected by sarcopenia than females,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> while another study showed a higher prevalence of sarcopenia and severe sarcopenia in women than in men.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> However, most studies to date have reported that there are no significant differences in sarcopenia prevalence between men and women.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2002">
        <title>The Relationship Between Sleep Duration and Sarcopenia</title>
        <p>Our results showed that the risk of developing sarcopenia in older adults who sleep less than 6 hours per night and more than 8 hours was 2.74 times and 1.84 times the risk in older adults who sleep between 6 and 8 hours per night, respectively. The results showed that both short and long sleep durations were associated with sarcopenia onset. Our results were in line with those of a cross-sectional previous study.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> The impact of short sleep duration on sarcopenia may be attributed to the following mechanisms. Regarding sleep-related hormonal pathways, many hormones for growth are released during sleep, such as protein synthesis, tissue growth, and muscle repair.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Thus, reduced duration of sleep potentially interferes by inhibiting protein synthesis pathways and inducing degradation in skeletal muscle pathways. In addition, short sleep duration caused by chronic insomnia might dysregulate the hypothalamopituitary adrenal axis resulting in endocrine changes, which also induce proteolysis, change body composition and lead to sarcopenia.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> The biological mechanisms underlying the relationship between sleep and sarcopenia remain unclear. Further research with larger sample sizes and longer follow-up durations is needed to better understand the relationship between sleep deprivation and sarcopenia.</p>
        <p>Several mechanisms may contribute to the understanding of this longitudinal association between long sleep duration and sarcopenia. First, sleep duration is closely linked to physical inactivity and sedentary lifestyle.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> Our results also showed that participants with longer sleep durations (&gt;8 h) had significantly longer sitting times (obtained from the IPAQ) than those who sleep between 6 and 8 hours (3.92±2.34 vs 4.57±2.56, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=0.038). Lifestyle factors including low physical activity, sedentary behaviour, and smoking have been reported to accelerate the progression of sarcopenia.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> Second, insulin resistance could be one possible link between sleep duration and sarcopenia. Long sleep duration is closely related to increased insulin resistance.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Resistance to insulin has been reported to contribute a decline in the synthesis of skeletal mass protein and finally ultimately result sarcopenia in older people.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Our cross-sectional study<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> and a previous study<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> also found that long duration sleepers had the lowest muscle strength and walking speed of all the groups and experienced the greatest decline in physical performance. Another link between sleep duration and sarcopenia could be chronic inflammation. It was reported that long- duration sleepers have significantly higher levels of proinflammatory markers, such as C-reactive protein and interleukin-6.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> These inflammatory mediators play an important role in sarcopenia by promoting muscle proteolysis.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Our cohort study also showed that participants with longer sleep durations had significantly more muscle loss, based on the percentage change in muscle at the three-year follow-up appointment relative to the baseline, than those with normal sleep durations (−6.34±1.94% vs −4.15±1.76%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.05).<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> In addition, circadian rhythm disruptions and hormonal changes associated with long sleep durations might also be a possible underlying mechanism explaining the relationship between sleep duration and sarcopenia.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2003">
        <title>Strengths and Limitations of the Study</title>
        <p>This study has a few strengths. First, this study was the first longitudinal study using AWGS criteria to examine the relationship between sleep duration and sarcopenia in Asia. Second, this study was also the first to examine a uniquely defined group of suburban older people living in a discrete geographical area. Our participants were recruited from a suburban area, and leading a more physically active lifestyle, which might be different from subjects in other geographical areas. Another strength of this study was its 3-year longitudinal cohort study design.</p>
        <p>Our study has several limitations. First, participants in this study were independent in their activities of daily living and relatively healthy, as we did not include participants who were unable to participate in the free annual national physical examination (eg, those who were bedridden or those with serious diseases). This may lead to an underestimation of the prevalence of sarcopenia and its associated health impact. Second, our study’s follow-up was short; as a result, the change in elderly health status over the short observation time was small. In future research we will increase the sample size and extend follow-up to increase power. In addition, we relied on self-reported estimates of sleep duration. This is a convenient way to estimate sleep duration, and was therefore appropriate for the large sample in our study. Self-reporting is not as accurate as actigraph-measured sleep duration. Previous studies have shown that self-reported sleep durations are moderately correlated with actigraph-measured sleep duration.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> In addition, we have published two articles<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> using the same method to assess sleep duration before. Therefore, self-reporting could be an effective way to assess sleep behaviour.</p>
        <p>In conclusion, we have shown that both short and long sleep durations were associated with a greater incidence of sarcopenia. Although further research is needed to confirm these findings, sleep duration should be considered in developing prevention and management strategies for sarcopenia.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (grant numbers 82172552), Shanghai Sailing Program (20YF1418200), Shanghai Municipal Health Commission (20214Y0329) and Scientific Research Foundation of SUMHS (SSF-21-03-007). The funders had an important role in study design, data collection and analysis, and decision to publish. Peipei Han and Lin Hou are co-first authors for this study.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0005">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>Peipei Han, Lin Hou, Zhenwen Liang, Wuxiong Chen, Junxue Li, Yazhou Cheng, Wenjing Zhou, Siya Zeng, Jiangtao Pan, Lanshan Xu, Yi Wang, Yangyi Chen, and Qi Guo declare that they have no conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Delmonico</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harris</surname>
<given-names>TB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Visser</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Longitudinal study of muscle strength, quality, and adipose tissue infiltration</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Clin Nutr</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>90</volume>:<fpage>1579</fpage>–<lpage>1585</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3945/ajcn.2009.28047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19864405</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fielding</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vellas</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Evans</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sarcopenia: an undiagnosed condition in older adults. Current consensus definition: prevalence, etiology, and consequences. International working group on sarcopenia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Med Dir Assoc</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>256</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jamda.2011.01.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21527165</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Curcio</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferro</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Basile</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Biomarkers in sarcopenia: a multifactorial approach</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Exp Gerontol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>85</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exger.2016.09.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27633530</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rasmussen</surname>
<given-names>BB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fujita</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wolfe</surname>
<given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insulin resistance of muscle protein metabolism in aging</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">FASEB J</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>768</fpage>–<lpage>769</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.05-4607fje</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16464955</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cesari</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kritchevsky</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nicklas</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Oxidative damage, platelet activation, and inflammation to predict mobility disability and mortality in older persons: results from the health aging and body composition study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Gerontol a Biol Sci Med Sci</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>671</fpage>–<lpage>676</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gerona/glr246</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22389462</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dowd</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goldman</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weinstein</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep duration, sleep quality, and biomarkers of inflammation in a Taiwanese population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>799</fpage>–<lpage>806</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.annepidem.2011.07.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21889359</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pyykkonen</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Isomaa</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pesonen</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration and insulin resistance in individuals without type 2 diabetes: the PPP-Botnia study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>324</fpage>–<lpage>329</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/07853890.2014.902226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24813456</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fex</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barbat-Artigas</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dupontgand</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Filion</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Karelis</surname>
<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aubertin-Leheudre</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Relationship between long sleep duration and functional capacities in postmenopausal women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>313</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.1922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22701389</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>RH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>KI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>YS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between sleep duration and body composition measures in Korean adults: the Korea National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey 2010</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Korean J Fam Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4082/kjfm.17.0030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29972900</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kwon</surname>
<given-names>YJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jang</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cho</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shim</surname>
<given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Linton</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Long sleep duration is associated with sarcopenia in Korean adults based on data from the 2008-2011 KNHANES</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1097</fpage>–<lpage>1104</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.6732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28760192</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pourmotabbed</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghaedi</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Babaei</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration and sarcopenia risk: a systematic review and dose-response meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>1267</fpage>–<lpage>1278</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-019-01965-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31832982</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nakakubo</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Doi</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsutsumimoto</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kurita</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ishii</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shimada</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep duration and progression to sarcopenia in Japanese community-dwelling older adults: a 4 year longitudinal study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cachexia Sarcopeni</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1034</fpage>–<lpage>1041</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcsm.12735</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>NBoSo</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Statistical Communiqué on the 2012 National Economy and Social Development of People’s Republic of China</italic></source>. <publisher-name>China Stat Press</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shen</surname>
<given-names>SX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Poor lower extremity function was associated with pre-diabetes and diabetes in older Chinese people</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e115883</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0115883</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25531769</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>PP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence and factors associated with sarcopenia in suburb-dwelling older Chinese Using the Asian working group for sarcopenia definition</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Gerontol a-Biol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>529</fpage>–<lpage>535</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gerona/glv108</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fu</surname>
<given-names>LY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jia</surname>
<given-names>LY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The association between sleep duration and physical performance in Chinese community dwelling elderly</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e0174832</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28358845</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>CQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lam</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of physical activity strength on the diabetes mellitus prevalence in the elderly under the influence of international physical activity questionnaire</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Zhonghua Liu Xing Bing Xue Za Zhi</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>462</fpage>–<lpage>465</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19799141</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mui</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Geriatric depression scale as a community screening instrument for elderly Chinese immigrants</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int Psychogeriatr</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>445</fpage>–<lpage>458</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1041610296002803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9116180</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>LK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Woo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Assantachai</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Asian Working Group For Sarcopenia: 2019 consensus update on sarcopenia diagnosis and treatment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Med Dir Assoc</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>300–307</issue>):<fpage>e302</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jamda.2019.12.012</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stenholm</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kronholm</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bandinelli</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guralnik</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferrucci</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Self-reported sleep duration and time in bed as predictors of physical function decline: results from the InCHIANTI study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>1583</fpage>–<lpage>1593</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.1402</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22043129</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Brasure</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>MacDonald</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fuchs</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <source><italic toggle="yes">Management of Insomnia Disorder. AHRQ Comparative Effectiveness Reviews</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Rockville (MD)</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality</publisher-name>; <year>2015</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Incidence, risk factors, and the protective effect of high body mass index against sarcopenia in suburb-dwelling elderly Chinese Populations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Nutr Health Aging</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1056</fpage>–<lpage>1060</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12603-016-0704-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27925147</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suzuki</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Incidence and predictors of sarcopenia onset in community-dwelling elderly Japanese women: 4-year follow-up study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Med Dir Assoc</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>85</issue>):<fpage>e81</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jamda.2014.10.006</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Landi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liperoti</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fusco</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence and risk factors of sarcopenia among nursing home older residents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Gerontol a-Biol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>48</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gerona/glr035</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>HP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Syddall</surname>
<given-names>HE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jameson</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence of sarcopenia in community-dwelling older people in the UK using the European Working Group on Sarcopenia in Older People (EWGSOP) definition: findings from the Hertfordshire Cohort Study (HCS)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Age Ageing</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>378</fpage>–<lpage>384</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ageing/afs197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23384705</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gariballa</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alessa</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sarcopenia: prevalence and prognostic significance in hospitalized patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Nutr</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>772</fpage>–<lpage>776</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clnu.2013.01.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23395102</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>XY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>HZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dong</surname>
<given-names>BR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between sleep duration and sarcopenia among community-dwelling older adults A cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Medicine</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>e6268</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28272238</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Seelig</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Keller</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Klarhofer</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Neuroendocrine regulation and metabolism of glucose and lipids in primary chronic insomnia: a prospective case-control study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e61780</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061780</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23593497</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Al Lawati</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ayas</surname>
<given-names>NT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Epidemiology, risk factors, and consequences of obstructive sleep apnea and short sleep duration</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Prog Cardiovasc Dis</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>285</fpage>–<lpage>293</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pcad.2008.08.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19110130</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rom</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaisari</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aizenbud</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reznick</surname>
<given-names>AZ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Lifestyle and sarcopenia-etiology, prevention, and treatment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Rambam Maimonides Med J</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>e0024</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5041/RMMJ.10091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23908848</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fu</surname>
<given-names>LY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The relationship between sleep duration, falls, and muscle mass: a cohort study in an elderly Chinese population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Rejuv Res</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>390</fpage>–<lpage>398</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/rej.2018.2102</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Piovezan</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abucham</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dos Santos</surname>
<given-names>RV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mello</surname>
<given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tufik</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poyares</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The impact of sleep on age-related sarcopenia: possible connections and clinical implications</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ageing Res Rev</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>210</fpage>–<lpage>220</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arr.2015.07.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26216211</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lauderdale</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knutson</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yan</surname>
<given-names>LL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rathouz</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Self-reported and measured sleep duration: how similar are they?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Epidemiology</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>838</fpage>–<lpage>845</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/EDE.0b013e318187a7b0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18854708</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
