<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35707548</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">9189153</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">346941</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S346941</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>The Subjective and Objective Improvement of Non-Invasive Treatment of Schumann Resonance in Insomnia—A Randomized and Double-Blinded Study</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Huang et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Huang et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4015-5942</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <given-names>Yu-Shu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4259-5447</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Tang</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chin</surname>
            <given-names>Wei-Chih</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jang</surname>
            <given-names>Ling-Sheng</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Chin-Pang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>Chen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Chun-Pai</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0006" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cho</surname>
            <given-names>Shu-Ling</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0007" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Division of Pediatric Psychiatry and Sleep Center, Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Taoyuan</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>College of Medicine, Chang Gung University</institution>, <addr-line>Taoyuan</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Electrical Engineering, National Cheng Kung University</institution>, <addr-line>Tainan</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Biomedical Sciences and Engineering, National Central University</institution>, <addr-line>Taoyuan</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label><institution>Department of Neurology, Kuang Tien General Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Taichung</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0006"><label>6</label><institution>Department of Nutrition, Huang-Kuang University</institution>, <addr-line>Taichung</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0007"><label>7</label><institution>Department of Clinical Psychology, Fu Jen Catholic University</institution>, <addr-line>New Taipei City</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Shu-Ling Cho, <institution>Department of Clinical Psychology, Fu Jen Catholic University</institution>, <addr-line>New Taipei City</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan</country>, <phone>Tel +886-2-29053443</phone>, Email lincho056384@gmail.com</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>08</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <fpage>1113</fpage>
      <lpage>1124</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2022 Huang et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Huang et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p>Accumulated studies revealed that electromagnetic field can affect human brain and sleep, and the extremely low-frequency electromagnetic field, Schumann resonance, may have the potential to reduce insomnia symptoms. The purpose of this study was to investigate the responses of patients with insomnia to a non-invasive treatment, Schumann resonance (SR), and to evaluate its effectiveness by subjective and objective sleep assessments.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Patients and Methods</title>
          <p>We adopted a double-blinded and randomized design and 40 participants (70% female; 50.00 ± 13.38 year) with insomnia completed the entire study. These participants were divided into the SR-sleep-device group and the placebo-device group and were followed up for four weeks. The study used polysomnography (PSG) to measure objective sleep and used sleep diaries, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Inventory (PSQI), Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS), and visual analogy of sleep satisfaction to measure subjective sleep. The 36-Item Short-Form Health Survey (SF-36) was used to evaluate quality of life. Chi-square test, Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test, and Wilcoxon test were used to analyze the data.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>About 70% of the subjects were women, with an average age of 50±13.38 years and an average history of insomnia of 9.68±8.86 years. We found that in the SR-sleep-device group, objective sleep measurements (sleep-onset-latency, SOL, and total-sleep-time, TST) and subjective sleep questionnaires (SOL, TST, sleep-efficiency, sleep-quality, daytime-sleepiness, and sleep-satisfaction) were significantly improved after using the SR-sleep-device; in the placebo-device group, only such subjective sleep improvements as PSQI and sleep-satisfaction were observed.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>This study demonstrates that the SR-sleep-device can reduce the insomnia symptoms through both objective and subjective tests, with minimal adverse effects. Future studies can explore the possible mechanism of SR and health effects and, with a longer tracking time, verify the effectiveness and side effects.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>insomnia</kwd>
        <kwd>Schumann resonance</kwd>
        <kwd>effectiveness</kwd>
        <kwd>polysomnography</kwd>
        <kwd>questionnaire</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="1"/>
        <table-count count="10"/>
        <ref-count count="46"/>
        <page-count count="12"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Insomnia is the most common sleep disorder in the world and affects as much as 10% of the general population and approximately 15% of adults.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> According to the International Classification of Sleep Disorders, third edition (ICSD-3), insomnia is defined as (1) difficulty initiating sleep, maintaining sleep, or waking up earlier than desired; (2) sleep disturbance resulting in marked personal distress or interference with daily living; and (3) sleep disturbances and associated daytime symptoms occurring at least three times per week for at least three months.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Insomnia not only includes sleep disturbance at night but also a decline in daytime functions such as fatigue, impairment in attention and memory; impaired social, academic, or occupational performance; and mood disturbance.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> In addition, many studies have shown that people with insomnia have a higher risk of cardiovascular disease,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> chronic pain,<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> and type II diabetes.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Furthermore, the comorbidity rate of insomnia and other mental disorders is as high as 41–53%,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> After cognitive behavioral therapy for insomnia (CBTi), patients with comorbid mental illness not only have improved symptoms of insomnia but have improved symptoms of the comorbidities as well.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></p>
      <p>Although the pathophysiologic features of insomnia remain largely unknown, increasing evidence has shown that insomnia is a persistent condition and a complex disease. One cohort study of 3073 adults followed up annually for 5 years confirmed that 41.6% of the participants had persistent insomnia. This finding suggests that early intervention could prevent the development of insomnia chronicity and reduce its associated morbidity on sedatives and sleeping pills.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Previous studies have indicated that up to 13% of US adults have reported benzodiazepine use in the last year.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> The outpatient use of benzodiazepines has also increased significantly.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> The long-term use and overdoses of sleeping pills may cause side effects.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Although the insomnia treatment guidelines provide established clinical practice recommendations for CBTi as a first-line treatment, such treatment has not been popularized in many countries so far. Moreover, the inconvenience of and patient compliance with CBTi are still key issues in the implementation of this treatment. Therefore, exploring the effectiveness of other and more emerging non-pharmaceutical treatments of insomnia is important.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></p>
      <p>In recent years, research has been done on the developments of various noninvasive treatments for insomnia, including mindfulness therapy,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> acupressure,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> acupuncture therapies,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> cranial electrotherapy stimulation (CES)<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> or repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS),<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> etc. Another special discovery found in past 20 years is that ambient electromagnetic fluctuations, such as geomagnetic activity, may affect our physiology, psychology, and behavior.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Previous physics research showed “an electroencephalographic power revealed particular associations with the right parietal lobe for theta activity and the right frontal region for gamma activity,” and some studies have shown moderate strength correlations between increases in geomagnetic activity and various behavioral inferences of cerebral activity.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></p>
      <p>Wang et al (2019) used an electroencephalogram (EEG) study and reported a strong, specific human brain response to ecologically relevant rotations of Earth-strength magnetic fields. Following geomagnetic stimulation, a drop in amplitude of EEG alpha oscillations (8–13 Hz) occurred in a repeatable manner.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> In 1954, Winfried Otto Schumann reported on the existence of a natural extremely low-frequency field of about 7.83 Hz called the Schumann resonance (SR) frequency in earth’s atmosphere that globally propagates electromagnetic field (EMF) waves.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Its peak intensity can be detected at ~8 Hz, along with its harmonics with a lower intensity at 14, 20, 26, 33, 39, and 45 Hz due to frequency-related, ionospheric propagation loss.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> The Schumann resonances found within both global human quantitative electroencephalographic activity and earth-ionosphere activity may suggest a causal relationship.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> Moreover, Ghione et al found significant positive associations between geomagnetic activity and (daytime and 24-h) systolic and (daytime, nighttime, and 24-h) diastolic blood pressure.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> Burch et al also found that increasing geomagnetic activity combined with elevated 60 Hz MF is associated with reduced nocturnal excretion of a melatonin metabolite in humans, meaning that EMF will affect human brain and sleep.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></p>
      <p>With these accumulated evidence, extremely low-frequency EMF-Schumann resonance may improve human sleep. In this study, we use a sleep device with “Schumann resonance” function that outputs the low frequency of “Schumann resonance frequency (7.83 Hz) wave” in an attempt to resonate the user’s brain waves to make it easier to fall asleep, reach deep sleep, and maintain sleep. Since the effectiveness and side effects of the “Schumann waves” in treating insomnia are still unclear, this study was aimed to examine the effects of the Schumann resonance on insomnia symptoms through both subjective and objective sleep assessments.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p>In this study, patients with insomnia were recruited through hospital outpatient clinics, and 46 participants met the inclusion criteria and entered the study after providing their informed consent. Of those, four withdrew as they were unable to attend the follow-up visit time, and two participants experienced headache and dizziness after randomization and stopped from the follow-up visit. A total of 40 participants completed the study. The study was approved by Chang Gung Hospital IRB: No. 201701063A3 and No. 202101267B0 (clinical trial ID: NCT05053919, study period: 2021/7/27~2022/1/19) and complied with the Declaration of Helsinki.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Inclusion Criteria</title>
        <p>The inclusion criteria include (1) participants are between 20 and 70 years old; (2) participants must meet the DSM-5 diagnostic criteria for insomnia and have been diagnosed for more than three months; (3) participants must be willing to sign an informed consent form; and (4) participants who took sleep aiding pills must cooperate not to change any medication and dosage during the study.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Exclusion Criteria</title>
        <p>Exclusion criteria include (1) participants using pacemakers or cardiac monitors; (2) participants with severe physical illness or after surgery, such as heart disease, metabolic diseases, or cancer; (3) participants with severe mental disorders, such as schizophrenia, severe major depression, severe anxiety, bipolar disorder, dementia, substance use disorder; or severe neurological diseases such as a seizure, stroke or Parkinson’s disease; (4) participants with other serious sleep disorders, such as severe sleep obstructive apnea, severe periodic limb movement syndrome or narcolepsy; (5) participants who are unable to attend regular follow-up evaluations; and (6) participants who are unable to keep good sleep hygiene and cannot stop using electronic products before going to bed.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Experimental Design</title>
        <sec id="s0002-s2004-s3001">
          <title>Randomization</title>
          <p>This study is a randomized double-blinded and case–control study. All participants who met the inclusion criteria were randomly assigned to the “SR-sleep-device group” or “placebo-device group”. There were no significant differences between the two groups in terms of background variables such as gender ratio, age, and years of insomnia.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2004-s3002">
          <title>Procedure</title>
          <p>All participants were randomly assigned to two groups and used the “sleep device” for 4 weeks.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2004-s3003">
          <title>Outcome Measure</title>
          <p>The primary outcome measure is the changes in polysomnography, and the secondary outcome measures are changes in the subjective questionnaires including the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Inventory (PSQI) and the Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS), the sleep diaries, the visual analogy of sleep satisfaction scale and the 36-Item Short-Form Health Survey (SF-36).</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Schumann Resonance Sleep Device/Placebo Device</title>
        <p>The SR device is designed by Professor Ling-Sheng Zhang from National Cheng Kung University, Taiwan (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>: “Enerkey Kingdom SR Sleep device”). The sleep instrument was capable of generating the “low frequency of the Schumann resonance frequency (7.83 Hz) wave” and obtained the Taiwan Patent (No. TW M530656U) on May 4, 2016. After the sleep device is turned on, it stably outputs the composite frequency of “the Schumann resonance frequency (7.83 Hz) wave, theta wave, and delta wave”. A placebo-device is an instrument with the same appearance and operation as the SR-sleep-device but does not output any frequency wave. The subjects were asked to use the device (place it next to the bed facing the subject’s head, turn it on about one hour before going to bed every night, and turn it off after getting up the next day) every night for four weeks and keep recording sleep by sleep logs.<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>SR sleep device.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-1113-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2006">
        <title>Objective Sleep Measurements</title>
        <sec id="s0002-s2006-s3001">
          <title>Polysomnography (PSG)</title>
          <p>Standard overnight PSG was performed to document sleep in all participants before the SR-sleep-device/placebo-device was used and for four weeks after use. Participants were asked to attend at 9 pm, guided by a sleep technician to the examination room and wear a sensor device, and lie down on the bed at 10 pm. The examination finished around 6 am the next morning. Standard overnight polysomnographic evaluation involved systematic monitoring of the following variables: 4 EEG leads, 2 electro-oculogram (EOG) leads, chin and leg electromyogram (EMG) leads, and 1 electrocardiogram (ECG) lead; respiration was monitored with a nasal cannula pressure transducer, a mouth thermistor, thoracic and abdominal inductive plethysmography bands, a finger oxygen saturation (MasimoTM) oximeter with derivation of oximetry and finger plethysmography signals, a neck microphone, diaphragmatic-intercostal, abdominal muscle EMGs, and a transcutaneous CO2 electrode; leg EMGs were also monitored. Subjects were continuously video monitored during the recording. Recordings were performed following the recommendation of the American-Academy of Sleep-Medicine-AASM and PSG scoring was also done following AASM recommendations with hypopnea scored for either a 3% oxygen saturation drop or an arousal response.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2007">
        <title>Subjective Sleep Measurements</title>
        <sec id="s0002-s2007-s3001">
          <title>Sleep Diaries</title>
          <p>Participants completed the sleep diaries every day for two weeks before using the SR-sleep-device/placebo-device and for four weeks during use of the device to record their sleep. From the diaries, an estimate was computed for an average of SOL, TST, SE, and WASO.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2007-s3002">
          <title>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Inventory (PSQI)</title>
          <p>The PSQI is a self-rated questionnaire for assessing the subjective sleep quality, which consists of 19 items and can be calculated and combined into 7 clinically derived component score (0–3), with higher scores indicating worse sleep quality.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> Participants completed the PSQI before use, two weeks after use, and four weeks after use, of the SR-sleep-device/placebo-device.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2007-s3003">
          <title>Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS)</title>
          <p>The ESS consists of 8 items (each scored from 0 to 3) and was used to assess the individual’s daytime sleepiness.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> Participants completed the ESS before use, two weeks after use, and four weeks after use, of the SR-sleep-device/placebo-device.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2007-s3004">
          <title>Visual Analogy of Sleep Satisfaction Scale</title>
          <p>Subjects were also asked to use a seven-point scale before use and four weeks after use to evaluate their degree of satisfaction with their sleep in the past week (a higher score represents a higher degree of satisfaction with sleep).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2007-s3005">
          <title>Quality of Life: 36-Item Short-Form Health Survey (SF-36)</title>
          <p>SF-36 includes 11 major questions that evaluate eight components. These components include physical functioning, role limitations due to physical health, role limitations due to emotional problems, energy/fatigue, emotional wellbeing, social functioning, pain, and general health. The scale can be used to estimate a patient’s general quality of life status. Higher scores mean better physical or mental functions.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2008">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>We used SPSS 22.0 to analyze our data. Data were presented as number, mean, percentage, and standard deviation. We used chi-square test for group comparisons of percentage and Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test to analyze the differences in objective and subjective measurements between SR sleep device group and placebo group. We used Wilcoxon test to analyze the differences before and after using the device. A p-value of less than 0.05 was considered significant.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Differences of Background Variables Between Groups</title>
        <p>About 70% of the 40 subjects were women, with an average age of 50±13.38 years and an average history of insomnia of 9.68±8.86 years. <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> lists the characteristics of participants at baseline. No significant differences were observed in gender, age, years of insomnia history, education status, marital status, socioeconomic status, or comorbidity between the two groups.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic Data of the SR-Sleep-Device Group and Placebo-Device Group</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SR-Sleep-Device Group (n = 20)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo-Device Group (n = 20)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender (male) n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (40%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (20%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.301</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (year) M (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.90 (12.97)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.10 (14.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.676</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Years of insomnia history (year) M (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.83 (7.18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.53 (6.71)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.892</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education status, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.562</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Junior high</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (15%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Senior high</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (25%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (25%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> University or above</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (60%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marital status, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.348</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Single</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (15%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (20%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Married</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (60%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Divorce</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (15%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Widowed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (10%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (10%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Socioeconomic status, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.749</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> High</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (55%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (60%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Middle</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (45%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (40%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comorbidity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hypertension, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Diabetes, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Thyroid disorders, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Differences of the Objective Sleep Measurements in the SR-Sleep-Device/Placebo-Device Groups</title>
        <sec id="s0003-s2002-s3001">
          <title>PSG Results</title>
          <p>Comparisons of objective sleep measurements between, before, and four weeks after using the SR-sleep-device/placebo-device are presented in <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. A significant reduction in SOL (p = 0.012) and a significant increase in TST (p = 0.037) were observed in the SR-sleep-device group. No significant difference was observed in the placebo-device group. Although there was no significant difference between the two groups before and after treatment via Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test, there was a trend that many parameters of the SR-sleep-device group were improved, especially SOL (p = 0.055).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Differences of the Objective PSG Findings in the SR-Sleep-Device/Placebo-Device Groups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">(M ± SD)</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">SR-Sleep-Device Group (N = 20)</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Placebo-Device Group (N = 20)</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">p2</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p1</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.91 ± 4.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.12 ± 4.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.272</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.56 ± 2.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.42 ± 2.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.248</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.253</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.37 ± 36.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.31 ± 19.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.61 ± 30.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.84 ± 27.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.520</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.055</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SWS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5 ± 5.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.66 ± 7.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.851</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.61 ± 7.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.29 ± 9.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.208</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.820</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TIB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">415.19 ± 27.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">428.26 ± 21.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.351</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">411.49 ± 51.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">423.44 ± 41.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.198</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.799</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TST</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">295.59 ± 87.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">322.1 ± 75.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">306.53 ± 76.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">307.53 ± 90.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.444</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.495</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Efficiency</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.06 ± 20.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.2 ± 17.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.121</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.65 ± 16.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.47 ± 20.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.687</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.231</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WASO</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.87 ± 71.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.03 ± 66.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.629</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.87 ± 63.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.62 ± 73.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.546</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.444</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arousal index (events/hr)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.99 ± 16.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.9 ± 18.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.247</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.95 ± 11.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.55 ± 23.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.586</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.989</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI (events/hr)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.58 ± 19.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.76 ± 23.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.108</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.48 ± 9.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.97 ± 17.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.856</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.327</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AI (events/hr)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.96 ± 10.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6 ± 12.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.554</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12 ± 2.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 ± 1.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.275</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.627</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HI (events/hr)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.16 ± 11.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.17 ± 13.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.586</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.36 ± 7.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2 ± 5.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.698</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.792</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DI (events/hr)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.24 ± 17.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.65 ± 19.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.108</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.46 ± 3.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2 ± 4.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.420</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.314</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Awake (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.44 ± 20.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.79 ± 17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.370</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.94 ± 16.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.2 ± 19.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.421</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.341</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage N1 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.33 ± 17.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.83 ± 18.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.970</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.71 ± 14.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.58 ± 14.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.872</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.565</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage N2 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.71 ± 18.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.73 ± 18.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.086</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.76 ± 13.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.36 ± 12.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.409</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.086</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM sleep (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.83 ± 7.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.77 ± 7.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.191</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.93 ± 8.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.78 ± 7.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.215</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLMI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.93 ± 2.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 ± 2.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.173</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.63 ± 7.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.48 ± 6.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.807</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.496</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Snore index (events/hr)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">188.24 ± 301.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">206.54 ± 292.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.826</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">115.15 ± 153.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">193.46 ± 308.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.469</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.968</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean O<sub>2</sub> (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.45 ± 1.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.5 ± 1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.831</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.45 ± 1.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.35 ± 0.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.617</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.698</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Note</bold>: *p &lt; 0.05.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: p1, Wilcoxon test; p2, Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test (comparison of the difference between the two groups before and after); SOL, sleep onset latency; SWS, slow wave sleep; TIB, time in bed; TST, total sleep time; WASO, wake after sleep onset; BMI, body mass index; AHI, apnea-hypopnea index; AI, apnea index; REM, rapid eye movement; HI, hypopnea index; DI, O<sub>2</sub> desaturation index; PLMI, Periodic Limb Movement Index; Mean SaO<sub>2</sub>, mean oxygen saturation; hr, hour.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Differences of the Subjective Sleep Measurements in the SR-Sleep-Device/Placebo-Device Groups</title>
        <p>Comparisons of subjective sleep measurements between before, 2 weeks after, and 4 weeks after using the SR-sleep-device/placebo-device are presented in <xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Differences of the Subjective Sleep Measurements in the SR-Sleep-Device/Placebo-Device Groups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">(M ± SD)</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">SR-Sleep-Device Group (N = 20)</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Placebo-Device Group (N=20)</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">p2</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre (1)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">After 2 Weeks (2)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">After 4 Weeks (3)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre (1)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">After 2 Weeks (2)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">After 4 Weeks (3)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p1</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep diary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.74 ± 22.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.41 ± 17.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.06 ± 15.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004** (1 &gt; 3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.12 ± 43.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.16 ± 30.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.15 ± 39.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.638</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.175</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TIB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">511.77 ± 84.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">503.38 ± 103.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">503.04 ± 50.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.756</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">494.03 ± 66.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">515.91 ± 70.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">505.50 ± 82.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.064</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.204</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TST</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">380.79 ± 84.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">389.42 ± 113.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">402.44 ± 67.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047* (3 &gt; 1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">368.49 ± 86.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">410.53 ± 51.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">396.07 ± 68.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.074</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.923</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 ± 0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77 ± 0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 ± 0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017* (3 &gt; 1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 ± 0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 ± 0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 ± 0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.259</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.184</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WASO</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.42 ± 36.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.38 ± 38.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.48 ± 39.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.646</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.97 ± 21.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.4 ± 21.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.46 ± 24.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.471</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.945</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subjective sleep quality</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95 ± 0.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5 ± 0.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 ± 0.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001** (1 &gt; 2, 3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 ± 0.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75 ± 0.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85 ± 0.67</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042* (1 &gt; 2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep latency</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 ± 0.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9 ± 0.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 ± 0.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003** (1, 2 &gt; 3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 ± 0.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 ± 0.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.05 ± 0.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.485</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.142</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 ± 0.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 ± 0.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45 ± 0.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021* (1 &gt; 2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.05 ± 0.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 ± 0.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55 ± 1.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009** (1 &gt; 2, 3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.398</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitual sleep efficiency</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65 ± 0.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75 ± 0.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55 ± 0.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.646</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.45 ± 0.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9 ± 0.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95 ± 1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.301</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep disturbance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 ± 0.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 ± 0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5 ± 0.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.336</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8 ± 0.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 ± 0.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55 ± 0.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.093</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.583</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Use of sleep medicine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 ± 1.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 ± 1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 ± 1.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.223</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 ± 1.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 ± 1.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15 ± 1.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.368</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.445</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daytime dysfunction</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 ± 0.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 ± 0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 ± 0.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.301</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 ± 0.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 ± 0.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 ± 0.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.186</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.547</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Global score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 ± 2.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6 ± 2.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.95 ± 2.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034* (1 &gt;2, 3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 ± 3.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1 ± 3.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.15 ± 4.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.044* (1 &gt; 2, 3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.445</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6 ± 4.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.55 ± 3.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.15 ± 3.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019* (1 &gt; 3; p = 0.055)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.55 ± 5.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4 ± 5.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2 ± 4.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.430</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.289</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01. (<bold>1</bold>): pre, (<bold>2</bold>): after 2 weeks, (<bold>3</bold>): after 4 weeks.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: p1, Friedman test; post hoc, Wilcoxon test; p2, Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test (comparison of the difference between the two groups before and after 4 weeks); SOL, sleep onset latency; TIB, time in bed; TST, total sleep time; SE, sleep efficiency; WASO, wake after sleep onset; PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Inventory; ESS, Epworth Sleepiness Scale.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
        <sec id="s0003-s2003-s3001">
          <title>Sleep Diaries</title>
          <p>A significant reduction in SOL (p = 0.004) and a significant increase in TST (p = 0.047) and SE (p = 0.017) were observed in the SR-sleep-device group (all the differences were between pre and week 4). No significant difference was observed in the placebo-device group.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2003-s3002">
          <title>PSQI and ESS</title>
          <p>A significant reduction in sleep latency index (p = 0.003, the significance was between “pre, week 2” and “week 4”) was observed in the SR-sleep-device group but not in the placebo-device group. Significant improvements in subjective sleep quality index (p<sub>SR</sub> = 0.001 (pre &gt; week 2, week 4); p<sub>placebo</sub> = 0.042 (pre &gt; week 2)), sleep duration index (p<sub>SR</sub> = 0.021 (pre &gt; week 2); p<sub>placebo</sub> = 0.009 (pre &gt; week 2, week 4)), global score index (p<sub>SR</sub> = 0.034 (pre &gt; week 2, week 4); p<sub>placebo</sub> = 0.044 (pre &gt; week 2, week 4)), and ESS (p<sub>SR</sub> = 0.019 (pre &gt; week 4, p = 0.055)) were observed in both groups. Furthermore, the “Sleep Quality” parameter of the SR-sleep-device group improved significantly (p = 0.046).</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Differences of Quality of Life (SF-36) and Visual Analogy of Sleep Satisfaction in the SR-Sleep-Device/Placebo-Device Groups</title>
        <p>Comparisons of subjective quality of life (SF-36) between before, 2 weeks after, and 4 weeks after using the SR-sleep-device/placebo-device are presented in <xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. Significant improvements in energy/fatigue (p = 0.008) and bodily pain (p = 0.031) were observed in the SR-sleep-device group but not in the placebo-device group. We observed significant improvements in mental health (p<sub>SR</sub> = 0.005; p<sub>placebo</sub> = 0.023) in the two groups. Sleep satisfaction in both groups was significantly improved (p<sub>SR</sub> &lt; 0.001; p<sub>placebo</sub> = 0.004). In addition, the change from baseline in sleep satisfaction score (p = 0.046) was greater in the SR-sleep-device group than in the placebo-device group.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0004" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Differences of the Health Survey (SF-36) and Sleep-Satisfaction in the SR-Sleep-Device/Placebo-Device Groups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">(M ± SD)</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">SR-Sleep-Device Group (N = 20)</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Placebo-Device Group (N=20)</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">p2</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre (1)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">After 2 Weeks (2)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">After 4 Weeks (3)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre (1)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">After 2 Weeks (2)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">After 4 Weeks (3)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p1</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The 36-Item Short-Form Health Survey (SF-36)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical function</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.00 ± 12.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.25 ± 14.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.00 ± 14.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.156</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.50 ± 17.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.50 ± 21.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.00 ± 20.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.982</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.398</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Role limitations due to physical health</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.00 ± 40.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.00 ± 40.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.00 ± 41.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.773</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.25 ± 45.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.25 ± 43.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.25 ± 36.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.358</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.192</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Role limitations due to emotional problems</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.00 ± 47.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.67 ± 49.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.67 ± 42.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.301</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.67 ± 39.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.67 ± 39.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.00 ± 41.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.598</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.314</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Energy/fatigue</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.50 ± 22.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.00 ± 21.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.00 ± 23.25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008* (2, 3 &gt; 1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.00 ± 16.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.00 ± 19.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.50 ± 21.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.054</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.738</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mental health</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.60 ± 18.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.20 ± 18.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.60 ± 18.67</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005** (2, 3 &gt; 1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.80 ± 17.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.40 ± 19.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.40 ± 19.18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023* (2, 3 &gt; 1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.640</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Social functioning</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.88 ± 17.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.75 ± 19.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.13 ± 19.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.442</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.88 ± 21.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.00 ± 24.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.25 ± 23.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.487</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.779</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bodily pain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.13 ± 15.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.25 ± 15.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.38 ± 13.03</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031* (3 &gt; 1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.38 ± 16.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.00 ± 15.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.13 ± 13.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.098</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.968</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">General health</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.00 ± 22.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.50 ± 22.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.75 ± 22.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.867</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.25 ± 23.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.25 ± 20.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.75 ± 25.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.072</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.174</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep satisfaction</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.95 ± 1.21</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.75 ± 1.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.20 ± 1.24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.18 ± 1.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046*</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001. (<bold>1</bold>): pre, (<bold>2</bold>): after 2 weeks, (<bold>3</bold>): after 4 weeks.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0006"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: p1, Friedman test; p2, Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test (comparison of the difference between the two groups before and after).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2005">
        <title>Adverse Events</title>
        <p>Among the 46 participants, two participants experienced headache and dizziness when using the device (1 was in SR-sleep-device group and 1 was in placebo-device group) and stopped following. There is no other adverse event.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>This study examines whether 40 participants with insomnia can experience improvements in subjective and objective sleep measurements after using an SR-sleep-device/placebo-device for four weeks. Only two participants experienced side effects of headache and dizziness (study group n = 1; placebo group n = 1) and left the study. This study is the first to investigate whether SR affects sleep and insomnia.</p>
      <p>In the SR-sleep-device group, objective PSG measurements (SOL and TST but not SWS) and subjective sleep measurements (SOL, TST, SE, sleep quality, daytime sleepiness, sleep satisfaction) were both significantly improved after using the SR-sleep-device. However, in the placebo-device group, objective sleep measurements were not showed any differences after using the device, and there was only subjective sleep improvement in sleep satisfaction and some components of PSQI. This finding indicates that the SR can reduce the symptoms of insomnia symptoms, especially in the “sleep onset” and “total sleep time.” Another important finding is that fifty-five percent of the placebo group had improvement shown by PSQI and Sleep satisfaction scale, and it may be explained by the common placebo effect in treating insomnia.<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></p>
      <p>Currently, we do not fully understand the mechanism of the SR in improving insomnia and sleep. Previous studies have shown that changes in geomagnetic activity have been linked to epileptic seizures,<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> myocardial infarction,<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> stroke,<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> and depression.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> Biogenic magnetite provides a molecular mechanism for geomagnetic sensing,<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> which has been found in the human brain.<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> Cherry (2002) suspected SR, which globally propagates extremely low frequency (ELF) waves, to be “the possible biological mechanism” that explains biological and human health effects of geomagnetic activity. The peak SR frequencies undergo a moderate diurnal variation of approximately ± 0.5 Hz. Interestingly, the first four SR modes happen to be within the frequency range of the first four EEG bands (ie, delta 0.5–3.5 Hz, theta 4–7 Hz, alpha 8–13 Hz, and beta 14 to 30 Hz).<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> Some studies have also found that human brain waves and SR share the same frequency range. The human body detects, absorbs, and responds to natural EMF by the process of resonance matching of frequency. With this matching, natural EMF can influence biological communication phenomena in cell-to-cell communication in the human body.<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> Pall (2013) also reported that exposure to EMF would promote Ca2+ influx via the voltage-gate Ca2+ channel, which can increase Ca2+ concentration in the cytosol and then cause biological effects.<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> Wang (2019) also indicated that extremely low-frequency magnetic stimulation can induce low-frequency activities and lead to resonance effects in the human brain.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> The “biophysical mechanism” for the human health effect mechanism may explain biological and human health effects of geomagnetic activity.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> An increasing number of psychiatrists have been integrating electrophysiotherapy treatments into their clinical practice because they are noninvasive, have few side effects, and can treat anxiety, depression, and insomnia simultaneously.</p>
      <p>From our results of improving SOL, it can be inferred that SR can make participants’ brain waves resonate to 7.83 Hz waves and relax their body so that people can fall asleep easily and increase total sleep time. Another hypothesis is that EMF is related to human melatonin metabolites,<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> which could also explain the improvement of participants’ total sleep time and sleep quality after 4 weeks of treatment. However, this study did not show a significant increase in the deep sleep ratio (SWS %). It may relate to the small sample size or the first night effect of PSG. The 4-week treatment period may be too short or does not affect melatonin yet. Therefore, these findings and hypotheses require more rigorous and long-term research.</p>
      <p>A recent systematic review and meta-analysis of CBTi showed significant effects on daytime symptoms including daytime sleepiness, although the effect size is only small to moderate. By improving nighttime symptoms, CBTi can have a positive effect on daytime symptoms indirectly.<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> Similarly, the SR-sleep-device group in this study has a significant effect on the level of daytime sleepiness, which means that the SR may improve insomnia patients’ daytime quality of life (such as energy/fatigue, bodily pain, and mental health). Furthermore, Kay reported that SR improves depression.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> Besides the possible benefits of sleep shown by this study, other therapeutic effects of SR such as improved daytime sleepiness and depression and the role of SR in these correlated conditions require further investigation.</p>
      <p>Though with a randomized, double-blinded design, it still has limitations. First, the sample size was very small (N = 40) although we did reach the estimated sample size (N = 38). Second, several patients had received hypnotics and could not stop hypnotics, but they kept the same drugs and same dose during the study. There can be sampling errors if we only included drug naive participants. Third, the “first night effect” should be considered when performing PSG and can possibly explain the improvement in PSG. However, only the SR-sleep-device group had significant improvement in PSG, and the finding supported the effects of SR on sleep. Furthermore, we cannot truly verify compliance, but we supervised our participants to turn on the machine every night during the study period.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>This study shows that the SR can reduce the insomnia symptoms, supported by both objective and subjective measurements, although the sample size is small. Future studies should explore the possible mental and physical effects of Schumann resonance with larger sample sizes, as well as use a longer tracking time to verify the effectiveness and side effects, and explore possible mechanism.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>This study was designed by Professor Guilleminault before his passing on July 9, 2019. Although he could not be the corresponding author for this study, we would like to thank and honor him. He was among the most important and fundamental person in the field of sleep medicine. Without his inspiration and vision, we could not have completed this study.</p>
      <p>This study was supported by Chang Gung Memorial Hospital grant No. CMRPG 3J 0131 and 3J 0133 to Dr. Yu-Shu Huang and Chang Gung Memorial Hospital grant No. CMRPG 3L0291 to Dr. Wei-Chih Chin.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p>The data that support the findings of this study are available from the first author or corresponding author upon reasonable request after getting the permission of Chang Gung Hospital IRB. Additionally, the individual deidentified participant data are available after contacting the first author or corresponding author via email. The data will be available immediately following publication without an end date.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0007">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors declare to have no financial arrangements or connections with regard to this study. This research did not receive any specific grant from funding agencies in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors. The patent TW M530656 U license (SR device) belongs to Professor Ling-Sheng Jang. The authors report no other conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Morin</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benca</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Chronic insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>379</volume>:<fpage>1129</fpage>–<lpage>1141</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(11)60750-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22265700</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">The International Classification of Sleep Disorders</italic></source>. <edition>3rd</edition> ed. <publisher-loc>Darien (IL)</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</publisher-name>; <year>2014</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bertisch</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pollock</surname>
<given-names>BD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mittleman</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia with objective short sleep duration and risk of incident cardiovascular disease and all-cause mortality: sleep heart health study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>zsy047</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsy047</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Generaal</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vogelzangs</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Penninx</surname>
<given-names>BW</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia, sleep duration, depressive symptoms, and the onset of chronic multisite musculoskeletal pain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>zsw030</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hein</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lanquart</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Loas</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence and risk factors of type 2 diabetes in insomnia sufferers: a study on 1311 individuals referred for sleep examinations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2018.02.006</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Harvey</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia: symptom or diagnosis?</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Psychol Rev</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>1037</fpage>–<lpage>1059</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0272-7358(00)00083-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11584515</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baglioni</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Battagliese</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feige</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia as a predictor of depression: a meta-analytic evaluation of longitudinal epidemiological studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Affect Disord</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>135</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2011.01.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21300408</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dolsen</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Asarnow</surname>
<given-names>LD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harvey</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia as a transdiagnostic process in psychiatric disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Psychiatry Rep</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>471</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11920-014-0471-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25030972</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sateia</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krystal</surname>
<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Clinical practice guideline for the pharmacologic treatment of chronic insomnia in adults: an American Academy of Sleep Medicine clinical practice guideline</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>349</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.6470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27998379</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Morin</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jarrin</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ivers</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Incidence, persistence, and remission rates of insomnia over 5 years</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Netw Open</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>e2018782</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.18782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33156345</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Maust</surname>
<given-names>DT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blow</surname>
<given-names>FC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Benzodiazepine use and misuse among adults in the United States</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatr Serv</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ps.201800321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30554562</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Agarwal</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Landon</surname>
<given-names>BE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Patterns in outpatient benzodiazepine prescribing in the United States</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Netw Open</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>e187399</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2018.7399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30681713</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buscemi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vandermeer</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Friesen</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The efficacy and safety of drug treatments for chronic insomnia in adults: a meta-analysis of RCTs</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Gen Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1335</fpage>–<lpage>1350</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-007-0251-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17619935</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Glass</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lanctôt</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Herrmann</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sedative hypnotics in older people with insomnia: meta-analysis of risks and benefits</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>331</volume>:<fpage>1169</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.38623.768588.47</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16284208</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Edinger</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arnedt</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bertisch</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Behavioral and psychological treatments for chronic insomnia disorder in adults: an American Academy of Sleep Medicine clinical practice guideline</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.8986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33164742</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ong</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sholtes</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A mindfulness-based approach to the treatment of insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>1175</fpage>–<lpage>1184</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jclp.20736</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20853441</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gong</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ni</surname>
<given-names>CX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>YZ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Mindfulness meditation for insomnia: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychosom Re</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychores.2016.07.016</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Carotenuto</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gallai</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parisi</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Acupressure therapy for insomnia in adolescents: a polysomnographic study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>157</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NDT.S41892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23378768</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yeung</surname>
<given-names>WF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>KF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poon</surname>
<given-names>MMK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Acupressure, reflexology, and auricular acupressure for insomnia: a systematic review of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>971</fpage>–<lpage>984</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2012.06.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22841034</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sok</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Erlen</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>KB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of acupuncture therapy on insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Adv Nurs</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>375</fpage>–<lpage>384</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.0309-2402.2003.02816.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14651709</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yin</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gou</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Efficacy and safety of acupuncture treatment on primary insomnia: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2017.02.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28899535</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kirsch</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nichols</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cranial electrotherapy stimulation for treatment of anxiety, depression, and insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatr Clin North Am</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psc.2013.01.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23538086</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zou</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effect of repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) for insomnia: a protocol for a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ open</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e029206</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2019-029206</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Belisheva</surname>
<given-names>NK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Popov</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petukhova</surname>
<given-names>NV</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Qualitative and quantitative assessment of exposure to geomagnetic field variations on the functional status of the human brain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biofizika</italic></source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>1005</fpage>–<lpage>1012</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8555283</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Mulligan</surname>
<given-names>BP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suess-Cloes</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mach</surname>
<given-names>QH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <source><italic toggle="yes">Geopsychology Geophysical Matrix and Human Behaviour</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Man and the Geosphere, Nova Science Publishers</publisher-name>; <year>2010</year>:<fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>141</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>CX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hilburn</surname>
<given-names>IA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Transduction of the geomagnetic field as evidenced from alpha-band activity in the human brain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">eneuro</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<page-range>ENEURO.0483–18.2019</page-range>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/ENEURO.0483-18.2019</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Sentman</surname>
<given-names>DD</given-names></string-name>. <part-title>Schumann resonances</part-title>. In: <string-name><surname>Volland</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, editor. <source><italic toggle="yes">Handbook of Atmospheric Electrodynamics</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Boca Raton (FL)</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>; <year>1995</year>:<fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>298</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cherry</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Schumann resonances, a plausible biophysical mechanism for the human health effects of solar</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Natural Hazards</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>279</fpage>–<lpage>331</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1015637127504</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Persinger</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Schumann resonance frequencies found within quantitative electroencephalographic activity: implications for earth-brain interactions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int Lett Chem Phys Astron</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>24</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18052/www.scipress.com/ILCPA.30.24</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ghione</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mezzasalma</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Del Seppia</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Do geomagnetic disturbances of solar origin affect arterial blood pressure?</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Hum Hypertens</italic></source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>749</fpage>–<lpage>754</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.jhh.1000708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9844945</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Burch</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reif</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yost</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Geomagnetic disturbances are associated with reduced nocturnal excretion of a melatonin metabolite in humans</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurosci Lett</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>266</volume>:<fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>212</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-3940(99)00308-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10465710</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rechtschaffen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kales</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A manual of standardized terminology; techniques and scoring systems for sleep stages of human subjects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>1968</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>305</fpage>–<lpage>310</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>CF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monk</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The Pittsburgh sleep quality index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0165-1781(89)90047-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2748771</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tsai</surname>
<given-names>PS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>MY</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Psychometric evaluation of the Chinese version of the Pittsburgh sleep quality index (CPSQI) in primary insomnia and control subjects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Qual Life Res</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1943</fpage>–<lpage>1952</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16155782</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Johns</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A new method for measuring daytime sleepiness: the Epworth sleepiness scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>540</fpage>–<lpage>545</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/14.6.540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1798888</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Brazier</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harper</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Validating the SF-36 health survey questionnaire: new outcome measure for primary care</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic></source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>305</volume>:<fpage>160</fpage>–<lpage>164</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.305.6846.160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1285753</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Koffel</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koffel</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gehrman</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A meta-analysis of group cognitive behavioral therapy for insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2014.05.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24931811</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Persinger</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Psych</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sudden unexpected death in epileptics following sudden, intense, increases in geomagnetic activity: prevalence of effect and potential mechanisms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Biometeorol</italic></source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>180</fpage>–<lpage>187</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01245386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7601551</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stoupel</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abramson</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sulkes</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Relationship between suicide and myocardial infarction with regard to changing physical environmental conditions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Biometeorol</italic></source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01245389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7601553</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Feigin</surname>
<given-names>VL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nikitin</surname>
<given-names>YP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vinogradova</surname>
<given-names>TE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Solar and geomagnetic activities: are there associations with stroke occurrence?</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cerebrovasc Dis</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>345</fpage>–<lpage>348</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000108220</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kay</surname>
<given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Geomagnetic storms: association with incidence of depression as measured by hospital admission</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Br J Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>164</volume>:<fpage>403</fpage>–<lpage>409</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/bjp.164.3.403</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8199794</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Phillips</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deutschlander</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Magnetoreception in terrestrial vertebrates: implications for possible mechanisms of EMF interaction with biological systems. The melatonin hypothesis: electric power and the risk of breast cancer</article-title>. <publisher-name>Battelle Press, Columbus Ohio</publisher-name>; <year>1997</year>:<fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>172</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kirschvink</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kobayashi-Kirschvink</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Woodford</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Magnetite biomineralization in the human brain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</italic></source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>7683</fpage>–<lpage>7687</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.89.16.7683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1502184</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cherry</surname>
<given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Human intelligence: the brain, an electromagnetic system synchronised by the Schumann resonance signal</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Med Hypotheses</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>843</fpage>–<lpage>844</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0306-9877(03)00027-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12699709</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pall</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Electromagnetic fields act via activation of voltage-gated calcium channels to produce beneficial or adverse effects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cell Mol Med</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>958</fpage>–<lpage>965</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcmm.12088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23802593</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Benz</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knoop</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ballesio</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The efficacy of cognitive and behavior therapies for insomnia on daytime symptoms: a systematic review and network meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Psychol Rev</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>80</volume>:<fpage>101873</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cpr.2020.101873</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32777632</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
