<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35923809</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">9342428</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">361318</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S361318</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Comparison of Composite Lipid Indices in Patients with Obstructive Sleep Apnoea</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Bikov et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Bikov et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8983-740X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Bikov</surname>
            <given-names>Andras</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7469-6755</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Frent</surname>
            <given-names>Stefan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Reisz</surname>
            <given-names>Daniela</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Negru</surname>
            <given-names>Alina</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0006" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5204-6954</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Gaita</surname>
            <given-names>Laura</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0007" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Breban Schwarzkopf</surname>
            <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0008" ref-type="aff">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8897-8342</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Mihaicuta</surname>
            <given-names>Stefan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>North West Lung Centre, Wythenshawe Hospital, Manchester University NHS Foundation Trust</institution>, <addr-line>Manchester</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Division of Immunology, Immunity to Infection and Respiratory Medicine, University of Manchester</institution>, <addr-line>Manchester</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Center for Research and Innovation in Precision Medicine of Respiratory Diseases, Department of Pulmonology, “Victor Babes” University of Medicine and Pharmacy Timisoara</institution>, <addr-line>Timisoara</addr-line>, <country>Romania</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Neurology, “Victor Babes” University of Medicine and Pharmacy Timisoara</institution>, <addr-line>Timisoara</addr-line>, <country>Romania</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label><institution>Department of Cardiology (II), “Victor Babes” University of Medicine and Pharmacy Timisoara</institution>, <addr-line>Timisoara</addr-line>, <country>Romania</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0006"><label>6</label><institution>Department of Clinical Research, Institute of Cardiovascular Diseases</institution>, <addr-line>Timisoara</addr-line>, <country>Romania</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0007"><label>7</label><institution>Second Department of Internal Medicine, “Victor Babes” University of Medicine and Pharmacy Timisoara</institution>, <addr-line>Timisoara</addr-line>, <country>Romania</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0008"><label>8</label><institution>Department of Anatomy, “Victor Babes” University of Medicine and Pharmacy Timisoara</institution>, <addr-line>Timisoara</addr-line>, <country>Romania</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Stefan Frent; Daniela Reisz, Email frentz.stefan@umft.ro; reisz.daniela@umft.ro</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>27</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <fpage>1333</fpage>
      <lpage>1340</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>06</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2022 Bikov et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Bikov et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p>Obstructive sleep apnoea (OSA) is a recognised risk factor for cardiovascular disease. However, it is difficult to evaluate the risk of cardiovascular disease in patients with OSA due to multiple shared risk factors. Composite lipid indices, such as atherogenic index of plasma (AIP), visceral adiposity index (VAI) and lipid accumulation product (LAP) have been shown to predict cardiovascular disease better than their individual lipid components. This study aimed to evaluate these indices in patients with OSA.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Patients and Methods</title>
          <p>Six hundred sixty-seven (667) patients with OSA and 139 non-OSA control volunteers participated in the study. Fasting serum triglycerides, total cholesterol, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-C) levels were measured, and AIP, LAP and VAI were calculated following cardiorespiratory polygraphy. The relationship between lipid parameters, OSA and its comorbidities was evaluated using receiver operating curve (ROC) analysis.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>We found a significant difference in all lipid parameters between OSA patients and controls. Comparing ROCs, LAP was significantly more strongly associated with OSA compared to all the other parameters. The optimal cut-off value for LAP to detect OSA was 76.4, with a sensitivity of 63% and a specificity of 76%. In addition, LAP was the best parameter to predict hypertension and diabetes in patients with OSA, and it was predictive for ischaemic heart disease together with HDL-C.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>Our results support the use of LAP in clinical practice when evaluating cardiovascular risk in patients with OSA. However, the optimal cut-off value should be determined in large-scale follow-up studies.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>lipid indices</kwd>
        <kwd>cholesterol</kwd>
        <kwd>triglyceride</kwd>
        <kwd>obstructive sleep apnea</kwd>
        <kwd>cardiovascular risk</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="1"/>
        <table-count count="7"/>
        <ref-count count="35"/>
        <page-count count="8"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Obstructive sleep apnoea (OSA) is a common condition characterised by repetitive partial or complete collapse of the pharynx during sleep resulting in intermittent hypoxaemia and sleep fragmentation. OSA is broadly recognised as a risk factor for cardiovascular morbidity and mortality. This association is driven by multiple processes induced by OSA, such as systemic inflammation and oxidative stress, sympathetic activity, hypertension and dyslipidaemia.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></p>
      <p>Obstructive sleep apnoea can cause dyslipidaemia via various mechanisms. First, patients with OSA tend to consume more fat-rich meals.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Second, OSA is associated with higher postprandial plasma levels of triglycerides, suggesting an accelerated lipid absorption and decreased lipoprotein lipase activity.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Third, the hepatic synthesis of triglycerides is accelerated in OSA due to hypoxaemia-sensitive mechanisms.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Forth, intermittent hypoxaemia triggers hormone sensitive lipases in the adipose tissues leading to the release of free fatty acids into circulation.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Finally, the clearance of low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL-C) from circulation is reduced in OSA.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Not surprisingly, OSA is associated with high triglyceride (TGs) and low high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-C) levels.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Of note, obesity is a well known risk factor for OSA<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> and a significant confounder for the association between OSA and dyslipidaemia.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></p>
      <p>The link between dyslipidaemia and cardiovascular risk cannot be entirely evaluated by investigating single lipid components due to the dynamic interaction between different lipoprotein fractions.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> To address this, the logarithmic ratio of high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-C) and triglycerides, the so called Atherogenic Index of Plasma (AIP) has been investigated in OSA before in several studies.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12–15</xref> In addition, visceral fat distribution was demonstrated to be a better predictor for cardiovascular disease than the body mass index (BMI).<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> In line with this, composite indices which take into account both, lipid parameters and waist circumference, were better predictors for cardiovascular disease than single lipid components.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> These indices include the visceral adiposity index (VAI) and lipid accumulation product (LAP), both of which were investigated in OSA.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19–24</xref></p>
      <p>Despite previous research, it remains unclear which index should be used in clinical practice in OSA. These indices were directly compared only in three studies;<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> however, all were performed in Chinese populations. Notably, the clinical value of lipid indices depends on ethnicity,<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> therefore these results are not fully translatable to a Caucasian population. Moreover, only one of these studies has investigated the prediction of metabolic consequences in OSA. Wei et al reported that LAP was more strongly related to insulin resistance than VAI, but only in normal-weight subjects.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></p>
      <p>The aim of the current study was to analyse if AIP, VAI and LAP are more strongly related to OSA than the individual lipid components, how they change with disease severity and how they correlate with cardiovascular disease, hypertension and diabetes.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Study Design and Subjects</title>
        <p>Eight hundred six (806) consecutive volunteers participated in the study. All patients were referred with symptoms and/or medical history suggestive for OSA (ie snoring, witnessed apnoeas, daytime somnolence, treatment-resistant comorbidities). Medical history was taken, blood pressure, height, weight, waist (WC), hip (HC) and neck circumference (NC) were measured, and the subjects filled out the Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS). Following an inpatient diagnostic sleep test, fasting blood sample was drawn for measuring total cholesterol, LDL-C, HDL-C and triglycerides. Comorbidities were defined by patient self-report, available medical records, and prescription charts. The study was approved by the local Ethics Committee (“Victor Babes” University of Medicine and Pharmacy Timisoara 22/2014/24.07.2019) and patients gave their informed consent before participation. All procedures performed in our study were in accordance with the ethical standards of the 1964 Helsinki declaration and its later amendments.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Sleep Studies</title>
        <p>Inpatient cardiorespiratory polygraphy was performed with Porti 7 SLEEP DOC DeVilbiss or Stardust Philips Respironics. Apnoea was defined as a drop in nasal flow of at least 90%, lasting for minimum 10 seconds. Hypopnoea was defined as a drop in nasal flow of at least 30%, associated with a drop in oxygen saturation of at least 3% lasting for minimum 10 seconds (according to the American Academy of Sleep Medicine Scoring Manual, version 2.5.). Apnoea-hypopnoea index (AHI) and oxygen desaturation index (ODI) were calculated and were used to define OSA severity. OSA was defined by AHI≥5/h, and patients with OSA were categorised into mild (AHI 5–14.9/h), moderate (AHI 15–29.9/h) and severe (AHI≥30/h) subgroups.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Measurement of Lipid Components and Composite Indices</title>
        <p>The samples were analysed with a COBAS INTEGRA 400 plus analyzer (Roche Diagnostics, Switzerland). Lipid levels were estimated by the enzymatic colorimetric method with an inter-assay coefficient of variability of 1.6%, 0.5%, 1.3% and 1.13%, for triglyceride, total cholesterol, LDL-C and HDL-C, respectively. The laboratory is SR EN ISO 15189:2013 certified.</p>
        <p>AIP was calculated as <inline-formula id="ilm0001"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-1333-e0001.jpg"/><tex-math id="Tex001">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$$Lo{g_{10}}\left({{{Tg} \over {HDL - C}}} \right)$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula>, VAI was calculated as <inline-formula id="ilm0002"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-1333-e0002.jpg"/><tex-math id="Tex002">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$${{WC} \over {(39.68 + \left({1.88 \times BMI} \right)}} \times {{TG} \over {1.03}} \times {{1.31} \over {HDL - C}}$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula> for men and <inline-formula id="ilm0003"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-1333-e0003.jpg"/><tex-math id="Tex003">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$${{WC} \over {36.58 + \left({1.89 \times BMI} \right)}} \times {{TG} \over {0.81}} \times {{1.52} \over {HDL - C}}$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula> for women, while LAP was calculated as <inline-formula id="ilm0004"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-1333-e0004.jpg"/><tex-math id="Tex004">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$$\left({WC - 65} \right) \times TG$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula> for men and <inline-formula id="ilm0005"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-1333-e0005.jpg"/><tex-math id="Tex005">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$$\left({WC - 58} \right) \times TG$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula> for women where WC was expressed in cm and TGs and HDL-C were both expressed in mmol/l.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>JASP 0.14 (JASP Team, University of Amsterdam, The Netherlands) and MedCalc 19.5.3 (MedCalc Software Ltd, Belgium) were used for statistical analysis. The normality of the data was assessed with the Shapiro–Wilk test. The OSA and control groups were compared with Mann–Whitney and Chi-square tests. The relationship between lipids and OSA severity was investigated with the non-parametric analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) test adjusted for age, BMI and gender followed by the Dunn’s test where OSA severity groups were compared to the control group. In addition, the relationship between lipid parameters and OSA severity was also analysed with multiple linear regression analysis using AHI, age, gender and BMI as independent variables. The relationship between lipids and ESS was investigated with the Spearman’s test. The associations between AIP, LAP and VAI and OSA, and their predictive value for ischaemic heart disease, hypertension and diabetes were evaluated with the Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) analysis and compared to each other and to TGs, LDL-C and HDL-C using the DeLong test.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> The ROC analyses for comorbidities were performed only in patients with OSA. Data were expressed as median /interquartile range/. A p value &lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Comparison of OSA and Control Groups</title>
        <p>Six hundred sixty-seven (667) patients were diagnosed with OSA. Patients in OSA group were older, had higher WC, HC and NC values, higher total cholesterol, LDL-C and triglyceride levels and lower HDL-C levels. We found a higher prevalence of male gender, hypertension, ischaemic heart disease, and diabetes in the OSA group. There was no difference in smoking habits between the two groups. All three investigated composite lipid indices were significantly higher in OSA compared to controls. The patients’ characteristics are summarised in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Subjects’ Characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control (n=139)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSA (n=667)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild OSA (n=81)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate OSA (n=204)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe OSA (n=382)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.0 /35.5–55.0/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.0 /47.0–64.0/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0 /42.0–60.0/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.0 /45.0–64.0/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.0 /49.0–64.0/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender (n, % male)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80, 58%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">455, 68%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43, 53%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">133, 65%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">279, 73%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.0 /24.8–32.1/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.6 /29.7–37.9/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.5 /26.1–35.4/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.9 /28.0–35.6/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.1 /31.9–39.1/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WC (cm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101 /95–111/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">116 /107–126/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107 /98–119/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">112 /104–120/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120 /110–129/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HC (cm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105 /99–112/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">114 /107–122/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108 /103–118/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110 /106–120/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">117 /110–126/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC (cm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 /36–42/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 /40–45/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 /37–42/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 /39–43/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 /41–47/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoker (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42, 30%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">178, 27%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20, 25%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46, 23%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">112, 29%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53, 42%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">507, 77%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43, 55%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">145, 72%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">319, 84%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ischaemic heart disease (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6, 5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">136, 21%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7, 9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37, 19%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92, 24%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes mellitus (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7, 6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">159, 24%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13, 17%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39, 20%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107, 28%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBP (mmHg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">127 /120–140/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">135 /125–141/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">130 /120–140/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">131 /125–140/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">135 /127–142/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DBP (mmHg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79 /71–85/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 /75–90/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 /72–85/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 /75–90/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81 /77–90/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triglycerides (mmol/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31 /1.14–1.72/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75 /1.26–2.20/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71 /1.14–2.06/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61 /1.14–2.04/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.86 /1.37–2.23/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total cholesterol (mmol/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.89 /4.63–5.15/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.16 /4.32–5.72/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.20 /4.45–5.64/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.98 /4.31–5.92/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.22 /4.38–5.92/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL-C (mmol/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.56 /2.38–2.83/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.26 /2.57–4.11/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.15 /2.56–3.98/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.10 /2.46–3.88/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.41 /2.61–4.24/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL-C (mmol/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 /1.10–1.35/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12 /1.04–1.30/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19 /1.09–1.40/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 /1.04–1.32/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 /1.01–1.25/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AIP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 /-0.05–0.19/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19 /0.00–0.32/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13 /-0.07–0.27/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15 /-0.04–0.28/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22 /0.05–0.35/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82 /1.32–2.50/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50 /1.65–3.48/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.38 /1.35–3.32/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.21 /1.46–3.22/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63 /1.80–3.54/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LAP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.35 /35.95–75.01/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.26 /60.06–128.45/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.15 /40.24–116.24/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.02 /49.68–109.60/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101.16 /71.98–143.26/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 /4–10/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 /6–12/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 /5–10/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 /5–11/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 /6–13/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI (1/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7 /3.2–4.0/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.1 /21.1–54.4/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8 /7.3–12.8/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.2 /18.9–25.8/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.7 /38.2–67.4/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ODI (1/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0 /2.2–3.4/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.8 /17.1–50.9/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7 /4.0–10.6/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5 /14.5–22.6/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.1 /32.9–67.0/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Note</bold>: The p value reflects on the comparison between the control and OSA groups.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: AHI, apnoea-hypopnoea index; AIP, atherogenic index of plasma; BMI, body mass index; DBP, diastolic blood pressure; ESS, Epworth Sleepiness Scale; HC, hip circumference; HDL-C, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol; LAP, lipid accumulation product; LDL-C, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol; NC, neck circumference; ODI, oxygen desaturation index; OSA, obstructive sleep apnoea; SBP, systolic blood pressure; VAI, visceral adiposity index; WC, waist circumference.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>The Relationship Between OSA Severity, Lipids and Lipid Indices</title>
        <p>Eighty-one (81) patients were diagnosed with mild (AHI 5–14.9/h), 204 with moderate (AHI 15–29.9/h) and 382 with severe (AHI≥30/h) OSA. All lipid fractions were related to OSA severity (p&lt;0.01); however, progressive changes were noticed only for HDL-C and LAP. A significant difference in total cholesterol level was noticed between severe OSA and control groups (p&lt;0.05). LDL-C and LAP were different from the control group in mild, moderate and severe OSA subgroups (all p&lt;0.05), while triglycerides, HDL-C, AIP and VAI were different from controls in moderate and severe OSA subgroups (all p&lt;0.05, <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The AHI independently related to triglycerides, total cholesterol, LDL-C and LAP (all p&lt;0.05); however following adjustment for age, gender and BMI, there was no relationship between AHI and HDL-C (p=0.82), VAI (p=0.06) or AIP (p=0.09). All lipid parameters were related to ESS (ρ=0.18, ρ=0.12, ρ=0.14, ρ=−0.13, ρ=0.18, ρ=0.14, ρ=0.28, all p&lt;0.01, for triglycerides, total cholesterol, LDL-C, HDL-C, AIP, VAI and LAP, respectively).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Receiver Operating Characteristic Analysis on the Association Between Lipid Indices and OSA</title>
        <p>All lipid parameters were significantly associated with OSA; however, we found significant differences in the AUC of ROC curves for the lipid parameters and indices assessed (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The AUC for LAP was significantly larger than of triglycerides (p&lt;0.01), total cholesterol (p&lt;0.01), HDL-C (p&lt;0.01), AIP (p&lt;0.01) and VAI (p&lt;0.01) and tended to be larger than of LDL-C (p=0.056). The AUC of AIP and LDL-C were larger than of VAI (both p=0.04) and of total cholesterol (both p&lt;0.01). No further differences in the AUCs were observed. LAP was significantly more strongly associated with OSA compared to the other parameters, while AIP performed significantly better than VAI (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). The optimal cut-off for LAP to predict OSA was 76.4, that was associated with a 63% sensitivity and a 76% specificity.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of Lipid Parameters’ Receiver Operating Characteristic Curves to Detect OSA</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUC</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard Error</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% Confidence Interval</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triglycerides</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.643</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.609 to 0.676</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total cholesterol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.587</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.552 to 0.621</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL-C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.683</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.649 to 0.715</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL-C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.635</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.601 to 0.668</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AIP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.653</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.619 to 0.686</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.632</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.598 to 0.666</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LAP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.726</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.694 to 0.757</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: AIP, atherogenic index of plasma; AUC, area under the curve; HDL-C, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol; LAP, lipid accumulation product; LDL-C, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol; VAI, visceral adiposity index.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of lipid indices’ receiver operating characteristic curves to detect OSA.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-1333-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Receiver Operating Characteristic Analysis on the Association Between Lipid Indices and Comorbidities</title>
        <p>Investigating the predictive value of lipid parameters for hypertension, ischaemic heart disease and diabetes, not all lipid parameters were significant (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Specifically, for hypertension the AUCs of triglycerides, AIP, VAI, and LAP were significant (all p&lt;0.05), and the AUC of LAP was significantly larger than of all the other parameters (all p&lt;0.01). For ischaemic heart disease, only the AUCs of HDL-C and LAP were significant, without any difference between the two AUCs (p=0.61). For diabetes, the AUCs of triglycerides, HDL-C, AIP, VAI and LAP were significant (p&lt;0.05), and the AUC of LAP was significantly larger than of any other lipid parameter (p&lt;0.01).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Comparison of Lipid Parameters’ Receiver Operating Characteristic Curves to Detect Comorbidities in Patients with OSA</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Hypertension</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Ischaemic Heart Disease</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Diabetes</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUC</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% Confidence Interval</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUC</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% Confidence Interval</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUC</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% Confidence Interval</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triglycerides</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.589</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.550 to 0.627</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.521</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.482 to 0.560</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.594</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.555 to 0.632</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total cholesterol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.508</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.469 to 0.547</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.523</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.484 to 0.562</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.510</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.471 to 0.549</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL-C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.503</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.464 to 0.542</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.528</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.489 to 0.567</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.518</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.479 to 0.557</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL-C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.536</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.497 to 0.574</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.560</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.521 to 0.598</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.584</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.545 to 0.622</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AIP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.582</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.543 to 0.620</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.533</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.494 to 0.572</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.602</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.564 to 0.640</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.582</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.543 to 0.620</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.538</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.499 to 0.577</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.608</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.569 to 0.645</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LAP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.658</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.620 to 0.694</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.576</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.537 to 0.614</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.666</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.628 to 0.702</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: AIP, atherogenic index of plasma; AUC, area under the curve; HDL-C, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol; LAP, lipid accumulation product; LDL-C, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol; VAI, visceral adiposity index.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In this study we have assessed several lipid parameters and composite lipid indices in subjects with or without OSA. We found that the lipid accumulation product (LAP) was most strongly associated with OSA, related to disease severity, and also had the highest predictive value for comorbidities.</p>
      <p>The LAP was first introduced in 2005. The equation was derived from the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey data, where it was found to be a better predictor for cardiovascular disease than the BMI.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> Subsequently, it was validated as a useful clinical marker to predict future cardiovascular events and cardiovascular mortality,<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> and it was also proven to be superior to BMI in predicting diabetes.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> Regarding OSA, Bianchi et al reported higher LAP values in patients at high risk of OSA based on Berlin questionnaire, however in this study the diagnosis was not confirmed by a diagnostic sleep test.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> In patients with diabetes, LAP was associated with OSA, however, interestingly, it was not related to disease severity.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> When investigating only patients with OSA, LAP was related to insulin resistance in normal-weight male subjects.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> In our study, we reported that LAP was associated with hypertension, diabetes, and ischaemic heart disease. We did not investigate male and female, as well as normal and abnormal weight subjects separately, as the prevalence of comorbidities in some subgroups was low and the study was not powered to assess subgroups.</p>
      <p>The visceral adiposity index was introduced in 2010 and it was demonstrated to be significantly associated with cardiovascular disease and metabolic syndrome.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Several studies investigated VAI in OSA. Interestingly, Mazzuca et al reported no relationship between VAI and OSA, but concluded that it might be beneficial in predicting metabolic syndrome in patients with sleep apnoea.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> In line with this, VAI was not related to OSA in a large Chinese study.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> In contrast, Chen et al found that VAI was increased in patients with OSA, and it was related to disease severity and metabolic syndrome.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Investigating patients with OSA, VAI was also shown to be related to insulin resistance in normal-weight female subjects.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> In our study, VAI was higher in patients with OSA compared to controls, but the difference was significant only in moderate-to-severe disease. In addition, when adjusting for age, gender and BMI, the association between VAI and OSA no longer became significant. Differences in OSA severity and patient characteristics between the previous studies could explain some of the contradictory results. We found VAI to be related to hypertension and diabetes, but not to cardiovascular disease. Taking into account the difficulty of calculating VAI compared to LAP, we suggest that this marker may have limited value in clinical practice when assessing patients with OSA.</p>
      <p>A dynamic interaction has been observed between HDL and VLDL particles; therefore, HDL-C and triglyceride levels should not be interpreted in isolation.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> The AIP was introduced as a marker which reflects on the esterification rate of HDL particles.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> It was shown to better predict cardiovascular morbidity<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> and mortality<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> than the single lipid components. Cao et al reported that AIP was higher in OSA and was related to disease severity.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> These findings were in line with the study by Wysocki et al who reported a direct relationship between AIP and AHI.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Shimizu et al found that AIP was related to OSA, but only in normal-weight subjects.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> In a previous study, we have reported that AIP was higher in OSA and was related to disease severity, however HDL-C alone more precisely discriminated patients with OSA from controls. Furthermore, compared to single lipid components, AIP did not show a better value in predicting cardiovascular disease or diabetes.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> In the current study, AIP was increased in OSA, but only in subjects with moderate-to-severe disease and related to hypertension and diabetes, while being inferior to LAP in detecting comorbidities and was less strongly associated with OSA than the LAP. In addition, AIP was not superior to single lipid components when evaluating cardiometabolic disease. Hence, our results suggest no additional value for this marker in clinical practice.</p>
      <p>To date, composite lipid indices were compared to each other only in a few studies. In their report, Zhao et al have investigated LAP and VAI in a large cross-sectional cohort and in 86 patients who underwent bariatric surgery. The authors have concluded that LAP was more strongly associated with OSA than VAI.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Zou et al compared VAI, LAP and the triglyceride glucose index (TyG) in another large Chinese cohort and found that LAP predicted OSA better than the two other composite indices.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> Our results are in line with these findings, however the optimal cut-off value was more than twice higher in our study than in theirs (76.4 vs 33.15). A possible reason for the difference could be ethnicity, as it was previously reported that OSA-related rise in triglycerides is genetically determined.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Investigating only patients with OSA, Wei et al compared LAP, VAI and TyG. The authors have found that the TyG and LAP were most strongly associated with insulin resistance, but only in normal-weight subjects.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Finally, Ramesh et al have evaluated numerous demographical and clinical data to compute a predictive model for OSA. Although LAP, VAI and TyG were all evaluated, only LAP was included in the final model.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></p>
      <p>In our large group of subjects, lipid parameters were significantly different between the OSA and control groups. To compare the strength of associations between OSA and composite lipid indices we used ROC analysis followed by the DeLong test.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> This should not be interpreted as a prediction model analysis, as OSA should still be diagnosed with sleep studies. However, high LAP values should give indications to screen for OSA in routine clinical practice. The DeLong test allowed us to compare the predictive value of lipid indices to detect cardiovascular disease. In this respect, LAP has performed the best.</p>
      <p>Our study has some limitations. First, although medications, diet and regular exercise could affect lipid values, these factors were not evaluated in the current study. Second, we used cardiorespiratory polygraphy over polysomnography as a diagnostic test for OSA. Polygraphy is an accepted diagnostic test, however it tends to underestimate disease severity.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> Third, this is a cross-sectional study, and the clinical value of lipid indices should be evaluated in interventional trials. We believe that our data could serve as a potential basis for the design of these studies.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>We have demonstrated that compared to single lipid components and other composite indices, LAP was most strongly associated with OSA and its comorbidities. However, as its value could be affected by lifestyle factors, the causality between LAP and OSA need to be tested in interventional studies, such as randomized controlled trials. We suggest using this marker in the routine assessment of patients with OSA; however, the exact cut-off value for this marker needs to be further determined in follow-up studies.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>Andras Bikov is supported by NIHR Manchester Biomedical Research Centre.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0006">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Marin</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carrizo</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vicente</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Agusti</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Long-term cardiovascular outcomes in men with obstructive sleep apnoea-hypopnoea with or without treatment with continuous positive airway pressure: an observational study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>365</volume>:<fpage>1046</fpage>–<lpage>1053</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(05)71141-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15781100</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Waight</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Doyle</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rossa</surname>
<given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sullivan</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Liking for high fat foods in patients with obstructive sleep apnoea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Appetite</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>185</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.appet.2014.03.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24699392</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jun</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shin</surname>
<given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yao</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Acute hypoxia induces hypertriglyceridemia by decreasing plasma triglyceride clearance in mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>303</volume>:<fpage>E377</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpendo.00641.2011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22621867</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Morin</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mauger</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amaratunga</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Imbeault</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effect of acute intermittent hypoxia on postprandial triglyceride levels in humans: a randomized crossover trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Transl Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>268</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12967-021-02933-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34158069</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grigoryev</surname>
<given-names>DN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ye</surname>
<given-names>SQ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Chronic intermittent hypoxia upregulates genes of lipid biosynthesis in obese mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Appl Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>99</volume>:<fpage>1643</fpage>–<lpage>1648</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/japplphysiol.00522.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16037401</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Barceló</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Piérola</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de la Peña</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Free fatty acids and the metabolic syndrome in patients with obstructive sleep apnoea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Respir J</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>1418</fpage>–<lpage>1423</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.00050410</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21177837</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Meszaros</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kunos</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tarnoki</surname>
<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tarnoki</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lazar</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bikov</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The role of soluble low-density lipoprotein receptor-related protein-1 in obstructive sleep apnoea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1494</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm10071494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33916750</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Barros</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>García-Río</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea and dyslipidemia: from animal models to clinical evidence</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>42</volume>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsy236</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Peppard</surname>
<given-names>PE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Young</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barnet</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Palta</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hagen</surname>
<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hla</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Increased prevalence of sleep-disordered breathing in adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>177</volume>:<fpage>1006</fpage>–<lpage>1014</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kws342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23589584</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Guan</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yi</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zou</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Distinct severity stages of obstructive sleep apnoea are correlated with unique dyslipidaemia: large-scale observational study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Thorax</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>347</fpage>–<lpage>355</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2015-207403</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26883674</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kjeldsen</surname>
<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thomassen</surname>
<given-names>JQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frikke-Schmidt</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>HDL cholesterol concentrations and risk of atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease - Insights from randomized clinical trials and human genetics</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biochim Biophys Acta Mol Cell Biol Lipids</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>1867</volume>:<fpage>159063</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbalip.2021.159063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34637926</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cao</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fan</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Independent association of severity of obstructive sleep apnea with lipid metabolism of atherogenic index of plasma (AIP) and apoB/apoAI ratio</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>1507</fpage>–<lpage>1513</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-020-02016-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31981042</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wysocki</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Balcerzak</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Prus</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Niemczyk</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lachowska</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep quality and atherogenic risk in sleep apnea patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Gen Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>28</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shimizu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yoshimine</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nagayoshi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Serum triglyceride levels in relation to high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (TG-HDL) ratios as an efficient tool to estimate the risk of sleep apnea syndrome in non-overweight Japanese men</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Environ Health Prev Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>321</fpage>–<lpage>326</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12199-016-0532-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27095251</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bikov</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meszaros</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kunos</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Negru</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frent</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mihaicuta</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Atherogenic index of plasma in obstructive sleep apnoea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>417</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm10030417</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33499142</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vgontzas</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bixler</surname>
<given-names>EO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chrousos</surname>
<given-names>GP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Metabolic disturbances in obesity versus sleep apnoea: the importance of visceral obesity and insulin resistance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>254</volume>:<fpage>32</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2796.2003.01177.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12823641</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kahn</surname>
<given-names>HS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The “lipid accumulation product” performs better than the body mass index for recognizing cardiovascular risk: a population-based comparison</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Cardiovasc Disord</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>26</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2261-5-26</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16150143</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Amato</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Giordano</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Galia</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Visceral adiposity index: a reliable indicator of visceral fat function associated with cardiometabolic risk</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes Care</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>920</fpage>–<lpage>922</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc09-1825</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20067971</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zou</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The use of visceral adiposity variables in the prediction of obstructive sleep apnea: evidence from a large cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>1373</fpage>–<lpage>1382</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-019-01980-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31832983</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bianchi</surname>
<given-names>VE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Herbert</surname>
<given-names>WG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Myers</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ribisl</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>LE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dalman</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Relationship of obstructive sleep apnea and cardiometabolic risk factors in elderly patients with abdominal aortic aneurysm</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>593</fpage>–<lpage>598</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-014-1053-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25204854</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>GP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Qi</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>BY</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Applicability of visceral adiposity index in predicting metabolic syndrome in adults with obstructive sleep apnea: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Pulm Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12890-016-0198-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26931776</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mazzuca</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Battaglia</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marrone</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Gender-specific anthropometric markers of adiposity, metabolic syndrome and visceral adiposity index (VAI) in patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24118617</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Qian</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Abdominal obesity is more strongly correlated with obstructive sleep apnea than general obesity in China: results from two separated observational and longitudinal studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Obes Surg</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>2535</fpage>–<lpage>2547</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11695-019-03870-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31111342</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Body fat indices as effective predictors of insulin resistance in obstructive sleep apnea: evidence from a cross-sectional and longitudinal study: BFI as predictors of IR in OSA</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Obes Surg</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>2219</fpage>–<lpage>2230</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11695-021-05261-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33569729</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim-Dorner</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deuster</surname>
<given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zeno</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Remaley</surname>
<given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poth</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Should triglycerides and the triglycerides to high-density lipoprotein cholesterol ratio be used as surrogates for insulin resistance?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Metabolism</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>299</fpage>–<lpage>304</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.metabol.2009.07.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19796777</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>DeLong</surname>
<given-names>ER</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>DeLong</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clarke-Pearson</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Comparing the areas under two or more correlated receiver operating characteristic curves: a nonparametric approach</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biometrics</italic></source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>837</fpage>–<lpage>845</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2531595</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3203132</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ioachimescu</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brennan</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoar</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoogwerf</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The lipid accumulation product and all-cause mortality in patients at high cardiovascular risk: a PreCIS database study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Obesity</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1836</fpage>–<lpage>1844</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/oby.2009.453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20035284</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yan</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elia</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of lipid accumulation product trajectories with 5-year incidence of type 2 diabetes in Chinese adults: a cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nutr Metab</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>72</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12986-019-0399-7</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dong</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Lipid accumulation product (LAP) was independently associated with obstructive sleep apnea in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Endocr Disord</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>179</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12902-020-00661-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33298050</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dobiásová</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frohlich</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The plasma parameter log (TG/HDL-C) as an atherogenic index: correlation with lipoprotein particle size and esterification rate in apoB-lipoprotein-depleted plasma (FER(HDL))</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Biochem</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>583</fpage>–<lpage>588</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0009-9120(01)00263-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11738396</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cai</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xue</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The atherogenic index of plasma is a strong and independent predictor for coronary artery disease in the Chinese Han population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Medicine</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>e8058</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000008058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28906400</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Edwards</surname>
<given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blaha</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Loprinzi</surname>
<given-names>PD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Atherogenic index of plasma and triglyceride/high-density lipoprotein cholesterol ratio predict mortality risk better than individual cholesterol risk factors, among an older adult population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mayo Clin Proc</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>680</fpage>–<lpage>681</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mayocp.2016.12.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28385200</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Meszaros</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tarnoki</surname>
<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tarnoki</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea and hypertriglyceridaemia share common genetic background: results of a twin study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>e12979</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12979</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31908118</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ramesh</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Keeran</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sagahyroon</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aloul</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Towards validating the effectiveness of obstructive sleep apnea classification from electronic health records using machine learning</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Healthcare</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1450</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/healthcare9111450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34828496</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kapur</surname>
<given-names>VK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Auckley</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chowdhuri</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Clinical practice guideline for diagnostic testing for adult obstructive sleep apnea: an American Academy of sleep medicine clinical practice guideline</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>479</fpage>–<lpage>504</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.6506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28162150</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
