<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36263372</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">9575586</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">378970</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S378970</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Peripheral Iron Metabolism is Associated with Leg Movements on Polysomnography but Not with the Severity of Restless Legs Syndrome or Its Impact on Patients</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Wang et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Wang et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Tiantian</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>Jiahui</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>Qinglin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
            <given-names>Rui</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pan</surname>
            <given-names>Liuqing</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>Danyan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pan</surname>
            <given-names>Yu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Lehui</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0006" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lou</surname>
            <given-names>Guodong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2315-8244</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>Xiaoye</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0007" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3840-4778</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Jin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3774-9926</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Lisan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0002" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Pharmacy, Xiasha Campus, Sir Run Run Shaw Hospital, School of Medicine, Zhejiang University</institution>, <addr-line>Hangzhou</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Neurology/Center for Sleep Medicine, Sir Run Run Shaw Hospital, School of Medicine, Zhejiang University</institution>, <addr-line>Hangzhou</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Institute of Pharmacology and Toxicology, College of Pharmaceutical Science, Zhejiang University</institution>, <addr-line>Hangzhou</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Neurology, Sir Run Run Shaw Hospital, School of Medicine, Zhejiang University</institution>, <addr-line>Hangzhou</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label><institution>Department of Pharmacy, Sir Run Run Shaw Hospital, School of Medicine, Zhejiang University</institution>, <addr-line>Hangzhou</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0006"><label>6</label><institution>Department of Internal Medicine, Hangzhou Wuyunshan Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Hangzhou</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0007"><label>7</label><institution>Department of Nursing, Sir Run Run Shaw Hospital, School of Medicine, Zhejiang University</institution>, <addr-line>Hangzhou</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Jin Wang, <institution>Department of Neurology, Sir Run Run Shaw Hospital, School of Medicine, Zhejiang University</institution>, <addr-line>3 Qingchundong Road</addr-line>, <addr-line>Hangzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Zhejiang Province</addr-line>, <addr-line>310016</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, <phone>Tel +86-135-1681-8933</phone>, Email wangjinjoy@zju.edu.cn</corresp>
        <corresp id="an0002">Lisan Zhang, <institution>Department of Neurology/Center for Sleep Medicine, Sir Run Run Shaw Hospital, School of Medicine, Zhejiang University</institution>, <addr-line>3 Qingchundong Road</addr-line>, <addr-line>Hangzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Zhejiang Province</addr-line>, <addr-line>310016</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, <phone>Tel +86-138-0575-2614</phone>, Email zls09@zju.edu.cn</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>13</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <fpage>1829</fpage>
      <lpage>1842</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>02</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2022 Wang et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Wang et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p>This study investigated the associations of peripheral iron status with different manifestations of restless legs syndrome (RLS), including leg movements (LMs) on polysomnography (PSG), disease severity, and impact on patients.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Patients and Methods</title>
          <p>In this cross-sectional study, 108 patients with RLS were enrolled at Sir Run Run Shaw Hospital’s Center for Sleep Medicine. Demographic information, disease characteristics, RLS severity, and impact on patients were assessed through a semi-structured questionnaire. Peripheral iron indicators [serum ferritin, iron, and transferrin concentrations; unsaturated iron-binding capacity (UIBC) and total iron-binding capacity (TIBC); transferrin saturation (TSAT)] were measured following PSG to assess sleep stages, respiratory events, microarousals and LM parameters. Data from patients with and without ferritin concentration &lt; 50 µg/L were compared in crude analyses, and Spearman correlations of other iron indicators with RLS data were examined. An ordinal logistic regression model was used to adjust for age, sex, body mass index, years of education, age at the time of RLS onset, prior treatment (yes/no), C-reactive protein (CRP)/hemoglobin level, total sleep time and apnea-hypopnea index.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>Multivariate analysis showed that periodic LMs during sleep (PLMS) and other LM parameters were significantly associated with a ferritin concentration &lt; 50 µg/L, UIBC, TIBC, and serum transferrin concentration, but not serum iron or TSAT. By contrast, the severity and impact of RLS were not associated with a ferritin concentration &lt; 50 µg/L or other peripheral iron indicators in the multivariate model.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>In this study, peripheral iron status was associated mainly with motor components (LMs on PSG) rather than sensory components (severity and impact of RLS) after adequately controlling for potential confounders, such as CRP and hemoglobin levels. Commonly used peripheral iron metabolism indicators may therefore not be ideal biomarkers of RLS severity or impact on patients.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>restless legs syndrome</kwd>
        <kwd>peripheral iron metabolism</kwd>
        <kwd>polysomnography</kwd>
        <kwd>leg movements</kwd>
        <kwd>severity</kwd>
        <kwd>impact</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="0"/>
        <table-count count="10"/>
        <ref-count count="71"/>
        <page-count count="14"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s0001">
      <title>Statement of Significance</title>
      <p>Although iron deficiency contributes to RLS, the relationship between peripheral iron metabolism and RLS is controversial. The present study investigated the associations of peripheral iron status with different manifestations of RLS and observed the following. In patients with RLS, commonly used peripheral iron metabolism indicators were mainly related to motor rather than sensory components of RLS, suggesting that abnormal peripheral iron metabolism is not a risk factor for RLS severity or a negative impact on patients, and that the two clinical presentations of RLS are likely independent of each other. Leg movement parameters were associated with a ferritin concentration &lt; 50 µg/L, UIBC, TIBC and the serum transferrin concentration, but not with serum iron or TSAT. Complex iron metabolism, involving storage and transport processes, may underlie the motor components of RLS. (3) As well as PLMS, other LMs were related to peripheral iron metabolism. PLMS/LMs during wakefulness and arousal were not associated with peripheral iron measures. Overall, our study demonstrates that peripheral iron metabolism is involved in several complex RLS mechanisms. Further studies are needed to determine how peripheral iron status participates in the pathophysiology of RLS.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0002">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Restless legs syndrome (RLS) is a common sensorimotor disorder characterized by a prominent circadian pattern and a rest-induced, movement-responsive, mostly nocturnal urge to move the legs.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Brain iron deficiency is the key initial pathobiological factor in RLS; it induces the hypoadenosinergic, hyperglutamatergic, and hyperdopaminergic states involved in the sensorimotor signs and arousal components of RLS.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> The clinical expression of RLS is variable and may depend on genetic, environmental, or medical factors.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> However, in a systematic review, only iron deficiency and kidney disease increased the prevalence of RLS.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Based on clinical research,<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> iron deficiency is currently recognized as an independent risk factor for RLS, and iron supplementation has effectively treated some forms of RLS.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6–9</xref> Additionally, based on imaging and postmortem findings<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> as well as genome-wide association studies<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10−12</xref>, the pathophysiology of RLS is linked to iron homeostasis.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></p>
      <p>As the current RLS treatment guidelines<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14–16</xref> recommend iron treatment for patients with low peripheral iron levels, the systemic iron parameters of patients with RLS should be measured routinely. To examine the iron status of patients with RLS, initial and periodic measurement of the serum iron, transferrin, and ferritin concentrations; total iron-binding capacity (TIBC); and transferrin saturation (TSAT) is recommended.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> Ferritin is a circulating iron storage protein and acute-phase reactant; thus, the C-reactive protein (CRP) level or erythrocyte sedimentation rate should be considered when interpreting the ferritin concentration.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></p>
      <p>Although iron deficiency has been considered an independent risk factor for RLS, the association is controversial. Leung et al<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> published a review of the association of iron deficiency with RLS based on 74 studies and identified gaps in the research. Although most of the studies found a positive association, this was not seen in some cross-sectional (10/25) and cohort studies (4/5).<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Moreover, the CRP level was measured together with the ferritin concentration in only three studies<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19–21</xref> and iron deficiency was not associated with RLS in any of them. In addition to potential cofounders such as CRP, these contradictory results regarding the association of iron deficiency with RLS may be due to the use of univariate analysis, small sample sizes,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> and non-linear relationships.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> To date, the effects of the serum iron and transferrin concentrations, TIBC, and TSAT on RLS have received much less attention. A few studies demonstrated that iron ions, transferrin, soluble transferrin receptor concentrations, and TSAT were not significantly different between patients with RLS and Healthy controls.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24–26</xref> Hence, the generalizability of the relationship between peripheral iron metabolism and RLS is limited.</p>
      <p>Periodic leg movements during sleep (PLMS) are defined as movements in which at least four LMs take place, with intervals of 5–90 s between them.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> However, LMs during sleep also include other movements not meeting this requirement or separated by interval &gt; 90s. PLMS may therefore differ from other types of LM in terms of its specific characteristics and duration, as well as other features such as high sensitivity to dopamine agonists, reduced frequency at night, and associations with diseases other than RLS.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> As LMs have yet been thoroughly assessed, the associations of PLMS and LMs with peripheral iron status remain to be determined.</p>
      <p>The aim of this study was to investigate the associations of various peripheral iron parameters with LMs on polysomnography (PSG), RLS severity, and the impact on patients, after adjusting for confounding variables. As well as the serum ferritin concentration (the only indicator of iron-status measured in most studies), this study analyzed several other indicators, including serum iron and transferrin concentrations, TIBC, and TSAT. Other categories of LM in addition to PLMS were also examined. Moreover, patient demographics, symptom characteristics, RLS severity, on the impact on patients, and polysomnographic data were assessed.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Patients</title>
        <p>We continuously recruited patients with RLS to this study conducted at the Center for Sleep Medicine, Sir Run Run Shaw Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, from March 2019 to December 2020. According to the International RLS Study Group,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> five essential diagnostic criteria for RLS are uncomfortable and unpleasant sensations in the limbs usually causing an urge to move (mainly in the legs), initiation or worsening of these symptoms when at rest or inactive, partial or complete remission of the symptoms while activity continues, the occurrence or increased severity of symptoms at night, and the absence of another condition explaining the symptoms.</p>
        <p>Written informed consent was obtained from all individuals included in the study. This study was approved by the Institutional Review Board of Sir Run Shaw Hospital (permit number: 20190226–9), and all procedures involving human subjects adhered to the Helsinki Declaration as revised in 1989. The study was registered in Chinese Clinical Trial Registry (clinical trial registration number: ChiCTR2000040784).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Clinical Assessments</title>
        <p>A neurologist with expertise in sleep medicine administered a semi-structured questionnaire to the study participants to collect information on their demographic characteristics, symptom characteristics (age at time of RLS onset, duration of RLS, family history of RLS), and medical histories/co-morbidities. Current RLS medication use was recorded, and levodopa equivalent doses were calculated for patients receiving dopaminergic therapy.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> Augmentation was assessed using the criteria of the Max Planck Institute.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></p>
        <p>Although not life-threatening, patients with RLS often have compromised health and poor quality of life. Thus, comprehensive clinical assessment is essential to fully understand the impacts of RLS on patients. In this study patients were assessed in terms of sleep quality, daytime sleepiness, fatigue, quality of life, emotional state (depression/anxiety), and cognitive function using the following validated scales: the International Restless Legs Syndrome Study Group Severity Scale (IRLS),<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI),<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS),<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> Chalder Fatigue Scale (CFS),<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> Medical Outcomes Study 36-item short-form health survey (SF-36),<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> Beck Depression Inventory-13 (BDI-13),<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> Beck Anxiety Inventory (BAI),<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA),<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> and Mini-Mental Status Examination (MMSE).<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Comorbidities</title>
        <p>Given the complex etiology of RLS, which likely involves environmental and genetic interactions, it can occur in isolation or with comorbidities.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> Only iron deficiency anemia and kidney disease have been identified as factors increasing the prevalence of RLS, although it may be associated with other comorbidities such as cardiovascular disease, arterial hypertension, diabetes, migraine and Parkinson disease.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Therefore, patients were questioned about these diseases when their demographic information was collected (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) (Pregnancy, kidney disease, migraine, and Parkinson’s disease were not reported by any of the patients).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of Demographic and Disease Characteristics Between RLS Patients with and without a Ferritin Concentration &lt; 50 µg/L</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin &lt; 50 µg/L (n=32)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin ≥ 50 µg/L (n=76)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">χ</italic><sup>2</sup><italic toggle="yes">/t/z</italic> value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Demographic characteristics</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29(90.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44(57.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years), mean ± SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.56±12.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.82±14.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.077</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.003</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male, mean ± SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.33±4.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.56±14.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.910</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.369</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female, mean ± SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.14±12.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.18±14.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.916</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.6(20.1–22.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.6(21.2–26.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.870</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.004</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education (years), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12(8–15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8(5–12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.474</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.013</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geographical distribution, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> East China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27(84.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68(89.5)</td><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">1.920</td><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">0.667</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Northeast China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(6.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(2.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> North China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(1.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Central China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3(9.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5(6.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Disease characteristics</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age of RLS onset (years), mean ± SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.13±15.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.66±17.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.827</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.071</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Early onset of RLS, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23(71.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48(63.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.760</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.506</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of RLS (years), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6(2–15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10(3.25–17.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.189</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.235</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family history of RLS, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10(31.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28(36.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.309</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.578</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current augmentation, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(3.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12(15.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.320</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.128</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Therapy, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22(68.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44(57.9)</td><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">1.601</td><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">0.730</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> α2δ-ligands</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Combination medication</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(1.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Others</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(2.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Dopaminergic agents</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10(31.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29(38.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Levodopa-equivalent dose (mg)<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0(21.875, 50.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0(12.5, 50.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.234</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.815</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Comorbidities, n (%)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiovascular disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(3.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5(6.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.667</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arterial hypertension</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3(9.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18(23.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.944</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.112</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(3.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9(11.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.131</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.288</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insomnia disorders</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3(9.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3(3.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.358</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep-related breathing disorders (AHI ≥ 5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6(18.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30(39.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.352</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.045</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>a</sup>The levodopa equivalent dose for commonly used agents was calculated according to protocol reported by Tomlinson et al (2010). Significant results (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) are shown in boldface.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: RLS, restless legs syndrome; SD, standard deviation; BMI, body mass index; IQR, interquartile range.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <p>Because the sleep scales used in this study were not specific to RLS, participants with other non-RLS sleep disorders according to third edition of the International Classification of Sleep Disorder<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> were included in the analysis (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) (No patient had been diagnosed with central disorders of hypersomnolence, circadian rhythm sleep-wake disorders, sleep-related movement disorders (except RLS), parasomnias, or other sleep disorders).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Polysomnography Recordings</title>
        <p>PSG was performed using a Trackit 32-channel PSG monitor (Nihon Kohden Corporation, Tokyo, Japan), which has six electroencephalogram leads, two electro-oculograms, one chin electromyogram, and an electrocardiogram. Nasal cannula/pressure transducer, mouth thermistor, chest and abdominal bands, and pulse oximeter data were obtained to monitor respiration. Similarly, PLMS/LMs were recorded by surface electromyogram electrodes placed on the anterior tibialis muscles.</p>
        <p>Measurements of sleep stage, respiratory events, microarousals, and LM parameters (such as LM events and PLMS) were based on the criteria of the American Academy of Sleep Medicine (version 2.4).<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> All of the above parameters were analyzed by at least one physician specializing in sleep medicine.</p>
        <p>The PLMS arousal index is calculated as flows: PLMS with arousals × 60 / total sleep time (TST, in min). The PLMS sequence index is calculated as the number of PLM series × 60 / TST (in min). PLMS sequence duration is calculated as the total duration of PLMS (in min) × 60 / TST (in min). The LM index with microarousal is calculated as LM with microarousals × 60 / TST (in min). The LM index without arousal is calculated as the total LM with microarousal × 60 / TST (in min).</p>
        <p>No patients took RLS medications on the night of the PSG examination.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2005">
        <title>Laboratory Measurements</title>
        <p>Antecubital venous blood samples were obtained from patients between 6:00 and 8:00 a.m. after an overnight fast following standardized procedures. Hemoglobin and CRP levels were measured. Peripheral iron metabolism was evaluated by measuring the serum ferritin, iron, and transferrin concentrations, unsaturated iron-binding capacity (UIBC), TIBC, and TSAT.</p>
        <p>Serum ferritin concentrations were measured by an electrochemiluminescence assay (Roche Diagnostics, Mannheim, Germany). Serum iron concentrations and TSAT were determined using an iron/UIBC kit (Roche Diagnostics). The concentration of transferrin was determined by immuno-turbidimetry using a transferrin assay kit (332028; Shanghai Jiemen Bio-Technology Co. Ltd., Shanghai, China).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2006">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>Data on participants’ demographics, disease characteristics, RLS severity and impact on patients, and polysomnographic parameters are presented as means ± standard deviations for normally distributed variables, medians (interquartile ranges) for non-normally distributed variables, and frequencies (percentages) for categorical variables. These variables were analyzed using independent <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-tests, non-parametric tests, and chi-squared tests, respectively.</p>
        <p>Associations of participants’ peripheral iron status with RLS severity and impact on patients, as well as LM parameters, were examined. A crude comparative analysis was employed to assess ferritin deficiency (concentration &lt; 50 µg/L), and Spearman correlation analysis was applied to examine the other iron-status indicators. Variables associated with LM parameters (at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.3) and disease severity/impact (at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.15) were included in an ordinal logistic regression model adjusted for age, sex, body mass index (BMI), years of education, age at RLS onset, prior treatment (yes/no), CRP/hemoglobin level, TST and the apnea-hypopnea index (AHI) to obtain adjusted odds ratios (ORs) for indicators of peripheral iron status; non-normally distributed continuous independent variables were grouped into quartiles. When the parallel regression assumption was rejected, we used binary logistic regression to analyze the data. All tests were two-sided and the significance level was set to <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05. Statistical analyses were performed using IBM SPSS Statistics 25.0 (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, USA).</p>
        <p>The original LM data for six patients were lost. They were replaced using multiple imputations, and the averages of four imputation values were included in the analysis.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0004-s2001">
        <title>Characteristics of Patients with RLS</title>
        <p>We analyzed data from 108 of the 119 participants enrolled in this study. Eleven participants were excluded because their symptoms mimicked RLS (n = 6) or they did not have RLS, nor any mimicking symptoms (n = 5). In 32 of the 108 patients the ferritin concentration was &lt; 50 µg/L and in 76 patients it was ≥ 50 µg/L. Among the 107 participants examined for associations of peripheral iron status with LM parameters, one patient refused PSG. The average age of the 108 patients with RLS was 51.1 ± 14.8 years; 73 (67.6%) patients were female, the average age at the time of RLS symptom onset was 39.7 ± 17.2 years and RLS was untreated in 66 (61.1%) patients.</p>
        <p>The demographic and disease characteristics of patients with and without ferritin deficiency are shown in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The levodopa-equivalent dose for commonly used agents was calculated according to a previously reported protocol.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Patients with ferritin deficiency were more likely to be female (<italic toggle="yes">χ</italic><sup>2</sup> = 11.013, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.001), were younger (<italic toggle="yes">t</italic> = –3.077, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.003), and had more years of education (<italic toggle="yes">z</italic> = –2.474, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.013) and a lower BMI (<italic toggle="yes">z</italic> = –2.870, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.004) compared with those without ferritin deficiency.</p>
        <p>Patients with ferritin deficiency had longer TSTs (<italic toggle="yes">z</italic> = −2.218, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.027), were more likely to have an AHI &lt; 5 (<italic toggle="yes">χ</italic><sup>2</sup> = 4.537, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.033), and had lower 3% oxygen desaturation indices than patients without ferritin deficiency (<italic toggle="yes">z</italic> = −2.429, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.015; <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Polysomnography in RLS Patients with and without a Ferritin Concentration &lt; 50 µg/L</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin &lt; 50 µg/L (n=32)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin ≥ 50 µg/L (n=75)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">χ</italic><sup>2</sup><italic toggle="yes">/t/z</italic> value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total sleep time (minutes), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">402.5(347.1–452.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">337.5(263.5–419.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.218</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.027</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep efficiency (%), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.7(65.0–82.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.4(53.1–79.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.653</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.098</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wake time after sleep onset (minutes), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120(76.9–173.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">133.0(92.0–211.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.735</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.462</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep latency (minutes), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.8(7.3–36.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11(5–29)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.898</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.369</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM sleep latency (minutes)<sup>a</sup>, mean ± SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">149.8±97.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">166.4±110.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.733</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.465</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N1 (%), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7(4.1–11.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5(4.6–11.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.463</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.644</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N2 (%), mean ± SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.0±9.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.1±12.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.043</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.965</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N3 (%)<sup>b</sup>, mean ± SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.4±11.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.6±11.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.071</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.944</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM (%)<sup>a</sup>, mean ± SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.1±6.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.6±7.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.970</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.334</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Microarousal index (/h), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2(6.6–15.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4(7.0–18.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.079</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.281</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM-related arousal index (/h), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3(0.7–6.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2(1.4–6.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.272</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.785</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI, median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8(1.5–3.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7(1.5–8.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.351</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.177</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI&lt;5, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26(81.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45(60.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.537</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.033</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower 3% oxygen desaturation index (/h), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3(0.5–4.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2(1.2–7.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.429</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.015</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLMS index (/h), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.20(4.15–26.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.60(2.30–25.70)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.199</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.230</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLMS arousal index (/h), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85(0.00–2.88)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80(0.00–2.79)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.486</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.627</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLMS sequences index (/h), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23(0.56–1.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83(0.29–1.65)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.203</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.229</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of PLMS sequences (minutes/h), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.71(1.58–11.63)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.54(0.73–9.24)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.213</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.225</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total LM index (/h), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.54(20.63–59.16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.57(16.67–65.27)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.429</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.668</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index in N1 (/h), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.70(9.56–46.51)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.82(4.80–50.20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.650</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.515</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index in N2 (/h), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.22(12.15–43.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.55(8.67–38.39)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.735</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.083</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index in N3 (/h)<sup>b</sup>, median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.37(3.51–42.74)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.57(1.28–37.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.602</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.109</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index in REM (/h)<sup>a</sup>, median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.07(4.31–27.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.80(3.47–25.78)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.355</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.722</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index with awakening (/h), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.21(5.66–20.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.23(5.54–37.34)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.034</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.301</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index with microarousal (/h), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.86(0.24–6.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.28(1.15–6.26)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.453</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.651</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index without arousal (h), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.94(17.59–56.15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.86(14.19–56.76)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.527</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.598</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>a</sup>Two patients had no REM stage and relevant data. <sup>b</sup>Five patients had no N stage and relevant data. Significant results (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) are shown in boldface.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: RLS, restless legs syndrome; IQR, interquartile range; SD, standard deviation; LM, limb movement; AHI, apnea-hypopnea index; PLMS, periodic leg movements during sleep.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2002">
        <title>Association of Peripheral Iron Measures with PSG Leg Movement Parameters</title>
        <p>In the Multivariate logistic regression analyses, ferritin deficiency was associated with the PLMS index [odds ratio (OR) = 3.074; 95% confidence interval (CI), 1.266–7.456; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.013], PLMS sequences index (OR = 3.655; 95% CI, 1.484–9.007; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.005), duration of PLMS sequences (OR = 3.238; 95% CI, 1.334–7.870; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.009), LM index during N2 sleep (OR = 3.579; 95% CI, 1.458–8.785; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.005), and LM index during N3 sleep (OR = 3.099; 95% CI, 1.256–7.645; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.014) (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Associations of Leg Movement Parameters on Polysomnography with a Ferritin Concentration &lt; 50 µg/L in RLS Patients According to Ordinal Logistic Regression Models</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Dependent Variables<sup>a</sup></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Independent Variables</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 1<sup>b</sup></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 2<sup>c</sup></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">PLMS index (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin ≥ 50 µg/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin &lt; 50 µg/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.455(0.691, 3.062)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.324</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.074(1.266, 7.456)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.013</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">PLMS sequences index (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin ≥ 50 µg/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin &lt; 50 µg/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.594(0.757, 3.360)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.220</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.655(1.484, 9.007)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Duration of PLMS sequences<sup>d</sup> (minutes/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin ≥ 50 µg/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin &lt; 50 µg/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.502(0.713, 3.161)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.284</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.238(1.334, 7.870)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.009</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">LM index in N2 (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin ≥ 50 µg/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin &lt; 50 µg/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.839(0.869, 3.892)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.111</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.579(1.458, 8.785)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">LM index in N3<sup>d</sup> (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin ≥ 50 µg/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin &lt; 50 µg/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.844(0.860, 3.959)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.116</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.099(1.256, 7.645)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.014</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">LM index with awakening (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin ≥ 50 µg/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin &lt; 50 µg/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.736(0.350, 1.547)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.418</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.826(0.745, 4.477)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.188</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>a</sup>Dependent variables were included when the <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value was &lt; 0.3 in a comparative analysis. <sup>b</sup>Model 1: unadjusted associations. <sup>c</sup>Model 2: adjusted for age, sex, body mass index, years of education, age at the time of RLS onset, prior treatment (yes/no), C-reactive protein level, total sleep time, and the apnea-hypopnea index. <sup>d</sup>The parallel regression assumption in the ordinal regression was not met and binary logistic regression was thus used. Significant results (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) are shown in boldface.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0006"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: RLS, restless legs syndrome; PLMS, periodic leg movements during sleep; LM, leg movements.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <p>LMs during N2 sleep were related to UIBC (r = 0.221, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.022) and TIBC (r = 0.229, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.018); no other correlations were significant in Spearman’s correlation analyses(data not shown).</p>
        <p>After adjustment for potential confounders, the UIBC was related significantly to the PLMS sequences index (OR = 1.046; 95% CI, 1.003–1.091; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.035), total LM index (OR = 1.052; 95% CI, 1.008–1.099; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.021), and LM index without arousal (OR = 1.050; 95% CI, 1.005–1.096; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.028; <xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). The TIBC was related significantly to the PLMS index (OR = 1.062; 95% CI, 1.009–1.117; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.022), PLMS sequences index (OR = 1.055; 95% CI, 1.002–1.111; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.041), duration of PLMS sequences (OR = 1.070; 95% CI, 1.017–1.127; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.010), LM index during N2 sleep (OR = 1.070; 95% CI, 1.015–1.127; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.011) and LM index during REM sleep (OR = 1.084; 95% CI, 1.027–1.143; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.003) (<xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). Serum transferrin concentration was associated with the duration of PLMS sequences (OR = 2.980; 95% CI, 1.025–8.654; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.045), the LM index during N2 sleep (OR = 3.607; 95% CI, 1.206–10.794; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.022), and the LM index during REM sleep (OR = 4.450; 95% CI, 1.465–13.504; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.008) (<xref rid="t0006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). Neither the serum iron concentration (<xref rid="t0007" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>) nor the TSAT (<xref rid="t0008" ref-type="table">Table 8</xref>) was associated with any of the PSG LM parameters.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Associations of Unsaturated Iron Binding Capacity with Leg Movement Parameters on Polysomnography in RLS Patients According to Ordinal Logistic Regression Models</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Dependent Variables<sup>a</sup></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 1<sup>b</sup></th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 2<sup>c</sup></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLMS index (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.022(0.993, 1.052)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.137</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.030(0.989, 1.074)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.148</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLMS sequences index (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.033(1.002, 1.064)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.034</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.046(1.003, 1.091)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.035</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of PLMS sequences (minutes/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.024(0.995, 1.054)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.109</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.037(0.995, 1.080)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.085</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total LM index (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.023(0.994, 1.053)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.052(1.008, 1.099)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.021</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index in N1<sup>d</sup> (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.018(0.989, 1.048)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.220</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.025(0.984, 1.068)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.234</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index in N2 (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.034(1.003, 1.065)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.030</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.037(0.995, 1.081)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.087</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index in N3 (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.024(0.993, 1.057)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.023(0.979, 1.069)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.307</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index with awakening (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.012(0.983, 1.042)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.425</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.040(0.996, 1.084)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.076</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index without arousal (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.020(0.991, 1.050)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.181</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.050(1.005, 1.096)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.028</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0007"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>a</sup>Variables were included when the <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value was &lt; 0.3 in Spearman correlation analysis. <sup>b</sup>Model 1: unadjusted associations. <sup>c</sup>Model 2: adjusted for age, sex, body mass index, years of education, age at the time of RLS onset, prior treatment (yes/no), hemoglobin level, total sleep time, and the apnea-hypopnea index. <sup>d</sup>The parallel regression assumption in the ordinal regression was not met and binary logistic regression was thus used. Significant results (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) are shown in boldface.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0008"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: RLS, restless legs syndrome; LM, limb movement; PLMS, periodic leg movements during sleep.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Associations of Total Iron-Binding Capacity with Leg Movement Parameters on Polysomnography in RLS Patients According to Ordinal Logistic Regression Models</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Dependent Variables<sup>a</sup></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 1<sup>b</sup></th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 2<sup>c</sup></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLMS index (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.042(0.998, 1.088)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.060</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.062(1.009, 1.117)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.022</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLMS sequences index (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.039(0.995, 1.083)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.080</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.055(1.002, 1.111)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.041</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of PLMS sequences (minutes/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.048(1.004, 1.094)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.030</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.070(1.017, 1.127)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.010</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index in N2 (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.049(1.005, 1.094)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.030</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.070(1.015, 1.127)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.011</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index in N3<sup>d</sup> (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.034(0.990, 1.079)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.134</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.047(0.995, 1.102)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.078</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index in REM<sup>d</sup> (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.047(1.002, 1.093)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.040</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.084(1.027, 1.143)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.003</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0009"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>a</sup>Variables were included when the <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value was &lt; 0.3 in Spearman correlation analysis. <sup>b</sup>Model 1: unadjusted associations. <sup>c</sup>Model 2: adjusted for age, sex, body mass index, years of education, age at the time of RLS onset, prior treatment (yes/no), hemoglobin level, total sleep time, and the apnea-hypopnea index. <sup>d</sup>The parallel regression assumption in the ordinal regression was not met and binary logistic regression was thus used. Significant results (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) are shown in boldface.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0010"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: RLS, restless legs syndrome; LM, limb movement; PLMS, periodic leg movements during sleep.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0006"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Associations of Serum Transferrin with Leg Movement Parameters on Polysomnography in RLS Patients According to Ordinal Logistic Regression Models</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Dependent Variables<sup>a</sup></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 1<sup>b</sup></th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 2<sup>c</sup></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of PLMS sequences (minutes/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.038(0.923, 4.504)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.078</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.980(1.025, 8.654)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.045</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index in N2 (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.340(1.053, 5.202)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.037</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.607(1.206, 10.794)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.022</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index in REM (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.632(0.733, 3.629)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.230</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.450(1.465, 13.504)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.008</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0011"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>a</sup>Variables were included when the <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value was &lt; 0.3 in a Spearman correlation analysis. <sup>b</sup>Model 1: unadjusted associations. <sup>c</sup>Model 2: adjusted for age, sex, body mass index, years of education, age at the time of RLS onset, prior treatment (yes/no), hemoglobin level, total sleep time, and the apnea-hypopnea index. Significant results (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) are shown in boldface.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0012"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: RLS, restless legs syndrome; LM, limb movement; PLMS, periodic leg movements during sleep.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0007"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Associations of Serum Iron Level with Leg Movement Parameters on Polysomnography in RLS Patients According to Ordinal Logistic Regression Models</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Dependent Variables<sup>a</sup></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 1<sup>b</sup></th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 2<sup>c</sup></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index in N3 (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.983(0.935, 1.033)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.488</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.033(0.966, 1.104)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.345</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index in REM (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.031(0.985, 1.079)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.186</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.035(0.975, 1.099)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.255</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index with awakening (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.972(0.929, 1.017)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.222</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.962(0.905, 1.023)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.217</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index without arousal (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.981(0.938.1.026)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.414</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.008(0.949, 1.071)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.785</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0013"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>a</sup>Variables were included when the <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value was &lt; 0.3 in Spearman correlation analysis. <sup>b</sup>Model 1: unadjusted associations. <sup>c</sup>Model 2: adjusted for age, sex, body mass index, years of education, age at the time of RLS onset, prior treatment (yes/no), hemoglobin level, total sleep time, and the apnea-hypopnea index.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0014"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: RLS, restless legs syndrome; LM, limb movement.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0008"><label>Table 8</label><caption><p>Associations of Transferrin Saturation with Leg Movement Parameters on Polysomnography Models in RLS Patients According to Ordinal Logistic Regression Models</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Dependent variables<sup>a</sup></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 1<sup>b</sup></th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 2<sup>c</sup></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLMS index (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.989(0.968, 1.011)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.322</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.992(0.964, 1.022)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.614</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLMS sequences index (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.979(0.958, 1.001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.060</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.973(0.945, 1.004)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.087</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of PLMS sequences (minutes/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.990(0.969, 1.012)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.385</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.991(0.962, 1.021)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.551</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total LM index (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.984(0.963, 1.005)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.141</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.979(0.949, 1.009)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.176</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index in N1<sup>d</sup> (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.986(0.965, 1.008)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.211</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.991(0.962, 1.020)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.540</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index in N2 (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.983(0.962, 1.004)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.119</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.992(0.964, 1.022)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.617</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index in N3 (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.987(0.964, 1.011)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.283</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.001(0.968, 1.035)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.976</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index with awakening (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.987(0.966, 1.009)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.236</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.971(0.942, 1.003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.073</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM index without arousal (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.985(0.965, 1.007)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.186</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.982(0.952, 1.013)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.246</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0015"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>a</sup>Variables were included when the <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value was &lt; 0.3 in Spearman correlation analysis. <sup>b</sup>Model 1: unadjusted associations. <sup>c</sup>Model 2: adjusted for age, sex, body mass index, years of education, age at the time of RLS onset, prior treatment (yes/no), hemoglobin level, total sleep time, and the apnea-hypopnea index. <sup>d</sup>The parallel regression assumption in the ordinal regression was not met and binary logistic regression was used.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0016"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: RLS, restless legs syndrome; LM, limb movement; PLMS, periodic leg movements during sleep.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2003">
        <title>Peripheral Iron Measures are Not Associated with RLS Severity or Impact</title>
        <p>Comparison of the severity/impact of RLS between patients with and without ferritin deficiency revealed no significant difference in the IRLS, PSQI, ESS, CFS, SF-36, BDI-13, BAI, MoCA, or MMSE score (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05), but there was a significant difference in the MoCA recall score (<italic toggle="yes">z</italic> = –2.009, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.045; <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=378970.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link></underline>). In the Spearman correlation analysis, other indicators of peripheral iron status were not related to the severity/impact of RLS, except the serum iron concentration, which was associated with SF-36 physical function (r = 0.198, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.040; data not shown).</p>
        <p>The severity and impact of RLS were not significantly associated with ferritin deficiency (<xref rid="t0009" ref-type="table">Table 9</xref>). The relationships of other iron-status indicators and RLS severity and impact were also non-significant after adjustment for confounders (<xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 10</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0009"><label>Table 9</label><caption><p>Associations of Severity and Impact of RLS with a Ferritin Concentration &lt; 50 µg/L According to Ordinal Logistic Regression Models</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Dependent Variables<sup>a</sup></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Independent Variables</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 1<sup>b</sup></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 2<sup>c</sup></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Total score in IRLS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin ≥ 50 µg/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin &lt; 50 µg/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.488(0.230, 1.036)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.062</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.867(0.364, 2.063)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.747</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Severity score in IRLS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin ≥ 50 µg/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin &lt; 50 µg/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.457(0.215, 0.972)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.042</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.637(0.268, 1.516)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.308</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Role-physical in SF-36<sup>d</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin ≥ 50 µg/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin &lt; 50 µg/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.670(0.708, 3.944)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.242</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.358(0.502, 3.677)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.547</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Health transition in SF-36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin ≥ 50 µg/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin &lt; 50 µg/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.882(0.850, 4.165)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.119</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.689(0.676, 4.223)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.262</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Total score in MoCA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin ≥ 50 µg/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin &lt; 50 µg/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.934(0.784, 4.772)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.152</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.551(0.472, 5.101)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.470</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Recall in MoCA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin ≥ 50 µg/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin &lt; 50 µg/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.441(0.982, 6.066)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.055</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.838(0.589, 5.732)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.294</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0017"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>a</sup>Dependent variables were included when the <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value was &lt; 0.15 in a comparative analysis. <sup>b</sup>Model 1: crude associations. <sup>c</sup>Model 2: model adjusted for age, sex, body mass index, years of education, age at the time of RLS onset, prior treatment (yes/no), C-reactive protein level, total sleep time, and the apnea-hypopnea index. <sup>d</sup>The parallel regression assumption in the ordinal regression was not met and binary logistic regression was thus used. Significant results (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) are shown in boldface.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0018"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: RLS, restless legs syndrome; IRLS, the International Restless Legs Syndrome Study Group Severity Scale (IRLS); SF-36, Medical Outcomes Study 36-item short-form health survey; MoCA, Montreal Cognitive Assessment.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0010"><label>Table 10</label><caption><p>Associations of Severity and Impacts of RLS with Other Peripheral Iron Status Indicators According to Ordinal Logistic Regression Models</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Dependent Variables<sup>a</sup></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Independent Variables<sup>a</sup></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 1<sup>b</sup></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 2<sup>c</sup></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daytime function in PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TIBC (µmol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.043(1.000, 1.089)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.046(0.999, 1.095)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.058</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Physical function in SF-36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum iron (µmol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.057(1.009, 1.108)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.019</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.051(0.996, 1.110)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.071</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TIBC (µmol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.036(0.993, 1.081)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.105</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.011(0.965, 1.059)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.639</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transferrin saturation (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.018(0.996, 1.041)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.111</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.017(0.991, 1.044)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.200</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BAI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum transferrin (g/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.371(0.628, 2.992)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.428</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.089(0.456, 2.598)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.848</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Recall in MoCA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TIBC (µmol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.060(0.995, 1.128)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.072</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.066(0.991, 1.145)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.084</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum transferrin (g/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.502(0.845, 7.409)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.098</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.100(0.855, 11.242)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.085</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0019"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>a</sup>Variables were included when <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value was lower than 0.15 in Spearman correlation analysis. <sup>b</sup>Model 1: unadjusted associations. <sup>c</sup>Model 2: adjusted for age, sex, body mass indices, years of education, age at the time of RLS onset, prior treatment (yes/no), hemoglobin level, total sleep time, and the apnea-hypopnea index. Significant results (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) are shown in boldface.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0020"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: RLS, Restless Legs Syndrome; PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index; SF-36, Medical Outcomes Study 36-item short-form health survey; BAI, Beck Anxiety Inventory; MoCA, Montreal Cognitive Assessment; TIBC, total iron-binding capacity.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Our study showed that a ferritin concentration &lt; 50 µg/L, UIBC, TIBC and the serum transferrin concentration, but not the serum iron concentration or TSAT, were associated with most LMs; peripheral iron indicators were not related to RLS severity or impacts.</p>
      <p>The association of peripheral iron indicators with LMs in patients with RLS in this study was surprising. Most LMs were not related significantly to iron metabolism in unadjusted analyses, but the associations changed in our multivariate logistic regression model. On PSG, patients with ferritin deficiency were about three times more likely to have higher PLMS and LM index values during N2 and N3 sleep than patients with a ferritin concentration ≥ 50 µg/L. A similar association was found between low ferritin concentrations and more PLMS by Li et al, independent of genetic polymorphisms, in a general population of older adults, implying that low iron stores play a role in the expression of these phenotypes.<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> However, in a study of Korean patients with RLS,<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> there was no correlation between the ferritin concentration and PLMS in logistic regression models. However, the credibility of the results is undermined by the lack of adjustment for the CRP level. Stefansson et al<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> identified a common variant in an intron of BTBD9 on chromosome 6p21.2, as a genetic determinant of PLMS, which correlated inversely with serum ferritin levels, indicating that iron metabolism was involved in the pathogenesis of PLMS.</p>
      <p>In this study, ferritin deficiency, the serum transferrin concentration, TIBC, and UIBC, but not the serum iron concentration or TSAT, were associated with certain LM parameters. The transferrin concentration serves as a proxy for the TIBC; it decreases as blood iron levels increase and increases with iron deficiency.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> Peripheral iron is transmitted to the brain across the blood-brain barrier. During this process, transferrin, as a receptor-mediated transporter, plays a key role in iron metabolism and maintaining iron homeostasis.<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> Magnetic susceptibility in the substantia nigra was significantly associated with PLMS measures, suggesting a link between brain iron deficiency and PLMS.<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> Earley et al<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> reported that the serum ferritin value was associated with the ferritin concentration in the cerebrospinal fluid. Compared with the control group, there was a significant reduction in the slope of the linear regression line for RLS patients. We therefore speculate that iron deficiency in the substantia nigra is more severe in RLS patients with more PLMS, in whom iron transport across the blood-brain barrier is altered. Serum iron represents the level of circulating iron, ie, of iron bound to transferrin. TSAT is the ratio of total iron and TIBC.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> Serum iron levels are highly variable and may be affected by several factors, such as diet, stress, and sleep,<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> which could explain the lack of a significant correlation between serum iron, TSAT and LM parameters. Therefore, complex iron metabolism involving iron storage and transport may contribute to the abnormal LMs seen in RLS.</p>
      <p>RLS severity and impact on patients were not related to peripheral iron indicators, implying that abnormal peripheral iron metabolism may not be a risk factor for RLS. Brain iron insufficiency and the iron–dopamine interaction play important roles in the etiology of RLS.<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> Recent studies of the mechanism of peripheral iron metabolism in RLS have focused on lymphocytes,<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> extracellular vesicles,<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> and mitochondrial dysfunction<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> and suggested that abnormal peripheral iron transport, rather than iron storage levels, is the mechanism underlying RLS. During the uptake of iron by the brain, the blood-brain barrier not only serves as a channel for iron transport, but also regulates the iron transport process.<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52–54</xref> However, in a blood-brain barrier model there was no correlation between the serum ferritin concentration and iron transport.<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> Other indicators, such as hepcidin<xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref> have been investigated and merit further exploration in patients with RLS. We conclude that the peripheral iron indicators measured in common clinical practice should be interpreted carefully, and that ferritin may not be the best RLS biomarker.</p>
      <p>Why were peripheral iron parameters in our patients with RLS related to motor components (ie, LMs on PSG) but not sensory components (RLS severity and impact on patients)? Although PLMS occur in &gt; 80% of patients with RLS<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref> and support the diagnosis of this syndrome,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> the relationship between PLMS and RLS is controversial.<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref> The motor and sensory symptoms of RLS may be separate but loosely linked, since the PLMS index alone does not reliably predict the diagnosis of RLS in children or adolescents<xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref> and the phenotypical presentation of RLS may differ by sex<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> (with women experiencing more sensory symptoms than men, who have more motor symptoms). PLMS may also be an endophenotype of RLS<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> and PLMS may be a biomarker<xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref> or genetic risk marker of RLS.<xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref> Furthermore, the pathophysiology of LMs may not generalize to idiopathic RLS.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62–64</xref> The characteristic “urge to move” may be due to lesions in ascending sensory pathways or thalamocortical circuits, and may not be accompanied by PLMS.<xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref> Our study and previous ones together indicate that the motor and sensory features of RLS are two different presentations of a common basic neurologic disorder.<xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref> As a complex disease with multiple manifestations and undefined mechanisms, the etiology of RLS may involve genetic defects in brain iron homeostasis and developmental abnormalities in cortico-striatal-thalamic-cortical circuits related to hypoadenosinergic, hyperglutamatergic, and hyperdopaminergic states.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> It is therefore likely that the different clinical features of RLS are modulated by multiple neurotransmitter systems and downstream signaling pathways.</p>
      <p>The classical PLMS index does not appear to be specific enough for the diagnosis of RLS or assessment of its clinical significance.<xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref> When used alone, the PLMS index is insufficient for characterizing the nature and structure of LM activity during sleep,<xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref> although the duration and number of PLM sequences are associated with sleep disturbances in patients with RLS.<xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,<xref rid="cit0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref> In this study, the duration of PLMS sequences was measured. The ferritin concentration, UIBC, TIBC, and serum transferrin concentration were all related to at least one PLMS measurement. In Dauvilliers et al,<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref> only the hepcidin level and hepcidin/ferritin ratio were measured, and both correlated positively with PLM during both sleep and wakefulness. Consequently, our study therefore adds to the limited knowledge regarding relationship between peripheral iron status and PLMS. In addition to PLMS, total LMs and their distribution in different sleep stages were analyzed. No peripheral iron measures were related to LM indexes during N1 sleep, while TIBC and serum transferrin and ferritin concentrations were all associated with the LM index during N2 sleep. We also found that serum ferritin and transferrin correlated with LMs during N3 and REM sleep, respectively. However, as the relationship between peripheral iron status and LMs was not assessed in previous studies, this result should be interpreted with caution and confirmed in future studies. It should be noted that none of the peripheral iron measures were related to PLM/LMs during wakefulness or arousal. Given the association of peripheral iron measures with PLM/LMs in sleep, we speculate that distinct biological mechanisms underlie the coupling of arousal and motor systems. First, dopamine agonists may have little impact on arousals, despite strongly reducing PLMS, and a targeted pharmaceutical strategy may be able to separate PLMS from arousal events.<xref rid="cit0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref> Second, different neurotransmitters may be involved in PLMS and short-interval LM wakefulness (and arousal).<xref rid="cit0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref> Third, a hierarchy has been described in the arousal response, from autonomic activation to cortical arousals and PLMS.<xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref> The above findings support the notion that the complex mechanisms subtending the fluctuating arousal and motor systems may partly explain the lack of an association between peripheral iron measures and PLMs/LMs during wakefulness and arousal.</p>
      <p>Our study had several limitations. First, its cross-sectional design and observational nature prevented determination of the causal relationship between peripheral iron metabolism and RLS. Second, the participants underwent only one night of PSG, such that night-to-night variability in LM parameters could not be captured, although this issue might have been mitigated by the inclusion of a large number of patients. Third, there may have been bias in patient selection and unmeasured confounding factors. For patients with low educational attainment, some self-report scales were completed orally, such that an influence of dialects cannot be excluded. Fourth, the population under study was relatively small, although it was well characterized clinically and through a PSG assessment.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>In conclusion, this study examined the association of peripheral iron metabolism with RLS and demonstrated that peripheral iron status was associated mainly with the motor rather than sensory components of RLS, indicating that, in RLS, the metabolic factors potentially underlying sensory symptoms differ from those underlying movement symptoms. The findings of this study strengthen the idea that the commonly used peripheral iron metabolism indicators may not be ideal biomarkers of RLS severity and impact on patients. Considering the key role of brain iron deficiency in the mechanism of RLS, further research on other iron metabolism indicators is an essential next step in confirming the role of iron metabolism in RLS.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>Abstracts of this study were displayed for colleagues at the 3rd Congress of the Asia Society of Sleep Medicine (2021). The authors gratefully thank Professor Fang Guo for helpful suggestions.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p>The datasets analyzed in the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0008">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest related to this work. This research was supported by the Medical Health Science and Technology Project of Zhejiang Provincial Health Commission under award number 2020383055/2020KY164.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ferré</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>García-Borreguero</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Earley</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>New insights into the neurobiology of restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroscientist</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1073858418791763</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30047288</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Garcia-Borreguero</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cano-Pumarega</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>New concepts in the management of restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>356</volume>:<fpage>j104</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.j104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28242627</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Trenkwalder</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Högl</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paulus</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Winkelmann</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Restless legs syndrome associated with major diseases: a systematic review and new concept</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>86</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>1336</fpage>–<lpage>1343</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000002542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26944272</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Auerbach</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bahrain</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Auerbach</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Earley</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The prevalence and impact of restless legs syndrome on patients with iron deficiency anemia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Hematol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>88</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>261</fpage>–<lpage>264</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ajh.23397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23494945</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Frauscher</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gschliesser</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brandauer</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The severity range of restless legs syndrome (RLS) and augmentation in a prospective patient cohort: association with ferritin levels</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>611</fpage>–<lpage>615</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2008.09.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19200780</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cho</surname>
<given-names>YW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Earley</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Clinical efficacy of ferric carboxymaltose treatment in patients with restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>16</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2016.06.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27823710</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adler</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Du</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Butcher</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bregman</surname>
<given-names>DB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Earley</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Clinical efficacy and safety of IV ferric carboxymaltose (FCM) treatment of RLS: a multi-centred, placebo-controlled preliminary clinical trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>906</fpage>–<lpage>913</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2011.06.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21978726</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Macher</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Herster</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holter</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The effect of parenteral or oral iron supplementation on fatigue, sleep, quality of life and restless legs syndrome in iron-deficient blood donors: a secondary analysis of the ironwoMan RCT</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nutrients</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1313</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu12051313</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Reilly</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Venkataraman</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mysliwiec</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mysliwiec</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Efficacy of oral iron in patients with restless legs syndrome and a low-normal ferritin: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>973</fpage>–<lpage>975</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2008.11.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19230757</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Winkelman</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Periodic limb movements in sleep - endophenotype for restless legs syndrome?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>357</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>703</fpage>–<lpage>705</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMe078129</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17634452</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stefansson</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rye</surname>
<given-names>DB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hicks</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A genetic risk factor for periodic limb movements in sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>357</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>639</fpage>–<lpage>647</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa072743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17634447</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schormair</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bell</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Identification of novel risk loci for restless legs syndrome in genome-wide association studies in individuals of European ancestry: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>898</fpage>–<lpage>907</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(17)30327-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29029846</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Catoire</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dion</surname>
<given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xiong</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Restless legs syndrome-associated MEIS1 risk variant influences iron homeostasis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>70</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>170</fpage>–<lpage>175</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ana.22435</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21710629</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Winkelman</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Armstrong</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Practice guideline summary: treatment of restless legs syndrome in adults: report of the guideline development, dissemination, and implementation subcommittee of the American Academy of neurology</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>87</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>2585</fpage>–<lpage>2593</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000003388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27856776</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Winkelmann</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hogl</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Treatment of restless legs syndrome: evidence-based review and implications for clinical practice (revised 2017) (section sign)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mov Disord</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1077</fpage>–<lpage>1091</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mds.27260</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29756335</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Picchietti</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Auerbach</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Evidence-based and consensus clinical practice guidelines for the iron treatment of restless legs syndrome/Willis-Ekbom disease in adults and children: an IRLSSG task force report</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2017.11.1126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29425576</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Garcia-Malo</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miranda</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peralta</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cano-Pumarega</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ponte</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garcia-Borreguero</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Iron replacement therapy in restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Treat Option Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>114</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11940-020-0617-7</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Leung</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Singh</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McWilliams</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stockler</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ipsiroglu</surname>
<given-names>OS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Iron deficiency and sleep – a scoping review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>101274</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2020.101274</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32224451</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>KW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yoon</surname>
<given-names>IY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence, comorbidities and risk factors of restless legs syndrome in the Korean elderly population - results from the Korean longitudinal study on health and aging</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1 Pt 1</issue>):<fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.2009.00739.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19686313</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Benediktsdottir</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Janson</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lindberg</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence of restless legs syndrome among adults in Iceland and Sweden: lung function, comorbidity, ferritin, biomarkers and quality of life</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1043</fpage>–<lpage>1048</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2010.08.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20961808</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Berger</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>von Eckardstein</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trenkwalder</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rothdach</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Junker</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weiland</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Iron metabolism and the risk of restless legs syndrome in an elderly general population--the MEMO-study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>249</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1195</fpage>–<lpage>1199</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00415-002-0805-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12242538</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Holzknecht</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hochleitner</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wenning</surname>
<given-names>GK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hogl</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stefani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Gender differences in clinical, laboratory and polysomnographic features of restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>e12875</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12875</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31162763</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Connor</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patton</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oexle</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Iron and restless legs syndrome: treatment, genetics and pathophysiology</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2016.07.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28057495</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lammers</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Curry-Hyde</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Are serum ferritin and transferrin saturation risk markers for restless legs syndrome in young adults? Longitudinal and cross-sectional data from the Western Australian pregnancy cohort (raine) study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e12741</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30062860</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Haschka</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Volani</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stefani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of mitochondrial iron deficiency and dysfunction with idiopathic restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mov Disord</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>114</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mds.27482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30311259</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mizuno</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mihara</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miyaoka</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Inagaki</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Horiguchi</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>CSF iron, ferritin and transferrin levels in restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.2004.00403.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15743333</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="newspaper"><string-name><surname>Richard</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berry</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rita Brooks</surname>
<given-names>MRR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The AASM manual for the scoring of sleep and associated events: rules, terminology and technical specifications (version 2.4)</article-title>; <year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ferri</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>DelRosso</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Silvani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Peculiar lifespan changes of periodic leg movements during sleep in restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e12896</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12896</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31313413</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Picchietti</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garcia-Borreguero</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Restless legs syndrome/Willis-Ekbom disease diagnostic criteria: updated International Restless Legs Syndrome Study Group (IRLSSG) consensus criteria--history, rationale, description, and significance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>860</fpage>–<lpage>873</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2014.03.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25023924</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tomlinson</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stowe</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rick</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gray</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clarke</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Systematic review of levodopa dose equivalency reporting in Parkinson’s disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mov Disord</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>2649</fpage>–<lpage>2653</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mds.23429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21069833</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Garcia-Borreguero</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kohnen</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Diagnostic standards for dopaminergic augmentation of restless legs syndrome: report from a world association of sleep medicine-international restless legs syndrome study group consensus conference at the Max Planck Institute</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>520</fpage>–<lpage>530</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2007.03.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17544323</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Walters</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>LeBrocq</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dhar</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Validation of the international restless legs syndrome study group rating scale for restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>132</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s1389-9457(02)00258-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14592342</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>CF</given-names> 3rd</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monk</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berman</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kupfer</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Pittsburgh sleep quality index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0165-1781(89)90047-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2748771</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Johns</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A new method for measuring daytime sleepiness: the Epworth sleepiness scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>540</fpage>–<lpage>545</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/14.6.540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1798888</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chalder</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berelowitz</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pawlikowska</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Development of a fatigue scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychosom Res</italic></source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>147</fpage>–<lpage>153</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0022-3999(93)90081-P</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8463991</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McHorney</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ware</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names> Jr</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sherbourne</surname>
<given-names>CD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>The</surname>
<given-names>MOS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>36-item short-form health survey (SF-36): III. Tests of data quality, scaling assumptions, and reliability across diverse patient groups</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Med Care</italic></source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005650-199401000-00004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8277801</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vandeputte</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Weerd</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disorders and depressive feelings: a global survey with the Beck depression scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>343</fpage>–<lpage>345</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1389-9457(03)00059-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14592308</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Beck</surname>
<given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Epstein</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Steer</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>An inventory for measuring clinical anxiety: psychometric properties</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Consult Clin Psychol</italic></source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>893</fpage>–<lpage>897</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0022-006X.56.6.893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3204199</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nasreddine</surname>
<given-names>ZS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Phillips</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bédirian</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The Montreal cognitive assessment, MoCA: a brief screening tool for mild cognitive impairment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Geriatr Soc</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>695</fpage>–<lpage>699</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1532-5415.2005.53221.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15817019</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Folstein</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Folstein</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McHugh</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>”Mini-mental state”. A practical method for grading the cognitive state of patients for the clinician</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychiatr Res</italic></source>. <year>1975</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>198</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0022-3956(75)90026-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1202204</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Trenkwalder</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Högl</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Comorbidities, treatment, and pathophysiology in restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>994</fpage>–<lpage>1005</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(18)30311-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30244828</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Darien</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">American Academy of Sleep Medicine International Classification of Sleep Disorders</italic></source>. <edition>3rd</edition> ed. <publisher-loc>Darien, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</publisher-name>; <year>2014</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moore</surname>
<given-names>HT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of low ferritin with PLM in the Wisconsin sleep cohort</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1413</fpage>–<lpage>1418</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2015.05.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26498245</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shin</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koo</surname>
<given-names>YS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>BU</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence and characteristics of periodic limb movements during sleep in Korean adult patients with restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>08</issue>):<fpage>1089</fpage>–<lpage>1097</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.6042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27306390</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Belaidi</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bush</surname>
<given-names>AI</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Iron neurochemistry in Alzheimer’s disease and Parkinson’s disease: targets for therapeutics</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurochem</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>139</volume>(<issue>Suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>197</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jnc.13425</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Piao</surname>
<given-names>YS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lian</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Restless legs syndrome in Parkinson disease: clinical characteristics, abnormal iron metabolism and altered neurotransmitters</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>10547</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-10593-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28874701</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Earley</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Brain iron deficiency in idiopathic restless legs syndrome measured by quantitative magnetic susceptibility at 7 tesla</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2016.05.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27544840</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Earley</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Connor</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beard</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malecki</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Epstein</surname>
<given-names>DK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Abnormalities in CSF concentrations of ferritin and transferrin in restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1698</fpage>–<lpage>1700</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.54.8.1698</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10762522</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Earley</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Connor</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garcia-Borreguero</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Altered brain iron homeostasis and dopaminergic function in restless legs syndrome (Willis-Ekbom disease)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1288</fpage>–<lpage>1301</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2014.05.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25201131</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Earley</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ponnuru</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Altered iron metabolism in lymphocytes from subjects with restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>847</fpage>–<lpage>852</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/31.6.847</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18548829</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chawla</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gulyani</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Extracellular vesicles reveal abnormalities in neuronal iron metabolism in restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>7</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsz079</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Simpson</surname>
<given-names>IA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ponnuru</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Klinger</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A novel model for brain iron uptake: introducing the concept of regulation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cereb Blood Flow Metab</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>48</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jcbfm.2014.168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25315861</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Connor</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ponnuru</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>XS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patton</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Earley</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Profile of altered brain iron acquisition in restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>134</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>959</fpage>–<lpage>968</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awr012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21398376</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Connor</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duck</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patton</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Evidence for communication of peripheral iron status to cerebrospinal fluid: clinical implications for therapeutic strategy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Fluids Barriers CNS</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12987-020-00190-8</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0055">
        <label>55.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chenini</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Delaby</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rassu</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Hepcidin and ferritin levels in restless legs syndrome: a case-control study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>11914</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-68851-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32681031</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0056">
        <label>56.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dauvilliers</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chenini</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vialaret</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association between serum hepcidin level and restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mov Disord</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>618</fpage>–<lpage>627</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mds.27287</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29418021</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0057">
        <label>57.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ohayon</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Hara</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vitiello</surname>
<given-names>MV</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Epidemiology of restless legs syndrome: a synthesis of the literature</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>283</fpage>–<lpage>295</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2011.05.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21795081</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0058">
        <label>58.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Montplaisir</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boucher</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poirier</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lavigne</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lapierre</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lespérance</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Clinical, polysomnographic, and genetic characteristics of restless legs syndrome: a study of 133 patients diagnosed with new standard criteria</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mov Disord</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mds.870120111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8990055</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0059">
        <label>59.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ferri</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>DelRosso</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aricò</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Leg movement activity during sleep in school-age children and adolescents: a detailed study in normal controls and participants with restless legs syndrome and narcolepsy type 1</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>4</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsy010</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0060">
        <label>60.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ferri</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koo</surname>
<given-names>BB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Picchietti</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fulda</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Periodic leg movements during sleep: phenotype, neurophysiology, and clinical significance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2016.05.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28341521</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0061">
        <label>61.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Högl</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stefani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Restless legs syndrome and periodic leg movements in patients with movement disorders: specific considerations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Movement Disord</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>669</fpage>–<lpage>681</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mds.26929</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28186669</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0062">
        <label>62.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Moore</surname>
<given-names>HT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Winkelmann</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Finn</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peppard</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mignot</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Periodic leg movements during sleep are associated with polymorphisms in BTBD9, TOX3/BC034767, MEIS1, MAP2K5/SKOR1, and PTPRD</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1535</fpage>–<lpage>1542</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.4006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25142570</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0063">
        <label>63.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Czesnik</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Howells</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bartl</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>I(h) contributes to increased motoneuron excitability in restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>597</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>599</fpage>–<lpage>609</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/JP275341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30430565</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0064">
        <label>64.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cha</surname>
<given-names>KS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Brain regions associated with periodic leg movements during sleep in restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep UK</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1610</fpage>–<lpage>1615</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0065">
        <label>65.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ferri</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sparasci</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Castelnovo</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Leg movement activity during sleep in multiple sclerosis with and without restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.9466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34216201</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0066">
        <label>66.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pelletier</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lorrain</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Montplaisir</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sensory and motor components of the restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1663</fpage>–<lpage>1666</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.42.9.1663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1513452</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0067">
        <label>67.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ferri</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The time structure of leg movement activity during sleep: the theory behind the practice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>433</fpage>–<lpage>441</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2011.10.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22325713</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0068">
        <label>68.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Boehm</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wetter</surname>
<given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trenkwalder</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Periodic leg movements in RLS patients as compared to controls: are there differences beyond the PLM index?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>566</fpage>–<lpage>571</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2008.04.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18753004</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0069">
        <label>69.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Manconi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferri</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zucconi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Dissociation of periodic leg movements from arousals in restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>834</fpage>–<lpage>844</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ana.23565</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22718547</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0070">
        <label>70.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Manconi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferri</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feroah</surname>
<given-names>TR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zucconi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferini-Strambi</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Defining the boundaries of the response of sleep leg movements to a single dose of dopamine agonist</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1229</fpage>–<lpage>1237</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18788648</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0071">
        <label>71.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sforza</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nicolas</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lavigne</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gosselin</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petit</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Montplaisir</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>EEG and cardiac activation during periodic leg movements in sleep: support for a hierarchy of arousal responses</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>786</fpage>–<lpage>791</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.52.4.786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10078729</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
