<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36507312</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">9733560</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">388203</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S388203</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Risk Factors of Nonalcoholic Fatty Liver Disease and Liver Fibrosis in Non-Obese Patients with Obstructive Sleep Apnea</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Lian et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Lian et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Lian</surname>
            <given-names>Ningfang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>Jiawei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Biying</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>Su</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <given-names>Jiefeng</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Jia</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>Qichang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine, The First Affiliated Hospital of Fujian Medical University; Fujian Provincial Sleep-Disordered Breathing Clinic Center; National Regional Medical Center, Binhai Campus of The First Affiliated Hospital, Fujian Medical University; Institute of Respiratory Disease, Fujian Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Fuzhou</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Liver Research Center, The First Affiliated Hospital of Fujian Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Fuzhou</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Qichang Lin, <institution>Department of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, The First Affiliated Hospital of Fujian Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>No. 20, Chazhong Road, Taijiang District</addr-line>, <addr-line>Fuzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Fujian Province</addr-line>, <addr-line>350005</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, <phone>Tel +86-591-87981698</phone>, <fax>Fax +86-591-83318716</fax>, Email linqc_fy@126.com</corresp>
        <fn id="ft0001">
          <label>*</label>
          <p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>05</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <fpage>2143</fpage>
      <lpage>2149</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>08</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2022 Lian et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Lian et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p>Liver injury in non-obese obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) patients has received much attention in recent years. This study aimed to investigate risk factors of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) and liver fibrosis in non-obese patients with OSA.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>A retrospective study was conducted in the Sleep Center of the First Affiliated Hospital of Fujian Medical University. All consecutive non-obese patients with suspected sleep apnea admitted to the center were enrolled. The clinical characteristics of patients with simple snoring and with different severity OSA were compared. Multivariate logistic regression models were used to analyze the risk factors of NAFLD and liver fibrosis.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>A total of 410 patients were enrolled. The levels of triglyceride, alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) increased with the aggravation of OSA (All p&lt;0.05). Among non-obese patients with OSA, 17 (5%) were diagnosed with liver fibrosis and 228 (65%) with NAFLD; Apnea‑hyponea index (AHI) was an independent predictor for NAFLD and liver fibrosis [OR (95% CI): 1.02 (1.00–1.03), 1.04 (1.00–1.07), both p&lt;0.05]; hypertriglyceridemia was an independent predictor for NAFLD [OR (95% CI): 1.13 (1.12–1.99), p&lt;0.05].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>NAFLD and liver fibrosis were common in non-obese OSA patients and the severity of OSA was an independent risk factor for them.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>obstructive sleep apnea</kwd>
        <kwd>non-alcoholic fatty liver disease</kwd>
        <kwd>liver fibrosis</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>the Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Medical Elite Cultivation Program of Fujian in China</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported by the Natural Science Foundation of China; under Grant number 82170101; The Medical Elite Cultivation Program of Fujian in China, under Grant number 2020GGA044.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="0"/>
        <table-count count="4"/>
        <ref-count count="28"/>
        <page-count count="7"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) is a chronic respiratory disease characterized by periodic hypoxia and reoxygenation during sleep.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> The prevalence of OSA has raised to approximately 25% of adults in USA.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> OSA usually occurs in obese individuals, but increasing evidence indicates that OSA is also common in non-obese population.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Among individuals aged 30 to 49 years with a body mass index (BMI) less than 25, the prevalence of OSA among men is 7.0%.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></p>
      <p>OSA resulted in multiple organs injury, including cardiovascular injury and metabolic disorders.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> OSA and metabolic syndrome shared considerable overlap with risk factors, including obesity, sedentary behavior, and genetics.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Nocturnal oxygen saturation parameters were independent risk factors for Type 2 Diabetes among OSA Patients.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> In recent years, OSA-related liver injury has received much attention. Savransky et al reported that OSA was associated with nonalcoholic steatohepatitis in obese subjects.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Zhang et al found apnea‑hyponea index (AHI) was an independent risk factor for elevated alanine aminotransferase (ALT) levels in severely obese patients.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Huang et al reported that intermittent hypoxia was an independent predictor for nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) in severe OSA patients.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Wojciech et al found increased liver stiffness in patients with metabolic comorbidities and severe OSA.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Most of the previous clinical studies focused on obese people, as obesity was an important risk factor for both OSA and liver injury. The mechanism of liver injury in OSA patients was due to intermittent hypoxia related systemic inflammatory, oxidative stress, mild tissue ischemia and increased output of the sympathetic nervous system.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> The pathophysiological injury associated with intermittent hypoxia occurred not only in obese people but also in non-obese people. So, liver injury in non-obese OSA patients deserved more attention.</p>
      <p>NAFLD is a common chronic liver disease featured by the accumulation of lipid in the liver. The disease spectrum includes simple hepatic steatosis, steatohepatitis, fibrosis and cirrhosis. Previous studies found that the degree of liver fibrosis determined the outcomes in NAFLD patients.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Fibrosis-4 Index (FIB-4) has been widely used in recent years as a noninvasive method for detecting liver fibrosis with acceptable sensitivity and specificity.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></p>
      <p>This study aimed to discuss the risk factors of NAFLD and liver fibrosis in non-obese OSA patients.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <p>The retrospective study was conducted in Sleep Respiratory Disease Research Center, First Affiliated Hospital of Fujian Medical University. The informed consents were obtained from the study participants prior to study commencement. All consecutive patients with suspected sleep apnea admitted to the center were enrolled in the study between January 2, 2016 and December 23, 2019. Including criteria were as follows: (1) All subjects enrolled aged 18–80 years. (2) BMI &lt;28kg/m<sup>2</sup>, met the non-obese standard of Chinese population.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> (3) The subjects completed overnight polysomnography. (4) The abdominal ultrasonography was performed during hospitalization. (5) With completed clinical data. Subjects with infectious disease within 1-month, alcoholic liver disease, liver malignancy, various viral hepatitis or other known chronic liver disease were excluded. Sedatives and naps were prohibited prior to sleep monitoring to minimize the interferences with the results. This study complied with the Declaration of Helsinki. The study design was approved by the Ethics Committee of the First Affiliated Hospital of Fujian Medical University.</p>
      <p>All data were collected from electronic medical records. Age, sex, height, weight, neck circumference, waist circumference and Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS) were measured at admission. Sleep monitoring was performed using polysomnography respiratory monitoring system (Condi Australia). AHI, mean oxygen saturation (MSaO2), lowest oxygen saturation (LSaO2), the percentage of sleep time with SpO2&lt;90% (T90%) and oxygen desaturation index (ODI) were obtained from the polysomnography monitoring report. Apnea was defined as at least 90% drop in oronasal air flow for at least 10 s. Hypopnea was defined as at least 30% drop in oronasal air flow for ≥10 s associated with ≥4% oxygen desaturation or at least 50% drop in oronasal air flow for ≥10 s associated with ≥3% oxygen desaturation. The diagnosis and severity of OSA were based on 2012 American Academy of Sleep Medicine (AASM) criteria as follows:<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Without OSA, AHI &lt; 5 events/h; mild-to-moderate OSA, AHI 5.0–29.9 events/h; severe OSA, AHI 30–49.9 events/h; very severe OSA, AHI ≥ 50.0 events/h. Blood routine test, liver function, blood glucose, blood cholesterol, and triglycerides were performed on the next day after Polysomnography in fasting conditions.</p>
      <p>Fatty liver disease in the study was diagnosed via the results of abdominal ultrasonography. After excluding the subjects with excessive alcohol consumption, NAFLD was diagnosed. Fibrosis-4 Index (FIB-4) was calculated as following: Age (ys) ×AST (IU/L)/(platelet count (×10<sup>9</sup>/L) ×ALT (IU/L) <sup>1/2</sup>). The values of Fib-4 upper than 2.67 were defined as with liver fibrosis.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> All the subjects with elevated levels of ALT or AST were defined as liver injury. The levels of ALT &gt;40 U/L in males or &gt;31 U/L in females was defined elevated ALT.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></p>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>After the normality test, continuous variables were described using mean± standard deviation or median (interquartile range) value. Categorical variables were described as percentages. The analysis of variance was used to compare multiple groups of continuous variables. The chi-square test was used to compare categorical variable. Furthermore, binary logistic regression models were built to identify independent risks of NAFLD and liver fibrosis. All statistical analyses were performed using SPSS 22.0. The significance was set at a P value less than 0.05.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>A total of 410 subjects were included in this study. The mean age of was 53.0± 14.4 years, and 324 (79%) were male. The median value of BMI was 25.3 (23.7–26.6) kg/m<sup>2</sup>. A total of 59 (14%) patients were simple snoring and 351 (86%) patients met the diagnostic criteria of OSA.</p>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>The Comparison of the Baseline Characteristics Among Four Groups</title>
        <p>The comparison of the baseline characteristics among four groups are shown in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. There were significant differences in age, BMI, neck circumference, waistlines, and sleep related parameters (AHI, ESS score, T90%, LSaO2, MSaO2 and ODI) among patients with simple snoring, mild-moderate, severe and very severe OSA groups (all P&lt;0.05). The levels of triglyceride increased with the aggravation of OSA, while the levels of high-density lipoprotein cholesterol decreased with the aggravation of OSA (both P&lt;0.05), shown in <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The Basic Characteristics and Sleep Parameters of Patients in Four Groups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control N=59</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild-to-Moderate N=190</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe N=97</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very Severely N=64</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (68%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">151 (79%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81 (84%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (81%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.0±15.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.3±14.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.0±13.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.8±12.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (49.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101 (52.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (47.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (40.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.373</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (9.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (13.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (19.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (14.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.201</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hyper lipidaemia (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (6.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (12.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (16.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (15.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.282</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (20.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (31.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (28.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (31.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.201</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lipid-lowering therapy (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (6.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (4.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (9.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.355</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neck circumference (cm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.0 (34.8–38.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.0 (36.0–40.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.8 (37.0–40.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.0 (37.0–41.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Waistlines (cm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.2 (82.3–95.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.8 (89.0–97.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.0 (90.0–99.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.0 (92.3–102.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (2–8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (3–9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (4–10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (6–12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4 (1.8–3.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.9 (9.7–21.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.3 (33.8–42.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.7 (53.6–71.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.1 (22.6–26.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.5 (23.7–26.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.7 (24.2–26.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.2 (24.8–27.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ts90 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 (0.0–1.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 (0.7–8.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5 (8.1–36.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.7 (28.9–144.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSaO2 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88 (84–90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82 (77–86)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 (66–81)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (65–75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MSaO2 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96 (95–96)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95 (94–96)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93 (92–94)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91 (89–93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ODI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9 (1.1–4.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5 (5.6–14.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.9 (23.0–36.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (45–65)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Data were presented as n (%), median (IQR) or mean ± standard deviation.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: BMI, body mass index; AHI, apnea‑hyponea index; ESS, Epworth Sleepiness Scale; MSaO2, mean oxygen saturation; LSaO2, lowest oxygen saturation; T90%, the percentage of sleep time with SpO2&lt;90%; ODI, oxygen desaturation index.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Metabolic Markers and Liver Function Among Four Groups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control N=59</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild-to-Moderate N=190</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe N=97</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very Severely N=64</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glucose (mmol/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8 (4.5–5.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0 (4.5–5.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9 (4.6–5.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9 (4.6–5.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.647</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBP (mmHg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">131±15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">132±17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">132±16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">133±12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.953</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DBP (mmHg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79±10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80±12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80±11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84±10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.054</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL (mmol/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.89–1.23)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 (0.90–1.23)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 (0.91–1.27)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 (0.84–1.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triglyceride (mmol/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (0.9–1.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 (1.1–2.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 (1.0–2.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 (1.4–2.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cholesterol (mmol/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3±0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7±1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6±1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6±0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.111</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL (mmol/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7±0.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0±0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9±0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9±0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.072</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total bilirubin (μmmol/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4 (7.1–14.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6 (8.6–15.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9 (8.5–13.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9 (8.1–13.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.490</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT (u/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (13–30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (17–38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (18–33)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (22–42)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AST (u/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21±7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23±9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23±11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28±18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALP (u/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72±26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76±35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69±22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67±24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.091</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGT (u/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (17–35)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (18–55)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (19–53)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (23–60)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FiB-4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.8–1.58)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 (0.74–1.41)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 (0.72–1.52)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 (0.62–1.17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NAFLD (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (55.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">121 (63.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (53.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (85.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver injury (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (15.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (25.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (22.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (32.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.050</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Data were presented as n (%), median (IQR) or mean ± standard deviation.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: SBP, systolic blood pressure; DBP, diastolic blood pressure; HDL, high density lipoprotein‑cholesterol; LDL, low density lipoprotein‑cholesterol; ALT, alanine aminotransferase; AST, aspartate aminotransferase; ALP, alkaline Phosphatase; GGT, gamma glutamyltransferase; Fib-4, Fibrosis-4 Index; NAFLD, nonalcoholic fatty liver disease.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>NAFLD and Liver Fibrosis in Non-Obese OSA</title>
        <p>Among non-obese patients with OSA, 17 (5%) were diagnosed with liver fibrosis and 228 (65%) with NAFLD; While in simple snoring group, 0 (0%) liver fibrosis and 33 (56%) NAFLD were diagnosed. Meanwhile, the significant differences of ALT, AST and GGT among all groups were found (all P&lt; 0.05). The lowest values were found in simple snoring group and the highest values were found in severe OSA group. There were no differences in total bilirubin or ALP among all groups. The ratio of liver injury and NAFLD were significantly different among all groups, and the incidence of liver injury and NAFLD was the highest in severe OSA group, shown in <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>The Risk Factor of NAFLD and Fibrosis in Non-Obese OSA</title>
        <p><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> shows the correlations between NAFLD, liver fibrosis and the other variables in non-obese OSA patients. BMI, triglyceride, glucose and ODI were significantly correlated with NAFLD (all P&lt;0.05). Age, hypertension history, triglyceride and cholesterol were significantly correlated with liver fibrosis (all P&lt;0.05).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Spearman’s Rank Correlation Coefficients Between NAFLD, Liver Fibrosis and Clinical Characteristics in OSA Patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">NAFLD</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Liver Fibrosis</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p values</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p values</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.054</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.318</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.077</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.153</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.039</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.472</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.227</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.075</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.161</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.922</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.859</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hyperlipemia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.090</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.093</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.642</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.318</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.052</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.337</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triglyceride (mmol/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.259</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.166</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cholesterol (mmol/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.453</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.155</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glucose (mmol/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.036</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.508</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.092</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.829</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ODI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.112</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.036</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.767</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSaO2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.029</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.592</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.088</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.100</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: BMI, body mass index; AHI, apnea‑hyponea index; ODI, oxygen desaturation index; LSaO2, lowest oxygen saturation; NAFLD, nonalcoholic fatty liver disease.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <p>As shown in <xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>, Logistic regression suggested that AHI, BMI and triglyceride were independent predictors for NAFLD in non-obese OSA patients (P&lt;0.05). After adjusting for various confounding factors, AHI was an independent predictor for liver fibrosis in non-obese OSA patients (P&lt;0.05).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Logistic Regression Analysis of NAFLD and Liver Fibrosis in OSA Patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">NAFLD</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Liver Fibrosis</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p values</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p values</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 (1.05–1.17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 (0.02–1.23)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.075</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13 (1.01–1.27)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 (0.81–1.30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.818</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triglyceride</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13 (1.12–1.99)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33 (0.11–0.99)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.050</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cholesterol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 (0.84–1.37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.571</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 (0.39–1.39)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.352</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glucose</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (0.89–1.12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.721</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80 (0.50–1.27)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.340</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (1.00–1.03)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (1.00–1.07)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.045</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0006"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: BMI, body mass index; AHI, apnea‑hyponea index; NAFLD, nonalcoholic fatty liver disease.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>This study showed that the incidence of NAFLD and liver fibrosis was high in non-obese OSA patients. AHI is an independent risk factor for NAFLD and liver fibrosis in non-obese OSA patients.</p>
      <p>The correlation between OSA and liver injury has attracted more and more attention. Some studies suggested that OSA-related intermittent hypoxia was an independent risk factor for liver enzyme elevation in addition to confounding factors such as obesity.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Although NAFLD is commonly associated with obesity, non-obese individuals has gradually attracted the attention of researchers.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> It was reported that around 40% of the global NAFLD population was classified as non-obese. In our study, 65% non-obese OSA patients had NAFLD, the incidence was higher than that of the control group (56%). Especially in very severe non-obese OSA patients, the incidence of NAFLD reached 86%.</p>
      <p>In previous study, liver enzymes did not increase with the aggravating of OSA in non-obese OSA patients.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> This is different from the results of our study. The levels of ALT, AST and GGT elevated in OSA patients in our study, especially in very severe OSA patients. The differences may be related to the small sample size of previous study, only 106 cases. Furthermore, in this study, the very severe subgroup was separated from the severe OSA patients. The increased liver enzyme and incidence of liver injury in very severe group supported that severe intermittent hypoxia was an important cause of liver injury.</p>
      <p>For non-obese OSA patients, AHI and hypertriglyceridemia were independent risk factors for NAFLD. Previous studies found that insulin resistance was more commonly in non-obese NAFLD patients than in healthy subjects.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Insulin resistance and dysfunctional lipid metabolism were common complications of OSA.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> Furthermore, a twin study showed the OSA and hypertriglyceridemia shared common genetic background; Excluding the confounding effects of obesity, genetically increased triglyceride levels increased the risk of OSA.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> So, we speculated that genetic background and intermittent hypoxia-associated lipid metabolism disorders and insulin resistance may be responsible for NAFLD in non-obese OSA individuals. This finding suggested that obesity should not be the screening criterion for NAFLD in OSA patient. Even lean patients with severe OSA should be screened for NAFLD.</p>
      <p>In the study, the diagnosis of liver fibrosis was based on Fib-4, a non-invasive indicator. A 2.67 was used as the cut-off value of Fib-4.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> Age is one of the variables used to calculate this index. In this study, the younger average ages in very severe OSA patients may lead to the lower Fib-4 value. The diagnostic value of Fib4 still lagged behind that of invasive tests such as liver biopsy. As a result, a more reliable method to diagnose liver fibrosis should be explored in future studies.</p>
      <p>This study had some limitation: (1) The nature of this retrospective study might compromise the conclusion. (2) Fatty liver, liver injury and liver fibrosis were diagnosed by non-invasive methods. It may affect the reliability of research conclusions.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, NAFLD and liver fibrosis was common in non-obese OSA patients. AHI was an independent risk factor for NAFLD and liver fibrosis in non-obese OSA patient. Intense monitoring and evaluation of liver function in non-obese patients with severe OSA should be considered.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p>Data is available on request from the correspondence author.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>Ningfang Lian designed the study and revised the manuscript, Jiawei Wu analyzed the data and prepared the manuscript, Jiefeng Huang and Jia Chen collected the data and performed manuscript drafting, Biying Wang searched the literature, analyzed the data and revised the manuscript, Su Lin analyzed the data and revised the manuscript, Qichang Lin designed the study, reviewed the results and made critical comments on the manuscript. All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation, or in all these areas; took part in drafting, revising or critically reviewing the article; gave final approval of the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0007">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Veasey</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosen</surname>
<given-names>IM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea in adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>380</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>1442</fpage>–<lpage>1449</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMcp1816152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30970189</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Young</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peppard</surname>
<given-names>PE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gottlieb</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Epidemiology of obstructive sleep apnea: a population health perspective</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>165</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1217</fpage>–<lpage>1239</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.2109080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11991871</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bikov</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frent</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meszaros</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Triglyceride-glucose index in non-diabetic, non-obese patients with obstructive sleep apnoea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1932</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm10091932</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33947164</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gottlieb</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Punjabi</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Diagnosis and management of obstructive sleep apnea: a review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>323</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>1389</fpage>–<lpage>1400</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.3514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32286648</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mysliwiec</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ulmer</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The management of chronic insomnia disorder and obstructive sleep apnea: synopsis of the 2019 U.S. department of veterans affairs and U.S. department of defense clinical practice guidelines</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>172</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>325</fpage>–<lpage>336</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M19-3575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32066145</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gaines</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vgontzas</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fernandez-Mendoza</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bixler</surname>
<given-names>EO</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea and the metabolic syndrome: the road to clinically-meaningful phenotyping, improved prognosis, and personalized treatment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>219</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2018.08.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30279095</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gabryelska</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chrzanowski</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sochal</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Nocturnal oxygen saturation parameters as independent risk factors for type 2 diabetes mellitus among obstructive sleep apnea patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>3770</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34501217</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Savransky</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nanayakkara</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vivero</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Chronic intermittent hypoxia predisposes to liver injury</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hepatology</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1007</fpage>–<lpage>1013</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.21593</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17393512</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meng</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea and liver injury in severely obese patients with nonalcoholic fatty liver disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1515</fpage>–<lpage>1521</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-020-02018-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32002742</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ding</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>HS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The association between glycometabolism and nonalcoholic fatty liver disease in patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>373</fpage>–<lpage>378</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-018-1744-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30349997</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Trzepizur</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boursier</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Le Vaillant</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Increased liver stiffness in patients with severe sleep apnoea and metabolic comorbidities</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Respir J</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1800601</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.00601-2018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29880653</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mesarwi</surname>
<given-names>OA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Loomba</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malhotra</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea, hypoxia, and nonalcoholic fatty liver disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>199</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>830</fpage>–<lpage>841</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201806-1109TR</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30422676</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dulai</surname>
<given-names>PS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Singh</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Increased risk of mortality by fibrosis stage in nonalcoholic fatty liver disease: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hepatology</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1557</fpage>–<lpage>1565</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.29085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28130788</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mózes</surname>
<given-names>FE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Selvaraj</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Diagnostic accuracy of non-invasive tests for advanced fibrosis in patients with NAFLD: an individual patient data meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Gut</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1006</fpage>–<lpage>1019</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gutjnl-2021-324243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34001645</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>FC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The guidelines for prevention and control of overweight and obesity in Chinese adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biomed Environ Sci</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Berry</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Budhiraja</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gottlieb</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Rules for scoring respiratory events in sleep: update of the 2007 AASM manual for the scoring of sleep and associated events. deliberations of the sleep apnea definitions task force of the American academy of sleep medicine</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>597</fpage>–<lpage>619</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.2172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23066376</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Castellana</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Donghia</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guerra</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Fibrosis-4 index vs nonalcoholic fatty liver disease fibrosis score in identifying advanced fibrosis in subjects with nonalcoholic fatty liver disease: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Gastroenterol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>116</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1833</fpage>–<lpage>1841</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14309/ajg.0000000000001337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34160377</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="newspaper"><string-name><surname>Gunter</surname>
<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lewis</surname>
<given-names>BG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koncikowski</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Laboratory procedures used for the third national health and nutrition examination survey (NHANES III)</article-title>; <year>1996</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jullian-Desayes</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trzepizur</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boursier</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease and NAFLD: an individual participant data meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>357</fpage>–<lpage>364</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.04.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32843301</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>QC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>LD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>GP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association between nocturnal hypoxia and liver injury in the setting of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>280</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-014-1008-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24870112</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ye</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zou</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yeo</surname>
<given-names>YH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Global prevalence, incidence, and outcomes of non-obese or lean non-alcoholic fatty liver disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Gastroenterol Hepatol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>739</fpage>–<lpage>752</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2468-1253(20)30077-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32413340</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ahadi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Molooghi</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Masoudifar</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Namdar</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vossoughinia</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Farzanehfar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A review of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease in non-obese and lean individuals</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Gastroenterol Hepatol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1497</fpage>–<lpage>1507</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jgh.15353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33217052</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Qi</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>QC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Relationship between obstructive sleep apnea and nonalcoholic fatty liver disease in nonobese adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>529</fpage>–<lpage>535</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-015-1232-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26174847</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Khalyfa</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gozal</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Masa</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep-disordered breathing, circulating exosomes, and insulin sensitivity in adipocytes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Obes</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1127</fpage>–<lpage>1139</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41366-018-0099-9</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jun</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shin</surname>
<given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Devera</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Intermittent hypoxia-induced glucose intolerance is abolished by α-adrenergic blockade or adrenal medullectomy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>307</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>E1073</fpage>–<lpage>E1083</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpendo.00373.2014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25315697</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Meszaros</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tarnoki</surname>
<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tarnoki</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea and hypertriglyceridaemia share common genetic background: results of a twin study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e12979</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12979</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31908118</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>YD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The causal effects of lipid profiles on sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Nutr</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>910690</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnut.2022.910690</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35799595</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shah</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lydecker</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Murray</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tetri</surname>
<given-names>BN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Contos</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sanyal</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Comparison of noninvasive markers of fibrosis in patients with nonalcoholic fatty liver disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1104</fpage>–<lpage>1112</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cgh.2009.05.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19523535</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
