<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36945230</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">10024909</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">400745</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S400745</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Clinical Characteristics Combined with Craniofacial Photographic Analysis in Children with Obstructive Sleep Apnea</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Wang et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Wang et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Huijun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>Wen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
            <given-names>Anqi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>Dance</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Yanru</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Han</surname>
            <given-names>Demin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Otorhinolaryngology Head and Neck Surgery, Beijing Tongren Hospital, Capital Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Key Laboratory of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Ministry of Education, Capital Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Demin Han; Yanru Li, <institution>Beijing Tongren Hospital, Capital Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>1 Dongjiaominxiang, Dongcheng District</addr-line>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, Email deminhan_ent@hotmail.com; liyanruru@aliyun.com</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2023</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>15</volume>
      <fpage>115</fpage>
      <lpage>125</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>08</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2023 Wang et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Wang et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Distinguishing obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) in a high-risk population remains challenging. This study aimed to investigate clinical features to identify children with OSA combined with craniofacial photographic analysis.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">One hundred and forty-five children (30 controls, 62 with primary snoring, and 53 with OSA) were included. Differences in general demographic characteristics and surface facial morphology among the groups were compared. Risk factors and prediction models for determining the presence of OSA (obstructive sleep apnea-hypopnea index&gt;1) were developed using logistic regression analysis.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The BMI (z-score), tonsil hypertrophy, and lower face width (adjusted age, gender, and BMI z-score) were showed significantly different in children with OSA compared with primary snoring and controls (adjusted p&lt;0.05). The screening model based on clinical features and photography measurements correctly classified 79.3% of the children with 64.2% sensitivity and 89.1% specificity. The area under the curve of the model was 81.0 (95% CI, 73.5–98.4%).</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">A screening model based on clinical features and photography measurements would be helpful in clinical decision-making for children with highly suspected OSA if polysomnography remains inaccessible in resource-stretched healthcare systems.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>obstructive sleep apnea</kwd>
        <kwd>clinical features</kwd>
        <kwd>photographic measurements</kwd>
        <kwd>children</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="open-funder-registry">10.13039/501100001809</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>This study was funded by National Natural Science Foundation of China (81970866), the Consulting research project of Chinese Academy of Engineering (2019-XZ-29).</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="2"/>
        <table-count count="4"/>
        <ref-count count="38"/>
        <page-count count="11"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep-disordered breathing (SDB) describes a range of breathing problems during sleep, from primary snoring (PS) to obstructive sleep apnea (OSA).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The morbidity rate of OSA in children is 1–5%.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> It is a frequent condition characterized by repeated events of partial or complete upper airway obstruction during sleep, and is linked to a series of consequences, including neurodevelopmental disorders, cardiopulmonary dysfunction, behavioral problems, and a reduction in learning ability.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The early diagnosis of OSA is essential for disease management in patients with SDB.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In children, lymphoid tissue hyperplasia is the most common anatomical abnormality associated with OSA, and adenotonsillectomy is an effective treatment for reducing upper airway collapse.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Some patients show incomplete or worsening resolution after surgical intervention.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Upper airway volume in children undergoes dynamic changes due to the inter-reactions of maxillofacial growth, fat deposition, lymphoid tissue hyperplasia, and respiratory patterns. It is therefore critical to understand the complexity and individual differences in the etiology of OSA in children.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Craniofacial morphology is explained by genetic and environmental factors that change during periods of active growth. Compared to Caucasians, OSA in Chinese adults appear to be driven much more by the contribution of anatomical predisposition.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Studies have suggested that the craniofacial features of increased face height, higher mandible angle, mandibular retrognathia, and malocclusion present with higher incidence rates in children with OSA, which may correlate with airway volume.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> However, due to the heterogeneity of methodology, evidence has not confirmed an association between OSA and craniofacial features.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Lateral cephalometry, computed tomography (CT), and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) are used for craniofacial evaluations. These methods have rarely been applied to community or pediatric sleep clinics because of their expense, time-consuming nature, and/or radiation exposure. Photographic measurements, with the advantages of non-invasiveness and easy acceptance, have been applied in adults for craniofacial assessments to predict OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Sutherland also confirmed that clinical photography is feasible for evaluating facial features in children with OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This study aimed to investigate facial photography and clinical features associated with SDB using craniofacial photographic analysis, and to select risk factors for OSA prevalence in children to establish a predictive model for children.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The study protocol was conducted according to the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki and was approved by the appropriate Institutional Review Board of Beijing Tongren Hospital, Capital Medical University (TRECKY2019-057). The participants’ parents signed written informed consent forms before the study for the inclusion of their children in the study and the use of photos and medical records.</citation_analysis></p>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All participants were 5–12 years of age and consulted at the Department of Otolaryngology, Head and Neck Surgery from 2019 to 2021. They had the clinical symptoms reported by guardians (such as snoring, witnessed apneas, mouth breathing, nasal congestion, or hearing loss) and were suspected of combined sleep-disordered breathing. Children’s guardians voluntarily participated in the study and signed informed consent forms.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The exclusion criteria were as follows: (1) failure to cooperate with clinical evaluation, facial photography, and overnight polysomnography; (2) suffering craniofacial trauma and deformity, central sleep apnea, or other severe medical or psychiatric diseases; (3) a history of maxillofacial surgery, adenotonsillectomy, and orthodontic treatment.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The participants were divided into three groups as follows:
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><list list-type="order"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Controls, children with no snoring throughout the night and an obstructive apnea-hypopnea index (OAHI) ≤ 1/h;</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The PS group, children with a snoring complaint and an OAHI ≤ 1/h;</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The OSA group, children with an OAHI &gt; 1/h.</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Physical Examination</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Height (in cm) and weight (kg) were measured after participants removed their shoes and outerwear. The BMI was calculated as the body weight divided by the squared height (kg/m</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">), and z-scores were calculated using the WHO Anthroplus™ software. Neck circumference was measured at the level of the lower edge of the cricoid cartilage. The Neck-to-height ratio was calculated as the neck circumference divided by the height (%). Otolaryngologists evaluated the scale of adenoid, tonsils, tongue, and oropharynx (see </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=400745.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplemental Material</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16–18</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Obstructive Sleep Apnea Questionnaire-18 (OSA-18)</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">OSA-18 questionnaire was accomplished by the parents who fully understand their children’s condition. The Chinese version questionnaire was verified with satisfactory test-retest reliability and internal consistency.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The OSA-18 questionnaire consisted of 18 items classified into five domains: sleep disturbance, physical suffering, emotional distress, daytime problems, and caregiver concerns. Each item was scored on a 7-point ordinal scale (all scores range from 18 to 126).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> OSA-18 questionnaire was used to assess the impact of sleep-related symptoms on quality of life in children.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Polysomnography (PSG)</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">All subjects completed PSG monitoring in the sleep medicine center. We used the data collection system of the Compumedics S series (Compumedics Inc, Australia) and Alice 6 (Phillips Inc, America). The following parameters were measured: electroencephalography (C3/A2, C4/A1), electrooculography, electromyography, electrocardiography, snoring, nasal and oral cannula pressure, thoracoabdominal movement, and pulse oximetry. In addition, we simultaneously captured video and audio throughout the night. Sleep stages and respiratory events were marked by the highly trained, experienced technicians following the AASM guidelines (2016).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Craniofacial Photogrammetry</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Craniofacial Photogrammetry has been widely used to evaluate maxillofacial structures in adults with OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> We applied an accessible smartphone to photograph the front and right sides of the subjects. Subjects were required to look straight and place objects of interest in front if necessary to keep the natural head posture, and their ears were symmetrically visible in the front photo. Subjects were asked to close their mouth with lips slightly touching. The photographer placed a scale plate (3cm nylon washer) on his face. Profile photos were taken after the child turned 90 degrees left.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Quantitative measurements were performed using image analysis software (Image J version 1.8.0, NIH, Bethesda, Maryland, United States). The craniofacial marker points of interest were captured (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). The pixel coordinates (x, y) were pasted to a custom spreadsheet to calculate the distance, angle, and ratio.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Facial landmarks in frontal and profile views.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-115-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Note</bold>: (L) = left side of the participants, (R) = right side of the participants.</attrib><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: Cl, calibration point (L); Cr, calibration point (R); Ns, nasion; Enl, endocanthion (L); Enr, endocanthion (R); Exl, exocanthion (L); Exr, exocanthion (R); T, tragion; Tl, tragion (L); Tr, tragion (R); Prn, prenasale, Sn, subnasion; Anl, ala nasi (L); Anr, ala nasi (R); Las, labrale superior; Lai, labrale inferior; Lal, labrale (L); Lar, labrale (R); Sto, stomion; Ul, upper lip protrusion; Ll, upper lip protrusion; Sl, sublabiale; Pog, pogonion; Me, mentum; Go, gonion; Stl, face point on stomion plane (L); Str, face point on stomion plane (R).</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Front and right side photographs of 20 subjects were selected and measured again after a 2-week interval. The landmark digitization accuracy and test-retest reliability were indicated by intra-class correlation coefficients (ICCs). The ICCs in this study ranged between 0.872 and 0.945.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2006">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Statistical analyses were performed using SPSS 27.0 (IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows, Version 27.0. Armonk, NY: IBM Corp). Continuous variables were analyzed using analysis of variance or the Kruskal–Wallis test. The chi-squared test or Fisher’s exact test was used for categorical variables. We compared the craniofacial parameters in the three groups using analysis of covariance, adjusted for age, sex, and BMI (z-score). Statistical significance was set at P &lt; 0.05. The Bonferroni-corrected significance level was set at P &lt; 0.0167 (0.05/3). Significant variables tested in the case-control analysis were fitted into a univariate logistic regression model, and the factors were pooled into multivariate regressions to further identify significant factors using forward selection (conditional). The performance of the models was evaluated using the sensitivity, specificity, and area under the curve (AUC) of the receiver operating characteristics (ROC).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Participant Characteristics</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">One hundred and seventy-one children were enrolled in the study and 26 were excluded, as shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=400745.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Figure S1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. There were no significant differences in sex, age, and BMI between the included and excluded participants (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=400745.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Table S1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). The selected children were classified into three groups: control (n=30), PS (n=62), and OSA (n=53). In a high-risk population suspected of having adenoid hypertrophy and/or tonsillar hypertrophy, the prevalence of OSA was 36.55%. No significant differences were observed between the controls and children with PS in terms of demographic and respiratory parameters, as shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. When compared with the control and PS groups, individuals with OSA had a higher BMI (z-score), apnea-hypopnea index, and oxygen desaturation index, and lower oxygen saturation (p&lt;0.05).
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Demographic and Respiratory Parameters Between the Participants</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Controls (n=30)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PS (n=62)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSA (n=53)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.07±1.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.88±1.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.75±1.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.723</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender (Male/%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14, 46.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42, 66.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37, 69.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.091</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (<italic toggle="yes">z</italic> score)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32±1.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31±1.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88±1.23<sup>‡§</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.028</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neck circumference (cm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.05[25.40, 27.55]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.56[24.88, 27.70]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.70[25.90, 29.10]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.169</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neck-to-height ratio (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.52±1.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.49±1.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.11±1.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.084</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mouth breathing (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/30.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21, 33.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21, 39.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.656</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30[0.10, 0.22]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66[0.24, 1.20]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00[3.04, 11.71]<sup>‡§</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSaO<sub>2</sub> (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.00[92.00, 97.00]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.00[92.00, 96.00]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.00[85.00, 92.00]<sup>‡§</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ODI (/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10[0.00, 0.50]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20[0.00, 090]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.70[1.90, 11.30]<sup>‡§</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: The bold text highlights the significant differences between the three groups. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>‡</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">p&lt;0.05 between OSA group and control group. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>§</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">p&lt;0.05 between OSA group and PS group.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: PS, primary snoring; BMI, body mass index; AHI, apnea-hypopnea index; LSaO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, the lowest oxygen saturation; ODI, oxygen desaturation index.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Sleep-Related Symptoms and Upper Airway Structure</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">There were significant differences in the quality of life (QOL) as evaluated by the OSA-18 questionnaire between the controls and children with SDB (PS and OSA) (52.43±12.27, 65.63±14.25, and 65.63±14.25, respectively (p&lt;0.001)). Children in the PS and OSA groups showed similar sleep-related symptoms and reduced quality of life (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). The symptoms of loud Snoring, breath holding/pauses, choking or gasping, fragmented sleep and Caregiver concerned not enough air occurred more frequently in children with OSA compared to controls (adjusted p&lt;0.05) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=400745.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Table S2</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Comparison of the Score of OSA-18 and Pharyngeal Examination Between Groups</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Controls (n=30)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PS (n=62)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSA (n=53)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSA-18 questionnaire</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep disturbance (Item1–4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.70±3.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.56±3.56<sup>†</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.21±4.73<sup>‡</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical suffering (Item5–8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.67±3.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.69±2.93<sup>†</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.09±3.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.036</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emotional distress (Item9–11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.77±3.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.45±4.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.17±4.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.188</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daytime problems (Item12–14)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.67±3.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.16±3.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.09±3.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.121</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caregiver concerns (Item15–18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.63±5.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.76±5.30<sup>†</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.36±5.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.033</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.43±12.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.63±14.25<sup>†</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.92±16.31<sup>‡</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Friedman tongue position (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.924</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10, 33.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18, 29.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12, 22.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16, 53.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37, 59.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29, 54.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11, 36.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18, 29.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17, 32.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0, 0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2, 3.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1, 1.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pharyngeal grade (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.028</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2, 6.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4, 6.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0, 0%<sup>§</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9, 30.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19, 30.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8, 15.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12, 40.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29, 46.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24, 45.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7, 23.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10, 16.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21, 39.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tonsil hypertrophy (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8, 26.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22, 35.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34, 64.2%<sup>‡§</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adenoid hypertrophy (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3, 10%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18, 29.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24, 45.3%<sup>‡</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.003</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: The bold text highlights the significant differences between the three groups. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>†</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">P&lt;0.05 between PS group and control group. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>‡</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">p&lt;0.05 between OSA group and control group. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>§</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">p&lt;0.05 between OSA group and PS group.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The pharyngeal structures of the three groups are listed in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. The pharyngeal grade, proportion of tonsil hypertrophy, and adenoid hypertrophy were significantly different among the three groups (p&lt;0.05). Compared with the controls, there were narrow-oropharynx and nasopharyngeal regions in the OSA group due to tonsillar and adenoid enlargements (p&lt;0.001 and p=0.001, respectively). Only a difference in oropharynx narrowing was observed between the PS and OSA groups, including the proportion of tonsil hypertrophy and pharyngeal grade (p=0.002 and p=0.005, respectively). The Friedman tongue position grading was similar in all groups (p=0.924).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Surface Facial Measurements</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Based on the facial landmark measurements, the 30 craniofacial features were compared among the three groups, as shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. The results were summarized as follows according to the different craniofacial regions.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0003" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Craniofacial Photogrammetry - Primary Analysis</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Craniofacial Parameters</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Facial Landmarks</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Unadjusted (M±SD)</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">p value</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Adjusted for Age, Gender, BMI (z Score)(M±SE)</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">p value</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Controls</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PS</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PS</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSA</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Face</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper face width (UFW)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tl-Tr</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.18±0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.16±0.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.58±0.75<sup>§</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.017</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.25±0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.21±0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.48±0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.085</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower face width (LFW)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stl-Str</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.75±0.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.05±1.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.72±1.22<sup>‡§</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;<bold>0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.85±0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.14±0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.57±0.13<sup>‡§</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.003</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper face height (UFH)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ns-Sn</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.32±0.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.16±0.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.97±0.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.429</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.37±0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.49±0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.53±0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.189</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower face height (LFH)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sn-Me</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.39±0.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.49±0.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.51±0.44<sup>‡</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.018</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.39±0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.66±0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.80±0.08<sup>‡</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.017</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Face height (FH)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ns-Me</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.75±0.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.13±1.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.35±0.95<sup>‡</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.025</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.76±0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.15±0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.32±0.10<sup>‡</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper part of LFH (ULFH)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sn-Sto</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06±0.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15±0.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14±0.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.226</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06±0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15±0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.13±0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.185</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower part of LFH (LLFH)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sto-Me</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.31±0.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.48±0.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.70±0.58<sup>‡§</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.008</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.33±0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.51±0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.66±0.07<sup>‡</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.014</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UFW/FH</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ns-Me/Tl-Tr</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14±0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10±0.06<sup>†</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11±0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.034</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15±0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10±0.01<sup>†</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11±0.01<sup>‡</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.009</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LFW/FH</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ns-Me/Stl-Str</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91±0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90±0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94±0.07<sup>‡§</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.003</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92±0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91±0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93±0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.085</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UFH/LFH</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ns-Sn/Sn-Me</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02±0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99±0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96±0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.093</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01±0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98±0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97±0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.304</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ULFH/LLFH</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sn-Sto/Sto-Me</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63±0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63±0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59±0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.038</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63±0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62±0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60±0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.167</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facial convexity angle</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ns-Sn-Sl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">164.77±5.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">161.78±5.19<sup>†</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">164.46±5.09<sup>§</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.007</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">164.68±0.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">162.00±0.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">164.24±0.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.023</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Eyes and Nose</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inner-canthus width</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enl-Enr</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.36±0.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.47±0.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.53±0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.085</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.37±0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.48±0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.51±0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.127</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lateral-canthus width</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exl-Exr</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.36±0.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.38±0.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.55±0.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.173</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.39±0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.40±0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.52±0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.275</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nose width</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anl-Anr</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.33±0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.39±0.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.47±0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.055</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.34±0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.39±0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.47±0.03<sup>‡</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.019</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nasal convexity angle</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pm-Ns-Sn</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.94±2.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.41±2.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.98±2.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.308</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.17±0.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.42±0.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.83±0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.273</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Mouth</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lip width</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lal-Lar</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.72±0.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.84±0.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.94±0.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.082</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.72±0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.84±0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.95±0.05<sup>‡</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.023</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lip height</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Las-Lai</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63±0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60±0.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66±0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.627</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61±0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61±0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66±0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.602</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nasal-upper lip relationship angle</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pm-Sn-Ul</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">122.12±7.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">126.11±8.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125.33±8.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.093</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">122.19±1.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125.94±1.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125.49±1.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.110</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lips relationship angle</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ul-Sto-Ll</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">118.96±11.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">114.52±9.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">114.36±15.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.194</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">118.79±2.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">114.32±1.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">114.69±1.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.237</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower lips-mandibular convexity angle</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ll-Sl-Pog</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">151.71±10.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">146.54±12.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">146.03±13.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.107</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">152.03±2.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">146.42±1.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">145.98±1.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.072</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Mandible and Maxilla</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maxillary length</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-Sn</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.03±1.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.04±1.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.02±0.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.991</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.09±0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.11±0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.91±0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.516</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mandibular length 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-Sl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.53±1.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.53±1.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.60±1.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.938</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.56±0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.61±0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.49±0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.814</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mandibular length 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Go-Me</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.58±1.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.66±0.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.87±1.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.376</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.63±0.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.72±0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.77±0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.795</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mandibular length 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Go-Pog</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.57±1.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.60±1.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.87±1.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.313</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.64±0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.68±0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.74±0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.894</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Posterior mandibular height</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-Go</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.63±0.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.70±0.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.73±0.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.788</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.63±0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.74±0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.66±0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.742</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maxillary depth angle (SNA)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-Ns-Sn</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.91±5.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.40±6.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.45±6.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.472</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.88±1.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.62±0.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.21±0.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.409</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mandibular<break/>depth angle (SNB)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-Ns-Sl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.72±5.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.87±5.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.12±6.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.468</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.61±1.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.19±0.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.82±0.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.658</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maxillary-mandibular relationship angle (ANB)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sn-Ns-Sl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.19±2.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.53±2.44<sup>†</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.33±2.47<sup>§</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.014</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.28±0.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.44±0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.39±0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.037</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mandibular angle</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-Go-Me</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">136.14±7.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">137.5±7.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">134.98±10.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.313</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">135.29±1.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">137.30±1.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">135.72±1.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.477</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The bold text highlights the significant differences between the three groups. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>†</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">P&lt;0.05 between PS group and control group. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>‡</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">p&lt;0.05 between OSA group and control group. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>§</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">p&lt;0.05 between OSA group and PS group. Linear measurements are in cm, angles in degrees.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Face</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Compared with the control group, children in the OSA group had increased face width (lower face width, LFW) and face height (face height, FH; lower face height, LFH), especially the lower part of LFH (LLFH) below the orofacial cleft (adjusted p&lt;0.05). LFH/FH was larger in the OSA group, while UFH/FH was smaller, suggesting a more significant increase in lower facial width in children with OSA. Except for the upper facial width, the facial width and height measurements in the PS group were between those in the OSA group and the control group. In the sagittal plane, the facial convexity angle increased in children in the PS group (p=0.007). Compared to the PS group, the OSA children still had larger facial width and LLHF. Adjusted for age, sex, and BMI (z-score), the LFW is the only craniofacial parameter that effectively differentiates children with OSA from those without OSA (p=0.003).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2005">
        <title>Eyes and Nose</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In the OSA group, the inner-canthus width, lateral-canthus width, and nose width tended to increase, which was not statistically significant. After controlling for sex, age, and BMI (z-score), the nasal width of children in the OSA group was significantly higher than that of the control group (adjusted p&lt;0.05). There was no significant difference in nasal convexity angle among the groups.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2006">
        <title>Mouth</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The lip morphology of children in the OSA group was similar to that of non-OSA children, including lip width, lip height, and upper and lower lip angle relationship. After controlling for sex, age, and BMI (z-score), the lip width of children in the OSA group was significantly higher than that of the control group (adjusted p&lt;0.05).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2007">
        <title>Mandible and Maxilla</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">No significant differences were found in maxillary length, mandibular length, and posterior mandibular height in the groups (p&gt;0.05). Compared with the control group, there was a trend of increasing maxillary depth angle (SNA) in the PS group, and SNA and mandibular depth angle (SNB) in the OSA group. Maxillary-mandibular relationship angle (ANB) was significantly increased in the PS group (PS 8.53±2.44 vs controls 7.19±2.72 vs OSA 7.33±2.47, p=0.014). After matching sex, age, and BMI (z-score), the above differences remained statistically significant (p=0.037).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2008">
        <title>Risk Factors for OSA in Children</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">The potential risk factors for OSA are presented in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=400745.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Table S3</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative">. The BMI (z-score), neck-to-height ratio(%), sleep disturbance scores, pharyngeal grade, tonsil hypertrophy, and adenoid hypertrophy are risk factors for OSA in children (p&lt;0.05). Significant craniofacial risk factors for children with OSA were nose width, UFW, LFW, and LLFH. The higher the above structural measurements, the higher the risk of OSA in children.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We developed predictive models for OSA in children based on clinical symptoms, physical examination, and craniofacial measurement parameters. Multivariate stepwise logistic regression and ROC curve analyses are shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">, respectively. Lower face width was the only included craniofacial parameter for OSA predicting (OR 1.703, 95% CI 1.255–2.310), which can significantly improve the model’s specificity to 73.9%. Based on the score of the OSA-18 questionnaire (Item 1–4), adenoid hypertrophy, pharyngeal grade, and lower face width, the model achieved the best performance, with 64.2% sensitivity and 89.1% specificity at the best cutoff point (0.479), classifying 79.3% of the children correctly. The AUC of the model was 81.0 (95% CI, 73.5–98.4%), the positive predictive value (PPV) was 76.0%, and the negative predictive value (NPV) was 81.4%.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The Logistic Regression Model for Predicting Children with Obstructive Sleep Apnea</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beta Estimate (SE)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR [95% CI]</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUC[95% CI]</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Youden Index</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accuracy</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensitivity</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specificity</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSA-18 questionnaire (Item 1–4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.171</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.187[1.087, 1.295]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.707[0.617, 0.796]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.334</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.703</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.660</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.674</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.868</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (<italic toggle="yes">z</italic> score)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.405</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.500[1.096, 2.054]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.750[0.668, 0.832]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.455</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.690</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.792</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.663</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tonsil hypertrophy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.364</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.911[1.840, 8.313]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adenoid hypertrophy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.006</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.734[1.242, 6.022]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.518</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower face width</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.532</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.703[1.255, 2.310]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.691[0.601, 0.781]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.343</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.697</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.604</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.739</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.046</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSA-18 questionnaire (Item 1–4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.133[1.030, 1.247]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.810[0.735, 0.984]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.533</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.793</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.642</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.891</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adenoid hypertrophy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.038</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.824[1.152, 6.925]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pharyngeal grade</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.935</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.548[1.468, 4.424]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower face width</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.543</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.721[1.220, 2.428]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−11.027</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Model 1, the prediction model of subjective symptoms; Model 2, the prediction model of physical examinations; Model 3, the prediction model of craniofacial measurement; Model 4, the ensemble prediction model.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">ROC curves for predictive model.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-115-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: Model 1: OSA-18 questionnaire (Item 1–4); Model 2: BMI (<italic toggle="yes">z</italic> score), tonsil hypertrophy, adenoid hypertrophy; Model 3: Lower face width; Model 4: OSA-18 questionnaire (Item 1–4), pharyngeal grade, adenoid hypertrophy, lower face width.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">This prospective study comprehensively compared the symptoms, signs, and facial morphology in a population at high risk of SDB aged 5–12 years, summarized the clinical characteristics of children with OSA and developed a prediction model combining craniofacial parameters for children with OSA. The lower face width was a valid indicator for identifying children with OSA. In addition, the prediction model incorporating the score of the OSA-18 questionnaire (Item 1–4), adenoid hypertrophy, pharyngeal grade, and lower facial width correctly classified 79.3% of children at high risk for the disease.</citation_analysis></p>
      <sec id="s0004-s2001">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics of Children with OSA</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Pediatric OSA is a heterogeneous diseases, in which the risk factors and clinical characteristics vary with subjects included. In children with 5–12 years, we analyzed the different clinical impressions in the control, PS, and OSA groups using an available questionnaire as well as physical examinations. The OSA-18 questionnaire scores could distinguish children with and without SDB, but it was not an effective tool for recognizing OSA and PS. Parents’ poor awareness of disease severity and excessive concerns about their children’s sleep problems are possible causes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> The BMI (z-score), neck-to-height ratio(%), sleep disturbance scores, pharyngeal grade, tonsil hypertrophy, and adenoid hypertrophy are risk factors for OSA in children (p&lt;0.05). As in previous studies, obesity, pharyngeal lymphoid hyperplasia and arrowing of the pharyngeal space were important etiological components of OSA prevalence in Chinese children. Unlike some studies,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> our study did not find an effect of mouth breathing on OSA. The reason for this is considered to be that the frequency, intensity and duration of mouth breathing in children have not been assessed in detail, which need to be further explored. Friedman et al showed OSA severity in adult were significantly association with Friedman tongue position (FTP), with a a correlation of 0.351 (0.094–0.564, P&lt;0.01).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, FTP is not commonly used as a method of airway assessment in children, which may be related to poor cooperation in children and low inter-examiner agreement.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Our study also confirmed that there was no significant difference in FTP scores between the groups of children.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2002">
        <title>Facial Features of Children with OSA Obtained by Craniofacial Photography</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In most studies, the maxillofacial assessment method used was cephalometry, and the collected parameters mainly included the angles and distance in the sagittal plane. The contribution of maxillofacial factors to OSA onset in children remains controversial.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Deng and Gao showed that children in the OSA group presented with a retrusive mandible, deficient chin, and a long lower face.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Furthermore, Di Francesco et al found that dolichocephalic facial pattern (r=−0.33), mandibular plane (r=0.48), and facial depth (r=−0.33) were correlated with OSA among boys.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> However, other studies did not report significant differences in craniofacial morphology.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29–31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> OSA with risk factors and clinical features that vary with age among pediatric patients,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> which may explain the heterogeneous reported results.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Surface facial parameters containing skeletal and soft tissues reflect phenotypic information regarding upper airway structures.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> We comprehensively analyzed the distances, ratios, and angles of both the frontal and profile views, observing a trend towards increased coronal and vertical plane distances in children in the OSA group, which was similarly observed in adults.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Lee et al discovered that the strongest correlations were demonstrated between tongue volume and face width when compared with BMI in adults.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Our study identified LFW as a marker that can distinguish OSA from other children. The results still remained significant after adjusting for BMI, age, and sex. LFW may better reflect airway structure and fat distribution.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In the profile view, there were controversial viewpoints on cephalometric angles of children (maxillary depth angle, mandibular depth angle, ANB), which was explained by the heterogeneity between the studies and could be regarded as having marginal clinical significance.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> A study of 382 children aged 6–8 years reported an association between a more convex facial profile and higher SDB risk.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> We found that a greater ANB and convex facial profiles were observed only in the PS group after adjusting for BMI (z-score), and profile angles were insufficient to distinguish between the controls and patients with OSA. Whether the increased angular of ANB and convex facial profiles are compensatory changes in children with snoring who do not develop OSA needs further study. Our study also found an increase in nasal width and mouth width in children with OSA, and we speculate that this morphological change may be an adaptive change to the increased airway resistance in children.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Based on craniofacial photography, studies in adults suggest that Asian and Caucasian patients with OSA have similar craniofacial morphology compared to controls, including larger face width, mandibular width, and cervicomental angle.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The craniofacial characteristics of Chinese children were similar to those of children in the Sutherland et al study (including 73.1% Caucasian), with OSA children tending larger facial convexity angle, longer lower facial height, and smaller maxillary-mandibular relationship angle relative to children with primary snoring.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> However, Sutherland’s study did not include frontal measurement variables to compare face width in the two groups of children, and fewer subjects were included. Our approach allows for more extensive validation. Asian adults appear to have more severe OSA at lower levels of obesity, suggesting that skeletal restriction may be more important for OSA risk in Asians,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> which have inferior positioning of the hyoid bone and retropositioning of the mandible examined by the CT scans. No studies have yet revealed the contribution of craniofacial restriction and increased soft tissue to OSA in children of different races. Moreover, large-scale phenotype studies of children need fully consider the confounding factors, such as the degree of obesity, adenotonsillar hypertrophy, mouth breathing, and growth status affecting the maxillofacial structure.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2003">
        <title>Applicability of Craniofacial Feature-Based Models for Predicting OSA</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Overnight polysomnography remains the gold standard for diagnosing OSA, but this method is limited by its availability and accessibility. Questionnaires and physical examinations are often essential for OSA screening. The OSA-18 questionnaire was used for QOL assessment in children, which hardly predicted OSA due to its poor sensitivity (0.53).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In our study, the total and five domain scores of the OSA-18 were used in the logistic regression analysis; items of sleep disturbance achieved higher accuracy (70.3%) and sensitivity (66.0%). In adults, craniofacial photographic measurements (face width, eye width, cervicomental angle, and mandibular length) correctly classified 76.1% of individuals with or without OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In children, only the LFW could be used for OSA prediction in high-risk children, with a sensitivity of 60.4% and a specificity of 73.9%. Based on symptom questionnaires, pharyngeal structures, and facial measurements, the model could effectively distinguish between children without the disease. Continuous follow-up or sleep breathing monitoring assisted in clinical decision-making for children with highly suspected OSA. Although we fully considered the effects of obesity, anatomy, and lymphoproliferation in children, non-anatomical factors remain an essential part of the phenotyping analyses and for improving the prediction ability in future studies, such as loop gain.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Limitations</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The present study had some limitations. First, the proportion of children with moderate-to-severe OSA in the study sample was small, and a subgroup analysis was not performed according to disease severity. Second, two-dimensional photographs might still be unable to provide nonlinear information, such as shape and contour; further studies are still needed to demonstrate the relationship between surface facial structures and the soft tissue and skeletal structures of the upper airway. Third, the external validity of predictive models requires further validation, and the cost and benefit of medical care using this predictive model in children require further cost-benefit or cost-utility analyses.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This study demonstrated the different clinical manifestations and facial morphologies of children with OSA. Obesity, narrowing of the pharynx, and lower face imbalance can distinguish children with OSA from primary snorers. The addition of surface craniofacial structures improves the performance of prediction models in children, which will help with the early identification of OSA in children if PSG remains inaccessible in resource-stretched healthcare systems.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors would like to thank the study participants, technologists, and physicians at the Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Beijing Tongren Hospital.</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">AHI, Apnea-hypopnea Index; BMI, Body Mass Index; ICCs, Intra-class Correlation Coefficients; LSaO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, the Lowest Oxygen Saturation; OAHI, Obstructive Sleep Apnea-hypopnea Index; ODI, Oxygen Desaturation Index; OSA, Obstructive Sleep Apnea; SDB, Sleep-disordered Breathing; PS, Primary Snoring; PSG, Polysomnography.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0008">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">All authors contributed to data analysis, drafting or revising the article, have agreed on the journal to which the article will be submitted, gave final approval of the version to be published, and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0009">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Sheldon</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferber</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kryger</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <source><italic toggle="yes">Principles and Practice of Pediatric Sleep Medicine</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Elsevier Inc</publisher-name>; <year>2014</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Marcus</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brooks</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Draper</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, et al; <collab>American academy of pediatrics</collab>. <article-title>Diagnosis and management of childhood obstructive sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatrics</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>130</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>576</fpage>–<lpage>584</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2012-1671</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22926173</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nosetti</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zaffanello</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Katz</surname>
<given-names>ES</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Twenty-year follow-up of children with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1573</fpage>–<lpage>1581</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.9922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35164899</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Capdevila</surname>
<given-names>OS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kheirandish-Gozal</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dayyat</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Pediatric obstructive sleep apnea: complications, management, and long-term outcomes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Am Thorac Soc</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>274</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1513/pats.200708-138MG</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18250221</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>CN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kang</surname>
<given-names>KT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yao</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Changes in cone-beam computed tomography pediatric airway measurements after adenotonsillectomy in patients with OSA</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>148</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>621</fpage>–<lpage>629</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaoto.2022.0925</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35616957</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>YS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guilleminault</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Treatment outcomes of adenotonsillectomy for children with obstructive sleep apnea: a prospective longitudinal study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.3310</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24470697</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Maeda</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsuiki</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nakata</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Craniofacial contribution to residual obstructive sleep apnea after adenotonsillectomy in children: a preliminary study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>540</fpage>–<lpage>547</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.4028</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>O’Driscoll</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Landry</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pham</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The physiological phenotype of obstructive sleep apnea differs between caucasian and Chinese patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>zsz186</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsz186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31418028</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sutherland</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>RWW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>TO</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Craniofacial phenotyping in Chinese and caucasian patients with sleep apnea: influence of ethnicity and sex</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1143</fpage>–<lpage>1151</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.7212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29991423</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>de Oliveira</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pinheiro</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Freitas</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Relationship between craniofacial and dental arch morphology with pharyngeal airway space in adolescents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Orofac Orthop</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>. <comment>English</comment>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00056-022-00403-9</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Flores-Mir</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Korayem</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heo</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Craniofacial morphological characteristics in children with obstructive sleep apnea syndrome: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Dent Assoc</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>144</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>269</fpage>–<lpage>277</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14219/jada.archive.2013.0113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23449902</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fagundes</surname>
<given-names>NCF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gianoni-Capenakas</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heo</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Craniofacial features in children with obstructive sleep apnea: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1865</fpage>–<lpage>1875</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.9904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35074045</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grunstein</surname>
<given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Craniofacial phenotyping in obstructive sleep apnea--a novel quantitative photographic approach</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19189777</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The predictive value of photogrammetry for obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>202</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.8836</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32996460</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sutherland</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weichard</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davey</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Craniofacial photography and association with sleep-disordered breathing severity in children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1173</fpage>–<lpage>1179</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-019-01928-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31468365</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Friedman</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tanyeri</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>La Rosa</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Clinical predictors of obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Laryngoscope</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>109</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1901</fpage>–<lpage>1907</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005537-199912000-00002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10591345</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Brodsky</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Modern assessment of tonsils and adenoids</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatr Clin North Am</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1551</fpage>–<lpage>1569</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0031-3955(16)36806-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2685730</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schwab</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leinwand</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bearn</surname>
<given-names>CB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Digital morphometrics: a new upper airway phenotyping paradigm in OSA</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>152</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>330</fpage>–<lpage>342</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chest.2017.05.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28526655</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Y-S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hwang</surname>
<given-names>F-M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>C-H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Clinical manifestations of pediatric obstructive sleep apnea syndrome: clinical utility of the Chinese-version obstructive sleep apnea questionaire-18</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>752</fpage>–<lpage>762</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pcn.12331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26129934</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Franco</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names> Jr</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosenfeld</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rao</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>First place--resident clinical science award 1999. Quality of life for children with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>123</volume>(<issue>1 Pt 1</issue>):<fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/mhn.2000.105254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10889473</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Malhotra</surname>
<given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kirsch</surname>
<given-names>DB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kristo</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, et al; <collab>American Academy of Sleep Medicine Board of Directors</collab>. <article-title>Polysomnography for obstructive sleep apnea should include arousal-based scoring: an American academy of sleep medicine position statement</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1245</fpage>–<lpage>1247</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.7234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29991439</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Carroll</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McColley</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marcus</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Inability of clinical history to distinguish primary snoring from obstructive sleep apnea syndrome in children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>108</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>610</fpage>–<lpage>618</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.108.3.610</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7656605</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Markkanen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rautiainen</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Himanen</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Snoring toddlers with and without obstructive sleep apnoea differed with regard to snoring time, adenoid size and mouth breathing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Paediatr</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>110</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>977</fpage>–<lpage>984</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/apa.15496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32734640</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Soh</surname>
<given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rowe</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davey</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The OSA-5: development and validation of a brief questionnaire screening tool for obstructive sleep apnea in children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>113</volume>:<fpage>62</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijporl.2018.07.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30174012</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Friedman</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hamilton</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Samuelson</surname>
<given-names>CG</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Diagnostic value of the Friedman tongue position and Mallampati classification for obstructive sleep apnea: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>148</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>540</fpage>–<lpage>547</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0194599812473413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23322629</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sundman</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fehrm</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Friberg</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Low inter-examiner agreement of the Friedman staging system indicating limited value in patient selection</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>275</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1541</fpage>–<lpage>1545</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00405-018-4970-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29663113</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Deng</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A case--control study of craniofacial features of children with obstructed sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1219</fpage>–<lpage>1227</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-011-0636-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22302200</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Di Francesco</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monteiro</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paulo</surname>
<given-names>MLDM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Craniofacial morphology and sleep apnea in children with obstructed upper airways: differences between genders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>616</fpage>–<lpage>620</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2011.12.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22459090</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Au</surname>
<given-names>CT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>KCC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Potential anatomic markers of obstructive sleep apnea in prepubertal children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1979</fpage>–<lpage>1986</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.7518</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30518439</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pirilä-Parkkinen</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Löppönen</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nieminen</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cephalometric evaluation of children with nocturnal sleep-disordered breathing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Orthod</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>662</fpage>–<lpage>671</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ejo/cjp162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20305055</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>[Cephalometry study of craniofacial growth in mixed dentition with OSAHS children]</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lin Chung Er Bi Yan Hou Tou Jing Wai Ke Za Zhi</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>1127</fpage>–<lpage>1129</lpage>. <comment>Chinese</comment>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23477119</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chuang</surname>
<given-names>HH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hsu</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chuang</surname>
<given-names>LP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Differences in anthropometric and clinical features among preschoolers, school-age children, and adolescents with obstructive sleep apnea-a hospital-based study in Taiwan</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>4663</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph17134663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32610444</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ikävalko</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Närhi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lakka</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Lateral facial profile may reveal the risk for sleep disordered breathing in children--the PANIC-study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Odontol Scand</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>73</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>550</fpage>–<lpage>555</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/00016357.2014.997795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25892581</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sutherland</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petocz</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Craniofacial phenotyping for prediction of obstructive sleep apnoea in a Chinese population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Respirology</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1118</fpage>–<lpage>1125</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/resp.12792</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27083503</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Incerti Parenti</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fiordelli</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bartolucci</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Diagnostic accuracy of screening questionnaires for obstructive sleep apnea in children: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>101464</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2021.101464</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33827032</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>RWW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petocz</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Prvan</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prediction of obstructive sleep apnea with craniofacial photographic analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19189778</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Amin</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khoo</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Loop gain in paediatric sleep-disordered breathing: a different story from adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Respirology</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1119</fpage>–<lpage>1120</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/resp.13897</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32602225</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bokov</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matrot</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Medjahdi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Crosssectional study of loop gain abnormalities in childhood obstructive sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>172</fpage>–<lpage>178</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.01.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32092476</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
