<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37032817</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">10075216</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">395732</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S395732</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Daytime Sleep-Tracking Performance of Four Commercial Wearable Devices During Unrestricted Home Sleep</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Chinoy et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Chinoy et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6613-6654</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Chinoy</surname>
            <given-names>Evan D</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cuellar</surname>
            <given-names>Joseph A</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jameson</surname>
            <given-names>Jason T</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Markwald</surname>
            <given-names>Rachel R</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Sleep, Tactical Efficiency, and Endurance Laboratory, Warfighter Performance Department, Naval Health Research Center</institution>, <addr-line>San Diego</addr-line>, <addr-line>CA</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Leidos, Inc</institution>, <addr-line>San Diego</addr-line>, <addr-line>CA</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Rachel R Markwald, <institution>Sleep, Tactical Efficiency, and Endurance Laboratory, Warfighter Performance Department, Naval Health Research Center</institution>, <addr-line>140 Sylvester Road</addr-line>, <addr-line>San Diego</addr-line>, <addr-line>CA</addr-line>, <addr-line>92106</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>, <phone>Tel +1 619 767 4494</phone>, Email rachel.r.markwald.civ@health.mil</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>01</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2023</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>15</volume>
      <fpage>151</fpage>
      <lpage>164</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>07</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2023 Chinoy et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Chinoy et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Previous studies have found that many commercial wearable devices can accurately track sleep-wake patterns in laboratory or home settings. However, nearly all previous studies tested devices under conditions with fixed time in bed (TIB) and during nighttime sleep episodes only. Despite its relevance to shift workers and others with irregular sleep schedules, it is largely unknown how devices track daytime sleep. Therefore, we tested the sleep-tracking performance of four commercial wearable devices during unrestricted home daytime sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Participants and Methods</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Participants were 16 healthy young adults (6 men, 10 women; 26.6 ± 4.6 years, mean ± SD) with habitual daytime sleep schedules. Participants slept at home for 1 week under unrestricted conditions (ie, self-selecting TIB) using a set of four commercial wearable devices and completed reference sleep logs. Wearables included the Fatigue Science ReadiBand, Fitbit Inspire HR, Oura Ring, and Polar Vantage V Titan. Daytime sleep episode TIB biases and frequencies of missed and false-positive daytime sleep episodes were examined.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">TIB bias was low in general for all devices on most daytime sleep episodes, but some exhibited large biases (eg, &gt;1 h). Total missed daytime sleep episodes were as follows: Fatigue Science: 3.6%; Fitbit: 4.8%; Oura: 6.0%; Polar: 37.3%. Missed episodes occurred most often when TIB was short (eg, naps &lt;4 h).</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">When daytime sleep episodes were recorded, the devices generally exhibited similar performance for tracking TIB (ie, most episodes had low bias). However, the devices failed to detect some daytime episodes, which occurred most often when TIB was short, but varied across devices (especially Polar, which missed over one-third of episodes). Findings suggest that accurate daytime sleep tracking is largely achievable with commercial wearable devices. However, performance differences for missed recordings suggest that some devices vary in reliability (especially for naps), but improvements could likely be made with changes to algorithm sensitivities.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>validation</kwd>
        <kwd>consumer sleep technology</kwd>
        <kwd>naps</kwd>
        <kwd>habitual sleep</kwd>
        <kwd>shift work</kwd>
        <kwd>sleep diary</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="4"/>
        <table-count count="2"/>
        <ref-count count="46"/>
        <page-count count="14"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep-tracking technology for consumer, research, or clinical use has grown rapidly over the past decade, with new devices and algorithms being released onto the market faster than researchers can evaluate their performance.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> While this upward trend in use and access to sleep-tracking technology has brought much deserved and overdue attention to the importance of sleep among health-care professionals and the public, the strengths and limitations of particular devices and algorithms are still being determined (and may change over time as technologies are regularly updated).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Developing standards and best practices will rely on robust and rapid testing under complementary protocols to evaluate different areas of device performance.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5–8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> This information is essential for obtaining accurate and reliable sleep device data for individual consumers and for ensuring that rigorous standards are met for research or clinical uses.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">An important area of wearable device performance is their ability to track daytime sleep episodes. However, relatively little is known about their performance under daytime conditions, as these devices are nearly always tested for their ability to track nighttime sleep episodes only. Also, devices are most often tested under controlled conditions such as in a sleep laboratory under a fixed time in bed (TIB). This type of testing protocol typically utilizes gold-standard polysomnography (PSG) as a reference, because PSG provides high-quality data on initial device sleep-tracking performance and thus has been recommended as the first step for evaluating devices as part of the “validation” process.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Most recent studies of newer devices have indeed found that their sleep-tracking performance is generally good, with many devices performing better than the first commercial wearable devices released around a decade ago,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10–12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and at levels that meet or exceed research-grade actigraphy</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13–17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> (the standard method for mobile sleep-wake tracking).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, daytime sleep tracking has still been absent from device performance evaluation studies,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> despite its clear relevance for individuals and communities who often sleep at irregular or daytime hours and in shorter or multiple daily bouts (eg, shift workers, military personnel, first responders, athletes, children, and patients with certain sleep or circadian disorders). For many of those people, daytime sleep is an essential part of their overall sleep and plays a critical role in maintaining their optimal health and performance that comes from achieving the recommended total daily sleep duration.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> This lack of research into daytime sleep evaluation with new devices is underscored by recent guidance from a group of sleep technology experts from the Sleep Research Society, who concluded that the “current evidence does not support the use of consumer wearable devices for daytime sleep assessment” and therefore recommended that devices “should not be used to assess daytime sleep or naps” for research or clinical purposes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">One of the key measures of a device’s real-world sleep-tracking performance is potential bias in the TIB domain.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Accurate TIB readings (ie, with small bias) are critical, because if a device cannot accurately identify the actual window of time when an individual attempts to sleep, then the other sleep-tracking outcomes it generates (eg, total sleep time (TST), sleep efficiency, sleep onset latency, wake after sleep onset) will likely be biased as well. Unfortunately, many real-world habits during wake (such as sedentariness) produce patterns of physical and physiological activity (eg, reduced movement and heart rate) that may be difficult to differentiate from signals generated when someone tries to fall asleep, which could confuse device sleep-tracking algorithms. Despite its importance, TIB tracking has also not been an outcome variable in most device performance evaluation studies because testing protocols largely control for environment, participant behavior, and TIB. In our previous device performance evaluation study of nighttime sleep under unrestricted real-world conditions,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> we found that four commercial wearable devices generally exhibited good performance with low biases for TIB and most other sleep-wake outcomes on the majority of nights. However, on some nights TIB biases were large (eg, &gt;1 h), which is a concern for the reliability and accuracy of data from wearables that automatically and passively track sleep patterns in real-world conditions. Such biases, even when occurring infrequently, could lead to reduced trust in a device for monitoring sleep and greater risk for discontinuing use of the device altogether. Additionally, it is likely that some proprietary commercial device algorithms are designed primarily for detecting nighttime sleep, so it is unknown how well these commercial devices perform at recording daytime sleep episodes at all.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Therefore, in the current study, we evaluated the daytime sleep-tracking performance of four commercial wearable devices that we tested previously under unrestricted nighttime conditions at home.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> In particular, we aimed to evaluate the performance of four wearable devices to track daytime sleep episodes for (1) bias in sleep timing outcomes (TIB, start time of sleep episode, end time of sleep episode) and (2) the frequencies of missed daytime sleep episodes and false-positive episodes mislabeled as sleep by the devices.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Participants and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Healthy young adults (n=16, 10 women, 6 men; 26.6 ± 4.6 years, mean ± SD) participated. Screening consisted of a self-report medical history questionnaire that assessed the following exclusion criteria: age &lt;18 or &gt;40 years, body mass index &lt;18.5 or ≥30.0 kg/m</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, any diagnosed sleep, mental health, or other medical disorder, use of any illegal drugs or any sleep medications (over-the-counter or prescription) in the previous month, current pregnancy, and any physical or living conditions affecting the ability to sleep uninterrupted. Participants also had to report a habitual schedule of regular daytime sleep, which, for enrollment, was defined as sleeping between 06:00 and 22:00 with TIB ≥1 h at least twice weekly.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The study protocol was approved by the Naval Health Research Center Institutional Review Board and was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. Participants provided informed consent prior to the study and were compensated with gift cards.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Study Protocol</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Participants were given a set of four commercial sleep-tracking devices to use, while they slept at home for one week. They also completed detailed sleep logs to report their sleep schedule after each sleep episode. The timing and duration of their sleep episodes were self-selected and unrestricted, except for the requirement to attempt a minimum of two daytime (occurring between 06:00 and 22:00) sleep episodes during the study week. Thus, the number, timing, and sequence of daytime and nighttime sleep episodes logged by each participant varied, and only the qualifying daytime sleep episodes were included in the final analyses (see </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=395732.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Supplemental Figures S1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=395732.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">S2</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> for depictions of individual participant sleep schedules).</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The devices were worn simultaneously during all sleep episodes, along with a research-grade actigraphy watch (Actiwatch 2; Philips Respironics, Inc.; Murrysville, PA, USA) that was not part of the current analyses. Within one hour of awakening after each sleep episode across the study week (whether occurring in daytime, nighttime, or as a nap), participants were instructed to report their bed and wake times, and the times they physically entered and exited bed, using a digital sleep log (based on the consensus sleep diary</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) using an iPad tablet computer (Apple Inc.; Cupertino, CA, USA) that we provided. The sleep log was implemented in Smartabase (Fusion Sport; Broomfield, CO, USA), a data capture and management system application (“app”). Participants were also instructed to wear the devices as much as possible when not sleeping, but they could remove them during wake times if needed (eg, charging the devices, whenever devices could interfere with work duties, while showering or doing activities that could damage or submerge the devices). In such cases, participants were instructed to log these times using the Smartabase app.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Alcohol intake was not allowed during the study week. No other restrictions were placed on participants during the study week. They could consume caffeine and engage in other activities such as exercise during the study, but they were instructed to log these behaviors daily on the Smartabase app before each sleep episode. To improve the accuracy of sleep log entries and to ensure that the devices were charged and working correctly, researchers completed daily compliance checks online by viewing data on individual device apps and Smartabase and, if needed, promptly provided feedback to participants to enter their log data and sync devices.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Sleep-Tracking Devices</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The same four commercial sleep-tracking wearable devices were tested in this study as in our previous study,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> in which we evaluated the sleep-tracking performance of a set of devices during unrestricted nighttime sleep with a similar weeklong protocol design. However, unlike in our previous study, participants did not wear an electroencephalography headband device. The four devices tested were the Fatigue Science ReadiBand</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>TM</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> (version 5; Fatigue Science; Vancouver, BC, Canada), Fitbit</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>TM</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Inspire HR (Fitbit, Inc.; San Francisco, CA, USA), Oura</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>TM</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Ring (Gen 2; ŌURA Health Oy; Oulu, Finland), and Polar</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>®</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Vantage V Titan (Polar Electro Oy; Kempele, Finland).</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">At the start of the study, researchers reviewed the procedures with participants and instructed them on how to wear the devices comfortably and correctly. The four wrist devices (which included Actiwatch 2; data not shown) were worn in pairs on each wrist in the same manner as in our previous study.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The Actiwatch 2 and Polar Vantage V Titan were worn as a pair on one wrist, and the Fatigue Science ReadiBand and Fitbit Inspire HR were worn as a pair on the other wrist (with the Polar and Fitbit devices always worn closer to the wrist, because those two devices contained photoplethysmography [PPG] heart rate sensors that should be placed closer to the wrist). Wrist placement for each pair of devices was counterbalanced between participants, with half assigned to wear each pair on either their dominant or non-dominant wrist at the beginning of the study. After the fourth study day, participants were instructed to switch the device pairs to the other wrist, allowing an approximately equal number of assessment nights for each wrist device on either the dominant or non-dominant wrist. However, participants wore the Oura Ring on their non-dominant ring finger during the entire study week. Participants were instructed to keep devices charged as needed and to sync the data using their respective apps on the tablet within an hour of waking up from each sleep episode. See </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=395732.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Supplemental Materials</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> for details on device software and firmware versions.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Data Export and Preprocessing Procedures</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Device data were exported from the respective device apps and from the following online device account website portals from each device company, which allowed additional data access and management of participant accounts: Readi for the Fatigue Science ReadiBand, Oura Teams for the Oura Ring, and Polar AccessLink API for the Polar Vantage V Titan. Fitbit Inspire HR data were exported via Fitabase (Small Steps Labs, LLC; San Diego, CA, USA), a licensed third-party data management platform that allows access to Fitbit account data. Apps and online device account portals sometimes did not register data from every sleep episode that was present in the sleep log. Therefore, sleep episode data that were not present originally on the online device account portal but were present on the device app, or vice versa, were all exported or transcribed from either data source for inclusion in the final analyses. At the time of data collection, certain data export features were not available in Oura Teams and have since been added, including the export of all “sleep periods” (this includes episodes categorized as “rest” in addition to those categorized as sleep or naps). Although these additional data were available, some identified “rest” periods still did not meet the sleep duration criteria for a nap as defined by Oura (TST between 15 min and 3 h). Thus, “rest” periods with less than 15 min of scored TST did not qualify as naps and were not included in the analyses. Additionally, when a sleep episode occurs that is identified by the Oura algorithm as a nap or likely nap, the Oura app prompts the user to “confirm” the nap so that it can be added into the sleep data output (which also uses the nap to update the daily readiness and sleep scores). However, the nap confirmation prompt is available only within the same day. Since data collection in this study was passive and participants were not instructed specifically to confirm naps using the app prompts, it is possible that some naps were “unconfirmed” by the participant. As a result, these naps may instead have been categorized as a “rest” period and would thus have appeared in the Oura app activity data log, not in the app’s sleep data. However, unconfirmed naps would appear in the Oura Teams sleep periods export file and were used for analysis. For each device, TIB was the total time from the start to the end of the recording for each sleep episode (ie, the TST and the total wake occurring within each recorded episode).</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All 16 participants completed the weeklong study protocol. However, because sleep schedules were self-selected and unrestricted, the total number of sleep episodes that each participant had over the study week varied and the number of episodes that were classified into “daytime” versus “nighttime” categories varied as well. Across participants, a total of 83 reported sleep episodes (ranging from 2 to 9 per participant) met the criteria for daytime sleep. For this analysis, daytime episodes were defined as those with TIB starting between 06:00 and 20:00 and ending before midnight of the same calendar day. Additional information on individual sleep schedules and qualifying daytime sleep episodes for analysis are depicted in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=395732.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figures S1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=395732.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">S2</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Devices each collected sleep data passively and automatically, which is the default by which most users track their sleep with wearable devices. Our goal was to evaluate the devices in conditions that closely mirrored the daily use and real-world settings of typical users. To this end, we used only the sleep-tracking data that were originally provided by the device apps and data export portals regarding whether a device recorded a sleep episode and the timing/duration of that episode (ie, without additional editing to the device app inputs/outputs that some devices allow for users or researchers, to potentially correct TIB errors or log missed sleep episodes). For additional context, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=395732.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Supplemental Figure S3</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> depicts data from three example participants showing all their device TIBs alongside their sleep log TIBs across the study week.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">The two aims of this study were to evaluate daytime sleep episodes tracked from wearable devices for (1) bias in sleep timing outcomes (TIB, start time of sleep episode, end time of sleep episode) and (2) the frequencies of missing sleep episode recordings and false-positive episodes mislabeled as sleep. For Aim 1, we adopted the analysis standards (with minor modifications) recommended for evaluating summary bias for sleep devices as outlined by Menghini et al,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> which we had also applied in our previous device performance evaluation studies.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Since the focus of Aim 1 was on evaluating sleep timing outcomes (and not the epoch-by-epoch classifications for sleep-wake or sleep stages that we reported for these devices previously</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">), statistical output for this study included the means and bias summary tables and Bland-Altman plots</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> to depict performance against the sleep episode times reported in the reference sleep log. Additionally, repeated measures correlations</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> between the differences in the times reported for physically entering and exiting bed and the biases for device sleep start and end times were also calculated to evaluate whether observed device sleep timing biases were potentially related to the reported amount of time spent physically in bed outside of the TIB window for sleep (ie, as a measure of potential sedentary waking activity in bed such as reading, smartphone use, or watching television). For Aim 2, bar charts were constructed to depict the frequency of devices detecting versus missing daytime sleep episode recordings in aggregate and across hourly TIB bins. Performance for Aim 2 was also evaluated against daytime sleep episodes reported in the reference sleep log.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">For two participants, each had one daytime sleep episode recorded by Polar Vantage V Titan that was an extreme outlier on sleep timing outcomes (ie, sleep recordings continued for 291 and 758 min, respectively, after the end of those sleep episodes, despite reporting removal of the devices soon after those sleep episodes ended). Therefore, the Polar device data for those two episodes were included only in the frequency of missing sleep recordings analysis for Aim 2, but were excluded from the sleep timing bias analyses for Aim 1. No other data recorded from the devices were excluded from any analyses.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All analyses were conducted using the statistical computing language R, version 4.1.2 (R Foundation, Vienna, Austria).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Sleep episode timing summary results are shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and corresponding Bland-Altman plots in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001 f0002 f0003" ref-type="fig">Figures 1–3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. Expanded sleep-wake summary results are presented in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=395732.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Bland-Altman Summary Agreement</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outcome</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Device</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Device Mean (SD)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference Mean (SD)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean Bias (SD)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean Absolute Bias (SD)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">TIB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fatigue Science ReadiBand</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">328.1 (123.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">344.0 (125.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−15.8 (28.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.5 (22.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fitbit Inspire HR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">351.4 (113.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">353.4 (115.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.9 (45.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.3 (36.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oura Ring</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">362.0 (108.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">350.6 (115.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4 (32.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.5 (26.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polar Vantage V Titan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">394.0 (81.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">405.9 (73.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−11.8 (27.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.3 (20.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Start Time</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fatigue Science ReadiBand</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">641.8 (184.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">634.0 (186.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8 (20.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.1 (15.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fitbit Inspire HR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">625.2 (173.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">620.0 (173.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1 (27.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.3 (23.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oura Ring</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">626.9 (171.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">625.8 (177.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (18.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.1 (15.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polar Vantage V Titan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">601.8 (153.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">590.7 (147.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0 (17.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.9 (14.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">End Time</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fatigue Science ReadiBand</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">970.0 (156.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">978.0 (151.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.0 (20.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0 (16.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fitbit Inspire HR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">976.6 (152.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">973.4 (151.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2 (35.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.5 (31.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oura Ring</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">989.0 (152.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">976.4 (153.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6 (26.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.0 (23.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polar Vantage V Titan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">995.8 (143.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">996.6 (142.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.8 (22.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3 (17.5)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: Summary agreement between devices and reference for the Bland-Altman plots for TIB, sleep episode start time, and sleep episode end time. The sleep log served as reference for all outcome measures. All daytime sleep episodes with available data for both the device and reference were included in analyses, with the total number of nights (n) indicated in each row. Mean and SD are shown for each device and reference, with all values provided in minutes. Values for sleep start and end times are minutes since midnight. Mean bias and mean absolute bias columns compare the device and reference in linear bias terms (not regression bias terms, which are provided within the expanded bias statistics in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=395732.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative">). Positive and negative values in the mean bias column indicate overestimations or underestimations, respectively, for the device versus the reference sleep log.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: SD, standard deviation; TIB, time in bed.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Bland-Altman plots: TIB.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-151-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: Plots depict the mean bias (solid red line) and upper and lower limits of agreement (LOA; solid gray lines) for deviation in TIB for the devices compared with the reference sleep log. Black circles are individual nights. Dashed lines represent the 95% confidence intervals around the bias and LOA lines. Gray shaded regions on the right y-axis are density plots showing the distribution of individual night biases. Zero on the y-axis represents no difference, with positive and negative y-axis values indicating an overestimation or underestimation, respectively, compared with the reference. Diagonal mean bias lines indicate significant proportional bias. Non-parallel LOA lines indicate significant heteroscedasticity.</attrib><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: LOA, limits of agreement; TIB, time in bed.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Bland-Altman plots: sleep episode start time.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-151-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: Plots depict the mean bias (solid red line) and upper and lower limits of agreement (solid gray lines) for deviation in sleep episode start time of TIB for the devices compared with the reference sleep log. See <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> notes for additional figure details.</attrib><attrib><bold>Abbreviation</bold>: TIB, time in bed.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Bland-Altman plots: sleep episode end time.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-151-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: Plots depict the mean bias (solid red line) and upper and lower limits of agreement (solid gray lines) for deviation in sleep episode end time of TIB for the devices compared with the reference sleep log. See <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> notes for additional figure details.</attrib><attrib><bold>Abbreviation</bold>: TIB, time in bed.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Daytime Sleep Episode TIB Bias</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">For TIB (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">), the devices exhibited low bias for mean biases and most individual episodes. However, each device also had a few episodes that were more variable, such as those with biases &gt;1 h under or over the TIB reported in the sleep log. Corresponding to the variability observed in biases, which included both under- and over-estimations for the devices compared with the sleep log, mean biases were greater when expressed in absolute terms but were all &lt;30 min. The only device displaying a significant proportional mean bias for TIB was the Polar Vantage V Titan, which was in a positive direction.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Daytime Sleep Episode Start Time Bias</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The start time of sleep episodes for each device (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative">) also had low biases for the mean and most individual episodes. Like TIB, a few episodes for each device also exhibited large underestimations or overestimations compared with the sleep log. Significant proportional mean biases occurred for the Oura Ring (negative) and the Polar Vantage V Titan (positive).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Daytime Sleep Episode End Time Bias</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">For sleep episode end times (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">), device biases remained low for most episodes and the mean biases. Like TIB and episode start time biases, episode end times also had a few episodes with large biases. Only the Fatigue Science ReadiBand exhibited a significant proportional mean bias, which was in a positive direction.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Correlations Between Daytime Sleep Episode Start and End Time Biases and Physical in-Bed Times</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> displays correlations that tested whether the biases of start and end times of daytime sleep episodes were associated with the differences in the times that participants reported physically entering or exiting bed (which sometimes differ from the start and end times of the sleep episode TIB, such as when someone spends time in sedentary wake activities in bed prior to or after their attempted sleep episode). Across all devices, none of the correlations for the start time or end time of daytime sleep episodes reached statistical significance, suggesting that device start and end time biases for TIB were not associated with bed entry or exit times.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Correlations Between Daytime Sleep Episode Start and End Time Biases and Physical in-Bed Times</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bias Outcome</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Device</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Correlation Statistic</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Start Time</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fatigue Science ReadiBand</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.754</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fitbit Inspire HR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.104</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.412</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oura Ring</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.078</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.545</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polar Vantage V Titan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.038</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.819</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">End Time</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fatigue Science ReadiBand</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.167</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.184</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fitbit Inspire HR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.223</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.076</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oura Ring</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.131</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.304</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polar Vantage V Titan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.217</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.184</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: Correlations testing associations between sleep episode TIB start and end time biases and the differences in times when participants physically entered and exited bed, respectively. Participants reported all times in the sleep logs. Statistics are repeated measures correlations.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviation</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: TIB, time in bed.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2005">
        <title>Frequency of Missing Daytime Sleep Episode Recordings</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Histograms depicting the frequency of devices detecting or missing the reported daytime sleep episodes are shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. The Fatigue Science ReadiBand, Fitbit Inspire HR, and Oura Ring missed only a few episodes overall (3.6%, 4.8%, and 6.0%, respectively). For Fitbit and Oura, these missing episodes were mostly naps with shorter TIB. Notably, the Polar Vantage V Titan failed to detect the most episodes overall (37.3%), including all episodes with reported TIB &lt;4 h.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0004" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Frequency of missing daytime sleep episode recordings.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-151-g0004" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: Plots depict stacked histogram bars for the number of detected and missing daytime sleep episode recordings for the devices compared with those reported in the reference sleep log. Green bars represent correctly detected episodes and red bars represent missing episodes, for each 1-h TIB bin. TIB refers to the minutes of TIB reported for each daytime sleep episode in the sleep log, which may not necessarily equal the TIB of the corresponding daytime sleep episode recording by the device.</attrib><attrib><bold>Abbreviation</bold>: TIB, time in bed.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Additionally, devices sometimes produced false-positive daytime sleep recordings (ie, detecting additional daytime episodes when they were not reported in the sleep logs; see </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=395732.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Supplemental Figure S4</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). This type of error occurred less frequently than the error frequency for devices missing reported episodes, as described previously. Fatigue Science ReadiBand was the only device with a cluster of false-positive episodes, occurring most frequently for low TIBs (eg, extra naps recorded). The overall percentage of false-positive episodes mislabeled as sleep versus the total number of daytime episodes detected by each device were as follows: Fatigue Science ReadiBand (10.0%), Fitbit Inspire HR (4.9%), Oura Ring (3.7%), Polar Vantage V Titan (1.9%).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">During real-world conditions, we found that four commercial wearable devices exhibited low bias in general when measuring daytime sleep episode timing, but some devices had mixed or poor performance for detecting all the reported daytime sleep episodes (especially when TIB was short). Devices sometimes had large biases (eg, &gt;1 h) for estimating the sleep timing of daytime episodes, but there were few instances overall. The direction of the bias was variable (ie, both underestimations and overestimations occurred), which may have contributed to the low mean biases and few proportional biases observed for the devices across sleep timing outcomes. Daytime sleep timing biases were not correlated with the time that participants reported spending physically in bed before and after their sleep episode TIB, indicating that TIB biases may sometimes be due to potential behavioral and physiological factors other than engaging in sedentary wake activities in bed that occur before or after their attempted sleep episode. Differences observed between devices in their ability to correctly detect daytime sleep episodes, which also differed by TIB, suggest that different device sleep-tracking algorithms likely have varying sensitivities or thresholds for triggering the recording of daytime sleep and naps in general. Polar Vantage V Titan was especially poor at detecting shorter daytime episodes, missing over a third of total episodes including all episodes with TIB &lt;4 h; however, this finding aligns with the parameters of its sleep-tracking algorithm to not detect naps of that duration. This performance gap between devices has implications for their reliability and accuracy when used with shift workers or others who often sleep or nap during daytime hours. Overall, wearable devices exhibit promising performance for tracking the timing of daytime sleep episodes, but the mixed performance for daytime sleep episode detection (especially for shorter naps) raises some concerns for the reliability and accuracy of certain devices for daytime sleep tracking.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The finding that device-determined TIB is tracked with low bias for most episodes largely indicates promising daytime-sleep tracking performance for the accuracy of devices to measure sleep timing when an episode is recorded. Accurate detection of TIB is a critical performance outcome because measurement of the other major sleep summary outcomes of interest (eg, TST, sleep efficiency, wake after sleep onset, sleep onset latency) rely on first identifying the correct TIB window. Therefore, the few episodes we found with large TIB biases will also bias other sleep summary outcomes, which has implications for the reliability of sleep-tracking data in general and is a concern for their real-world use (especially for individuals who often sleep during the day).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> For all devices, biases occurred both as overestimations and underestimations. Therefore, the overall mean biases were often low because there were similar magnitudes of positive and negative individual bias values (averaging out close to zero). Thus, it is also important to consider measures of distribution for biases that contextualize the (sometimes) large variability in observed biases (eg, mean absolute bias, SD, and LOA). The importance of accurate TIB tracking was also considered in our previous study examining performance of these same devices for nighttime sleep, in which we also found that most episodes exhibited low TIB bias with some notable exceptions (eg, bias &gt;1 h).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> To enhance the use of devices for personal, research, or clinical purposes, sleep-tracking devices and algorithms should prioritize improving the accuracy of TIB tracking.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In the current study, we also examined potential biases at the start or end time of daytime sleep episodes. As with TIB, mean biases were low for all devices in their start or end time detection, only a few episodes exhibited large biases, and there was no evidence of any relationship with the extra time that participants spent in bed outside of the TIB window. Thus, the cause of bias may be in other potential factors (eg, demographics and behavior) that should be examined in future studies to better understand why a device may be biased to start or end at the wrong time, which would improve sleep tracking in general.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The main area of daytime sleep-tracking performance where we found differences between devices was in the frequency of detecting or missing daytime episode recordings. This was especially the case for the Polar Vantage V Titan, which missed the greatest number of episodes overall (37.3%) and failed to detect any daytime episodes with TIB &lt;4 h, a finding that has obvious implications for using Polar devices in daytime sleepers. However, this finding is not surprising given the information Polar provides regarding its sleep-tracking algorithm,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> which states that only the longest sleep episode per day (defined as 18:00 to 18:00) is tracked and that episodes &lt;4 h are not detected at all. These specific algorithm design choices currently make Polar devices largely unreliable sleep-tracking tools for those who nap or split their sleep episodes across multiple bouts per day, such as operational or clinical populations described previously. Oura Ring also missed a few of the shorter daytime episodes, which may also be concerning for its use in such populations. According to Oura, its sleep algorithm can detect naps for episodes with TST between 15 min and 3 h.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> It should also be noted that some newer features for the Oura Ring that are available to researchers on the data management platform Oura Teams may provide additional sleep and nap data beyond the data available to users on the Oura app (eg, extra “rest” periods), which is where some of the nap data were found for our analyses. Oura requires users to “confirm” naps on the same day they occur, with a prompt appearing on the Oura app (see Methods for more details). We could not verify which naps were “confirmed” by participants or not, therefore each participant’s Oura nap data were constructed from both the app and Oura Teams exports. For the shortest nap episodes, if the TST was under 15 min it would not reach Oura’s defined threshold for a nap and may have led to the nap not appearing in the sleep data outputs – thus, possibly accounting for some of the missing short daytime naps that we found for Oura. The Fitbit Inspire HR and Fatigue Science ReadiBand had the most reliable recording performances, each missing only a few daytime episodes. Fitbit states that naps &gt;1 h are tracked,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> which aligns well with our finding that the two naps logged that were &lt;1 h were missed, whereas almost all longer episodes were correctly detected. Although ReadiBand had a high rate for correctly detecting daytime sleep episodes regardless of TIB, ReadiBand notably had the most false-positive episodes recorded, especially short naps, detecting several that were not reported by participants. ReadiBand has been shown to track daytime sleep episodes in recent real-world observational studies in which it was used to measure the sleep patterns of shift-working nurses and police officers,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> although without reported reference metrics to examine potential performance biases (eg, TIB biases or missed and false-positive sleep episodes) for comparison to the current study. In the current study, differences between devices in their ability to detect episodes are potentially determined by designed settings in their proprietary sleep-tracking algorithms (eg, thresholds for activity, heart rate, TIB, or TST) and could be changed or updated in the future to better detect daytime sleep and naps. Thus, additional studies on daytime sleep tracking are needed to examine performance parameters and limitations or improvements, while new devices and algorithms continue to be released on the consumer market.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Previous studies have not specifically focused on the performance evaluation of naps or daytime sleep episodes with commercial wearable devices,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> therefore the findings of this study are novel. However, there is evidence from a few previous studies that wearable devices would not perform well for tracking naps or daytime sleep. A recent study found that the Garmin</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>TM</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Vivosmart HR device (Garmin, Olathe, KS, USA) was not able to detect daytime sleep episodes in police trainees when they switched from working day shifts (sleeping at night) to working night shifts (primarily sleeping during the daytime).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Additionally, a study with a previous-generation Fitbit device (Charge HR model) found that in a group of young athletes most of the daytime sleep episodes were missed, especially shorter naps with TIB of 1 or 2 h.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Finally, a study using a since-discontinued Jawbone device found that it could not reliably record sleep during daytime nap episodes in a multiple sleep latency test protocol.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In contrast, a recent study of the WHOOP</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>TM</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> strap device (WHOOP, Boston, MA, USA) under a controlled laboratory setting compared with PSG tested daytime sleep episodes, with a 7-h fixed TIB occurring in the afternoon-evening with an analysis of its auto-detection sleep-tracking feature.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> While the authors found the device generally had good sleep-tracking performance that was comparable to when TIB was entered manually for the same episodes, they also reported that no sleep episodes were missed with its auto-detection feature. The study, however, did not include naps or shorter daytime episodes, nor was TIB a reported outcome, and therefore those results cannot be compared directly with the bias outcomes of the current study.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">With the growing popularity of wearable devices for tracking sleep, physiology, and behavior, the relevance for understanding how devices perform across the 24-h day cannot be overstated, especially for groups at risk of safety, performance, and health decrements from irregular or insufficient sleep patterns (eg, shift workers, military personnel, patients with sleep or circadian disorders). Unsurprisingly, several review papers and editorials have highlighted the need for more studies examining naps or daytime sleep tracking with wearable devices.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> There is also a growing demand from sleep researchers who have expressed a preference for using wearable devices that feature nap detection for TIB as low as 20 min.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In the current study, only a few naps with TIB &lt;1 h were observed for analysis, however we found that the missed episodes were mostly from episodes with low TIB including many naps. Therefore, from the current study, it is largely unknown whether commercial wearable devices can reliably track naps with TIB as low as the researcher-preferred minimum of 20 min, although it is theoretically possible that algorithms can be made sensitive enough for devices to better detect very short naps. It is likely that studies or initiatives to use wearables to track sleep patterns or promote sleep health in groups such as shift workers will suffer from low compliance or adoption if devices do not first demonstrate good performance for detecting naps or sleep episodes across the 24-h day.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Research-grade actigraphy traditionally has been used for real-world tracking of sleep across the day and night in clinical and operational populations, but newer multi-sensor commercial wearable devices with their proprietary algorithms (or customized research algorithms for sleep or circadian rhythm tracking using data from wearables</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37–39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) theoretically could surpass standard actigraphy algorithms for daytime sleep tracking. This enhanced performance is necessary since actigraphy, which typically contains an accelerometry sensor input only, is often overly sensitive to classifying naps during times of sedentary activity.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Also, to improve accuracy of daytime sleep assessments with actigraphy, it is still recommended for participants to complete a reference sleep log every day to inform researchers when sleep was actually attempted to reduce the occurrence of potential false-positive naps.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Modern commercial wearable devices have the potential to track important real-world health statistics and clinical outcomes beyond sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Based on the promise of what wearables could deliver for everyday use and clinical endpoints,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> there is interest in the use and improvement of wearables from several different sectors (eg, research, industry, healthcare, and government) and an expansion of the already growing wearables market. These advancements will benefit the sleep field too,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> if wearables can be improved to reliably track the sleep of those with irregular sleep patterns such as shift workers and operational communities who make up a large and necessary part of the workforce and have known risks to their health, performance, and safety.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43–45</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This study has several strengths. Multiple devices were tested concurrently, which resulted in higher throughput of results and easier comparison of performance between devices. This study was a direct follow-up to our previous study</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> that tested the same set of four commercial wearable devices during nighttime sleep in a similar unrestricted home protocol, which now extends and better defines the performance of these devices. This was one of the first studies to focus on evaluating the daytime sleep-tracking performance of commercial devices in general. Device performance was assessed under real-world, unrestricted conditions, which yielded a wide range of episode TIBs. Finally, as in our previous performance evaluation studies,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> this study was also conducted independently without involvement or potential conflicts from the device companies.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This study also had limitations. The study design of self-selected and unrestricted sleep schedules resulted in sleep episodes with varying TIBs to test. However, the TIB bins were not balanced, and there were fewer episodes with shorter TIBs (naps) to evaluate than the longer main sleep episodes. Though we included many real-world shift workers, the study enrolled only young healthy adults and may not be representative of shift worker or operational populations who often have health issues and sleep disorders</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43–45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> that could affect wearable device performance. This was an initial study of the largely unknown performance of commercial devices to track daytime sleep; therefore, future studies into this area would benefit from including larger and more diverse samples of participants and by tracking sleep over periods longer than 1 week. The reference used for sleep schedule data was a digital self-report sleep log that enabled real-time compliance checks, but errors in reporting or recall may have been possible. We did not examine potential demographic differences in device performance. It is possible that wearable devices with PPG sensors, like some of those in the current study, may be prone to inaccuracies in heart rate measurements due to race, ethnicity, or skin tone,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> which we plan to examine in a forthcoming analysis. Finally, we chose to test a variety of wearable devices from established companies that are widely used by the public or by operational communities. However, the consumer market has a high turnover of devices, so it is possible that the specific device models or algorithms we tested in the current study may be updated or no longer available in the future.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our findings indicate that when daytime sleep episodes were recorded by the four wearable devices, TIB outcomes were largely tracked with low bias. However, performance differences between devices were revealed in their ability to reliably record daytime sleep episodes under certain conditions. In particular, naps and shorter sleep episodes with TIB &lt;4 h were missed altogether by the Polar Vantage V Titan, whereas the Fatigue Science ReadiBand, Fitbit Inspire HR, and Oura Ring missed few daytime episodes. However, ReadiBand was over-sensitive in detecting sleep and recorded several extra false-positive daytime sleep episodes that were not actual logged sleep episodes, especially naps with low TIB. These performance differences in detecting daytime sleep and naps are likely caused by differences between algorithm settings, and device performance in this area may improve if the algorithm’s sensitivity and use of thresholds (eg, for minimum duration of naps) are changed in the future. While we and others have found that many wearable devices (including this same set of four devices</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) largely perform well for tracking epoch-by-epoch and summary outcomes for sleep and wake, previous device evaluation study protocols were limited to testing sleep at night only and usually under fixed TIB. Thus, the assumption that devices may also perform well for tracking daytime sleep has been overlooked by initial studies, and this study represents one of the first to test such assumptions rigorously by examining daytime sleep-tracking performance specifically. These findings have implications for the use of devices in people who nap or sleep during the daytime and/or have irregular sleep schedules in general, such as shift workers (eg, hospital workers, first responders, and operational communities like the military) or individuals with sleep or circadian disorders. The use of unrestricted sleep schedules yielded naturalistic variations in TIB, including shorter naps where the majority of missed recordings for some devices were revealed, thereby providing greater translation of results to real-world device use. Additional studies evaluating these and other wearable devices under similar and different testing conditions and populations are needed to confirm and extend current findings and better refine the strengths, limitations, and recommendations for wearable devices across the 24-h day.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This research was funded by the Office of Naval Research, Code 34. The authors wish to thank Prayag Gordy for support with data analysis and visualization, and Liliya Silayeva, PhD, for helpful comments on the manuscript and project management support. Rachel R. Markwald is an employee of the US Government. This work was prepared as part of her official duties. Title 17, USC. §105 provides that copyright protection under this title is not available for any work of the US Government. Title 17, USC. §101 defines a US Government work as work prepared by a military service member or employee of the US Government as part of that person’s official duties. Report No. 22–81 was supported by the Office of Naval Research, Code 34, under work unit no. N1701. The views expressed in this article reflect the results of research conducted by the authors and do not necessarily reflect the official policy or position of the Department of the Navy, Department of Defense, nor the US Government. The study protocol was approved by the Naval Health Research Center Institutional Review Board in compliance with all applicable federal regulations governing the protection of human subjects. Research data were derived from an approved Naval Health Research Center Institutional Review Board protocol, number NHRC.2017.0008.</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">LOA, limits of agreement; PPG, photoplethysmography; PSG, polysomnography; SD, standard deviation; TIB, time in bed.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The datasets generated and/or analyzed during the current study are not publicly available due to security protocols and privacy regulations, but they may be made available on reasonable request by the Naval Health Research Center Institutional Review Board (contact phone +16195538400).</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0008">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Goldstein</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Current and future roles of consumer sleep technologies in sleep medicine</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Clin</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>391</fpage>–<lpage>408</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsmc.2020.05.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32762972</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baumert</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cowie</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Redline</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep characterization with smart wearable devices: a call for standardization and consensus recommendations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>zsac183</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsac183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35913733</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>de Zambotti</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cellini</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Menghini</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sarlo</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baker</surname>
<given-names>FC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sensors capabilities, performance, and use of consumer sleep technology</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Clin</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsmc.2019.11.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32005346</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lujan</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perez-Pozuelo</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grandner</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Past, present, and future of multisensory wearable technology to monitor sleep and circadian rhythms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Digit Health</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>721919</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fdgth.2021.721919</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34713186</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Khosla</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deak</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gault</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Consumer sleep technology: an American Academy of Sleep Medicine position statement</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>877</fpage>–<lpage>880</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.7128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29734997</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Depner</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>PC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Devine</surname>
<given-names>JK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Wearable technologies for developing sleep and circadian biomarkers: a summary of workshop discussions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>zsz254</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsz254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31641776</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schutte-Rodin</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deak</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khosla</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Evaluating consumer and clinical sleep technologies: an American Academy of Sleep Medicine update</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2275</fpage>–<lpage>2282</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.9580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34314344</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>de Zambotti</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Menghini</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grandner</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Rigorous performance evaluation (previously, “validation”) for informed use of new technologies for sleep health measurement</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Health</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>269</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleh.2022.02.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35513978</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Grandner</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosenberger</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>. <part-title>Chapter 12 - actigraphic sleep tracking and wearables: historical context, scientific applications and guidelines, limitations, and considerations for commercial sleep devices</part-title>. In: <string-name><surname>Grandner</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, editor. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep and Health</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>; <year>2019</year>:<fpage>147</fpage>–<lpage>157</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-815373-4.00012-5</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Montgomery-Downs</surname>
<given-names>HE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Insana</surname>
<given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bond</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Movement toward a novel activity monitoring device</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>913</fpage>–<lpage>917</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-011-0585-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21971963</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Meltzer</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hiruma</surname>
<given-names>LS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Avis</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Montgomery-Downs</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Valentin</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Comparison of a commercial accelerometer with polysomnography and actigraphy in children and adolescents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1323</fpage>–<lpage>1330</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.4918</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26118555</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Haghayegh</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khoshnevis</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smolensky</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Diller</surname>
<given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Castriotta</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Accuracy of Wristband Fitbit models in assessing sleep: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Med Internet Res</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e16273</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/16273</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31778122</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>XK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chee</surname>
<given-names>NIYN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ong</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Validation of a consumer sleep wearable device with actigraphy and polysomnography in adolescents across sleep opportunity manipulations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1337</fpage>–<lpage>1346</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.7932</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31538605</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kahawage</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jumabhoy</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hamill</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Zambotti</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drummond</surname>
<given-names>SPA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Validity, potential clinical utility, and comparison of consumer and research-grade activity trackers in insomnia disorder I: in-lab validation against polysomnography</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e12931</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31626361</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chinoy</surname>
<given-names>ED</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cuellar</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huwa</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Performance of seven consumer sleep-tracking devices compared with polysomnography</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>zsaa291</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsaa291</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33378539</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chinoy</surname>
<given-names>ED</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cuellar</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jameson</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Markwald</surname>
<given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Performance of four commercial wearable sleep-tracking devices tested under unrestricted conditions at home in healthy young adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Sci Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>493</fpage>–<lpage>516</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S348795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35345630</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Grandner</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bromberg</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hadley</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Performance of a multisensor smart ring to evaluate sleep: in-lab and home-based evaluation of generalized and personalized algorithms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>zsac152</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsac152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35767600</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ancoli-Israel</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cole</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alessi</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chambers</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moorcroft</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pollak</surname>
<given-names>CP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The role of actigraphy in the study of sleep and circadian rhythms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>342</fpage>–<lpage>392</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/26.3.342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12749557</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lambrechtse</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ziesenitz</surname>
<given-names>VC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van den Anker</surname>
<given-names>JN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bos</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>How reliable are commercially available trackers in detecting daytime sleep [letter to the editor]</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Br J Clin Pharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>84</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>605</fpage>–<lpage>606</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bcp.13475</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29341197</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Watson</surname>
<given-names>NF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Badr</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Belenky</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Recommended amount of sleep for a healthy adult: a joint consensus statement of the American Academy of Sleep Medicine and Sleep Research Society</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>843</fpage>–<lpage>844</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.4716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26039963</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Chinoy</surname>
<given-names>ED</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Markwald</surname>
<given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>. <part-title>Use of technology for real-world sleep and circadian research</part-title>. In: <source><italic toggle="yes">Encyclopedia of Sleep and Circadian Rhythms</italic></source>. <edition>2nd</edition> ed. <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>; <year>2023</year>:<fpage>156</fpage>–<lpage>168</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-822963-7.00200-0</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Carney</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ancoli-Israel</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The consensus sleep diary: standardizing prospective sleep self-monitoring</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>302</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.1642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22294820</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Menghini</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cellini</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goldstone</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baker</surname>
<given-names>FC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Zambotti</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A standardized framework for testing the performance of sleep-tracking technology: step-by-step guidelines and open-source code</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>zsaa170</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsaa170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32882005</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bland</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Altman</surname>
<given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Statistical methods for assessing agreement between two methods of clinical measurement</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>8476</issue>):<fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>310</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(86)90837-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2868172</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bakdash</surname>
<given-names>JZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marusich</surname>
<given-names>LR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Repeated measures correlation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>456</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2017.00456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28439244</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Polar Sleep Plus Stages<sup>TM</sup> FAQS</article-title>. <comment>Available from:</comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://support.polar.com/en/sleep-plus-stages-faqs" ext-link-type="uri">https://support.polar.com/en/sleep-plus-stages-faqs</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>February</month>
<day>2</day>, 2023</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Oura Nap Detection</article-title>. <comment>Available from:</comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://support.ouraring.com/hc/en-us/articles/1500009653181-Nap-Detection" ext-link-type="uri">https://support.ouraring.com/hc/en-us/articles/1500009653181-Nap-Detection</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>February</month>
<day>2</day>, 2023</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>How do I track my sleep with my Fitbit device?</article-title>
<comment>Available from:</comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://help.fitbit.com/articles/en_US/Help_article/1314.htm" ext-link-type="uri">https://help.fitbit.com/articles/en_US/Help_article/1314.htm</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>February</month>
<day>2</day>, 2023</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>James</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>James</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilson</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep health and predicted cognitive effectiveness of nurses working 12-hour shifts: an observational study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Nurs Stud</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>112</volume>:<fpage>103667</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2020.103667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32593476</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>James</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caruso</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>James</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pilot test of NIOSH training for law enforcement on shift work and long work hours</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Occup Environ Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>599</fpage>–<lpage>606</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JOM.0000000000002534</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35543640</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Erickson</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Counts</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Field-based assessments of behavioral patterns during shiftwork in police academy trainees using wearable technology</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Biol Rhythms</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>260</fpage>–<lpage>271</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/07487304221087068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35416084</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sargent</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lastella</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Romyn</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Versey</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roach</surname>
<given-names>GD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>How well does a commercially available wearable device measure sleep in young athletes?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Chronobiol Int</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>754</fpage>–<lpage>758</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07420528.2018.1466800</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29750580</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cook</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Prairie</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Plante</surname>
<given-names>DT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Ability of the multisensory jawbone UP3 to quantify and classify sleep in patients with suspected central disorders of hypersomnolence: a comparison against polysomnography and actigraphy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>841</fpage>–<lpage>848</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.7120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29734975</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roach</surname>
<given-names>GD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lastella</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A validation study of a commercial wearable device to automatically detect and estimate sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biosensors</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>185</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/bios11060185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34201016</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Devine</surname>
<given-names>JK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schwartz</surname>
<given-names>LP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Choynowski</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hursh</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Expert demand for consumer sleep technology features and wearable devices: a case study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">IoT</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>315</fpage>–<lpage>331</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/iot3020018</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Devine</surname>
<given-names>JK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schwartz</surname>
<given-names>LP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hursh</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Technical, regulatory, economic, and trust issues preventing successful integration of sensors into the mainstream consumer wearables market</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sensors</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>2731</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/s22072731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35408345</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Walch</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Forger</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goldstein</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep stage prediction with raw acceleration and photoplethysmography heart rate data derived from a consumer wearable device</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>zsz180</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsz180</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31579900</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Walch</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Predicting circadian misalignment with wearable technology: validation of wrist-worn actigraphy and photometry in night shift workers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>zsaa180</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsaa180</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32918087</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mayer</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Predicting circadian phase across populations: a comparison of mathematical models and wearable devices</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>zsab126</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsab126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34013347</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kanady</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drummond</surname>
<given-names>SPA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mednick</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Actigraphic assessment of a polysomnographic-recorded nap: a validation study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1 Pt 2</issue>):<fpage>214</fpage>–<lpage>222</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.2010.00858.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20626612</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dunn</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kidzinski</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Runge</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Wearable sensors enable personalized predictions of clinical laboratory measurements</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1105</fpage>–<lpage>1112</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-021-01339-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34031607</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mason</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kasl</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hartogensis</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Metrics from wearable devices as candidate predictors of antibody response following vaccination against COVID-19: data from the second TemPredict study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vaccines</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>264</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vaccines10020264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35214723</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drake</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Shift work disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurol Clin</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>563</fpage>–<lpage>577</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ncl.2019.03.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31256790</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Good</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brager</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Capaldi</surname>
<given-names>VF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mysliwiec</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep in the United States military</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropsychopharmacology</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>176</fpage>–<lpage>191</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41386-019-0431-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31185484</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gurubhagavatula</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barger</surname>
<given-names>LK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barnes</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Guiding principles for determining work shift duration and addressing the effects of work shift duration on performance, safety, and health: guidance from the American Academy of Sleep Medicine and the Sleep Research Society</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>zsab161</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsab161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34373924</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Colvonen</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>DeYoung</surname>
<given-names>PN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bosompra</surname>
<given-names>NOA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Owens</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Limiting racial disparities and bias for wearable devices in health science research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>zsaa159</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsaa159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32893865</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
