<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37038440</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">10082604</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">392441</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S392441</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Review</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>How Tired is Too Tired to Drive? A Systematic Review Assessing the Use of Prior Sleep Duration to Detect Driving Impairment</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Sprajcer et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Sprajcer et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4966-871X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Sprajcer</surname>
            <given-names>Madeline</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7385-5630</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Dawson</surname>
            <given-names>Drew</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kosmadopoulos</surname>
            <given-names>Anastasi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sach</surname>
            <given-names>Edward J</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Crowther</surname>
            <given-names>Meagan E</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5340-4701</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Sargent</surname>
            <given-names>Charli</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4005-1243</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Roach</surname>
            <given-names>Gregory D</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Appleton Institute for Behavioural Sciences, Central Queensland University</institution>, <addr-line>Wayville</addr-line>, <addr-line>SA</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Madeline Sprajcer, <institution>Central Queensland University, Appleton Institute</institution>, <addr-line>44 Greenhill Road</addr-line>, <addr-line>Wayville</addr-line>, <addr-line>SA</addr-line>, <addr-line>5034</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country>, Email m.sprajcer@cqu.edu.au</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>04</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2023</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>15</volume>
      <fpage>175</fpage>
      <lpage>206</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>03</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2023 Sprajcer et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Sprajcer et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Driver fatigue is a contributory factor in approximately 20% of vehicle crashes. While other causal factors (eg, drink-driving) have decreased in recent decades due to increased public education strategies and punitive measures, similar decreases have not been seen in fatigue-related crashes. Fatigued driving could be managed in a similar way to drink-driving, with an established point (ie, amount of prior sleep) after which drivers are “deemed impaired”. This systematic review aimed to provide an evidence-base for the concept of deemed impairment and to identify how much prior sleep may be required to drive safely. Four online databases were searched (PubMed, Web of Science, Scopus, Embase). Eligibility requirements included a) measurement of prior sleep duration and b) driving performance indicators (eg, lane deviation) and/or outcomes (eg, crash likelihood). After screening 1940 unique records, a total of 61 studies were included. Included studies were categorised as having experimental/quasi-experimental (n = 21), naturalistic (n = 3), longitudinal (n = 1), case–control (n = 11), or cross-sectional (n = 25) designs. Findings suggest that after either 6 or 7 hours of prior sleep, a modest level of impairment is generally seen compared with after ≥ 8 hours of prior sleep (ie, well rested), depending on the test used. Crash likelihood appears to be ~30% greater after 6 or 7 hours of prior sleep, as compared to individuals who are well rested. After one night of either 4 or 5 hours of sleep, there are large decrements to driving performance and approximately double the likelihood of a crash when compared with well-rested individuals. When considering the scientific evidence, it appears that there is a notable decrease in driving performance (and associated increase in crash likelihood) when less than 5h prior sleep is obtained. This is a critical first step in establishing community standards regarding the amount of sleep required to drive safely.</citation_analysis></p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>fatigue</kwd>
        <kwd>driving</kwd>
        <kwd>performance</kwd>
        <kwd>sleep</kwd>
        <kwd>safety</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Australian Government Office of Road Safety’s Road Safety Innovation Fund</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>This systematic review is supported by the Australian Government Office of Road Safety’s Road Safety Innovation Fund (RSIF2-73).</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="7"/>
        <table-count count="4"/>
        <ref-count count="90"/>
        <page-count count="32"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s0001">
      <title>Plain Language Summary</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Fatigue contributes to ~20% of road crashes.</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The number of road crashes caused by alcohol has decreased in recent decades, because of the introduction and enforcement of blood alcohol concentration limits for driving.</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">When drivers have a blood alcohol concentration over the established limit, they are legally deemed to be impaired.</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In this paper, we establish the concept of deemed impairment for fatigued driving.</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This systematic review presents evidence on where a potential point to deem impairment due to fatigue could be established (ie, how much sleep does an individual need to drive safely?)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Approximately double the risk of a crash is seen when drivers have had five or fewer hours of sleep in the previous twenty-four hours.</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0002">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Every year in Australia, road crashes result in ~1200 deaths, &gt;40,000 serious injuries and cost the economy AUD$30 billion.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Fatigue is the primary cause of ~20% of these crashes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In recent decades, crashes due to speeding and drink-driving have been reduced through deterrence approaches based on education campaigns and enforcement strategies.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In contrast, the crash rate due to fatigue has not fallen over the same period. Initiatives targeting speeding and drink-driving have been successful because they provide clear guidance regarding what is unsafe in terms of speed or blood alcohol concentration (BAC) and enforcement agencies have technologies to detect people driving over the limits for speed or BAC. Furthermore, people caught driving over those limits are deemed to be driving in an unsafe manner (in the case of speeding) or are deemed impaired (in the case of BAC) and can be sanctioned and/or punished accordingly. Public education campaigns and good guidance materials that enable people to make decisions regarding impaired driving due to alcohol have been highly successful in dramatically reducing the road toll. This reduction in the road toll due to alcohol-related impairment was seen only when clear and specific guidance was provided to road users – compared with previous generations who were provided with only general invocations, ie, “don’t drink and drive”.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Fatigued driving is still only subject to those general exhortation campaigns. Catchlines such as fatigued/drowsy drivers die or do not drive when fatigued/drowsy do not provide sufficient guidance to help a driver decide if they are fit-to-drive or not. In contrast to drink-driving, the public education and guidance necessary to support safe decision-making is not provided for impairment due to fatigue. People are currently expected to make decisions regarding fatigued driving without clear guidance on what constitutes being “too tired to drive”. While there is clear scientific evidence to determine fitness to drive based on prior sleep-wake behaviour, this information has not yet informed public education campaigns. Similarly, if people do not know how to assess their fitness to drive, then subsequent prosecution is difficult and the deterrent value that flows from that is significantly diminished.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">A potential strategy for reducing crashes due to fatigued driving is to introduce the concept of a minimum sleep requirement to legally drive. In the same way as has been done with drink-driving, a threshold minimum sleep requirement could be defined and where drivers have had less sleep than the threshold they can be legally deemed “impaired”. The concept of deeming individuals to be impaired based on prior sleep-wake behaviour has recently been introduced as a potential mechanism for deterring driving while fatigued.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In one jurisdiction (New Jersey), this has already been done in a 2003 law known as “Maggie’s Law”.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> This law allows individuals to be prosecuted if they cause a vehicle crash after having been awake for ≥24 hours. However, this law was based on evidence equating 24 hours of prior wakefulness with a BAC of 0.10%. Drivers with a BAC of 0.10% would now generally be considered highly impaired (double the legal BAC limit in Australia). Furthermore, evidence suggests that significant cognitive and performance impairments are seen far before a BAC of 0.10%,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7–9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> or indeed before 24 hours of prior wakefulness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> We therefore propose to determine a minimum sleep threshold based on the best available scientific evidence, community perceptions of fairness and political acceptability. As such, a review of the literature is required to identify how much prior sleep is required to drive safely, and the level of prior sleep below which an individual could be “deemed impaired”. This systematic review aims to provide an evidence base for the concept of deemed impairment, which may impact policy and reduce the likelihood of fatigued driving (and fatigue-related crashes).</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">A search strategy was developed to identify studies that have examined the effects of sleep loss on driving outcomes. This search targeted articles published in scientific journals encompassing a variety of multidisciplinary experimental and observational methodologies. This systematic review aligns with the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) guideline</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> as indicated by Cochrane methodology.</citation_analysis></p>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Eligibility Criteria</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Eligible studies were those conducted with human participants and published in English language peer-reviewed scientific journals from January 1, 2000, until October 7, 2021. Participants were required to be from non-clinical, non-sleep disordered populations and to be of legal driving age. Studies were excluded if participants were comprised exclusively of adolescents ≤18 years and/or adults ≥65 years of age. This review was not registered.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Studies were required to include sleep duration or time in bed (TIB) as predictors or comparators of driving performance or impairment. Eligible dependent variables were those sourced from driving real or simulated motor vehicles (eg, cars, trucks). These could be obtained via instrumented on-road vehicles, driving simulators, self-report, or incident reports and databases. Only studies that included two or more sleep dose comparators or specifically used sleep duration as a predictor of driving were assessed.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All types of study designs were eligible for inclusion, including experimental studies and observational designs, including case–control, naturalistic, cross-sectional, or longitudinal methodologies. Experimental studies were limited to those comparing acute sleep loss (either partial or total deprivation) to a control sleep condition (habitual or recommended sleep duration). Studies involving caffeine, alcohol, or other interventions were excluded unless the effects of sleep duration or TIB could be isolated with a placebo/control condition. In contrast, eligible observational studies could investigate the effects of either acute or chronic sleep loss (eg, sleep in the prior 24 h, habitual sleep in the past week).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Information Sources</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The literature search obtained records from 4 online databases: PubMed (National Library of Medicine), Web of Science (Clarivate), Scopus (Elsevier), and Embase (Elsevier). Databases were searched on October 7, 2021.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Search Strategy</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">To limit the number of irrelevant records returned by each database, the search strategy required that articles include key terms in four broad categories:</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">1. Sleep terms: eg, “sleep”, “nap”, “awake”, etc.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">2. Sleep modifiers/descriptors: eg, “extended”, “restricted”, “duration”, “deprivation”, etc.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">3. Driving-related terms: eg, “driving”, “automobile”, “motor vehicle”, “road traffic”, etc.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">4. Driving performance/impairment terms: eg, “accident”, “crash”, “injury”, “speeding”, “lane position”, etc.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The full list of search terms and Boolean strategy used for each database are described in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=392441.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Material A</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. Additional methodological details, including the selection process, data collection process, data items, synthesis methods, data analysis, and quality assessment can be seen in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=392441.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Materials B</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=392441.docx" ext-link-type="uri">C</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0004-s2001">
        <title>Study Selection</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Database searches produced a total of 3415 records. After removing duplicate records (n = 1475), 1940 unique records were eligible for screening. Based on the title and abstract, 1615 records were excluded. A total of 325 full-text records were assessed for eligibility, resulting in 61 studies included in the qualitative synthesis. See </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> for the PRISMA flowchart of study screening and inclusion/exclusion.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">PRISMA flowchart.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-175-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Notes:</bold> PRISMA figure adapted from Page MJ, McKenzie JE, Bossuyt PM, et al. The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews. Systematic Reviews. 2021/03/29 2021;10(1):89. Creative Commons.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2002">
        <title>Study Characteristics</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Of the 61 studies included in this review, there were 21 experimental or quasi-experimental studies,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14–34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> 3 naturalistic studies,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35–37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> 1 longitudinal study,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> 11 case–control studies,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39–49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and 25 cross-sectional studies.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50–74</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> A wide range of populations were included, though there were some differences based on study type. Experimental or quasi-experimental studies included university students (n = 2),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> young adults (n = 11),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15–18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27–29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and healthy adults of any age (n = 8).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Naturalistic studies were based on heavy vehicle drivers (n = 2),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and nurses (n = 1).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The only longitudinal study included was based on a sample of young adult drivers from New South Wales, Australia.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Case–control studies largely included samples of drivers who had been in a motor vehicle crash and matched controls (ie, drivers who had not been involved in a crash) (n = 10).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39–46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> One sample of participants was heavy vehicle drivers who had recently crashed (with matched heavy vehicle driver controls who had not crashed) (n = 1).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Cross-sectional studies were made up of members of the general driving population (n = 10),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51–53</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55–57</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71–73</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> drivers who had recently been in a crash (n = 1),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> heavy vehicle or commercial drivers (n = 8),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0063" ref-type="bibr">63–68</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> nurses (n = 1),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> young adults (n = 1),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> university students (n = 2),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> drivers in regional Australia (Queensland) (n = 1),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and drill sergeants (n = 1).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2003">
        <title>Experimental and Quasi-Experimental Studies</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Twenty-one experimental or quasi-experimental studies met the inclusion criteria (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). All experimental or quasi-experimental studies comprised at least two sleep doses, one of which served as the control condition representing “habitual” or “recommended” sleep durations (usually 7 –9 h), and one which served as the acute sleep loss condition (total or partial sleep deprivation). With the exception of one study using a quasi-experimental repeated measures design</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and two studies which randomly assigned participants to sleep dose conditions,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> the remaining 18 studies counterbalanced the order of conditions in within-subject crossover designs. Five studies also included additional experimental conditions, such as real-world versus simulated driving,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and placebo-controlled interventions involving alcohol,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> or caffeine.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Experimental and Quasi-Experimental Studies</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Citation</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study Design</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Duration Factor</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Driving Metric</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Results</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Akerstedt et al (2010)<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Private vehicle owners (n = 14)<break/>Age: 37.9 y (range = 24–57)<break/>Sex: 7f, 7m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Counterbalanced crossover design</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep conditions:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Rested control, 8 h TIB (23:00–07:00)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep restriction, 4 h TIB (03:00–07:00)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High-fidelity simulator, mobile base<break/>SDLP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">No main effect of SR on SDLP</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Significant interaction of sleep duration and time of day (p &lt; 0.01). Worse in SR vs control during afternoon.</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anderson and Horne (2013)<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy young men (n = 8)<break/>Age: 20–26 yrs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Counterbalanced crossover design</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep conditions:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Normal duration control, 8.1 h ± 0.2 (M ± SD)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep restriction, 5 h TIB</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High-fidelity simulator, fixed base<break/>Lane crossing incidents</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Drivers more distracted following SR vs control condition (180.9 ± 12.6 vs 107.6 ± 18.8, p &lt; 0.005)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">During SR, more distractions were associated with incidents than for control sleep (p &lt; 0.048)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Barrett et al (2004)<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy young women (n = 12)<break/>Age: 20.7 ± 0.1 y (M ± SEM)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Counterbalanced crossover design
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Placebo vs Alcohol</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep conditions:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Normal duration control, 8.1 h ± 0.2 h (M ± SEM)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep restriction, 5 h TIB (02:00–07:00)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High-fidelity simulator, fixed base
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Lane crossing incidents</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significant effect of condition (p &lt; 0.001):
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">5 h TIB (placebo) had 784% more incidents than normal sleep (placebo)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bartrim et al (2020)<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy young adults (n = 20)<break/>Age: 23.3 ± 5.7 y (M ± SD)<break/>Sex: 11f, 9m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Randomized crossover trial
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Placebo vs Caffeine</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep conditions:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Day 0: Rested control, ≥8 h TIB (wake time at 05:00)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Day 1–3: Sleep restriction, 5 h TIB (00:00–05:00)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medium-fidelity driving simulator, fixed-base
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">SDLP</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">SDSP</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Lane crossing</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">No main or interaction effects of day (8 h vs 5 h TIB) or treatment (placebo vs caffeine) on SDLP or lane crossing</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Main effect of day on SDSP (p = 0.025), with worse performance on day 1 (5 h TIB).</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cai et al (2021)<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Younger adults (n = 16)<break/>Age: 24.3 ± 3.1 y<break/>Sex: 7f, 9m<break/>Older adults (n = 17)<break/>Age: 57.3 ± 5.2 y<break/>Sex: 8f, 9m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed design, counterbalanced crossover</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep conditions:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Rested control, 8 h TIB</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep deprivation, 0 h TIB (≥24-h wakefulness)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">On-road assessment, closed-loop track
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Lane departures</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list><break/>Critical incidents (crashes, near-misses)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Younger drivers exhibited 7.37 × more lane departures, and 11 × greater risk of critical incidents following sleep deprivation.</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Older drivers exhibited 3.5 × more lane departures following sleep deprivation.</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caponecchia and Williamson (2018)<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy driving adults (n = 41)<break/>Mean age range: 37 ± 8.3–42.1 ± 6.3 y (M ± SD)<break/>Sex: 16f, 25m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Randomized control trial</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep conditions:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">0 h sleep loss – 7.59 ± 1.94 h of TST</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">2 h sleep loss – 5.05 ± 1.69 h of TST</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">4 h sleep loss – 4.06 ± 1.08 h of TST</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medium-fidelity driving simulator, fixed-base
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Percentage of speed limit</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list><break/>SDLP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Main effect of sleep loss (p = 0.001) on SDLP:
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">4 h sleep loss worse than 2 h (p = 0.016) and 0 h (p = 0.001) of sleep loss</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Main effect of sleep loss (p = 0.020) on percentage of speed limit:</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">2 h sleep loss drove slower vs 0 h (p = 0.031) and 4 h (p = 0.041) sleep loss</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">De Valck and Cluydts (2001)<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy young adults (n = 12)<break/>Age: 22.5 ± 1.6 y (M ± SD)<break/>Sex: 5f, 7m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Counterbalanced crossover design
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Placebo vs Caffeine</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep conditions:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Rested control, 7.5 h TIB (00:00–07:30)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep restriction, 4.5 h TIB (00:00–04:30)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC-based driving task
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Lane drifting</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">SDSP</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list><break/>Critical incident (crash, off-road event)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Worse lane drifting (p &lt; 0.05) for 4.5 h TIB than 7.5 h TIB (placebo condition)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Trend (p &lt; 0.10) of TIB effect for SDSP, 4.5 h worse than 7.5 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">More critical incidents (p &lt; 0.05) for 4.5 h TIB than 7.5 h TIB at 13:00 (placebo group)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Filtness et al (2012)<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy male drivers (n = 40)<break/>Age: young – 22.7 y (range = 20–26); older – 66.6 y (range = 52–74)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed design, counterbalanced crossover</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep conditions:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Normal duration control, mean range: 7.8–8.4 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep restriction, 5 h TIB</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High-fidelity simulator, fixed base<break/>Lane crossing incidents</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Significant (p &lt; 0.001) effect of sleep condition, with more sleep-related incidents following SR (young and old)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Horne et al (2003)<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy young men (n = 12)<break/>Age: 22.7 y (range = 20–26)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Counterbalanced crossover design
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Placebo vs Alcohol</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep conditions:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Normal duration control, 8.4 h (7.5–9 h)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep restriction, 5 h TIB</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High-fidelity simulator, fixed base
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Lane crossing</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significant effect of condition (p &lt; 0.001):
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">5 h TIB (placebo or alcohol) worse than habitual sleep (placebo)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jongen et al (2015)<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy adults (n = 24)<break/>Age: 26.9 ± 3.4 y (M ± SD)<break/>Sex: 12f, 12m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Counterbalanced crossover design</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep conditions:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Normal duration control, wake time &lt;07:45</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep deprivation, 0 h TIB (24-h wakefulness at 09:00)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">On-road assessment, motorway
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">SDLP</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">SDLP worse after sleep deprivation than control sleep (18.2 ± 0.7 vs 15.1 ± 0.6, p &lt; 0.001)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list><break/>SDSP worse after sleep deprivation than control sleep (2.50 ± 0.14 vs 2.09 ± 0.8, p &lt; 0.01)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Miyata et al (2010)<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy adults (n = 19)<break/>Age: 29.2 ± 8.1 y (M ± SD)<break/>Sex: 9f, 10m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Randomized crossover trial</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep conditions:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Rested control, 8 h TIB (23:00–07:00)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep restriction, 4 h TIB (03:00–07:00)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC-based driving task
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">SDLP</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Brake reaction times</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">No difference between sleep conditions for SDLP.</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Brake reaction time significantly longer in SR condition than control (546 ± 23 vs 478 ± 51 ms, p &lt; 0.05)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Otmani et al (2005)<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Young men (n = 10)<break/>Age: 29.6 ± 2.6 y (M ± SD)<break/>Middle-aged men (n = 10)<break/>Age: 49.6 ± 3.1 y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Counterbalanced crossover design</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep conditions:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Normal duration control, 8.0 h ± 0.9 h (M ± SD)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep restriction, 4h TIB (03:00–07:00)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High-fidelity simulator, mobile base
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">SDLP</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Steering wheel movements</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Lane crossings</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">More frequent edge-line crossings (p = 0.04) after sleep restriction (2.7 ± 3.8) than normal sleep (1.4 ± 1.9)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">No significant effect SDLP or steering wheel movements (p &gt; 0.05)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perrier et al (2016)<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy adults (n = 24)<break/>Age: 26.9 ± 3.4 y (M ± SD)<break/>Sex: 12f, 12m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Counterbalanced crossover design</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep conditions:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Normal duration control, wake time &lt;07:45</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep deprivation, 0 h TIB (24-h wakefulness at 09:00)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">On-road assessment, motorway<break/>SDLP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">7 driving sessions prematurely terminated following sleep deprivation</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Significant condition × TOT interaction (p &lt; 0.01). SDLP stable following normal sleep, but significantly increases with sleep deprivation</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Philip et al (2005a)<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy young men (n = 22)<break/>Age: 21.5 y (range = 18–24)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Randomized crossover trial</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep conditions:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Rested control, 8.5 h TIB (23:00–07:30)
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep restriction, 2 h TIB (23:00–01:00)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">On-road assessment, highway
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Lane crossing incidents</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Significantly more incidents after restricted sleep (535 crossings) vs normal sleep (66):</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Relative risk of inappropriate crossings increased 8.1 times (95% CI: 3.5–20.5)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Philip et al (2005b)<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy young men (n = 12)<break/>Age: 21.1 ± 1.6 y (M ± SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Randomized crossover trial
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Real vs Simulated driving</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep conditions:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Rested control, 8 h TIB (23:00–07:00)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep restriction, 2 h TIB (23:00–01:00)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">On-road assessment, highway
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Lane crossing incidents</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list><break/>PC-based driving task<break/>Lane crossing incidents</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">More lane crossing incidents in simulated task vs real driving (p &lt; 0.001)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">More line crossing incidents in sleep restriction condition vs control</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list><break/>In real drive, SR resulted in ~4–5 incidents per 1.75 h drive compared to &lt;1 for rested control</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pizza et al (2004)<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy young adults (n = 10)<break/>Age: 24.9 ± 0.6 y (M ± SD)<break/>Sex: 5f, 5m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Repeated measures design</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep conditions:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Normal duration control, minimum, 6–7 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep deprivation, 0 h TIB</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC-based driving task
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Crashes</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">SDLP</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list><break/>Speed exceedance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Worse performance across the day following sleep deprivation:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Crashes (p = 0.014),</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">SDLP (p = 0.003),</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Speed exceedance (p = 0.018), and SDLP (p = 0.003)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shekari Soleimanloo et al (2019)<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy driving adults (n = 12)<break/>Age: 33.7 ± 7.1 y (M ± SD)<break/>Sex: 6f, 6m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Randomized crossover trial</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep conditions:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Rested control, 8 h TIB (23:00–07:00)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep deprivation, 0 h TIB (≥24-h wakefulness at 07:00)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">On-road assessment, closed-loop track
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Lane departures</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Premature termination of drive with sleep deprivation, OR: 1.18 (p = 0.031)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Increased rate of out-of-lane events, relative risk: 3.71, (95% CI: 3.5–3.9, p &lt; 0.0001)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shiferaw et al (2018)<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy driving adults (n = 9)<break/>Age: 33 ± 7.1 y (male; M ± SD), 34 ± 10.2 y (female)<break/>Sex: 5f, 4m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Randomized crossover trial</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep conditions:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Rested control, 8 h TIB (23:00–07:00)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep deprivation, 0 h TIB (≥24-h wakefulness)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">On-road assessment, closed-loop track
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Lane departures</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">6 driving sessions prematurely terminated following sleep deprivation</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Odds ratio for lane departures, 6.53 (95% CI: 4.3–10.2) with sleep deprivation</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vakulin et al (2007)<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy young men (n = 21)<break/>Age: 22.5 ± 3.7 y (M ± SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Randomized crossover trial
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Placebo vs Alcohol (0.025%/0.035%)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep conditions:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Normal TIB control, 8.5 h ± 0.3 h (M ± SD)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep restriction, 4 h TIB (02:00–06:00)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC-based driving task
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Steering deviation</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">SDSP</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Critical incident (crash, off-road event, braking lapses)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">No effect of SR (placebo) vs control for steering or SDSP</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Significantly (p = 0.002) more participants crashed in SR (placebo: 19%, alcohol: 23–33%) vs control (4.7%) condition</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wijayanto et al (2021)<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male university students (n = 15)<break/>Age: 21.1 ± 0.8 y (M ± SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Randomized crossover trial</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep conditions:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Rested control, 8 h TIB (21:00–05:00)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep deprivation, 0 h TIB (≥24-h wakefulness at 07:00)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC-based driving task<break/>collisions</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Significant effect of sleep condition on collisions (p = 0.006), with more collisions following sleep deprivation than normal sleep (7 ± 1 vs 2 ± 1)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zeller et al (2020)<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">University students (n = 60)<break/>Age: 23.9 ± 3.9 y (M ± SD)<break/>Sex: 32f, 28m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Randomized control trial</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep conditions:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Long sleep, ≥8 h TIB (≤23:00–07:00)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Short sleep, ≤ 5h TIB (≥02:00–07:00)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC-based driving task
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">SDLP</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Worse SDLP for short sleep vs long sleep (p = 0.005)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Steeper decline of SDLP with TOT for short sleep vs long sleep (p = 0.01)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: TIB, time in bed; TOT, time on task; TST, total sleep time; SDLP, standard deviation of lane position; SDSP, standard deviation of speed; SR, sleep restriction.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Nine experimental studies compared driving following a night-time control sleep with driving following either total sleep deprivation (0 h TIB; n = 7)</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29–31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> or severe night-time restriction (2 h TIB; n = 2).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Two of the total sleep deprivation studies were conducted using a computer-based simulated driving task,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> while the other five were conducted in real on-road drives, either on closed-loop tracks</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> or on the highway with a licensed instructor.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The two studies involving severe sleep restriction of 2 h TIB also assessed driving on an open highway.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> As expected based on the effects of sleep loss in other domains of performance,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> these studies all showed severe and significant impairments in both real and simulated driving performance.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The most common measures of driving performance were the standard deviation of lane position (SDLP), the frequency of lane departures/crossings, and crashes. When undergoing total sleep deprivation, a number of studies found that driving performance was significantly worse as compared with well-rested conditions. Pizza et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and Jongen et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> found that SDLP became significantly worse compared to a normal duration of sleep (ie, at least 6–7 h), with on-road and PC-based simulator tasks, respectively. Shiferaw et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> reported an elevated odds of lane crossings (OR = 6.53), and Shekari Soleimanloo et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> reported an increased odds (OR = 1.18) of having to terminate the drive prematurely and an increased risk of out-of-lane events (OR = 3.71), both on on-road closed-loop tracks. Similar findings were reported by Cai et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> on a similar closed-loop track, with lane crossings increasing by 3.5 and 7.4 times in older and younger adults, respectively.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Twelve experimental studies investigated the effects of moderate sleep loss, ranging from 4 h to 5 h TIB. Of these studies, four assessed performance using computer-based simulated driving tasks</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and eight used medium- to high-fidelity driving simulators,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14–17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> which had wider display screens and more realistic vehicle controls. Overall, the results from these studies also indicate significantly worse performance for short sleep durations compared to normal sleep durations of 7.5 h to 8.5 h. When restricted to between 4 h and 5 h TIB, the SDLP tended to become larger and there were more frequent critical incidents, including crashes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> This was not uniform across all studies, however, as Miyata et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> observed no effect of 4-h TIB on SDLP on a PC-based driving task, though brake reaction times did become significantly longer. Research from the high-fidelity driving simulators with fixed base cabins also found significantly more lane crossings and increased SDLP with 5 h TIB. These measures also became significantly worse with high-fidelity driving simulations after 4 h TIB.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In a separate study, Caponecchia and Williamson</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> compared the effects of three sleep loss conditions on driving in a medium-fidelity simulator by requiring participants to reduce their normal sleep durations via delayed bedtimes – 0 h (control), 2 h, or 4 h. Participants obtained an average (± SD) of 7.6 (± 1.9) h, 5.1 (± 1.7) h, and 4.1 (± 1.1) h of sleep in each condition, respectively. It was found that SDLP during the subsequent morning drive was significantly worse for participants who slept ~4.1 h than for both other conditions, but sleeping ~5.1 h was not significantly worse than ~7.6 h. In terms of maintaining the speed limit, participants who slept ~5.1 h (mild sleep loss) drove slower than those in the control and moderate sleep loss conditions – possibly an indication of drivers with less sleep loss attempting to be more careful and drivers with greater sleep loss being more reckless. Although the effects of 4–5 h TIB have not compared against a control sleep, all the results show a consistent pattern of impairment on the primary driving measures. No experimental or quasi-experimental studies investigated the effects of sleep restriction to 6 h or 7 h TIB.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2004">
        <title>Naturalistic and Longitudinal Studies</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Naturalistic studies typically involve observation without the classification of participants into groups, and without the implementation of specific conditions. Just one longitudinal and three naturalistic studies were included in this review based on the predetermined selection criteria, the findings of which were all based on self-report measures (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). Two naturalistic studies were based on data collected from professional drivers (heavy vehicle drivers),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> with one naturalistic study of a population of nurses</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> and the one included longitudinal study based on a large sample of young drivers (aged 17–24 years).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> All studies included real-world driving outcomes, such as crash rates and driving performance measures (ie, lane deviation). Two studies</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> provided a comparison of driving outcomes in situations where prior sleep was either greater or less than 6 h in the previous day. Findings suggested that where drivers had fewer than 6 h of sleep prior to driving, there was an increased risk of crashes and critical incidents (ie, both crashes and near misses). However, neither study broke down prior sleep duration further than a simple pairwise comparison (ie, comparing a longer sleep with a shorter sleep group). Therefore, it is possible (and indeed likely) that greater performance decrements occur when fewer than 6 hours of prior sleep is obtained. One study</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> found that driving performance decrements were seen earlier in the drive in heavy vehicle drivers who obtained fewer than 7 h of sleep as compared with drivers who had obtained more sleep. Conversely, one study indicated that there was no difference in driving performance metrics (swerve and hard braking) based on prior sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Unfortunately, no appropriate odds ratios were included within any naturalistic or longitudinal study. As a result, we are limited to the conclusions we can draw from these studies on the relationship between prior sleep and driving performance – other than to state that more sleep is typically associated with improved performance.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Naturalistic and Longitudinal Studies</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Citation</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study Design</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Duration Factor</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Driving Metric</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Results</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hanowski et al (2007)<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Truck drivers (n = 82)<break/>Age: 39 years (range = 24–58 years)<break/>Sex: 1f, 81m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Naturalistic study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prior sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep duration prior to critical incident</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-report</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">On-road vehicle
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Critical incident (Crashes, near crashes and crash relevant conflicts)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration (p = 0.0001)<break/>Mean: 6.63 ± 1.47 h<break/>Prior to critical incident (all): 5.28 ± 2.03 h<break/>Sleep duration (p = 0.0005 compared with mean)<break/>Prior to critical incident (all): 5.25 ± 2.15 h</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liu et al (2019)<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heavy vehicle drivers (n = 96).<break/>Age: Not reported<break/>Sex: Not reported</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Naturalistic study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitual sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Insufficient sleep time (&lt;7 h) vs normal sleep time (7–9 h) vs abundant sleep time (&gt;9 h)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">On-road vehicle
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Lane deviation</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Lane crossing</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lane deviation<break/>Insufficient sleep time: Substantial increase after 8 h of driving, peak after 9 h of driving<break/>Normal sleep time: No increase based on driving hours<break/>Abundant sleep time: Substantial increase after 9 h of driving</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Martiniuk et al (2013)<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Young adult drivers aged in New South Wales (Australia) (n = 20,822)<break/>Age: 17 = 49%; 18–19 = 37%; 20–24 = 14%<break/>Sex: 10,502f, 8825m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longitudinal cohort</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitual sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-reported sleep duration: &lt;6 h vs &gt;6 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incident Database<break/>Crashes / accidents</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greater risk of crash in participants who reported sleeping less than 6 h/night compared with those who reported sleeping more than 6 h (relative risk [RR], 1.21; 95% CI, 1.04–1.41).</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smith et al (2021)<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Night shift nurses (n = 32)<break/>Age: 33.4 ± 7.2 years<break/>Sex: Not reported</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Naturalistic study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prior sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-reported prior sleep in previous 24 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">On-road vehicle
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Swerve</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Hard braking</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hours of prior sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Swerve (p = 0.84)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Hard braking (p = 0.98)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2005">
        <title>Case–Control Studies</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">After screening, 11 case–control studies were deemed eligible for inclusion (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). In the context of this review, these studies obtained driving incident records (cases) from crash databases, police reports, or at hospital emergency rooms. Comparisons of prior sleep duration were then made between these groups and matched controls (who had either not experienced a crash, had only experienced a non-sleep-related crash, or were not deemed culpable of a crash). There were some differences in how sleep-wake history was measured and how cases/controls were defined between case–control studies included in this review. Nine case–control studies measured self-reported sleep duration in the prior sleep period, prior night, or the prior 24 h immediately before the crash.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39–41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43–45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The remaining case–control studies measured average daily sleep over the past week and amount of sleep in the prior 48 h,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> or the average daily sleep in the last three months.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Cases were defined as crashes where at least one person died or was injured requiring hospitalization;</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> where the driver was admitted to the hospital emergency room;</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> where a fatality was caused by falling asleep at the wheel;</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> reported by police officers;</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and where the drivers were hospitalized and also deemed to be responsible for the crash.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0003" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Case–Control Studies</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Citation</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study Design</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Duration Factor</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Driving Metric</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Results</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cummings et al (2001)<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases (n = 200)<break/>Age ≤44 y: 62.5%<break/>Sex: 67.0% male<break/>Control (n = 199)<break/>Age ≤44 y: 53.3%<break/>Sex: 70.9% male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case–control</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average hours slept per night in last week<break/>Hours of sleep in previous 48 hours:</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Cases</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Car drivers interviewed within 96 h of crash</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Controls</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Drivers matched to reference crash location, hour, and day of the week</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Average hours asleep per night, adjusted RR of crash = 1.1 (95% CI: 0.9–1.3, p &gt; 0.05)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list>
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Increased crash risk for drivers who slept ≤9 h in the prior 48 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Connor et al (2002)<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases (n = 571)<break/>Age ≤44 y: 72.4%<break/>Sex: 65.3% male<break/>Controls (n = 588)<break/>Age ≤44 y: 60.5%<break/>Sex: 58.7% male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case–control</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep in previous 24 hours:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">≤5 h vs &gt;5 h (Ref.)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Cases</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: Car drivers admitted to hospital or died as result of a crash</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Controls</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Randomly selected drivers</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Compared to &gt;5 h, injury crash risk for drivers reporting ≤5 h of sleep in prior 24 h increased, OR 2.7 (95% CI: 1.4–5.4)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stutts et al (2003)<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases (n = 467)<break/>Age 35.7 y<break/>Sex: 70% male<break/>Positive Controls (n = 529)<break/>Age 39.4 y<break/>Sex: 55% male<break/>Negative Controls (n = 407)<break/>Age 57.5 y<break/>Sex: 48% male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case–control</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hours slept night/day before crash:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;4 h, 4–4.9 h, 5–5.9 h, 6–6.9 h, 7–7.9 h, 8 h (Ref.), &gt;8 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list><break/>Habitual hours sleep/night:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;5 h, 5–5.9 h, 6–6.9 h, 7–7.9 h, ≥8 h (Ref.)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Cases</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: “Sleep crash” driver identified as asleep or fatigued</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Positive control</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Crashes in which driver not identified as asleep or fatigued</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Negative control</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: sample of drivers with no history of crashes in prior 3 years</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep prior to crash (Ref. 8 h)
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep crash vs control crash, ≥8 h, OR 0.94 (95% CI: 0.56–1.58), 7–7.9 h, OR 1.25 (95% CI: 0.79–1.97), 6–6.9 h, OR 2.58 (95% CI: 1.63–4.09), 5–5.9 h, OR 9.80 (95% CI: 5.49–17.47), 4–4.9 h, OR 12.17 (95% CI: 6.20–23.89), &lt;4 h, OR 19.87 (95% CI: 9.89–39.92)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list><break/>Habitual sleep (Ref. ≥8 h):
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep crash vs No crash, 7–7.9 h, OR 0.94 (95% CI: 0.59–1.49), 6–6.9 h, OR 1.45 (95% CI: 0.91–2.30), 5–5.9 h, OR 4.00 (95% CI: 2.10–7.62), &lt;5 h, OR 6.13 (95% CI: 2.28–16.49)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorrian et al (2011)<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases (n = 62)<break/>Controls (n = 45)<break/>Age: Not reported<break/>Sex: Not reported</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case–control</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep in prior 24 h<break/>Sleep in prior 48 h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Cases</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: Single-vehicle non-fatal crashes attributed to fatigue</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Control</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: Single-vehicle non-fatal crashes not attributed to fatigue</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fatigue-related crash vs control:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep in prior 24 h, 6.9 ± 3.0 h vs 9.1 ± 2.1 h (p &lt; 0.01)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list>
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep in prior 48 h, 15.8 ± 4.5 h vs 17.7 ± 3.4 h (p &lt; 0.05)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bakiri et al (2013),<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> Galéra et al (2012)<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases (n = 453)<break/>Age ≤44 y: 67%<break/>Sex: 63% male<break/>Controls (n = 502)<break/>Age ≤44 y: 69%<break/>Sex: 59% male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case–control</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hours slept during the previous 24 h:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;6 h vs &gt;6 h (Ref.)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Cases</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Driver deemed responsible for crash, admitted to hospital in previous 72 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Control</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Driver deemed not responsible for crash, admitted to hospital in previous 72 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration in prior 24 h:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;6 h, 2.06 (95% CI: 1.31 to 3.23)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stevenson et al (2014)<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases (n = 530)<break/>Age: 44 y (range = 21–74)<break/>Controls (n = 517)<break/>Age: 46 y (range = 19–74)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case–control</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The hours of sleep in the prior day before the crash</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Cases</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Heavy-vehicle drivers involved in police-reported non-fatal crashes</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Control</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Heavy-vehicle drivers who had not crashed</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Likelihood of sleep duration affecting crash rate: OR 0.98 (95% CI: 0.97–1.00)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Herman et al (2014)<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases (n = 131)<break/>Age ≤44 y: 75.6%<break/>Sex: 95.4% male<break/>Controls (n = 752)<break/>Age ≤44 y: 74%<break/>Sex: 93.2% male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case–control</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amount of sleep in the previous 24 h:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;6 h vs ≥6 h (Ref.)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Cases</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Motor vehicles involved in crashes where at least one person died or was hospitalized</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Control</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: motor vehicles identified in roadside surveys</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increase in the odds those who reported &lt;6 h of sleep during the previous 24 h: OR 5.9 (95% CI: 1.66–20.85)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Philip et al (2014)<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases (n = 272)<break/>Age: 39.8 ± 16.9 y<break/>Sex: 42.7% male<break/>Controls (n = 272)<break/>Age: 43.9 ± 16.0 y<break/>Sex: 57.4% male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case–control</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleeping ≤6 h in the last three months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Cases</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Drivers of 4-wheel vehicles admitted to hospital emergency room after a traffic crash</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Control</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Drivers interviewed during random police road checks</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compared to &gt;6 h of sleep per night, sleeping ≤6 h significantly increased the crash risk. OR: 1.69 (95% CI: 1.00–2.85)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tefft (2018)<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases (n = 3600)<break/>Age ≤44 y: 68%<break/>Sex: 53% male<break/>Controls (n = 3245)<break/>Age ≤44 y: 63%<break/>Sex: 56% male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case–control</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hours of sleep in 24 h before crash:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;4:00 h, 4:00–4:59 h, 5:00–5:59 h, 6:00–6:59 h, 7:00–9:59 h (Ref.), ≥10:00 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Cases</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: drivers involved in a crash and deemed culpable</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Controls</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: drivers involved in a crash and deemed nonculpable</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compared to sleep ≥7 and &lt;10 h, the odds of being culpable for the crashes increased:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">≥10 h, OR 1.3 (95% CI: 0.9–1.7),</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">≥6–&lt;7 h, OR 1.3 (95% CI: 1.04–1.7),</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">≥5–&lt;6 h, OR 1.9 (95% CI: 1.1–3.2),</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">≥4–&lt;5 h, OR 2.9 (95% CI: 1.4–6.2),</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;4 h, OR 15.1 (95% CI: 4.2–54.4)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kalsi et al (2018)<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases (n = 122)<break/>Age: 44 ± 19 y<break/>Sex: 82% male<break/>Controls (n = 136)<break/>Age: 45 ± 19 y<break/>Sex: 85% male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case–control</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration the previous night:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;6 h vs ≥6 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Cases</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: fatal motor-vehicle crash caused by falling asleep at the wheel</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Controls</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: fatal motor-vehicle crash not caused by falling asleep</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compared to ≥6 h sleep, the OR of a sleep-related fatal crash increased with short sleep &lt;6 h, 9.45 (95% CI: 1.49–59.97)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Crash likelihood was assessed based on a selected sleep duration cut-point. Five studies investigated the odds of having an incident after &lt;6 h of sleep compared to &gt;6 h of sleep,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44–46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and one study compared the odds of an incident after &lt;5 h compared to &gt;5 h sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Bakiri et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> found that there was more than double the odds having a crash with &lt;6 h sleep (OR: 2.06, 95% CI: 1.31–3.23), and Herman et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> found that the odds of crashing were almost six times greater (OR: 5.9, 95% CI: 1.66–20.85). Kalsi et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> found that the odds of a fatal accident following &lt;6 h of sleep the previous night were significantly higher than with &gt;6 h of sleep (OR: 9.45, 95% CI: 1.49–59.97). When using a shorter sleep cut-point of &lt;5 h of sleep in the past 24 h, Connor et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> found that the odds of a serious crash were more than double for the short sleep group (OR: 2.7, 95% CI: 1.4–5.4).</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Unlike the aforementioned case–control studies, Stutts et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and Tefft</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> assessed the odds of having a crash based on multiple sleep duration conditions against a reference sleep. Compared to 8 h of sleep in the prior 24 h, the odds of a fatigue-related crash over a regular crash increased after 6–7 h of prior sleep (OR: 2.6, 95% CI: 1.6–4.1) but even more so after &lt;4 h of prior sleep (OR: 20, 95% CI: 9.9–39.9).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In the study by Tefft,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> drivers were most likely to be identified as culpable of causing a crash when obtaining less than 4 h sleep (OR: 15.1, 95% CI: 4.2–54.5). However, even a mild form of sleep loss (6–7 h sleep obtained in the last 24 h) increased the odds of being culpable of a crash (OR: 1.3, 95% CI: 1.04–1.7). Approximately double the risk of being culpable for a crash was seen at between ≥5–&lt;6 h (OR: 1.9, 95% CI: 1.1–3.2) and ≥4–&lt;5 h (OR 2.9, 95% CI: 1.4–6.2). See </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> for an overview of crash likelihood based on prior sleep within case–control studies that reported appropriate odds ratios.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Odds ratios for case–control studies assessing the likelihood of a crash based on prior sleep. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>†</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">OR of a fatigue crash vs non-fatigue crash, *OR of a fatigue crash vs no crash. Note Ref categories differ between studies (range: 6–8 h) but reflect a greater amount of prior sleep.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-175-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2006">
        <title>Cross-Sectional Studies</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Twenty-five cross-sectional studies met the inclusion criteria (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). A number of these studies were performed in large samples of the general population,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51–53</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55–57</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> with some performed in occupation-based samples, such as nurses</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and heavy vehicle drivers.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0063" ref-type="bibr">63–68</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Typically, these studies were based on either interview or survey data and therefore relied on individual recall.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0004" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Cross-Sectional Studies</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Citation</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study Design</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Duration Factor</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Driving Metric</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Results</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abe et al (2010)<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drivers who had been in a rear end, single vehicle, or other crash (n = 1772)<break/>Age = 35.2±15.5 years<break/>Sex: 510f, 1262m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prior sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep duration preceding crash</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;6 h vs &gt;6 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rear end, single vehicle collision, or other motor vehicle crash</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Results showed that the occurrence of rear-end collision was significantly associated with a sleep duration of less than 6 h (adjusted OR [95% CI] = 2.20 (1.31–3.70), p &lt; 0.01).</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Shorter sleep duration less than 6 h was also significantly associated with the occurrence of single-car crashes (adjusted OR [95% CI] = 2.45 (1.38–4.35), p &lt; 0.01)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abe et al (2011)<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">General population (n = 4097)<break/>Age = 42.5±13.4 years<break/>Sex: 873f, 3224m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitual sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-reported sleep duration on weekdays</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;6 h, 6 h–&lt;7h, 7 h–&lt;8 h, 8 h–&lt;9h, ≥9h</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported motor vehicle crashes in the last 5 years attributed to falling asleep</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reports of motor vehicle crash/es attributed to falling asleep in the last 5 years<break/>&lt;6 h: 2.2*<break/>6 h–&lt;7 h: 1.5%<break/>7 h–&lt;8 h: 0.2%<break/>8 h–&lt;9 h: 0.8%<break/>≥9 h: 0.0%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abe et al (2012)<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">General population (n = 4097)<break/>Age = 42.5±13.4 years<break/>Sex: 873f, 3224m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitual sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-reported sleep duration on weekdays</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;6 h, 6 h–&lt;7 h, 7 h–&lt;8 h, 8 h–&lt;9 h, ≥9 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported falling asleep at the wheel in the previous year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reports of having fallen asleep while driving<break/>&lt;6 h: 15.4%*<break/>6 h–&lt;7h: 9.7%*<break/>7 h–&lt;8h: 5.4%<break/>8 h–&lt;9h: 6.3%<break/>≥9 h: 11.1%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AlShareef et al (2021)<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">General population (n = 4679)<break/>Age = 32.3 ± 11.3 years<break/>Sex:638 f, 4071m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitual sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-reported average sleep duration</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported falling asleep at the wheel in the previous year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Shorter sleep duration [OR 0.91 (95% CI 0.84–0.97); p = 0.007] associated with increased odds of having fallen asleep while driving in the previous year</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Andreassen et al (2018)<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nurses (n = 1781)<break/>Age = 36.6 ± 8.8 years<break/>Sex: 1595f, 177m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitual sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-reported sleep duration</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported falling asleep at the wheel</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep duration (hours) was inversely and significantly related to dozing off while driving. OR [95% CI] = (0.71[0.55–0.92])</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Center for Disease Control and Prevention (2011)<xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">General population (n = 74,571)<break/>Age =<break/>19–24: 2330<break/>25–34: 6637<break/>35–44: 10645<break/>45–54: 15,407<break/>55–64: 16,385<break/>≥65: 23,167<break/>Sex: 46,241f, 28,330m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitual sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-reported average sleep duration</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;7 h\ vs ≥7 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported falling asleep at the wheel during the last 30 days</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">4.7% (95% CI: 4.2–5.1%) report nodding off/falling asleep while driving in past 30 days.</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Those sleeping &lt;7 h/day on average were more likely to report falling asleep while driving (7.3% vs 3%).</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Center for Disease Control and Prevention (2013)<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">General population (n = 147,076)<break/>Age =<break/>19–24: 4361<break/>25–34: 12,200<break/>35–44: 20,231<break/>45–54: 29,362<break/>55–64: 33,054<break/>≥65: 47,868<break/>Sex: 90,755f, 56,321m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitual sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-reported average sleep duration</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list>
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">≤6 h, 7 h–9 h, ≥10 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported falling asleep at the wheel during the last 30 days</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">4.2% (95% CI: 3.9–4.6%) fall asleep at the wheel in the past 30 days.</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list><break/>Prevalence of falling asleep at wheel:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">≤6h/night = 6.7% (95% CI: 6.1–7.5%)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">7–9h/night = 2.6% (95% CI: 2.3–2.9%)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">≥10h/night = 3.9% (95% CI: 2.5–6.0%)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chen et al (2010)<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">General population (n = 1781)<break/>Age = 46.6 ± 17.8 years<break/>Sex: 1595f, 177m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitual sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;7 h vs &gt;7 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported major injuries</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Non-significant increase in the odds of experiencing a traffic related injury among drivers reporting less than 7hrs habitual sleep time (OR = 1.35, 95% CI = 0.97–1.87).</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Di Milia et al (2012)<xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Commuters in regional Queensland (n = 649)<break/>Age = 43.8 ± 13.5 years<break/>Sex: 75%m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep in previous 48 hours: &gt;10 h vs &lt;10 h.<break/>Sleep in the previous 24 hours: &gt;5 h vs &lt;5 h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lane crossing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Subjects who reported less than 10 hours sleep in the previous 48 hours were more likely to report a lane crossing during their journey (adjusted OR 2.58, 95% CI 1.03–6.46, p = 0.05).</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">No significant associations between subjects who reported less than 5 hours sleep in the previous 24 hours with the odds of reporting a lane crossing (adjusted OR 1.04, 95% CI 0.44–2.38, p = 0.93)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elliman et al (2020)<xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drill sergeants (n = 856)<break/>Age = Not reported<break/>Sex: 203f, 652m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prior sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-reported average sleep per 24 h during past week</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">≤3 h, 4 h, 5 h, 6 h, 7 h, ≥8 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported falling asleep at the wheel during a multi-day training assignment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">29% of drill sergeants who slept ≥6 h fell asleep at least once while driving</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">47% of drill sergeants who slept ≤5 h fell asleep while driving.</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Odds ratio of falling asleep at wheel at least once on the trail with ≤5 h sleep compared to ≥6 h sleep, 2.12 (95% CI, 1.51–2.98).</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hutchens et al (2008)<xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Young adults (n = 506)<break/>Age: 17.8 years (range 14–22)<break/>Sex: 236f, 270m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitual sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-reported sleep duration</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&gt;8 h vs &lt;8 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported involvement in crash/es at any time</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">&lt;8 h sleep group 1.284 times more likely to be involved in a crash than &gt;8 h sleep group</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">OR = 1.28, 95% CI = 1.03–1.61, p = 0.029)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ikeda et al (2021)<xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short haul commercial truck drivers (n = 110)<break/>Age = 49.5 ± 11.4 years<break/>Sex: 110m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitual sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-reported sleep duration</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;5 h, 5 h, 6 h, ≥7 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Overspeeding</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sudden start and acceleration</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sudden deceleration</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sudden braking</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overspeeding (adjusted OR)<break/>&lt;5 h: 1.49 (0.47–4.71)<break/>5 h: 0.83 (0.30–2.30)<break/>6 h: 1.0 (reference)<break/>≥7 h: 0.64 (0.19–2.16)<break/>Sudden start and acceleration (adjusted OR)<break/>&lt;5 h: 1.75 (0.14–22.12)<break/>5 h: 0.38 (0.07–2.13)<break/>6 h: 1.0 (reference)<break/>≥7 h: 0.27 (0.04–1.69)<break/>Sudden deceleration (adjusted OR)<break/>&lt;5 h: 1.17 (0.31–4.34)<break/>5 h: 0.39 (0.13–1.16)<break/>6 h: 1.0 (reference)<break/>≥7 h: 0.69 (0.19–2.51)<break/>Sudden braking (adjusted OR)<break/>&lt;5 h: 2.87 (0.87–9.45)<break/>5 h: 1.08 (0.38–3.03)<break/>6 h: 1.0 (reference)<break/>≥7 h: 1.05 (0.31–3.53)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Johnson et al (2017)<xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medical students (n = 307)<break/>Age: 26.4 years (range 21–42)<break/>Sex: 169f, 111m, 27 did not respond</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitual sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-reported average weeknight sleep in the previous academic quarter</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list><break/>&lt;6 h vs 6–6.9 h vs &gt;7 h sleep/night</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported ‘nodding off’ at the wheel in the past year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported ‘nodding off’ while driving in the past year (p=0.01)
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;6 h (n = 20; 22%)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">6–6.9 h (n = 85; 14.5%)</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&gt;7 h (n = 201; 5.5%)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kim et al (2018)<xref rid="cit0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Commercial vehicle drivers (n = 89)<break/>Age = 41.5 ± 10.4 years<break/>Sex: 89m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitual sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-reported sleep duration on workdays</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">≥7 h, ≥6 h–&lt;7 h, &lt;6 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reported motor vehicle crash or near miss in the previous year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Motor vehicle crash (p=0.022)<break/>≥7 h: 0.0%<break/>≥6 h–&lt;7 h: 8.1%<break/>&lt;6 h: 23.8%<break/>Near miss (p=0.016)<break/>≥7 h: 30.8%<break/>≥6 h–&lt;7 h: 28.2%<break/>&lt;6 h: 63.6%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lemke et al (2016)<xref rid="cit0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Truck drivers (n = 260)<break/>Age = 46.6±10.5 years<break/>Sex: 260m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitual sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-reported sleep duration on workdays</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Low = less than 6.5 h daily</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Moderately low = 6.5 h to 7.49 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Average = 7.5 h to 8.49 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">High = 8.5 h or more</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-reported sleepy driving frequency over the past month</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-reported crashes/near misses</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Sleep duration had a significant impact on crash or crash risk over the past month</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Beta = −0.38, p &lt; 0.05</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mahajan et al (2019a)<xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Truck drivers (n = 453)<break/>Age = ≤25: 10.8%<break/>26–35: 47.9%<break/>36–45: 30.9%<break/>≥46: 10.4%<break/>Sex: 453m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitual sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-reported sleep duration</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&gt;10 h\</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list><break/>8 h–10 h<break/>6 h–8 h<break/>4 h–6 h<break/>&lt;4 h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Violations including:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Ignoring traffic lights</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Driving too close to lead vehicle</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Forgetting to use indicator at turn</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Forget to use indicator to overtake</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Overspeeding/racing on the road in hurry</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Compared to sleeping less than 4 h, sleeping 6 h–8 h is associated with reduced frequency of driving violations in past 5 years (B = −0.62, SEM = 0.23, Wald = 7.10 p = 0.01, Odds ratio Exp(B)= 0.54).</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All other associations non-significant.</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mahajan et al (2019b)<xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Truck drivers (n = 453)<break/>Age = ≤25: 10.8%<break/>26–35: 47.9%<break/>36–45: 30.9%<break/>46–55: 8.6%<break/>≥56: 1.8%<break/>Sex: 453m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitual sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-reported sleep duration</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&gt;10 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list><break/>8–10 h<break/>6–8 h<break/>4–6 h<break/>&lt;4 h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported falling asleep at the wheel</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Significant decrease in the odds of falling asleep while driving among drivers reporting a habitual sleep duration of 6 h–8 h compared to those who reported less than 4 h of sleep (OR = 2.52[1.63, 3.88]).</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">All other comparisons were non-significant.</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maia et al (2013)<xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Truck drivers (n = 31,522)<break/>Age = 46.0 ± 17.3<break/>years<break/>Sex: 16,224f, 15,298m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitual sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-reported sleep duration</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;5 h, 5 h–6 h, 7 h, 8 h–9 h, or ≥10 h/night</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported drowsy driving
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">“During the past 30 days, have you ever nodded off or fallen asleep, even just for a brief moment, while driving?”</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Adjusted logistic regression results for falling asleep at the wheel associated with sleep duration.</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Reported is OR (95% CI).</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">7 h category used as ref, only significant associations reported.</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Equal to or less than 5 h = 3.6(2.6,4.9); 6 h = 1.9(1.4,2.5); 9 h = 0.3(0.15,0.72).</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Morrow et al (2004)<xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Truck drivers (n = 116)<break/>Age = 43 (range: 22–63) years<break/>Sex: 96%m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitual sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-reported sleep duration</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">5 h vs &gt;5 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Crashes</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Near misses</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Hierarchical regression analysis predicting near misses, and crash involvement showed no significant associations with sleep duration.</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ohayon et al (2010)<xref rid="cit0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">General population (n = 3345)<break/>Age = 33.3–41.3 (mean range)<break/>Sex: Not reported</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitual sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-reported duration of main sleep episode</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">6.7 ± 1.5 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported driving crashes during the previous 12 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep duration &lt;6h per main sleep episode was independently associated with driving crashes the previous year (OR: 2.2[1.1–4.7]).</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Other sleep duration categories not reported.</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perttula et al (2011)<xref rid="cit0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heavy vehicle drivers (n = 683)<break/>Age = Not reported<break/>Sex: Not reported</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitual sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-reported amount of sleep before starting work</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;5 h, 5–7 h, &gt;7 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-reported falling asleep at the wheel during the last year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fallen asleep (n = 188)<break/>&lt;5 h: 16.0%<break/>5–7 h: 63.1%<break/>&gt;7 h: 20.9%<break/>Have not fallen asleep (n = 495)<break/>&lt;5 h: 6.9%<break/>5–7 h: 58.4%<break/>&gt;7 h: 34.7%<break/>&lt;5h more likely than &gt;7h group to report momentarily falling asleep at the wheel (adjusted OR 2.12, 95% CI not reported, p &lt; 0.05).</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quera Salva et al (2014)<xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">General population recruited mid-drive at tollbooth (n = 3051)<break/>Age = 46 ± 13 years<break/>Sex: 75%m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prior sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-reported sleep in previous 24 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Near miss sleepy accidents (NMSA)
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">During current drive</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In previous year</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list><break/>“Sleepiness-related accident” in the previous year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Prior sleep in the past 24 h was not significantly associated with the occurrence of near misses or crashes.</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Radun et al (2004)<xref rid="cit0072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">General population (n = 1469)<break/>Age = Not reported<break/>Sex: Not reported</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep obtained prior to vehicle crash
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">(ref. 7–8 h) vs &lt;6 h, 6–7 h, &gt;8 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">AND time awake: (ref. &lt;8 h) vs 8–16 h, &gt;16 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vehicle crash data from Finnish in-depth road accident investigation system data (FIRAIS)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 2 (including prior sleep) (p &lt; 0.001)<break/>Prior sleep<break/>&lt;6h**: 8.4%<break/>6–7h: 9.0%<break/>7–8h (ref): 22.3%<break/>&gt; 8h: 60.3%<break/>Model 3 (including prior sleep and time awake) (p=0.01)<break/>Prior sleep<break/>&lt;6 h: 8.0%<break/>6–7 h: 9.8%<break/>7–8 h (ref): 21.2%<break/>&gt; 8 h: 61.1%<break/>Time awake<break/>&lt;8 h (ref): 51.6%<break/>8–16 h: 43.7%<break/>&gt;16 h***: 4.7%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Watling et al (2020)<xref rid="cit0073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Queensland road users (n = 257)<break/>Age = 21.1± 2.2 years<break/>Sex: 53.7%f</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitual sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep duration on Sleep Timing Questionnaire (STQ)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Driver Behaviour Questionnaire (DBQ)
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Lapses</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Errors</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Highway code violations</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Aggressive violations</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep duration: 8.3 ± 1.1 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">No significant correlation between sleep duration and self-reported driving lapses (r=−.12), errors (r=−.05), code violations (r=−.09), sleep-related close calls (r=−.05)</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wu et al (2020)<xref rid="cit0074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">University students (n = 11,770)<break/>Age = 74.4% aged 20–22 years<break/>Sex: 47.8%f</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitual sleep
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-reported sleep duration</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;7 h vs &gt;7 h</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Road traffic injuries in the past 12 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Greater likelihood of being injured via automobile crash among drivers reporting less than 7 h habitual sleep duration compared to those who reported more than 7 h (OR = 1.58 [1.49, 1.67], p &lt; 0.01).</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: *p &lt; 0.05 compared with 7 h–&lt;8 h group. **Strong effect for under 6 hours compared with ref (OR 10.37, 95% CI 3.98–26.99). ***Strong effect for &gt;16 hours (OR 8.05, 95% CI 2.10–30.90).</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Most cross-sectional studies were based on habitual reports (ie, how much sleep is generally obtained and/or crashes or incidents that occurred over the previous month/year) (n = 20). As would be expected, poorer driving outcomes were generally seen when fewer hours of sleep were habitually obtained. Many studies broke the amount of prior sleep into categories for direct comparison (ie, comparing driving outcomes in individuals who regularly obtain more or less than X hours of sleep per night). However, due to the real-world nature of these data, and the fact that habitual sleep duration for most individuals is over 6 h,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> few cross-sectional studies included group comparisons based on short periods of sleep (eg, &lt;5 h sleep per night).</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Two included articles (based on the same dataset) included participants who reported severely truncated habitual sleep opportunities. This study on truck drivers in India found that when drivers reported a habitual sleep duration of less than 4 h per night, there was an increased likelihood of driving violations, as compared with those who regularly obtained 6–8 h of sleep (OR: 0.87 when &lt;4 h prior sleep used as reference).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The second article using this dataset reported a similar increase in the likelihood of falling asleep while driving in individuals who regularly obtained less than 4h sleep/night (OR = 2.52).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In a study of 683 heavy vehicle drivers, individuals who habitually obtained 5 h sleep/night were over twice as likely to fall asleep at the wheel than drivers who regularly obtain more than 7 h/sleep per night.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> This aligns with findings of a study of over 31,000 truck drivers, where a significantly higher likelihood of having fallen asleep while driving over the past month was reported if the driver habitually reported obtaining either 5 h or 6 h of sleep as compared with obtaining 7 h of sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Within this study, approximately double the crash risk was seen when drivers habitually obtained 5 h of sleep per night as compared with 6 h. Similarly, driving errors (speeding, sudden start and acceleration, sudden deceleration, sudden braking) have been shown to double between 5 h and 6 h of habitual sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> One study examined shorter amounts of prior sleep than 6 h but unfortunately did not report the outcomes of less than 5 h prior sleep separately.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> This study found that in drill sergeants during a multi-day training operation, 47% of participants with an average of ≤5 h sleep/night during the week fell asleep while driving. These participants were more than twice as likely to fall asleep while driving than participants who had ≥6 h/night during the week.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">A number of studies included in this review compared driving outcomes between groups who habitually obtained either greater than or less than 6 h prior sleep. The majority of these studies demonstrate that where less then 6h of sleep is obtained, there are significant increases in self-reports of falling asleep while driving,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> driving crashes during the previous year,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and both rear end collisions and single vehicle crashes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> One study found that the frequency of having fallen asleep while driving during the previous year was significantly greater for individuals who habitually obtain less than 6 h sleep/night (15.4% of all individuals) than those who obtain between 7 h and 8 h of sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> However, this study also showed a significant increase in crash likelihood for individuals who regularly obtain 6–7 h of sleep per night – though to a smaller magnitude (9.7% of individuals).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">When the rate of motor vehicle crashes that the participant attributed to falling asleep at the wheel was assessed as an outcome, a significant increase was seen when &lt;6 h of habitual sleep (2.2% of individuals having experienced a crash caused by falling asleep) was compared with 7–8 h (0.2%).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> A separate study included crash and near miss rates (though these were not necessarily attributed to fatigue/falling asleep at the wheel).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In this study, participants who habitually obtained less than 6 h sleep/night were far more likely to experience a crash in the previous year (24%) than participants who regularly obtained ≥7 h (0%) or between 6 h and 7 h (8%) of sleep per night. Similarly, approximately double the number of individuals who obtained less than 6 h of sleep per night had experienced a near miss in the previous year, when compared with those who obtained 7 h or more sleep each night. Another study, based on population-level crash data, found that when prior sleep and time awake were included in a predictive model, there was a strong effect for obtaining fewer than 6 h of sleep prior to the crash.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> This study also found a strong effect of prior wake time &gt;16 h when compared with &lt;8 h.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Several cross-sectional studies included in this review compared habitual prior sleep with a higher-level cut-point (ie, 7 or 8 h sleep). One study compared outcomes from a large (~74,000) sample of drivers from the general population who regularly obtained greater or less than 7 h of sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> This study found that the shorter sleep group were more likely to report having fallen asleep while driving in the last 30 days (7.3% vs 3% of participants). Similarly, a study of over 11,000 university students in China found a greater likelihood of being injured in an automobile crash in individuals who habitually obtained less than 7 h of sleep per night (OR = 1.58).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Additionally, a significant increase in crash risk was shown in a sample of young drivers who regularly obtain less than 8 h of sleep, compared with those who regularly obtain ≥8 h (OR = 1.28).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Some studies (n = 3) performed correlational or regression analyses (rather than comparing groups) and found that sleep duration was significantly associated with an increased crash risk.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Another study indicated that shorter sleep duration was associated with an increased likelihood of having fallen asleep while driving (as opposed to experiencing a crash) in the previous year.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Just one study examined sleep duration over the previous 48 h,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> finding that for participants who reported less than 10 h of sleep over this period, there was an increased likelihood of a lane crossing (adjusted OR 2.58). However, this study did not compare the difference in driving performance based on hours of sleep over the previous 48 h in any more granularity than a binary comparison.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Several cross-sectional studies did not find any significant differences in driving outcomes based on prior sleep. For example, when likelihood of experiencing a self-reported accidental injury of any kind (including traffic injuries) was assessed based on prior sleep, there were no differences between individuals who habitually obtained more or less than 7 h sleep per night.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Similarly, studies have reported no differences in lane crossings,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> near misses, or crashes</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> when prior sleep was broken into greater or less than 5 h. Furthermore, one study based on data collected mid-drive at a tollbooth found no relationship between prior sleep and near miss sleepy accidents (NMSA) either during the present drive or in the previous year,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> and also no significant relationships were seen between prior sleep and lapses, errors, code violations, or near misses while driving.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> presents odds ratios for cross-sectional studies based on both prior sleep duration (ie, 5h, 6h, 7h) and outcome measure. Outcome measures have been divided into either driving performance (eg, lane deviation, over-speeding) or the likelihood of a crash or falling asleep while driving. Studies where odds ratios were not available were not included. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> presents an overview of odds ratio outcomes of both case–control and cross-sectional studies based on the amount of prior sleep.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Odds ratios for cross-sectional studies assessing the adverse driving outcomes based on prior sleep. Note Ref categories differ between studies (range: 6–8 h) but reflect a greater amount of prior sleep.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-175-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0004" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Odds ratios for cross-sectional and case–control studies assessing the likelihood of an adverse driving outcome (driving errors, falling asleep while driving, or crashing) based on prior sleep. Note Ref categories differ between studies (range: 6–8 h) but reflect a greater amount of prior sleep. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>†</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Fatigued crash versus non-fatigued crash. *Fatigued crash versus no crash.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-175-g0004" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2007">
        <title>Meta-Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Three meta-analyses were conducted: five hours or more sleep vs less than five hours sleep, six hours or more sleep vs less than six hours sleep and seven hours or more sleep vs less than seven hours sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
        <sec id="s0004-s2007-s3001">
          <title>Five Hours vs Less Than Five Hours Sleep</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Two studies were eligible for inclusion in the five hours vs less than five hours sleep meta-analysis</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). Pooled odds ratio meta-analysis showed a significant difference in odds of a poor driving outcome between the five hours sleep and the less than five hours sleep groups OR = 1.63, 95% CI [0.07; 3.19] </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> = 0.040. The results showed no significant heterogeneity (I</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 53.2%, Q = 2.14, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> = 0.144). Visual analysis of funnel plots shows some possible publication bias (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=392441.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Material D: Supplementary Figure 1, Panel A</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0005" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Forest plot of odds ratio meta-analysis for five hours sleep vs less than five hours sleep. Diamond presents the pooled odds ratio of studies included in meta-analysis. Dotted line denotes the odds ratio prediction interval.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-175-g0005" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The sensitivity analysis showed that the overall effect did not change with either study omitted. The ORs from sensitivity analysis ranged from 1.04 to 2.70. Subgroup analysis showed no significant difference between study by driving outcome: crash (k = 1) and lane crossing (k = 1), </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.144.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0004-s2007-s3002">
          <title>Six Hours Sleep vs Less Than Six Hours Sleep</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Ten studies were eligible for inclusion in the six hours sleep vs less than six hours sleep meta-analysis</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44–46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). Pooled odds ratio meta-analysis showed a significant difference in odds of poor driving outcome between the six hours sleep and the less than six hours sleep groups, OR = 1.27, 95% CI [1.08; 1.45], </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> &lt; 0.0001. The results showed no significant heterogeneity I</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 5.90%, Q = 9.56, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> = 0.387. Egger’s test and funnel plot analysis showed possible publication bias (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=392441.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Material D: Supplementary Figure 1, Panel B</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p =</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> 0.006.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0006" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Forest plot of odds ratio meta-analysis for six hours or more sleep vs less than six hours sleep. Diamond presents the pooled odds ratio of studies included in meta-analysis. Dotted line denotes the odds ratio prediction interval. The red rectangle denotes the predicted confidence interval for pooled effect.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-175-g0006" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The sensitivity analysis showed that the overall effect did not change with any studies omitted. The ORs from sensitivity analysis ranged from 1.20 to 1.63. Subgroup analysis showed no significant difference between study by driving outcome: crash (k = 9) and falling asleep (k = 1) </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.083.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0004-s2007-s3003">
          <title>Seven Hours Sleep vs Less Than Seven Hours Sleep</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Six studies were eligible for inclusion in the seven hours sleep vs less than seven hours sleep meta-analysis</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). Pooled odds ratio meta-analysis showed a significant difference in odds of poor driving outcome between the seven hours sleep and the less than seven hours sleep groups, OR = 1.45, 95% CI [1.01; 2.50], </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> &lt; 0.0001. The results showed significant heterogeneity between studies I</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 73.20%, Q = 18.63, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> = 0.002. Egger’s test and funnel plot analysis showed no significant publication bias (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=392441.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Material D: Supplementary Figure 1, Panel C</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">), </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.080.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0007" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Forest plot for meta-analysis of seven hours or more sleep vs less than seven hours sleep. Diamond presents the pooled odds ratio of studies included in meta-analysis. Dotted line denotes the odds ratio prediction interval. The red rectangle denotes the predicted confidence interval for pooled effect.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-175-g0007" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The sensitivity analysis showed that the overall effect did not change with any studies omitted. The ORs from sensitivity analysis ranged from 1.22 to 1.94. Subgroup analysis showed a significant difference by driving outcome: crash (k = 4), falling asleep (k = 1) and Injury (k = 1), </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.001. Falling asleep contributed the largest OR = 1.23, 95% CI [1.16; 1.26], followed by injury OR = 1.35, 95% CI [0.90; 1.80] and then crash OR = 1.21 95% CI [1.15; 1.26].</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2008">
        <title>Study Quality</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The quality of studies included in this review was generally moderate to high, as indicated by completion of JBI critical assessment tools (randomized controlled trial, quasi-experimental, case–control, and cross-sectional tools). As noted above, studies were categorised as being of low quality if they scored ≤40%, moderate quality if they scored &gt;40 to ≤70%, and of high quality if they scored &gt;70%.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Questions are numbered within the tables, and question text can be found in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=392441.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Material C</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. Quality assessment outcomes with associated percentages of criterion questions answered “yes” for experimental studies can be seen in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=392441.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, for quasi-experimental studies in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=392441.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 2</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, for naturalistic and longitudinal studies in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=392441.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 3</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, for case–control studies in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=392441.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 4</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, and for cross-sectional studies in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=392441.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 5</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. Scores ranged from 8 to 11, 6 to 8, 3 to 7, 6 to 10, and 3 to 8 on the experimental, quasi-experimental, naturalistic/longitudinal, case–control, and cross-sectional studies, respectively. The average proportion of criterion answered “yes” was 72.5% for experimental studies, 81.0% for quasi-experimental studies, 56.5% for naturalistic and longitudinal studies, 82.7% for case–control studies, and 68.6% for cross-sectional studies. The average proportion of criterion answered “yes” across all studies was 73.2% (high quality). As such, we can be reasonably confident in the evidence presented within this review as a whole. In particular, the evidence provided by studies with a higher degree of control over variables (ie, experimental, quasi-experimental, and case–control studies) was of particularly high quality. We can therefore be particularly confident in the conclusions drawn from these studies.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">To determine a point at which it may be legally possible to deem an individual to be impaired, it is critical to review the evidence available on driving performance based on prior sleep-wake behaviour. This systematic review was performed to synthesise relevant literature based on key study designs: experimental or quasi-experimental, naturalistic, longitudinal, case control, and cross-sectional. For all study design types, there were a range of publications available (experimental = 21, naturalistic = 3, longitudinal = 1, case–control = 11, and cross-sectional = 25). As may be expected, findings of the studies included in this review generally indicated that there is a dose–response relationship between prior sleep duration and driving outcomes. That is, participants who had previously had more sleep tended to perform better on driving tasks (both in a simulator and on the road). These driving outcomes typically included either performance measures (eg, lane deviation, speeding) or fatigue-related events (eg, likelihood of a crash or falling asleep behind the wheel).</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">A meta-analysis was undertaken of 18 eligible studies to compare the odds of a fatigue-related driving incident (including a crash, falling asleep while driving, injury, and driving error) based on amount of prior sleep. Unfortunately, many studies included in the qualitative review could not be included in the meta-analysis as outcomes inconsistent with odds ratio meta-analysis were reported, or comparable reference and outcome categories were not included in study designs. Despite this, all three meta-analyses showed an increased odds of a driving incident. As may be expected, the greatest likelihood of a driving incident was seen when participants who obtained less than five hours of prior sleep were compared with more than 5 hours of prior sleep. It is crucial to acknowledge, however, that very few studies available could be included in the five-hour meta-analysis due to heterogeneity in the available studies (n = 2).</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">In determining the appropriate BAC at which to deem a driver to be impaired, the degree of associated crash risk is considered – and decisions can be made as to the degree of risk a jurisdiction is willing to accept. At the 0.05%BAC level, there appears to be at a minimum, double the relative crash risk, as compared with 0.00%BAC – regardless of driver age and gender.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> At the 0.08%BAC level, the relative risk of a crash doubles again (ie, a driver is four times more likely to have a crash at this BAC as compared with 0.00%BAC).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> For many industrialised jurisdictions, the point at which relative crash risk reliably doubles is established as the point at which an individual will be “deemed impaired”.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> It may not be unreasonable to consider the point at which relative risk doubles based on fatigue. That is, how much prior sleep can be lost before the risk of a crash doubles – and is this considered an appropriate point at which to deem a driver impaired?</citation_analysis></p>
      <sec id="s0005-s2001">
        <title>A Potential Point to Deem Impairment</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">To decide where to deem impairment, outcomes of all study types can be evaluated to establish an amount of prior sleep that is most likely to accurately reflect driving performance outcomes for most drivers, most of the time. Within the present review, most studies that included 4 h or 5 h sleep periods saw significant and severe decreases in driving performance and/or increases in the likelihood of falling asleep at the wheel or experiencing a vehicle crash. These decrements generally reflected approximately double the likelihood of an adverse outcome (with some studies suggesting a far higher likelihood). Of note, the meta-analysis comparing five hours or more sleep with less than five hours sleep was only able to include two studies, due to heterogeneity in the available studies. However, this analysis indicated a near doubling of the odds of a driving error.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Performance decrements seen when drivers had either six or seven hours of prior sleep were both lower in severity and less consistent in their occurrence. Despite reduced impairment, this evidence does not suggest that if &gt;5 h sleep is obtained, all individuals will be safe to drive. That is, while it may be fair to classify individuals as “impaired” if they have had four or five hours of prior sleep (as impairment would likely be experienced by most individuals, most of the time), the opposite is not necessarily true for greater than 5 h of prior sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Arguably, this synthesis of the literature would support the theoretical implementation of deemed impairment at the 4–5 h of prior sleep range, given that the relative risk of a crash and/or serious driving error appears to approximately double after less than 5 h prior sleep. However, we must also consider community expectations and the practicality of implementing and enforcing this type of regulation – in addition to the degree of acceptability from regulatory bodies. As with the advent of blood alcohol concentration limitations, it may be prudent to begin with slightly more permissive restrictions – which most individuals are currently likely to meet during most drives regardless of fatigue-related deemed impairment regulation. The requirement for drivers to obtain at least 4 h of sleep prior to driving may be a more practical first step, rather than requiring 5 h of prior sleep. This is consistent with a 2016 expert consensus statement based on a Delphi methodology, which identified 2 h sleep in the previous 24 h as a potential point after which individuals are definitely unsafe to drive, but note that a high degree of impairment is also likely after 3–5 h prior sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">While a review of the literature may be able to establish a comparison between fatigue-related driving impairment and alcohol-related driving impairment, public policy and regulation are typically based on more than scientific evidence in isolation. For example, community acceptance of driving limitations must be considered, in addition to the appetite of relevant regulatory bodies to both implement and enforce fatigue-related deemed impairment. Furthermore, the practicality of enforcement may also play a role in establishing this type of regulation (eg, the limitations of roadside testing and/or the inclusion of prior sleep-wake behaviour in post-crash legal proceedings). Furthermore, there may be the opportunity to change these restrictions over time as community acceptability and familiarity with the concept of fatigue-related deemed impairment grows. This tightening of restrictions has happened with alcohol use in several jurisdictions, including Australia, with the permitted BAC decreasing from 0.08%BAC to 0.05%BAC over time.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0005-s2002">
        <title>Considerations When Assessing Fatigue-Related Driving Impairment Literature</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Determining what constitutes sufficient sleep to drive safely is, by nature, arbitrary to a degree. However, experimental studies (which include a high degree of control over potentially confounding factors) generally indicated that significant and severe performance decrements were seen when drivers had five or fewer hours of sleep in the previous 24 h period. As may be expected, it appears that greater decrements to driving performance occur when fewer hours of sleep were obtained (ie, performance was poorer after 4 h of prior sleep than after 5 h of prior sleep). This was demonstrated by several high-quality studies, such as Caponecchia and Williamson,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> who found that there was a marked difference in driving performance between individuals who had 4 h of prior sleep and those who had 5 h of prior sleep. Compared to prior sleep of ~8 h, Otmani et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> found more frequent lane crossings and Åkerstedt,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> in a particularly high-quality study (as determined via JBI assessment), saw a worsening of lane deviation after 4 hours of prior sleep opportunity. Several other key studies with high-fidelity simulators show large performance decrements, including significantly more lane crossings, after a 5 h sleep opportunity compared to 8 h opportunity.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15–17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> All included experimental and quasi-experimental studies were classified as either of high or moderate quality according to JBI quality assessments, suggesting that these findings are likely reflective of actual impairment. It therefore appears that based on experimental data, a significant increase in fatigue-related performance impairments to driving is seen when the individual has had fewer than 4 h sleep the previous night, but substantial decrements are also generally seen with less than 5 h sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Experimental studies included in this review were typically based on simulated driving performance and differ from on-road studies in both outcome measures (ie, lane deviation/speeding on a simulated driving task as compared with real-world metrics such as motor vehicle crashes) and the amount of prior sleep that was typically reported. By nature, naturalistic, longitudinal, case–control, and cross-sectional studies are based on either survey-style data collection or similar (eg, sleep and driving recall diaries), or large-scale crash statistics. As a result, there is less capacity for these real-world studies to control the amount of sleep obtained prior to driving. This means that, for many real-world studies, the amount of prior sleep assessed was greater than within experimental studies. Therefore, a number of studies compared real-world driving outcomes after 6, 7, or 8 h of sleep in the previous 24 h. These studies suggest that the most substantial differences in driving outcomes, including crash likelihood, were seen when drivers obtained less than 6 h sleep the night before. Fortunately, several key studies examined driving performance where prior sleep was greater or less than 4 or 5 h the night before.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65–67</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> These studies found that for drivers who regularly obtain less than 4 h sleep/night,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> the odds of falling asleep while driving were more than double those who regularly obtain 6–8 h sleep/night. However, drivers who habitually obtained less than 5 h sleep/night were also twice as likely to fall asleep than drivers who obtained at least 7 h sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Double the level of risk (of both crashes and driving errors) was also reported by other studies after obtaining less than 5 h prior sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> As such, it appears that based on self-report and habitual data (eg, cross-sectional, naturalistic, and longitudinal studies), a significant (approximately double) level of risk is seen after obtaining less than 5 h sleep the previous night. However, it must be noted that three out of four studies in this category had JBI quality scores of 50% or less, suggesting an overall low quality of evidence.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In a similar way to many of the included cross-sectional, naturalistic, or longitudinal studies, all included case–control studies were based on on-road data. However, these designs allow for more direct comparisons – for example, between groups of individuals who either had (case) or had not experienced a motor vehicle crash (control). From these studies, we can estimate the likelihood of a crash based on prior sleep. Several studies found double or greater risk of a crash after having had less than 6 h sleep the night before, as compared to being well rested.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> With even less prior sleep (ie, 5 h), a greater likelihood of crash was seen (between two and twelve times more likely</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). However, as with many observational studies included in this review, little granularity is available differentiating between, for example, three, four, and five hours of prior sleep (ie, all sleep periods ≤5 h are categorised together). However, all case–control studies included in this review were of high or moderate quality according to JBI assessments, suggesting that we can have a high degree of trust in these outcomes. It is therefore likely that this high degree of variability in crash likelihood represents differences in total sleep time under 5 h.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">When determining a point at which to deem an individual impaired, we must also consider the quality of evidence available. For all study design types, JBI quality assessments indicated that the literature in this area is of moderate-to-high quality. As discussed, studies investigating driving performance have been performed using a variety of research designs. Each of these designs has both benefits and limitations. Experimental and quasi-experimental designs are able to clearly differentiate between participants based on prior sleep (as this is typically controlled by the research team). These studies are able to easily compare groups of individuals who obtained 4, 5, and 6 h of sleep the night before – and thus are able to make clear statements as to the likelihood of certain outcomes based on prior sleep. However, these designs typically do not use real-world measures of driving, and therefore rely on the validity of driving simulators to reflect certain performance decrements. While these simulators are typically good at identifying certain driving outcomes (eg, lane deviations or speeding), they have limited applicability to real-world driving outcomes. They are typically not performed over extended periods of time (and as such are less likely to identify the likelihood of falling asleep at the wheel) and do not measure real-world crash likelihood. Conversely, self-report studies (eg, typically naturalistic, or cross-sectional studies) measure real-world outcomes. However, these designs rely on the participant’s memory, which may not be reliable. Furthermore, these study designs are generally based on reports of habitual sleep duration (ie, how much sleep an individual typically obtains), rather than how much sleep an individual reported obtaining prior to a specific driving-related incident (eg, a crash). There may therefore be either an over- or under-estimation of the amount of sleep obtained prior to an incident. It is critical to note that there are both benefits and drawbacks of each design type in establishing the impact of prior sleep on subsequent driving performance. As such, it is likely prudent to consider the findings of all study designs, with particular weighting given to those identified as being of high quality (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=392441.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Tables 1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">–</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=392441.docx" ext-link-type="uri">5</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We must also consider the applicability of findings to all drivers. Many studies – particularly those with experimental designs – were based on small sample sizes, which by nature limit generalisability to the broader population. Many of these studies included participants who were young and healthy, with no major sleep or health problems under optimum laboratory conditions (ie, without external factors that typically result in higher levels of fatigue seen in younger drivers</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). Some included experimental studies may therefore overestimate driving performance in the general population. It is possible that different driving performance decrements are seen within older age groups or among individuals with certain health conditions.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Limitations</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In the context of this systematic review, deemed impairment has been conceptualised based on the amount of sleep an individual has had over the previous day. However, prior sleep in the previous 24 h does not take into consideration other factors that may impact fatigue. For example, time of day is likely to impact fatigue and cognitive performance,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> with greater driving impairment typically seen during the overnight period, independent of prior sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Additionally, time awake is likely to impact fatigue, and associated cognitive performance.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0085" ref-type="bibr">85</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> That is, even if an individual had an extended sleep period the night before, greater fatigue is generally seen when the individual has been awake for a longer period of time. Not only this but prior sleep-wake history across multiple days can have a cumulative impact on fatigue.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0087" ref-type="bibr">87</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> As a result, using prior sleep to deem impairment may not capture all causes of elevated fatigue-related driving risk. Furthermore, there are interindividual differences in impairment of performance based on prior sleep,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> which would be a limitation of using prior sleep to establish driving impairment. That is, some individuals (likely a small minority) may be prevented from driving when they are not impaired, and some individuals would be legally permitted to drive, despite experiencing a high degree of impairment. In addition, drivers who have sleep disorders (where sleep may have reduced restorative value) are likely to experience greater fatigue even in situations where they have had what is deemed to be “sufficient sleep”.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">When comparing the potential impact of deemed impairment for fatigued driving with existing drink-driving regulation and enforcement, we must acknowledge that there are inherent differences. For drink-driving, it is likely that significant decreases in crashes and fatalities can, at least in part, be attributed to the capacity for roadside testing.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Similar roadside testing for prior sleep or fatigue is less straightforward. While there has been some progress toward establishing a biomarker capable for roadside assessment of fatigue, this is not currently available.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> As such, a prior sleep requirement for driving may be difficult to enforce at the roadside. However, it may be possible to initially use fatigue-related deemed impairment regulation as both a deterrent and as part of post-crash prosecution (ie, where digital and/or surveillance records can be used).</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In basing this preliminary conceptualisation of deemed impairment on prior sleep only, we must acknowledge that this methodology has limitations. However, we must also consider potential public acceptance and ease of regulation. In this case, scientifically perfect may be the enemy of good policy. That is, a simple, easy to understand measure for deeming impairment (ie, prior sleep) would likely be much easier to implement and communicate to relevant stakeholders (both drivers and regulatory bodies). However, the use of prior sleep only is likely the first step toward a more complex methodology for deeming impairment. A more complex methodology may, for example, include measures of prior wakefulness and sleep over the previous 48 hours – and thus be able to detect fatigue-related impairment more effectively. If additional factors were added to the methodology for deeming impairment, it may be necessary to make simple calculator tools widely available (eg, smartphone applications). Prior sleep-wake behaviour over several days could be entered, with an algorithm indicating whether it is safe to drive. Fatigue calculator tools are currently used within some organisational fatigue management systems and can be an effective strategy for determining whether a task can or cannot be performed.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The findings of the current meta-analysis must also be interpreted in light of the limitations of available data. A limited number of studies could be included in each meta-analysis due to heterogeneity of reference and outcome categories. It was necessary to ensure that outcome (ie, less than five hours sleep) and reference (ie, more than five hours sleep) groups were consistent amongst all studies to ensure interpretability of findings. However, consequently, many studies did not meet the criteria for meta-analysis, and thus were excluded. Furthermore, there were not sufficient studies available to conduct meta-analyses separately based on driving incident type (eg, falling asleep while driving, crash, etc.) which limits the ability to quantitatively determine differences in specific driving risk in relation to time spent asleep. However, when considering the available studies, subgroup analysis showed no significant differences by driving error outcome.</citation_analysis></p>
      <sec id="s0006-s2001">
        <title>Implementation of “Deemed Impairment”</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The concept of fatigue-related deemed impairment must be considered in the context of community and regulatory appetites. When introducing a new regulatory framework, there is the potential to be too stringent with limitations – with potentially negative unintended consequences. For example, if impairment was strictly deemed at the point at which any degree of impairment is seen (ie, typically under 8h of prior sleep), it is likely that many drivers would be “over the limit” during the vast majority of drives.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> While this may have net positive safety outcomes, this level of stringency would likely be accompanied by low levels of both acceptability and practicality (both for drivers and enforcement). Strict limitations in the first instance would also likely be ethically problematic – given that failure to obtain sufficient sleep may be out of the driver’s control, as compared to the consumption of alcohol or other intoxicants (typically a conscious decision).</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">There may be negative implications of overly permissive regulations which must also be considered. If initial fatigue-related “deemed impairment” regulations are too permissive, a number of situations where a driver is clearly impaired will not be considered illegal. In this case, drivers may also believe that they are “safe” to drive simply because they have had 5 h prior sleep – despite experiencing a high level of impairment. Overly permissive regulations may therefore not have the desired road safety impact – though there may be legal consequences for certain (likely few) individuals. For example, in New Jersey, the “Maggie’s Law” legislation considers drivers to be deemed impaired due to fatigue if they have been awake for longer than 24 h.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> While this law may be applied if an individual is involved in a crash after having had no sleep the previous night, it is unlikely to a) act as a deterrent for other drivers or b) be applied consistently in any meaningful way (ie, via roadside assessment).</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">As a result of the potential consequences of either too permissive or too stringent points at which an individual may be “deemed impaired”, it may not be unreasonable to follow the strategy used by some jurisdictions when initially implementing BAC as a method of alcohol-related impairment detection. That is, there may be the opportunity to begin with more permissive limitations, while both community members and enforcement agencies adapt to these requirements. After community and regulatory acceptability are established at a more permissive level, the amount of prior sleep legally required prior to driving could be increased as/when appropriate – likely based on changing community standards.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This systematic review presents an overview of the current literature examining prior sleep duration and driving outcomes in an attempt to identify at what point individuals may be deemed to be impaired (ie, generally unable to safely operate a vehicle). The concept of deemed impairment is not new – and in fact has been used successfully in the context of alcohol-related impairment. It appears that there may be the potential for fatigue-related impairment to be deemed at between 4 and 5 h of prior sleep, where the likelihood of being in a fatigue-related vehicle crash is at least double that of a well-rested individual. However, it must be acknowledged that there is no right answer. In making this decision, it is not only the scientific evidence that must be considered but also community expectations and acceptability, practicality of enforcement, and regulatory appetites. Future investigation of these community attitudes, in addition to practical and enforcement matters, is required to understand the potential impact of fatigue-related deemed impairment on road users and road safety, and how regulation or legislation may be implemented effectively.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0008">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Professor Gregory Roach reports grants from Department of Infrastructure, Transport, Regional Development Communications and the Arts, during the conduct of the study. The authors declare no other conflicts of interest in this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="newspaper"><collab>International Transport Forum</collab>. <article-title>Road safety report: Australia 2020</article-title>; <year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Global Road Safety Partnership</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Speed Management: A Road Safety Manual for Decision-Makers and Practitioners</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Global Road Safety Partnership</publisher-name>; <year>2008</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Davey</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Freeman</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Improving road safety through deterrence-based initiatives: a review of research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sultan Qaboos Univ Med J</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21509205</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="newspaper"><string-name><surname>Agent</surname>
<given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Green</surname>
<given-names>ER</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Langely</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Evaluation of kentucky’s” you drink and drive. You lose” Campaign</article-title>; <year>2002</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dawson</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sprajcer</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thomas</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>How much sleep do you need? A comprehensive review of fatigue related impairment and the capacity to work or drive safely</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Accid Anal Prev</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>151</volume>:<fpage>105955</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aap.2020.105955</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33383522</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Levine</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A road to injustice paved with good intentions: maggie’s misguided crackdown on drowsy driving</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hastings Law J</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>1297</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Creaser</surname>
<given-names>JI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ward</surname>
<given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rakauskas</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shankwitz</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boer</surname>
<given-names>ER</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of alcohol impairment on motorcycle riding skills</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Accid Anal Prev</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>906</fpage>–<lpage>913</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aap.2009.04.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19664426</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="newspaper"><string-name><surname>Moskowitz</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burns</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fiorentino</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smiley</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zador</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Driver characteristics and impairment at various BACs</article-title>; <year>2000</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>J-L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gadegbeku</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Viallon</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laumon</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cannabis, alcohol and fatal road accidents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e0187320</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0187320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29117206</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Matthews</surname>
<given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferguson</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kosmadopoulos</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kennaway</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roach</surname>
<given-names>GD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Simulated driving under the influence of extended wake, time of day and sleep restriction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Accid Anal Prev</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>Supplement</issue>):<fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aap.2011.09.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22239933</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Matthews</surname>
<given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferguson</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Time-of-day mediates the influences of extended wake and sleep restriction on simulated driving</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chronobiol Int</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>572</fpage>–<lpage>579</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/07420528.2012.675845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22621353</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Page</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McKenzie</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bossuyt</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Syst Rev</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>89</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13643-021-01626-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33781348</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Peimani</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nasli-Esfahani</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sadeghi</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Patients’ perceptions of patient–provider communication and diabetes care: a systematic review of quantitative and qualitative studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chronic Illn</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1742395318782378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29895167</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Akerstedt</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ingre</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kecklund</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Reaction of sleepiness indicators to partial sleep deprivation, time of day and time on task in a driving simulator – the DROWSI project</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>298</fpage>–<lpage>309</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.2009.00796.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20050992</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Anderson</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Horne</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Driving drowsy also worsens driver distraction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>466</fpage>–<lpage>468</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2012.11.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23523431</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Barrett</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Horne</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reyner</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleepiness combined with low alcohol intake in women drivers: greater impairment but better perception than men?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1057</fpage>–<lpage>1062</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/27.6.1057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15532198</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bartrim</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCarthy</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCartney</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grant</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Desbrow</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Irwin</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Three consecutive nights of sleep loss: effects of morning caffeine consumption on subjective sleepiness/alertness, reaction time and simulated driving performance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Transp Res Part F Traffic Psychol Behav</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>124</fpage>–<lpage>134</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.trf.2020.02.017</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cai</surname>
<given-names>AWT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Manousakis</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Singh</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>On-road driving impairment following sleep deprivation differs according to age</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>21561</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-99133-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34732793</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Caponecchia</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williamson</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Drowsiness and driving performance on commuter trips</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Safety Res</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>186</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsr.2018.07.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30121104</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>De Valck</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cluydts</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Slow-release caffeine as a countermeasure to driver sleepiness induced by partial sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>209</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2869.2001.00260.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11696073</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Filtness</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reyner</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Horne</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Driver sleepiness-comparisons between young and older men during a monotonous afternoon simulated drive</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biol Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>89</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>580</fpage>–<lpage>583</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsycho.2012.01.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22266164</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Horne</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reyner</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barrett</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Driving impairment due to sleepiness is exacerbated by low alcohol intake</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Occup Environ Med</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>689</fpage>–<lpage>692</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/oem.60.9.689</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12937193</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jongen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perrier</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vuurman</surname>
<given-names>EF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramaekers</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vermeeren</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sensitivity and validity of psychometric tests for assessing driving impairment: effects of sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e0117045</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0117045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25668292</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Miyata</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Noda</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ozaki</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insufficient sleep impairs driving performance and cognitive function</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurosci Lett</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>469</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>233</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neulet.2009.12.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19969042</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Otmani</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pebayle</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roge</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Muzet</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effect of driving duration and partial sleep deprivation on subsequent alertness and performance of car drivers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiol Behav</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>84</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>715</fpage>–<lpage>724</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.physbeh.2005.02.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15885247</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Perrier</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jongen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vuurman</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bocca</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramaekers</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vermeeren</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Driving performance and EEG fluctuations during on-the-road driving following sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biol Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>121</volume>(<issue>PartA</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsycho.2016.09.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27697552</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Philip</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sagaspe</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moore</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Fatigue, sleep restriction and driving performance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Accid Anal Prev</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>473</fpage>–<lpage>478</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aap.2004.07.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15784201</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Philip</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sagaspe</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taillard</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Fatigue, sleepiness, and performance in simulated versus real driving conditions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1511</fpage>–<lpage>1516</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/28.12.1511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16408409</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pizza</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Contardi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mostacci</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mondini</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cirignotta</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A driving simulation task: correlations with multiple sleep latency test</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Res Bull</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>423</fpage>–<lpage>426</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainresbull.2003.12.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15245770</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shekari Soleimanloo</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilkinson</surname>
<given-names>VE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cori</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Eye-blink parameters detect on-road track-driving impairment following severe sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1271</fpage>–<lpage>1284</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.7918</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31538598</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shiferaw</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Downey</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Westlake</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Stationary gaze entropy predicts lane departure events in sleep-deprived drivers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>2220</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-20588-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29311619</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vakulin</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baulk</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Catcheside</surname>
<given-names>PG</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of moderate sleep deprivation and low-dose alcohol on driving simulator performance and perception in young men</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1327</fpage>–<lpage>1333</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/30.10.1327</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17969466</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wijayanto</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marcillia</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lufityanto</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wisnugraha</surname>
<given-names>BB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alma</surname>
<given-names>TG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abdianto</surname>
<given-names>RU</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effect of situation awareness on driving performance in young sleep-deprived drivers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">IATSS Res</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>218</fpage>–<lpage>225</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.iatssr.2020.10.002</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zeller</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williamson</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Friswell</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effect of sleep-need and time-on-task on driver fatigue</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Transp Res Part F Traffic Psychol Behav</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.trf.2020.08.001</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hanowski</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hickman</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fumero</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olson</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dingus</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The sleep of commercial vehicle drivers under the 2003 hours-of-service regulations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Accid Anal Prev</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1140</fpage>–<lpage>1145</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aap.2007.02.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17920836</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hanowski</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Assessing the impact of sleep time on truck driver performance using a recurrent event model</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Stat Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):<fpage>4096</fpage>–<lpage>4111</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/sim.8287</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31256434</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McDonald</surname>
<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sasangohar</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The impact of commutes, work schedules, and sleep on near-crashes during nurses’ post shift-work commutes: a naturalistic driving study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">IISE Trans Occup Ergon Hum Factors</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/24725838.2021.1945708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34157964</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Martiniuk</surname>
<given-names>ALC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Senserrick</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lo</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep-deprived young drivers and the risk for crash: the DRIVE prospective cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Pediatr</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>167</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>647</fpage>–<lpage>655</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapediatrics.2013.1429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23689363</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bakiri</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Galera</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lagarde</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Distraction and driving: results from a case-control responsibility study of traffic crash injured drivers interviewed at the emergency room</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Accid Anal Prev</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>588</fpage>–<lpage>592</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aap.2013.06.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23969270</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Galéra</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Orriols</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>M’Bailara</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Mind wandering and driving: responsibility case-control study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Br Med J</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>345</volume>(<issue>dec13 8</issue>):<fpage>e8105</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.e8105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23241270</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Connor</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Norton</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ameratunga</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Driver sleepiness and risk of serious injury to car occupants: population based case control study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Br Med J</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>324</volume>(<issue>7346</issue>):<fpage>1125</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.324.7346.1125</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12003884</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cummings</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koepsell</surname>
<given-names>TD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moffat</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rivara</surname>
<given-names>FP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Drowsiness, counter-measures to drowsiness, and the risk of a motor vehicle crash</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Inj Prev</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>194</fpage>–<lpage>199</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/ip.7.3.194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11565983</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dorrian</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sweeney</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dawson</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Modeling fatigue-related truck accidents: prior sleep duration, recency and continuity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Biol Rhythms</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1479-8425.2010.00477.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Herman</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kafoa</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wainiqolo</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Driver sleepiness and risk of motor vehicle crash injuries: a population-based case control study in Fiji (TRIP 12)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Injury</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>586</fpage>–<lpage>591</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.injury.2013.06.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23830198</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kalsi</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tervo</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bachour</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Partinen</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep versus non-sleep-related fatal road accidents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>148</fpage>–<lpage>152</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2018.04.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30179735</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Philip</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chaufton</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Orriols</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Complaints of poor sleep and risk of traffic accidents: a population-based case-control study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e114102</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25494198</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stevenson</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elkington</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sharwood</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The role of sleepiness, sleep disorders, and the work environment on heavy-vehicle crashes in 2 Australian states</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>179</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>594</fpage>–<lpage>601</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwt305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24352592</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stutts</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilkins</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Osberg</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vaughn</surname>
<given-names>BV</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Driver risk factors for sleep-related crashes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Accid Anal Prev</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>321</fpage>–<lpage>331</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0001-4575(02)00007-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12643949</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tefft</surname>
<given-names>BC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Acute sleep deprivation and culpable motor vehicle crash involvement</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsy144</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Abe</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Komada</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nishida</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hayashida</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Inoue</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Short sleep duration and long spells of driving are associated with the occurrence of Japanese drivers’ rear-end collisions and single-car accidents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>310</fpage>–<lpage>316</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.2009.00806.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20337905</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Abe</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Komada</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Asaoka</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ozaki</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Inoue</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Questionnaire-based evidence of association between sleepiness while driving and motor vehicle crashes that are subjectively not caused by falling asleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Biol Rhythms</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>134</fpage>–<lpage>143</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1479-8425.2011.00498.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Abe</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Komada</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Inoue</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Short sleep duration, snoring and subjective sleep insufficiency are independent factors associated with both falling asleep and feeling sleepiness while driving</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):<fpage>3253</fpage>–<lpage>3260</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2169/internalmedicine.51.7518</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23207120</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>AlShareef</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Excessive daytime sleepiness and associations with sleep-related motor vehicle accidents: results from a nationwide survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1671</fpage>–<lpage>1676</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-020-02260-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33242183</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Andreassen</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pallesen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moen</surname>
<given-names>BE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bjorvatn</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Waage</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schaufeli</surname>
<given-names>WB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Workaholism and negative work-related incidents among nurses</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ind Health</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>373</fpage>–<lpage>381</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2486/indhealth.2017-0223</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29760300</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0055">
        <label>55.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Center for Disease Control and Prevention</collab>. <article-title>Unhealthy sleep-related behaviors—12 States, 2009</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>238</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0056">
        <label>56.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Center for Disease Control and Prevention</collab>. <article-title>Drowsy driving—19 states and the District of Columbia, 2009–2010</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>61</volume>(<issue>51–52</issue>):<fpage>1033</fpage>–<lpage>1037</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2013.105</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0057">
        <label>57.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>YY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep habits and excessive daytime sleepiness correlate with injury risks in the general population in Taiwan</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Inj Prev</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>172</fpage>–<lpage>177</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/ip.2009.021840</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20570985</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0058">
        <label>58.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Di Milia</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rogers</surname>
<given-names>NL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Akerstedt</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gamble</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleepiness, long distance commuting and night work as predictors of driving performance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e45856</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0045856</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23029278</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0059">
        <label>59.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Elliman</surname>
<given-names>TD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schwalb</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adler</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep deprivation and hazardous unintended sleep in US army drill sergeants</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>350</fpage>–<lpage>357</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleh.2020.04.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32461157</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0060">
        <label>60.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hutchens</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Senserrick</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jamieson</surname>
<given-names>PE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Romer</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Winston</surname>
<given-names>FK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Teen driver crash risk and associations with smoking and drowsy driving</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Accid Anal Prev</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>869</fpage>–<lpage>876</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aap.2007.10.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18460353</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0061">
        <label>61.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ikeda</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matsumoto</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kubo</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Izawa</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Takahashi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Relationship between sleep problems and dangerous driving behaviors in Japanese short-haul commercial truck drivers: a cross-sectional survey using digital tachograph data</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Biol Rhythms</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>303</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s41105-021-00318-9</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0062">
        <label>62.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simon</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wicks</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barr</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Connor</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schaad</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Amount of sleep, daytime sleepiness, hazardous driving, and quality of life of second year medical students</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acad Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>669</fpage>–<lpage>673</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40596-017-0668-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28421480</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0063">
        <label>63.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shin</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep status and the risk factor of drowsy-related accidents in commercial motor vehicle drivers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Res</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17241/smr.2018.00283</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0064">
        <label>64.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lemke</surname>
<given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Apostolopoulos</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hege</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sonmez</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wideman</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Understanding the role of sleep quality and sleep duration in commercial driving safety</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Accid Anal Prev</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>97</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aap.2016.08.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27591416</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0065">
        <label>65.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mahajan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Velaga</surname>
<given-names>NR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Choudhary</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of driver sleepiness and fatigue on violations among truck drivers in India</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Inj Control Saf Promot</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>412</fpage>–<lpage>422</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17457300.2019.1660375</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0066">
        <label>66.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mahajan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Velaga</surname>
<given-names>NR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Choudhary</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Choudhary</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of driver work-rest patterns, lifestyle and payment incentives on long-haul truck driver sleepiness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Transp Res Part F Traffic Psychol Behav</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>366</fpage>–<lpage>382</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.trf.2018.10.028</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0067">
        <label>67.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Maia</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grandner</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Findley</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gurubhagavatula</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Short and long sleep duration and risk of drowsy driving and the role of subjective sleep insufficiency</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Accid Anal Prev</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>618</fpage>–<lpage>622</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aap.2013.07.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23973762</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0068">
        <label>68.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Morrow</surname>
<given-names>PC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crum</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Antecedents of fatigue, close calls, and crashes among commercial motor-vehicle drivers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Safety Res</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsr.2003.07.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14992847</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0069">
        <label>69.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ohayon</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smolensky</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roth</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Consequences of shiftworking on sleep duration, sleepiness, and sleep attacks</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chronobiol Int</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>575</fpage>–<lpage>589</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/07420521003749956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20524802</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0070">
        <label>70.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Perttula</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ojala</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuosma</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Factors in the fatigue of heavy vehicle drivers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Rep</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>108</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>507</fpage>–<lpage>514</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2466/06.13.22.Pr0.108.2.507-514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21675565</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0071">
        <label>71.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Quera Salva</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barbot</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hartley</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep disorders, sleepiness, and near-miss accidents among long-distance highway drivers in the summertime</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2013.06.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24286897</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0072">
        <label>72.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Radun</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Summala</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep-related fatal vehicle accidents: characteristics of decisions made by multidisciplinary investigation teams</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>224</fpage>–<lpage>227</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/27.2.224</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15124714</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0073">
        <label>73.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Watling</surname>
<given-names>CN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Young drivers who continue to drive while sleepy: what are the associated sleep- and driving-related factors?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e12900</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31347230</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0074">
        <label>74.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>TZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>XY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoe</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>LW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Behavioral and psychosocial correlates of road traffic injuries: evidence from a nationwide study on Chinese undergraduates</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Traffic Inj Prev</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>375</fpage>–<lpage>381</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15389588.2020.1770236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32496809</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0075">
        <label>75.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Belenky</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wesensten</surname>
<given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thorne</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Patterns of performance degradation and restoration during sleep restriction and subsequent recovery: a sleep dose-response study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2869.2003.00337.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12603781</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0076">
        <label>76.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Van Dongen</surname>
<given-names>HP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maislin</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mullington</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dinges</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The cumulative cost of additional wakefulness: dose-response effects on neurobehavioral functions and sleep physiology from chronic sleep restriction and total sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>129</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/26.2.117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12683469</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0077">
        <label>77.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name><surname>Adams</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Appleton</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McEvoy</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Antic</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Report to the sleep health foundation 2016 sleep health survey of Australian adults</article-title>. <source>Sleep Health Foundation</source>; <year>2016</year>. <comment>Available from:</comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://wwwsleephealthfoundationorgau/pdfs/surveys/SleepHealthFoundation-Surveypdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://wwwsleephealthfoundationorgau/pdfs/surveys/SleepHealthFoundation-Surveypdf</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>March</month>
<day>17</day>, 2023</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0078">
        <label>78.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Compton</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blomberg</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moscowitz</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burns</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peck</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fiorentino</surname>
<given-names>DD</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Crash Risk of Alcohol Impaired Driving</italic></source>. <publisher-name>International Council on Alcohol, Drugs and Traffic Safety</publisher-name>; <year>2002</year>:<fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0079">
        <label>79.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Czeisler</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wickwire</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barger</surname>
<given-names>LK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep-deprived motor vehicle operators are unfit to drive: a multidisciplinary expert consensus statement on drowsy driving</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Health</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>94</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleh.2016.04.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28923267</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0080">
        <label>80.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Homel</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Drink-driving law enforcement and the legal blood alcohol limit in New South Wales</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Accid Anal Prev</italic></source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>147</fpage>–<lpage>155</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0001-4575(94)90084-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8198683</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0081">
        <label>81.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lyon</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mayhew</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Granié</surname>
<given-names>M-A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Age and road safety performance: focusing on elderly and young drivers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">IATSS Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>212</fpage>–<lpage>219</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.iatssr.2020.08.005</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0082">
        <label>82.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferguson</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matthews</surname>
<given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep, wake and phase dependent changes in neurobehavioral function under forced desynchrony</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>931</fpage>–<lpage>941</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.1130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21731143</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0083">
        <label>83.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kosmadopoulos</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sargent</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The efficacy of objective and subjective predictors of driving performance during sleep restriction and circadian misalignment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Accid Anal Prev</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>99</volume>:<fpage>445</fpage>–<lpage>451</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aap.2015.10.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26534845</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0084">
        <label>84.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dawson</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reid</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Fatigue, alcohol and performance impairment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nature</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>388</volume>(<issue>6639</issue>):<fpage>235</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/40775</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9230429</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0085">
        <label>85.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lamond</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dawson</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Quantifying the performance impairment associated with fatigue. Article</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2869.1999.00167.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10646165</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0086">
        <label>86.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lamond</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dorrian</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roach</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The impact of a week of simulated night work on sleep, circadian phase, and performance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Occup Environ Med</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e13</fpage>–<lpage>e13</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/oem.60.11.e13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14573724</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0087">
        <label>87.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Riethmeister</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matthews</surname>
<given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dawson</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Boer</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brouwer</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bültmann</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Time-of-day and days-on-shift predict increased fatigue over two-week offshore day-shifts. Article</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Appl Ergon</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>163</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apergo.2019.02.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31046947</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0088">
        <label>88.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Van Dongen</surname>
<given-names>HP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caldwell</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names> Jr</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caldwell</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Individual differences in cognitive vulnerability to fatigue in the laboratory and in the workplace</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Prog Brain Res</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>190</volume>:<fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>153</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21531250</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0089">
        <label>89.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>de Mello</surname>
<given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Narciso</surname>
<given-names>FV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tufik</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep disorders as a cause of motor vehicle collisions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Prev Med</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>246</fpage>–<lpage>257</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23626880</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0090">
        <label>90.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wolkow</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rajaratnam</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Anderson</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Howard</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mansfield</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Recommendations for current and future countermeasures against sleep disorders and sleep loss to improve road safety in Australia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Intern Med J</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1181</fpage>–<lpage>1184</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/imj.14423</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31507045</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
