<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38235481</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">10793117</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">434148</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S434148</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Depression, Sleep Health &amp; Sociodemographic Correlates in a Nationwide Survey: Implications for Depression Treatment During the COVID-19</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Chery et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Chery et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9380-6649</contrib-id><name><surname>Chery</surname><given-names>Maurice Junior</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0002" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0961-9665</contrib-id><name><surname>Baral</surname><given-names>Amrit</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rolle</surname><given-names>LaShae D</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abdshah</surname><given-names>Alireza</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>Maritza J</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Poudel</surname><given-names>Laxmi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Francois</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>Deborah L</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6777-2724</contrib-id><name><surname>Jean-Louis</surname><given-names>Girardin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4489-8604</contrib-id><name><surname>Blanc</surname><given-names>Judite</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Public Health Sciences, the University of Miami Miller School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Miami</addr-line>, <addr-line>Florida</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Anne Bates Leach Eye Hospital at Bascom Palmer Eye Institute, the University of Miami Miller School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Miami</addr-line>, <addr-line>FL</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>South Florida Integrative Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Miami</addr-line>, <addr-line>FL</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, University of Miami Miller School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Miami</addr-line>, <addr-line>FL</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Judite Blanc, <institution>Department of Public Health Sciences, the University of Miami Miller School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>1120 NW 14th St, Room 1448</addr-line>, <addr-line>Miami</addr-line>, <addr-line>FL</addr-line>, <addr-line>33136</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>, <phone content-type="general">Tel +1 954 471 0739</phone>, Email juditeblanc@miami.edu</corresp><corresp id="an0002">Maurice Junior Chery, <institution>Department of Public Health Sciences, the University of Miami Miller School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>1120 NW 14th St, Room 1448</addr-line>, <addr-line>Miami</addr-line>, <addr-line>FL</addr-line>, <addr-line>33136</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>, <phone content-type="general">Tel +1 343 204 7128</phone>, Email mxc2759@miami.edu</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>06</day><month>9</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>04</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Chery et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Chery et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Purpose</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">The COVID-19 pandemic has had a profound impact on mental health worldwide, with depression and sleep problems among the most common issues experienced by many individuals. Depression can lead to sleep problems, which can increase the risk of developing depressive symptoms. However, it is unclear which United States (US) sub-population was most affected by depression and sleep problems during the pandemic.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We conducted a secondary analysis using self-reported data from the 2021 National Health Interview Survey (NHIS), focusing on adults aged 18 years and above (n=29,763). We utilized self-reported responses to questions about prescription medication and frequency of depressive feelings to determine participants’ depression status. Appropriate weights were applied to account for the sampling design of the surveys. Our analysis involved descriptive statistics and chi-squared tests to compare sociodemographic, clinical, behavioral, and sleep-related characteristics between US adults with and without depression. Additionally, logistic regression was used to examine the associations between sleep duration, sleep quality and depression.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The overall prevalence of depression in our sample was 44.4%. It were higher in certain demographic groups, including younger adults (18–39 years, 47.7%), non-Hispanic whites (47.9%), females (50.1%), those at the lower income bracket (52.2%), those with no college or degree (48.7%) uninsured individuals (45.2%), and those reporting poor general health (71.9%). Individuals with depression had a 12% increased odds of experiencing short sleep (aOR: 1.12, 95% CI:1.04–1.20, p&lt;0.001), 34% increased odds of experiencing long sleep (aOR: 1.34, 95% CI: 1.20–1.50, p &lt; 0.001) and more than 2.5 fold increased odds of reporting poor sleep quality (aOR:2.57, 95% CI: 2.40–2.78; p&lt;0.0001). In the multivariate analysis, all variables (sex, race/ethnicity, education, health insurance coverage, marital status, general health status and use of sleep medications, smoking and alcohol use status) were significantly predictors of poor sleep quality, with the exceptions of age and family income.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The findings emphasize the need to address sleep health in treating depression, especially during times of public health crises.</citation_analysis></p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>depression</kwd><kwd>sleep health</kwd><kwd>sleep hygiene</kwd><kwd>sleep disparities</kwd><kwd>sleep quality</kwd><kwd>COVID-19</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>The National Institutes of Health (NIH) National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI) Determinants of Insufficient Sleep among Blacks and Effects on Disparities in Health Outcomes (ESSENTIALS; R01HL142066-06) and Mechanisms of sleep deficiency and effects on brain injury and neurocognitive functions among older blacks (MOSAIC; R01AG067523-05)</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>The National Institutes of Health (NIH) National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI) Determinants of Insufficient Sleep among Blacks and Effects on Disparities in Health Outcomes (ESSENTIALS; R01HL142066-06) and Mechanisms of sleep deficiency and effects on brain injury and neurocognitive functions among older blacks (MOSAIC; R01AG067523-05).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="3"/><ref-count count="64"/><page-count count="15"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The COVID-19 pandemic, declared by the World Health Organization in March 2020, has profoundly impacted global health, extending beyond the direct effects of the SARS-CoV-2 virus.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In the US, the scenario during the NHIS 2020 was marked by escalating case numbers, stretching healthcare systems and leading to implementation of varying degrees of restrictions and lockdowns across different states to curb the virus spread.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> According to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), by the end of 2020, the US had reported over 20 million cases and more than 350,000 deaths attributed to COVID-19.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> To adapt to the evolving conditions and ensure the safety of both respondents and interviewers, the NHIS adjusted its data collection strategy, transitioning from in-person interviews to an online format, an adaptation that was pivotal in the continuity of the survey amidst the pandemic conditions.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> While the immediate physical health impacts have been widely studied, the pandemic’s mental health consequences, specifically depression and sleep outcomes, are becoming increasingly apparent.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Depression is a pervasive global health issue, affecting over 5% of adults and experiencing a marked increase in incidence over the past decade.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> According to the National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH), an estimated 19.4 million adults in the United States had at least one major depressive episode in 2019, and the prevalence continue to rise to nearly one in ten Americans by the end of the year.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> These trends were exacerbated by the COVID-19 pandemic, culminating to a more than three-fold increase in the prevalence of depression among adults, as compared to pre-pandemic levels.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Within the US, various studies have specifically focused on distinct demographics such as adolescents and university students. Collectively, these investigations have found depression prevalence rates averaging 36%, with specific studies reporting figures ranging from 10% to 48%.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11–15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Studies conducted in China during the lockdown reflect a surge in mental health issues among university students, with the prevalence of anxiety and depression rising sharply.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The lockdown, social isolation, and abrupt shift to online learning have heightened interpersonal sensitivity, exacerbating anxiety and depression levels.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In addition, another research underlines the grave mental health implications of the pandemic and lockdown measures.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> These findings echoed in other international contexts, emphasizing the universal nature of these mental health challenges. Along with depression, sleep, which is also essential for overall well-being and physical and mental health, has been notably disrupted during the pandemic.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> A trend of decreasing sleep duration has been reported, with almost 70% of adults in the US reporting insufficient sleep for at least one night per month and more than a third experiencing sleep disturbances, which disproportionately affect non-Hispanic Blacks.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Moreover, specific to the interaction between depression and sleep quality, another study among postgraduate students in China during the COVID-19 campus lockdown reveals a significant correlation between interpersonal sensitivity and depression, mediated and moderated by sleep quality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> This highlights the intricate interplay between these factors, accentuating the need for a comprehensive examination of these dynamics in varied geographical and cultural contexts.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">There is also a consequential association between depression and sleep health, where approximately 75% of individuals diagnosed with depression report sleep difficulties.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> This is a noteworthy association with significant consequences. However, the extent of this association during the unique circumstances of the COVID-19 pandemic has not been thoroughly examined on a large scale. Therefore, we used a population-based, nationally representative dataset, the National Health Interview Survey (NHIS), to examine the relationship between depression and sleep health during the COVID-19 outbreak.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Our study seeks to extend these insights, exploring the nuanced relationships between depression and sleep health in the context of the COVID-19 pandemic in the US, drawing parallels and distinctions with international findings. The outcomes of this study are aimed to contribute significantly to the global discourse on mental health, offering cross-cultural insights and evidence-based interventions to mitigate the ongoing and post-pandemic mental health crisis.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Data Source and Study Sample</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We utilized data from the 2021 National Health Interview Survey (NHIS) collected by the National Center for Health Statistics (NCHS) of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). The NHIS is a cross-sectional survey conducted annually to collect data through in-person interviews with non-institutionalized civilians in the US using validated instruments.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> We used a sample of adults aged 18 years and older with depression (N=29,763 unweighted). All data for this study were sourced from the National Health Interview Survey (NHIS), with strict adherence to the privacy and data protection protocols as mandated by the National Center for Health Statistics (NCHS), ensuring confidentiality and security of participant information through encryption and secure server storage, in compliance with relevant privacy legislation and NCHS guidelines.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In accordance with the definition of a “human subject” outlined in 45 CFR 46.102(e), our research was determined to not involve human subjects.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> As a result, the study was exempt from the need for IRB review, approval, or oversight.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Variables Definition</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In our study, the major dependent variables were nightly sleep duration and sleep quality. Sleep duration, measured through the National Health Interview Survey (NHIS) question “On average, how many hours of sleep do you get in 24 hours?”, was categorized into three levels: short sleep (less than 7 hours), normal sleep (7–8 hours), and long sleep (9 hours or more), based on existing literature.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">According to a recently published study</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> that utilized NHIS data, sleep quality was assessed using a binary variable based on responses to four NHIS questions: (a) Did you have trouble falling asleep in the past 30 days? (b) Did you have trouble staying asleep in the past 30 days? (c) Did you wake up feeling not well-rested in the past 30 days? And (d) Did you take any medication to help you fall asleep or stay asleep in the past 30 days? The responses were in the form of Yes/No. If any of the indicators were reported as “Yes”, the overall sleep quality was categorized as poor.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">The independent variable in our study is self-reported diagnosis of depression. To assess the current depression status, we constructed a depression status variable based on the responses to two self-questions. Participants were asked the following questions: 1. “Do you take prescription medication for depression?” with response options (yes/no). 2. “How often do you feel depressed?” with response choices including daily, weekly, monthly, a few times a year, or never. It’s important to note that if participants responded with daily, weekly, monthly, or a few times a year, it was interpreted as a “Yes” answer. Individuals who answered affirmatively to either of these two questions were classified as having depression. In the context of this paper, we will use the term “Depression” for brevity. However, it should be noted that when we refer to “Depression”, we are specifically referencing the “Self-reported diagnosis of depression”.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Other potential confounders and covariates, such as demographic characteristics (age group in years, sex, race/ethnicity, education, family income, health insurance, and marital status), clinical characteristics (general health status and use of sleep medications), and behavioral variables of interest (smoking and alcohol use status) were included in our analysis.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">First, we used descriptive statistics and chi-squared tests to examine the differences in the distribution of sociodemographic, clinical, behavioral, and sleep-associated characteristics among US adults by depression status (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Prevalence (Weighted Percentage) of Self-Reported Depression Among US Adults by Sociodemographic, Behavioral, Clinical, and Sleep Characteristics, 2021 NHIS</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Depression Status</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">*p-value</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Unweighted Sample (n, %)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(13,602, 44.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(16,161, 55.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Weighted Proportions</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Age Groups </italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18–39 </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40–64 </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Sex </italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Race/Ethnicity </italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Hispanic White</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Hispanic Black </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Education</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Less than high school</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High school degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some college, no degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Associate Degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bachelor’s degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Master’s degree and higher</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Family income ($ per year)</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0–34,999</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35,000–49,999</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50,000–74,999</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75,000–99,999</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥100,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Marital Status </italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Married </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living with a partner(unmarried) </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neither</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">General Health Status</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excellent</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very good</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fair</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Health Insurance Status</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5325</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Covered</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not covered</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Smoking Status </italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Former </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Alcohol Use Status </italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Former </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Duration</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short sleep (&lt;7 hours)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long sleep (≥9 hours)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal sleep (7–8 hours)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Poor Sleep Quality</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Take Sleep Medications</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Weighted proportions are row percentages and total proportions reflect column total </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>*</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">p-value are computed using Chi-squared test.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviation</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: NHIS, National Health Interview Survey.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Second, we used multivariable multinomial logistic regression to assess the odds of reporting short or long sleep compared to normal sleep among those with depression, as summarized in (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Weighted and Adjusted Odds Ratios for Nightly Sleep Duration Associated with Self-Reported Diagnosis of Depression Using Multivariate Multinomial Logistic Regression Analysis, 2021 NHIS</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Short Sleep VS Normal Sleep</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Long Sleep VS Normal Sleep</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">aOR (95% CI)*</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">aOR (95% CI)*</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Depression</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12 (1.04–1.20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34 (1.20–1.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No (Ref) </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Age Groups </italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18–39 </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 (1.10–1.32)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 (0.60–0.81)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40–64 </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45 (1.34–1.57)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 (0.50–0.63)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65+ (Ref) </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Sex </italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 (0.78–0.90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.92–1.20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4062</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male (Ref) </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Race/Ethnicity </italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Hispanic White (Ref) </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 (0.86–1.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7884</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.74–1.13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1014</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Hispanic Black </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40 (1.23–1.55)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (0.88–1.40)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5379</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19 (1.04–1.36)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 (0.66–1.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1872</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Education</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Less than high school (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High school degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 (0.93–1.21)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4390</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.75–1.40)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4407</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some college, no degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 (1.10–1.46)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 (0.67–1.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1408</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Associate Degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30 (1.10–1.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66 (0.52–0.84)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bachelor’s degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 (0.99–1.32)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0683</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62 (0.49–0.78)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Master’s degree and higher</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 (1.02–1.35)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0369</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68 (0.53–0.870)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Family income</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0–34,999</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.83–1.03)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2266</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 (0.83–1.30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6999</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35,000–49,999</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 (0.84–1.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3884</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 (0.80–1.22)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9361</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50,000–74,999</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 (0.86–1.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3965</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88 (0.71–1.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2765</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75,000–99,999</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (0.91–1.11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8315</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.73–1.12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3846</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥100,000 (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Marital Status </italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Married </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.96–1.12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3462</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88 (0.80–1.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0510</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living with a partner (Not married) </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (0.90–1.16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8534</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 (0.75–1.23)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7585</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neither (Ref) </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">General Health condition</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excellent</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 (0.55–0.90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28 (0.21–0.40)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very good</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 (0.68–1.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1806</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30 (0.21–0.40)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 (0.68–1.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1660</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32 (0.24–0.42)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fair</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 (0.68–1.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1990</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48 (0.40–0.63)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Health Insurance Status</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Covered</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 (0.95–1.24)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2263</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 (0.90–1.36)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3806</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not covered (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Smoking Status </italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16 (1.04–1.30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 (0.92–1.34)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2865</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Former </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.96–1.14)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2737</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 (0.93–1.21)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3923</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never (Ref) </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Alcohol Use Status </italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40 (1.24–1.58)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 (0.78–1.14)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5648</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Former </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42 (1.24–1.63)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 (0.90–1.28)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5877</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never (Ref) </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Poor Sleep Quality</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67 (1.55–1.80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (0.76–0.99)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0363</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Normal Sleep (7–8 hours), Short Sleep (&lt;7 hours), Long Sleep (≥ 9 hours). *Adjusting for age, sex, race/ethnicity, education, family income, marital status, health insurance status, general health condition, smoking status, alcohol use status, and poor sleep quality.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: NHIS, National Health Interview Survey; aOR, Adjusted Odds Ratio; CI, Confidence Interval.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Next, we used univariable binary logistic regression to examine the association between depression and three variables related to the quality of sleep (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Univariable and Multivariable Binary Logistic Regression Analysis Assessing the Predictors of Poor Sleep Quality, 2021 NHIS</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Univariable Analysis</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Multivariable Analysis<sup>a</sup></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">aOR</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Age Groups </italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18–39 </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82–0.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95–1.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2859</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40–64 </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93–1.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9081</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93–1.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7639</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65+ (Ref) </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Sex </italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41–1.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39–1.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male (Ref) </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Race/Ethnicity </italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Hispanic White (Ref) </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51–0.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62–0.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Hispanic Black </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57–0.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58–0.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59–0.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66–0.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Education</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Less than high school (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High school degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10–1.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05–1.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some college, no degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30–1.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14–1.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Associate Degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20–1.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10–1.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bachelor’s degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28–1.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24–1.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Master’s degree and higher</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24–1.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21–1.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Family income</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0–34,999</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98–1.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1035</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90–1.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8374</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35,000–49,999</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82–1.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1777</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21–1.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2744</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50,000–74,999</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82–1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0648</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79–0.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0262</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75,000–99,999</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76–0.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74–0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥100,000 (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Marital Status </italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Married </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84–0.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83–0.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0139</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living with a partner (Not married) </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99–1.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0607</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92–1.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3427</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neither (Ref) </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">General Health Status</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excellent</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20–0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23–0.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very good</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31–0.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34–0.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38–0.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44–0.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fair</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55–0.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63–1.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1016</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Health Insurance Status</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Covered</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30–1.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10–1.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not covered (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Smoking Status </italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38–1.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06–1.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Former </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22–1.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96–1.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2583</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never (Ref) </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Alcohol Use Status </italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.73–2.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38–1.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Former </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.64–2.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21–1.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never (Ref) </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Duration</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short sleep (&lt;7 hours)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66–1.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55–1.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long sleep (≥9 hours)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93–1.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3932</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78–1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0560</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal sleep (7–8 hours) (Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Depression</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00–3.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40–2.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No (Ref) </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes: <sup>a</sup></bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Adjusting for age, sex, race/ethnicity, education, family income, marital status, general health status, insurance status, smoking status, alcohol use status, and sleep duration.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0006"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: NHIS, National Health Interview Survey; OR, odds ratio; aOR, adjusted odds ratio; CI, confidence interval.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In our analytic approach, we incorporated variables that were identified as statistically significant predictors from the univariable analyses. Additionally, variables that were biologically and theoretically plausible were considered for inclusion in the multivariable regression models, ensuring a comprehensive and robust analysis.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Appropriate survey sampling weights provided by the NHIS were used as the basis for all analyses.  All statistical tests were two-tailed, with an alpha less than 0.05 considered statistically significant, and SAS version 9.4 (SAS Institute, Inc., Cary, NC, USA)</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> was used for statistical analysis. All participants provided informed consent at registration, and the available data were de-identified.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The analysis was based on a sample of 29,763 (unweighted) adults, with a mean age of 43 years (SD=10). The weighted total sample revealed that 44.4% of participants with depression (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Sociodemographic Characteristics</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The prevalence of depression decreases with age. Individuals aged 65 years and above had the lowest proportion (39.8%), whereas those aged 18–39 had the highest proportion (47.7%). Females (50.1%) reported a higher prevalence of depression than males (38.3%). Non-Hispanic Whites (47.9%) had a higher depression prevalence, followed by Blacks (38.0%), and Hispanics (37.5%). Individuals with high school degree reported the lowest proportion of depression (42.7%), while participants with some college, no degree reported having the highest proportion of depression (48.7%). When examining income, we observed a higher prevalence of depression (52.2%) among individuals in the lowest-income bracket ($0–34,999). In general, the reported depression proportion decreased as income increased. Those earning more than $100,000 reported the lowest prevalence of depression (39.4%). Furthermore, those without health insurance reported a higher depression proportion (45.2%) than those with health insurance coverage (44.3%). Participants living with a partner (49.7%) and single individuals (49.9%) reported higher depression than did married participants (39.4%). There was a dose-response relationship between general health status and the prevalence of depression, where those with poor general health status reported 71.9% prevalence of depression.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Behavioral and Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Current smokers (55.0%) reported a higher prevalence of depression than former smokers (47.4%) and nonsmokers (41.3%). Similarly, the prevalence of depression was highest among current alcohol users (46.1%), followed by former (45.2%) and non-drinkers (34.2%).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Sleep Characteristics</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The prevalence of depression was highest (49.2%) among those who were long sleepers (≥9 hours), followed by short sleepers (&lt;7 hours) (46.1%), compared to normal sleepers (7–9 hours) (39.8%). Individuals with poor sleep quality reported having higher prevalence of depression (52.0%) as compared to those without poor sleep quality (25.1%).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Regression Analyses: Association Between Depression and Sleep Health</title>
        <sec id="s0003-s2004-s3001">
          <title>Nightly Sleep Duration</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We conducted a multivariable multinomial logistic regression analysis to assess the relationship between night sleep duration and depression. The weighted and adjusted odds ratios (aORs) derived from this analysis are presented in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. Individuals with depression had higher odds of experiencing short sleep (aOR: 1.12, 95% CI:1.04–1.20, p &lt;0.01) and even greater odds of having long sleep (aOR: 1.34; 95% CI:1.20–1.50; p &lt; 0.001) in reference to normal sleep, than individuals without depression. Compared to people aged 65 years and older, those age range–18–39 and 40–64 were less likely to experience long sleep, with odds ratios (aOR:0.69, 95% CI:0.60–0.81, p &lt; 0.0001) and (aOR: 0.50, 95% CI:0.50–0.63, p &lt; 0.0001), respectively. Regarding gender differences, females had lower odds of being short sleepers (aOR: 0.84, 95% CI:0.78–0.90, p &lt; 0.0001) compared to males. Non-Hispanic Blacks had a markedly greater likelihood of experiencing short sleep (aOR:1.40, 95% CI: 1.23–1.55, p &lt; 0.0001) compared to their non-Hispanic White counterparts.</citation_analysis></p>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Current smokers had a higher likelihood of short sleep (aOR:1.16; 95% CI:1.04–1.30, p &lt; 0.01) than non-smokers. Alcohol users, both current (aOR: 1.40, 95% CI: 1.24–1.58, p&lt;0.0001) and former (aOR: 1.42, 95% CI: 1.24–1.63, p&lt;0.0001) had 40% and 42% greater odds of having short sleep as compared to non-drinkers respectively. Those with poor sleep quality had 67% greater odds of having short sleep (aOR: 1.67, 95% CI: 1.55–1.80, p&lt;0.0001) and 13% lower odds of experiencing long sleep (aOR: 0.87, 95% CI: 0.76–0.99, p=0.0363) as compared to those without poor sleep quality.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2004-s3002">
          <title>Sleep Quality Outcomes</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The results from both univariable and multivariable binary logistic regression models, which assess the association between depression and poor sleep quality as well as evaluate other predictors of poor sleep quality, are presented in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. In the univariable analysis, factors such as age, sex, race/ethnicity, education, family income, marital status, general health status, health insurance, smoking, alcohol use, and sleep duration all demonstrated a statistically significant association with poor sleep quality. Consequently, we incorporated these variables into the multivariable logistic regression analysis. In the multivariable model, individuals who reported depression were over twice as likely to experience poor sleep quality (aOR: 2.57, 95% CI: 2.40–2.78, p &lt; 0.0001). When comparing short sleep duration to normal sleep duration, there was a 67% increase in the odds of having poor sleep quality (aOR: 1.67, 95% CI: 1.55–1.81, p&lt;0.0001). In the univariable analysis, the 18–39 age group had slightly lower odds (OR: 0.89, 95% CI: 0.82–0.97, p&lt;0.01) of short sleep than those aged 65 and older. However, this association was not statistically significant in the adjusted analysis. Females had almost 50% greater odds (aOR: 1.49, 95% CI: 1.39–1.60, p&lt;0.0001) of experiencing poor sleep quality as compared to males The results also showed significant differences among ethnicities: Non-Hispanic Blacks had notably lower odds (aOR: 0.66, 95% CI: 0.58–0.74, P&lt;0.0001) of poor sleep quality, followed by Hispanics (aOR: 0.69, 95% CI: 0.62–0.77, p&lt;0.0001) when compared to non-Hispanic Whites.</citation_analysis></p>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Current smokers were 20% more likely (aOR: 1.20, 95% CI: 1.06–1.36, p&lt;0.01) to have poor sleep quality than non-smokers. Both current and former alcohol users reported greater odds of poor sleep quality. Specifically, current alcohol users had a 56% increased chance (aOR: 1.56, 95% CI: 1.38–1.75, p &lt; 0.0001), while former drinkers had 40% higher odds (aOR: 1.40, 95% CI: 1.21–1.60, p &lt; 0.0001) than non-drinkers. Lastly, those who were married had a slightly better sleep quality (aOR: 0.90, 95% CI: 0.83–0.98; p=0.0139) compared to those who were single or not living with a partner.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This study aimed to investigate the relationship between depression and sleep outcomes during the COVID-19 pandemic. We found a strong association between depression and sleep health in a nationally representative sample of adults during the COVID-19 pandemic period. The prevalence of depression in our sample was 44.4%, and was significantly affected by sleep duration and quality. In our sample, individuals with depression had a 12% higher likelihood of experiencing short sleep, 34% higher odds of experiencing long sleep durations and were more than 2.5 more likely to experience poor sleep quality. Our findings align with data from a nationally represented survey indicates that the prevalence of depression in the US surged to over three times its previous rate during the COVID-19 pandemic compared to the period before its onset.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Our results are also consistent with a nationwide study from Brazil, which reported a 28% rise in sleep duration issues and a significant 32% upswing in sleep quality problems during the COVID-19 pandemic.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> A 2020 study from a Kentucky University and data from Texas A&amp;M University both reported a depression prevalence rate of around 36%.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Similarly, during China’s lockdown, 46.8% noted depression symptoms, highlighting the significant increase in depression during such conditions.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In the context of broader research, our findings align seamlessly with prior studies that have underscored the disruption of sleep patterns in individuals with depression.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34–36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Such disturbances in sleep are characteristic features of depression and are often associated with diminished activity in the serotoninergic neurotransmission system.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34–36</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep influences an array of physiological functions, impacting everything from transient metabolic responses to sustained neurocognitive adaptations.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> One crucial aspect of sleep research is the delineation of normal sleep durations. Contemporary research posits that a sleep duration of 7–8 hours is generally conducive to positive health outcomes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Our study corroborates this finding, demonstrating that sleep durations at either extreme, too short, or excessively long, were associated with depression. Furthermore, it is critical to note that sleep quality is as important as sleep quantity, with evidence suggesting that interventions specifically targeting sleep quality might benefit patients more than those focusing solely on sleep duration.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Depression is a multifaceted condition that profoundly influences individuals’ overall health and functional capacity of individuals.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> It has a complex bidirectional relationship with numerous physical and psychological disorders, serving as both a contributor and consequence.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Depression and sleep disturbances share many pathophysiological mechanisms, and ameliorating depression often mitigates sleep disturbances, reinforcing this interconnectedness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Despite the historical view of sleep disturbances as merely symptomatic manifestations of depression, the current understanding identifies this relationship as bidirectional.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> While depression is a known risk factor for insomnia, recent research suggests that insomnia can also act as a precursor to the subsequent development of depression.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> This interplay presents a promising focal point for targeted intervention.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Older age is often linked to shorter sleep outcomes in the existing literature as it is associated with physiological changes, higher rates of chronic illnesses, and lifestyle factors leading to disrupted sleep patterns.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, our study found that younger individuals (18–39 years) accounted for a higher proportion of depression than their older counterparts did. Studies like that of Xu offer parallels, illuminating mental health struggles among younger Chinese college students during the COVID-19 lockdown.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> These findings diverge from conventional patterns in mental health research, implying that older adults may encounter more disruptions in their mental health.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The COVID-19 pandemic has brought about significant disruptions to daily life, and has profoundly affected mental health and, by extension, sleep health.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Younger individuals, particularly those between the ages of 18–39, have been confronted with many unique stressors.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Many have faced job insecurity owing to layoffs, furloughs, or the transition to remote work and education.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In addition, social isolation resulting from lockdowns and physical distancing measures could exacerbate feelings of loneliness and psychological distress, leading to increased rates of depression.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Furthermore, young adults are notably active on social media and other digital platforms that are rife with COVID-19-related content.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Overconsumption of pandemic-related news, often referred to as “doomscrolling”, could have led to increased stress, anxiety, and depressive symptoms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> These findings underscore the need for targeted mental health interventions for younger adults, especially in the context of a public health crisis such as the COVID-19 pandemic.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Our study is in line with the gender disparity in depression rates, with females reporting a higher prevalence of depression than males. This aligns with the existing literature, which has consistently indicated that females experience depression at a higher rate than males.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> An interesting difference was observed in the present study in terms of sleep health outcomes. Females had 16% lower odds of experiencing short sleep duration; they had a 49% higher likelihood of having poor sleep compared to their male counterparts. This distinction suggests that while females may achieve the recommended hours of sleep, the quality of sleep may be compromised, potentially due to difficulties in initiating and maintaining sleep. This is consistent with prior research that found that women report poorer sleep despite similar or longer sleep durations than men.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Biological factors, such as hormonal changes during the menstrual cycle, pregnancy, and menopause, can affect mood and sleep patterns in women.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Psychologically, women are more likely to ruminate during stressful events that can lead to depression and sleep disturbances.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Socially, the added stressors and demands that women face, such as caregiving and work-life balance issues, can also contribute to higher rates of depression and disrupted sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Nevertheless, it is crucial to emphasize the need for further studies to confirm these findings. A better understanding can inform the development of gender-tailored interventions to address depression and sleep health problems, particularly in stressful situations, such as the COVID-19 pandemic.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our results found that Non-Hispanic Whites, comprising approximately 2/3 of our sample size, had the highest prevalence of depression (47.9%) and reported 31% higher odds of poor sleep quality than Non-Hispanic Blacks and Hispanics. This deviates significantly from prior research that often emphasizes higher sleep disturbances among racial/ethnic minorities, particularly non-Hispanic Blacks.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> It’s essential to underscore that “taking medication for depression symptoms” was a key metric in our assessment of depression prevalence. This raises a pertinent point: the increased prevalence among Non-Hispanic Whites could be indicative of their comparatively greater access to healthcare systems and thus, to prescribed medications for depression.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> One of the pronounced elements was the intensified sense of social isolation that seemed to disproportionately affect Non-Hispanic Whites. Given the cultural and societal structures they predominantly inhabit, such as living alone or in smaller nuclear families, the brunt of social distancing and lockdown measures may have been felt more acutely by this group.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> On the other hand, racial and ethnic minorities often benefit from intrinsic cultural and community support systems.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> These networks, characterized by strong familial ties and close-knit communities, have historically played a role in resilience against external stressors. In the context of the pandemic, such protective communal bonds could have been instrumental in cushioning the adverse impacts of isolation and providing a supportive framework to navigate the challenges, thereby potentially offsetting the rates of depression and sleep disturbances seen in other groups.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We observed a higher prevalence of depression among individuals with some college level education (48.7%). These results mirror the existing literature that identifies lower educational attainment as a risk factor for poor mental health outcomes, likely exacerbated during the pandemic by factors such as job instability and exposure risk associated with lower-skilled jobs.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Participants with a (associate, bachelor, master or higher) degree reported the lower rate of depression, which might be attributed to a range of protective factors such as larger social networks, greater financial stability, and increased access to resources, including the ability to work remotely.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Remote work accessibility has been predominantly available to higher-educated individuals, potentially shielding them from the economic and psychological impacts of the pandemic.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Participants in the lowest-income bracket ($0–34,999 / year) exhibited a higher rate of depression (52.2%). The COVID-19 pandemic has been especially straining for low-income individuals, intensifying mental health problems.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Finally, those without health insurance coverage reported a slightly higher rate of depression (45.2%) than those who were insured (44.3%). This could be a result of underreporting because those without coverage might be less likely to seek help and be diagnosed.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref></citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Limitations and Strengths</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">We acknowledge several limitations in our study that are essential to consider when interpreting the results. Our study’s conclusions are primarily reliant on self-reported data from participants rather than direct medical evaluations, necessitating caution during their interpretation and application in a clinical context. In addition to the reliance on self-reported data, the cross-sectional design of our study is another limitation. This design inherently limits our ability to establish causal relationships between depression and sleep disturbances.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Despite these limitations, our study offers significant value using a nationally representative sample of the US population, which enables a thorough examination of self-reported depression status, sleep disturbances and sociodemographic factors. Robust and diverse sample sizes enhance the applicability and relevance of our findings.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This study emphasizes the well-documented association between depression and sleep health outcomes during the COVID-19 pandemic. Findings show that younger individuals, women, people of different racial and ethnic backgrounds, and socioeconomic statuses face unique challenges. Our results challenge various traditional views in mental and sleep health research, revealing a complex interplay between demographic and socioeconomic factors and mental health during the pandemic. Recognizing these patterns is crucial for clinicians and policymakers. It suggests a need for specialized interventions tailored to the needs of these specific populations. Furthermore, our results accentuate the importance of continuous research in this domain to ensure effective strategies are in place to support mental and sleep health, especially in times of crises.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0007">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cucinotta</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vanelli</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>WHO declares COVID-19 a pandemic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Bio Medica Atenei Parm</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>91</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>160</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.23750/abm.v91i1.9397</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gabriel</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>National Coronavirus lockdowns: the interplay of tightening and easing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">SSRN Electr J</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2139/ssrn.3732059</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><source>ptpmcrender.pdf</source>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xlink:href="https://europepmc.org/backend/ptpmcrender.fcgi?accid=PMC7286282%25252526blobtype=pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://europepmc.org/backend/ptpmcrender.fcgi?accid=PMC7286282&amp;blobtype=pdf</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>October</month>
<day>20</day>, 2023</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="newspaper"><string-name><surname>Shumskaya</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benjamin</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Niepielko</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lorusso</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Statistics with Epidemiology of COVID-19</article-title>; <year>2021</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.25334/H1HE-5Z05</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Blumberg</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parker</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moyer</surname>
<given-names>BC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>National Health Interview Survey, COVID-19, and online data collection platforms: adaptations, tradeoffs, and new directions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>111</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2167</fpage>–<lpage>2175</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2021.306516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34878857</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Xiong</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lipsitz</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nasri</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impact of COVID-19 pandemic on mental health in the general population: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Affect Disord</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>277</volume>:<fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2020.08.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32799105</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Santomauro</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mantilla Herrera</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shadid</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>COVID-19 Mental Disorders Collaborators. Global prevalence and burden of depressive and anxiety disorders in 204 countries and territories in 2020 due to the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Lond Engl</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>398</volume>(<issue>10312</issue>):<fpage>1700</fpage>–<lpage>1712</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(21)02143-7</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Santo</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peters</surname>
<given-names>ZJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>DeFrances</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Emergency department visits among adults with mental health disorders: United States, 2017–2019</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">NCHS Data Brief</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>426</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Goodwin</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dierker</surname>
<given-names>LC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Galea</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoven</surname>
<given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weinberger</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Trends in US depression prevalence from 2015 to 2020: the Widening Treatment Gap</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Prev Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>726</fpage>–<lpage>733</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2022.05.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36272761</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Scott</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Webb</surname>
<given-names>TL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martyn-St James</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rowse</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weich</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Improving sleep quality leads to better mental health: a meta-analysis of randomised controlled trials</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>101556</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2021.101556</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34607184</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hegde</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Son</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Keller</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sasangohar</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Investigating mental health of US college students during the COVID-19 pandemic: cross-sectional survey study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Med Internet Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e22817</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/22817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32897868</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jeong</surname>
<given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Stress, Anxiety, and Depression Among Undergraduate Students during the COVID-19 Pandemic and their Use of Mental Health Services</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Innov High Educ</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>519</fpage>–<lpage>538</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10755-021-09552-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33907351</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rudenstine</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McNeal</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schulder</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Depression and anxiety during the COVID‐19 pandemic in an urban, low‐income public university sample</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Trauma Stress</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>12</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jts.22600</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33045107</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>GTF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hyun</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hahm</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Factors associated with depression, anxiety, and PTSD symptomatology during the COVID-19 pandemic: clinical implications for US young adult mental health</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>290</volume>:<fpage>113172</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32512357</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hawes</surname>
<given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Szenczy</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Klein</surname>
<given-names>DN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hajcak</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nelson</surname>
<given-names>BD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Increases in depression and anxiety symptoms in adolescents and young adults during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>3222</fpage>–<lpage>3230</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0033291720005358</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33436120</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zeng</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The study of psychological traits among Chinese college students during the COVID-19 campus lockdown</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>13</volume>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2022.1051770</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pei</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yong</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pathway from interpersonal sensitivity to depression among Chinese college students during the COVID-19 campus lockdown</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Environ Health Prev Med</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>34</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1265/ehpm.22-00249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37286498</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Resilience and depressive symptoms mediated pathways from social support to suicidal ideation among undergraduates during the COVID-19 Campus Lockdown in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Res Behav Manag</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>2291</fpage>–<lpage>2301</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/PRBM.S377158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36039109</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lippman</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gardener</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rundek</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Short sleep is associated with more depressive symptoms in a multi-ethnic cohort of older adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>58</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2017.09.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29221780</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sheehan</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frochen</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Walsemann</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ailshire</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Are U.S. adults reporting less sleep?: findings from sleep duration trends in the National Health Interview Survey, 2004–2017</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>zsy221</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsy221</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jean-Louis</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Turner</surname>
<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seixas</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Epidemiologic methods to estimate insufficient sleep in the US population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>9337</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph17249337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33327388</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zeng</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of interpersonal sensitivity on depressive symptoms in postgraduate students during the COVID-19 pandemic: psychological capital and sleep quality as mediators</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>14</volume>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2023.1100355</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nutt</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilson</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paterson</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disorders as core symptoms of depression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Dialogues Clin Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>329</fpage>–<lpage>336</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.31887/DCNS.2008.10.3/dnutt</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18979946</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zablotsky</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lessem</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gindi</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maitland</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dahlhamer</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blumberg</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Overview of the 2019 national health interview survey questionnaire redesign</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>113</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>408</fpage>–<lpage>415</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2022.307197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36758202</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>NHIS</collab>. <article-title>2020 NHIS</article-title>; <year>2022</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhis/2020nhis.htm" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhis/2020nhis.htm</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>October</month>
<day>20</day>, 2023</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>NHIS</collab>. <article-title>About the National Health Interview Survey</article-title>; <year>2020</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhis/participants/yourprivacy.htm" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhis/participants/yourprivacy.htm</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>November</month>
<day>7</day>, 2023</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>45 CFR 46.102 -- Definitions for purposes of this policy</article-title>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ecfr.gov/current/title-45/part-46/section-46.102" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ecfr.gov/current/title-45/part-46/section-46.102</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>October</month>
<day>19</day>, 2023</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Heslop</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>GD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Metcalfe</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macleod</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hart</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep duration and mortality: the effect of short or long sleep duration on cardiovascular and all-cause mortality in working men and women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>305</fpage>–<lpage>314</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1389-9457(02)00016-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14592192</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Inam</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kianoush</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sheikh</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The association between race, ethnicity and sleep quality and duration: a National Health Interview Survey Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Probl Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>102004</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cpcardiol.2023.102004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37506957</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rodriguez</surname>
<given-names>RN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sas</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">WIREs Comput Stat</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wics.131</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ettman</surname>
<given-names>CK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abdalla</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>GH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sampson</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vivier</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Galea</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalence of depression symptoms in US adults before and during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e2019686</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.19686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32876685</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jahrami</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>BaHammam</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bragazzi</surname>
<given-names>NL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saif</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Faris</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vitiello</surname>
<given-names>MV</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep problems during the COVID-19 pandemic by population: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>299</fpage>–<lpage>313</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.8930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33108269</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Moreno</surname>
<given-names>CR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Conway</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Assis</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>COVID-19 pandemic is associated with increased sleep disturbances and mental health symptoms but not help-seeking: a cross-sectional nation-wide study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Sci</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5935/1984-0063.20220027</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Adrien</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Neurobiological bases for the relation between sleep and depression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>341</fpage>–<lpage>351</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/smrv.2001.0200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12531125</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Thase</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Depression and sleep: pathophysiology and treatment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Dialogues Clin Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>226</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.31887/DCNS.2006.8.2/mthase</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16889107</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mayers</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baldwin</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The relationship between sleep disturbance and depression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Psychiatry Clin Pract</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13651500500328087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24926763</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Worley</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The extraordinary importance of sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pharm Ther</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>758</fpage>–<lpage>763</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name><surname>Wyckoff</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ford</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Waits</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goulet</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sherlin</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep better, live better</article-title>; <year>2021</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xlink:href="https://getversus.com/s/Sleep-Better-Live-Better.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://getversus.com/s/Sleep-Better-Live-Better.pdf</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>October</month>
<day>24</day>, 2023</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bin</surname>
<given-names>YS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Is sleep quality more important than sleep duration for public health?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1629</fpage>–<lpage>1630</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.6078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27568809</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gaynes</surname>
<given-names>BN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burns</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tweed</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Erickson</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>DEPRESSION AND HEALTH-RELATED QUALITY OF LIFE</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Nerv Ment Dis</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>190</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>799</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005053-200212000-00001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12486367</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sheng</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shao</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Depression in sleep disturbance: a review on a bidirectional relationship, mechanisms and treatment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cell Mol Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>2324</fpage>–<lpage>2332</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcmm.14170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30734486</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Steiger</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pawlowski</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Depression and sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Mol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>607</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms20030607</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30708948</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Scullin</surname>
<given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bliwise</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep, cognition, and normal aging: integrating a half century of multidisciplinary research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Perspect Psychol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>137</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1745691614556680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25620997</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Lippe</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hall</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <part-title>Mental health disorders in older adult populations</part-title>. In: <string-name><surname>Gatchel</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schultz</surname>
<given-names>IZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ray</surname>
<given-names>CT</given-names></string-name> editors. <source><italic toggle="yes">Handbook of Rehabilitation in Older Adults. Handbooks in Health, Work, and Disability</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name>; <year>2018</year>:<fpage>243</fpage>–<lpage>261</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-03916-5_12</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Clemente-Suárez</surname>
<given-names>VJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martínez-González</surname>
<given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benitez-Agudelo</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on mental disorders. a critical review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>10041</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph181910041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34639341</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Allmang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Plummer</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Copeland</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Riascos</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Untangling the effects of COVID-19 on youth employment: directions for social work research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Soc Soc Work Res</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>433</fpage>–<lpage>439</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/720981</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ganson</surname>
<given-names>KT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsai</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weiser</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benabou</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nagata</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Job insecurity and symptoms of anxiety and depression among US young adults during COVID-19</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Adolesc Health</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jadohealth.2020.10.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33183926</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ellis</surname>
<given-names>WE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dumas</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Forbes</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Physically isolated but socially connected: psychological adjustment and stress among adolescents during the initial COVID-19 crisis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Can J Behav Sci Rev Can Sci Comport</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>187</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/cbs0000215</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Neavel</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Watkins</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chavez</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Youth, social media, and telehealth: how COVID-19 changed our interactions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatr Ann</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e161</fpage>–<lpage>e166</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3928/19382359-20220321-03</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35417309</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tiffany Field</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Social media and mental health in youth during COVID-19: a narrative review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Psychol Res Rev</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>54</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.28933/ijprr-2021-08-2905</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jia</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Mental health problems and social media exposure during COVID-19 outbreak</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e0231924</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32298385</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Seedat</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scott</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Angermeyer</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cross-national associations between gender and mental disorders in the World Health Association world mental health survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Gen Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>785</fpage>–<lpage>795</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2009.36</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19581570</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mallampalli</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carter</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Exploring sex and gender differences in sleep health: a Society for Women’s Health Research Report</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Womens Health</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>553</fpage>–<lpage>562</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/jwh.2014.4816</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jean-Louis</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ravenell</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A community-oriented framework to increase screening and treatment of obstructive sleep apnea among blacks</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>82</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2015.07.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26652238</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0055">
        <label>55.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nolen-Hoeksema</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Emotion regulation and psychopathology: the role of gender</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Annu Rev Clin Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>187</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-clinpsy-032511-143109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22035243</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0056">
        <label>56.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Maume</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sebastian</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bardo</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Gender, work-family responsibilities, and sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Gend Soc</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>746</fpage>–<lpage>768</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0891243210386949</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0057">
        <label>57.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rodriquez</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Livaudais-Toman</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gregorich</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jackson</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nápoles</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pérez-Stable</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Relationships between allostatic load, unhealthy behaviors, and depressive disorder in U.S. adults, 2005–2012 NHANES</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Prev Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ypmed.2018.02.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29421445</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0058">
        <label>58.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Caraballo</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Massey</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mahajan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Racial and ethnic disparities in access to health care among adults in the United States: a 20-year National Health Interview Survey Analysis, 1999–2018</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">medRxiv</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>2020</volume>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.10.30.20223420</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0059">
        <label>59.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chatters</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>HO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carr</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Race and objective social isolation: older African Americans, Black Caribbeans, and Non-Hispanic Whites</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Gerontol B Psychol Sci Soc Sci</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>74</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1429</fpage>–<lpage>1440</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/geronb/gby114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30289494</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0060">
        <label>60.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Belo</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Navarro-Pardo</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pocinho</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carrana</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Margarido</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Relationship between mental health and the education level in elderly people: mediation of leisure attitude</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2020.00573</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32063872</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0061">
        <label>61.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Niemeyer</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bieda</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Michalak</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schneider</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Margraf</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Education and mental health: do psychosocial resources matter?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">SSM Popul Health</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>100392</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ssmph.2019.100392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30989104</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0062">
        <label>62.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Orr</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Savage</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Expanding access to and ensuring equity in the benefits of remote work following the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sci Policy Governance</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.38126/JSPG180413</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0063">
        <label>63.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Relationship between income and mental health during the COVID-19 pandemic in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>8944</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph19158944</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35897317</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0064">
        <label>64.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Walker</surname>
<given-names>ER</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cummings</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hockenberry</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Druss</surname>
<given-names>BG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insurance status, use of mental health services, and unmet need for mental health care in the United States</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatr Serv Wash DC</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>578</fpage>–<lpage>584</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ps.201400248</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
