<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38348054</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">10859698</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">448346</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S448346</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Factors Associated with Persistent Obstructive Sleep Apnea After Bariatric Surgery: A Narrative Review</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Demaeyer and Bruyneel</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Demaeyer and Bruyneel</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Demaeyer</surname><given-names>Nathalie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7035-1266</contrib-id><name><surname>Bruyneel</surname><given-names>Marie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Pneumology, CHU Saint-Pierre, Université Libre de Bruxelles</institution>, <addr-line>Brussels</addr-line>, <country>Belgium</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Pneumology, CHU Brugmann, Université Libre de Bruxelles</institution>, <addr-line>Brussels</addr-line>, <country>Belgium</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Marie Bruyneel, <institution>Department of Pneumology, CHU Saint-Pierre</institution>, <addr-line>322 rue haute</addr-line>, <addr-line>Brussels</addr-line>, <addr-line>1000</addr-line>, <country>Belgium</country>, <phone>Tel +3225354219</phone>, <fax>Fax +3225353362</fax>, Email marie.bruyneel@stpierre-bru.be</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>07</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>123</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>05</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Demaeyer and Bruyneel.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Demaeyer and Bruyneel.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The prevalence of obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) among the bariatric surgery population is estimated to be 45–70%. However, weight loss obtained by bariatric surgery is not always associated with full remission of OSA, suggesting that other confounding factors are present. This article aims to review the current literature, focusing on factors that could predict the persistence of OSA after bariatric surgery. For this purpose, relevant studies of more than 50 patients that assessed pre- and post-operative presence and severity of OSA detected by poly(somno)graphy (PG/PSG) in bariatric populations were collected. Six retrospective and prospective studies were evaluated that included 1302 OSA patients, with a BMI range of 42.6 to 56 kg/m</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative">, age range of 44.8 to 50.7 years, and percentage of women ranging from 45% to 91%. The studies were very heterogeneous regarding type of bariatric surgery, diagnostic criteria for OSA and OSA remission, and delay of OSA reassessment. OSA remission was observed in 26% to 76% of patients at 11–12 months post-surgery. Loss to follow-up was high in all studies, leading to a potential underestimation of OSA remission. Based on this limited sample of bariatric patients, age, pre-operative OSA severity, proportion of weight loss, and type 2 diabetes (T2D) were identified as factors associated with OSA persistence but the results were inconsistent between studies regarding the impact of age and the magnitude of weight loss. Several other factors may potentially lead to OSA persistence in the bariatric surgery population, such as fat distribution, ethnicity, anatomical predisposition, pathophysiological traits, supine position, and REM-predominant hypopnea and apnea. Further well-conducted multicentric prospective studies are needed to document the importance of these factors to achieve a better understanding of OSA persistence after bariatric surgery in obese patients.</citation_analysis></p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>bariatric surgery</kwd><kwd>gastric sleeve</kwd><kwd>gastric bypass</kwd><kwd>obstructive sleep apnea</kwd><kwd>polygraphy</kwd><kwd>polysomnography</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>no funding to report</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>There is no funding to report.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="2"/><ref-count count="49"/><page-count count="13"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) results from repeated decrease or cessation of upper airway (UA) flow during sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> This condition, if left untreated, is associated with cardiovascular comorbidities (eg, myocardial infarction, diabetes, stroke, hypertension (HT)), increased risk of motor vehicle accidents, and premature mortality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> OSA is a heterogenous disease with varied predisposing factors, pathophysiological mechanisms, and multiple clinical manifestations (eg, excessive daytime sleepiness (EDS), fatigue, choking, gasping) while a significant proportion of patients who exhibit OSA on a sleep record are asymptomatic.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3–7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The prevalence of OSA syndrome (OSAS; ie, OSA associated with symptoms and/or comorbidities) is estimated to be 3–7% in adult men and 2–5% in adult women in the general population</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> and this is likely to grow over time due to the obesity epidemic.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In order to characterize the severity of OSA, obstructive apnea/hypopnea index (AHI) values of 5–14, 15–29, and ≥30 are used to define mild, moderate, and severe OSA, respectively. However, AHI is poorly correlated with the severity of clinical symptoms</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> despite the fact that there is a linear relationship between AHI and HT</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and AHI correlates with overall mortality in OSA patients.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> The non-modifiable risk factors for OSA are aging, ethnicity, male gender, menopause, and anatomic features.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">OSA is also associated with endocrine disorders (eg, acromegaly, hypothyroidism, type 2 diabetes (T2D)), heart failure, and renal insufficiency and, in these cases, the treatment of the underlying disorder can improve OSA. However, the main modifiable risk factor for OSA remains obesity</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> while sedentarity and lifestyle factors (eg, use of sedatives and hypnotics, alcohol and tobacco) also play a significant role.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13–15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Obesity is a strong risk factor for OSA, resulting in reduction of lung volume, related to an increase in abdominal fat, and narrowing of the UA due to fat deposition in the oropharyngeal muscle and the surrounding tissues such as the tongue, soft palate, uvula, and lateral pharyngeal wall and increase in neck circumference.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Weight loss is thus an efficient treatment in OSA but weight loss takes time and can be only be proposed as the sole treatment in mild-to-moderate OSA patients. In addition, the majority of patients are not able to maintain weight loss over the long-term, and gaining weight is associated with OSA reoccurrence/aggravation.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Therefore, bariatric surgery is a common strategy used to obtain a sustained and significant weight loss in obese patients.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16–20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The prevalence of OSA among the bariatric population is very high compared to the general population and is estimated to be 45%–70%.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> A recent meta-analysis based on 32 studies that included 2310 patients, reported an OSA remission rate of 65%. Remission was associated with improvements in sleep quality and EDS.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Nevertheless, weight loss obtained by bariatric surgery is not always associated with full remission of OSA, suggesting that other factors can contribute to OSA. Indeed, craniofacial disharmony is also a risk factor for OSA, related to reduction of pharyngeal airway space, an inferiorly placed hyoid bone, or increased anterior facial height.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Reduced pharyngeal airway space is associated with the position of tongue, soft palate, maxilla, and mandibula.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> An inferiorly placed hyoid bone increases the risk of pharyngeal collapse. The co-existence of bi-maxillary retrusion and acute cranial base angle may reduce the antero-posterior dimension of the pharyngeal airway. Increases in soft palate thickness and length can also contribute to OSA. Furthermore, increased area and length of the tongue among OSA patients suggests they have a more posterior position of the tongue.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In addition, people of African descent have a significantly larger tongue that could make them more susceptible to OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In addition to anatomic factors, the pathophysiological PALM classification has been developed to explain the dynamic factors associated with OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Four components contribute to OSA. The first is anatomic collapsibility, reflected by the critical occlusion pressure (Pcrit). Fat deposition in the UA and abdominal area (reduced lung volume) increase anatomic collapsibility. Snoring and repeated pharyngeal depression during obstructive events lead to chronic inflammation of the soft tissue, reducing the diameter of the UA and increasing anatomic collapsibility. Moreover, a supine position with rising of the diaphragm, and backdrop of the jaw and tongue also increases anatomic collapsibility. Pcrit can be measured by reduction of continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) levels, during sleep, determining the pressure at which the pharyngeal airway occludes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The second component in the PALM classification is the muscular upper airway gain (UAG). Different muscles are responsible for UA patency: muscles that regulate the position of the hyoid bone, tongue base muscles and pharyngeal constrictors, and muscles of the soft palate.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The interaction between anatomic collapsibility and neuromuscular compensation determines the extent of OSA. Either the neuromuscular compensation offsets the anatomic collapsibility (in all positions and in all sleep stages) or not.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The third aspect of the PALM system is the loop gain (LG), including 3 components: the control component, via chemoreceptors, the exchange component, via the lungs, and the connection component, regulated by the circulation. LG &gt; 1 reflects a (hyper-)sensitive system leading to excessive ventilatory response (periodic breathing), while LG &lt; 1 is associated with a more stable ventilatory system.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The last component of the PALM classification is the arousal threshold (AT), defined as the level of inspiratory effort at which obstructive events terminate with an arousal from sleep. If all the mechanisms successfully achieve UA patency and sustainable ventilation (VE), an arousal from sleep may not be required to support ventilation. The threshold required to achieve UA reopening (associated with sustainable VE) is defined as the threshold of effective recruitment (TER). The arousal at the end of an obstructive event occurs when the AT &lt; TER or when hyperventilation follows UA reopening (stimulation of the arousal center). A low AT causes sleep fragmentation, and ventilatory and pharyngeal muscular instability, promoting obstructive events recurrence and EDS.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Approximately 20% of OSA patients have high anatomic collapsibility and 80% have a combination of anatomic disharmonies and anomalies in AT/UAG/LG.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">PALM 1 (23%) represents very high UA collapsibility (Pcrit &gt; 2.5 cm H</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">O). In this case, weight loss, positional therapy, oral appliance (OA), CPAP, and UA surgery are the first-line treatments (anatomical treatments).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">PALM 2 (57%) represents intermediate collapsibility (Pcrit between +2.5 and −2.5 cm H</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">O).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Patients in subgroup 2a (no major non-anatomical impairment) are candidates for anatomical treatment. Patients in subgroup 2b (one or more non-anatomical impairments) are candidates for a combination of anatomical and non-anatomical treatments.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">PALM 3 (19%) represents low UA collapsibility (Pcrit &lt; −2.5 cm H</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">O). The treatment for these patients would be non-CPAP treatment options: weight loss, OA, oxygen, and drugs targeting the LG or the AT (eg, acetazolamide, Z-drugs).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">A therapeutic level of CPAP ≤ 8 cm H</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">O corresponds to the PALM 3 group of patients.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> From a pathophysiological point of view, patients exhibiting a PALM 1 and PALM 2a pattern are expected to improve with weight loss. Finally, aging is associated with an increased prevalence of OSA in both sexes, but remains higher in males.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The multiple factors implicated in OSA physiopathology may explain the potential persistence of OSA after bariatric surgery in obese patients. The aim of the present narrative review was to identify factors associated with persistence of OSA after bariatric surgery.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">For this analysis, relevant studies assessing pre- and post-operative presence and severity of OSA detected by PG/PSG in bariatric populations were selected.</citation_analysis></p>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Eligibility Criteria of the Studies</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Inclusion criteria: Prospective and retrospective studies assessing pre- and post-operative presence and severity of OSA by polygraphy (PG) or polysomnography (PSG) in adults undergoing bariatric surgery. Full text available in English, in PubMed central and Scopus databases. Relevant keywords: bariatric, gastric sleeve, gastric bypass, sleep apnea, hypopnea, polygraphy, polysomnography.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Exclusion criteria: the studies with a sample size less than 50 patients were excluded. Indeed, 45 participants would have to be included in the sample to show a AHI reduction of −25/h after bariatric surgery,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> with a power at 80%, Type I error (α)=0,05, Type II error (β)=0,2. If primary outcome was mean difference of BMI of – 13,2 (Type I error (α)=0.05 Type II error (β)=0.2 Power = 0.8), a number of 66 patients was required.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Based on these two hypotheses, it seems relevant that studies with a final sample size of &lt; 45–50 patients were excluded due to high risk of bias.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Six studies of interest that met inclusion criteria were selected, after exclusion of 23 studies with sample size between 8 and 46 patients (median: 24 patients), totalizing 574 patients.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The six studies are summarized in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. Yanari et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and Morong et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> were retrospective studies. The other four studies, de Raaff et al,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Peromaa-Havisto et al,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Haines et al,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and Ravesloot et al,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> were prospective studies. The only multicentric study was Peromaa-Havisto et al.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> These studies included 1302 OSA patients at inclusion (PG/PSG confirmed OSA cases among patients who are going to undergo bariatric surgery) and 690 patients in the final study samples. The flow chart of patient inclusion is shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Summary of the Six Included Studies Selected from the Literature Review Assessing Pre- and Post-Operative Presence and Severity of OSA by PG or PSG in Adults Undergoing Bariatric Surgery</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study and Date of Publication</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of Study</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Final Study Sample/ Number at Inclusion</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demographics</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surgery</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-Surgery Timing Assessment</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-BMI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-BMI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-AHI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-AHI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSA Diagnostic</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSA Remission</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Findings</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comments</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">de Raaff et al 2016<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<break/>2008–2015</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">205/437</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women: 63.4%<break/>Mean age: 48.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RYGB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Between 6–9m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSG/PG<break/>AASM 1999</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSG/PG showing<break/>AHI &lt;15:<break/>74.1%<break/>No CPAP wash-out</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predictive factors of OSA persistence: age ≥ 50 y, pre-AHI ≥ 30, EWL &lt; 60%, HT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45% PG pre-op, 31% post-op<break/>≤ AHI underestimated with PG<break/>≤ Probably higher OSA remission<break/>Lost to follow-up: 229/437 (52%)<break/>Death: 3<break/>More follow-up assumed among more symptomatic patients<break/>≤ patients with AHI &lt; 15 underestimated</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yanari et al 2022<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<break/>2013–2019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56/56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women: 45%<break/>Mean age: 44.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6m and 1y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.1 (6m)<break/>31.4<break/>(1y)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.4 (6m)<break/>23<break/>(1y)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSG<break/>AASM: NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSG showing<break/>AHI &lt;15<break/>at 1y: 51.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Correlation between EWL%, changes in tongue and uvula area and AHI changes<break/>Pre-op AHI and Post-op HbA1c = independent prognostic factors for OSA persistence<break/>Reduction of NC after SG but not correlated with OSA remission</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prevalence of micrognathia higher among Japanese people ≤ remission rate inferior in comparison with other studies<break/>Lost to follow-up: 0%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peromaa-Haavisto et al 2017<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P (multicentric)<break/>2010–2013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">164/187</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women: 64%<break/>Mean age: 50.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LRYGB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PG<break/>AASM 1999</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PG showing<break/>AHI &lt;5 at 1y: 45%<break/>(AHI&gt;15: 20% at 1y)<break/>De novo OSA occurred in 8% of the patients after surgery</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No predictive factor found for OSA remission/persistence<break/>Less effect on AHI in supine position compared to non-supine position</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 different hospitals<break/>Lost to follow-up: 23/187 (12%)<break/>554: referral patients but only 197 willing to participate at the study</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Haines et al 2006<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<break/>1998–2005</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96/289</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women: 91%<break/>Mean age: 45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RYGB<break/>(LRYGB50%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean: 11m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RDI: 51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RDI: 15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSG<break/>AASM 1999<break/>RDI<break/>0–5: absent<break/>6–20: mild<break/>21–40: moderate<break/>&gt; 40: severe</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Remission rate:<break/>52/83=63% (no longer need of CPAP/BiPAP)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, RDI, and CPAP use decreased post-surgery.<break/>On PSG: minimum oxygen saturation, sleep efficiency, REM latency improved</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lost to follow-up: 191/289 (66%)<break/>Death: 2<break/>Choice of RDI instead of AHI, reason unknown<break/>High variability in post-op timing evaluation (6–42months)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Morong et al 2014<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<break/>2008–2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">119/162</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women: 80.2%<break/>Mean age: 45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSG<break/>AASM 2007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSG showing AHI &lt; 5 at 7m: 35.2%<break/>POSA by Cartwright’s criteria<break/>POSA prevalence post-surgery: 62.7%<break/>44% who were originally diagnosed with OSA before developed POSA after surgery</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, neck circumference and AHI significantly lower in POSA patients.<break/>Low AHI is the only significant independent predictive factor for the presence of POSA<break/>Reduction of BMI, neck circumference, total AHI, desaturation, and better sleep efficiency post-surgery.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lost to follow-up: 43/162 (26%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ravesloot et al 2014<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1<break/>110/171<break/>T2 50/171</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women: 60.8%<break/>Mean age: NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LAGB<break/>LRYGB<break/>SG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">t1: 6m<break/>t2: 12m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110: pre-BMI 45.4<break/>50: pre-BMI 45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110: post-BMI 36.3<break/>50: post-BMI 35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110:pre-AHI 39.5<break/>50: pre-AHI 49.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110: post-AHI 15.6<break/>50: post-AHI 17.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSG<break/>AASM 2007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSG/PG showing AHI &lt; 5 at 6 m: 25.5%<break/>at 12 m: 24%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Improvement of clinical and sleep parameters during the first 7 months.<break/>No linear relationship between the extent of weight loss and improvement in OSA<break/>Age, pre-op weight/BMI are not predictive factors of OSA remission</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some patients with BMI &lt; 35 included if co-morbidities (HT, DT2, OSA, joint problems)<break/>Lost to follow-up:121/171 (70%)<break/>LRYGB &gt;LAGB &gt; SG<break/>More severely obese patients<break/>26% PG instead of post-op PSG<break/>≤ AHI underestimated with PG<break/>≤ Probably lower OSA remission</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: AASM, American Academy of Sleep Medicine scoring rules; AHI, apnea-hypopnea index; BiPAP, bilevel positive airway pressure; BMI, body mass index; CPAP, continuous positive airway pressure; DL, dyslipidemia; EWL, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><inline-formula id="ilm0001"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-111-e0001.jpg"/><tex-math id="Tex001">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
${{excess\ weight\ loss = }}{{{{Pre - op\ weight - follow - up\ weight}}} \over {{{pre - op\ weight - ideal\ weight}}}}{{ \times 100}}$\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">; HbA1c, glycated hemoglobin; HT, hypertension; LAGB, laparoscopic gastric banding; (L)RYGB, (Laparoscopic) Roux-en-Y gastric bypass; M, months; NC, neck circumference; NR, not reported; P, prospective; PG, polygraphy; POSA, positional obstructive sleep apnea; PSG, polysomnography; R, retrospective; RDI, respiratory disturbance index; SG, sleeve gastrectomy; T2D, type 2 diabetes; Y, years.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Pre-op mean body mass index (BMI) ranged from 42.6 to 56 kg/m</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and mean age varied from 44.8 to 50.7 years. Comorbidities, if reported, were frequent among these patients, with a high prevalence of T2D (from 42% to 67.2%)</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and HT (from 57.6% to 62%).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The majority of patients were females, ranging from 45% to 91% of the study population.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Patients were assessed by PG and/or PSG in all studies pre- and post-operatively. OSA severity was assessed using AHI calculated during PG/PSG or respiratory disturbance index (RDI), that included respiratory-related arousals, with different severity cut-offs (Haines et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) and according to different American Academy of Sleep Medicine (AASM) criteria.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Surgical procedures were Roux-en-Y gastric bypass (RYGB) for de Raaff et al,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Peromaa-Havisto et al,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and Haines et al,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> sleeve gastrectomy (SG) for Yanari et al,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and Ravesloot et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> compared laparoscopic gastric banding (LAGB) vs RYGB vs SG. In one study, the applied surgery was not reported (Morong et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Six-to-nine month post-surgery reassessment was available in 2 studies (de Raaff et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and Morong et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). Post-operative reevaluation was at 6 months and one year in 2 studies (Yanari et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and Ravesloot et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). Changes at 11 to 12 months were assessed in 2 studies (Peromaa-Havisto et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and Haines et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">During the postoperative OSA reassessment, sleep tests were repeated, but it is important to note that in de Raaff et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and in Ravesloot et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> some patients had PG instead of PSG and the reverse. Post-operative mean BMI decreased significantly in all studies with a decrease ranging between 9.1 and 18 kg/m</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. The remission rate for T2D ranged between 45% and 66.7%.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> For HT, this was 73% but was only reported by Peromaa et al.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> OSA remission rates exhibited quite a bit of variation among the studies, at between 24% and 74%, but the definition of remission varied between studies: AHI&lt; 5, AHI &lt; 15, or “no more need of CPAP/BiPAP”.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Regarding factors associated with persistence of OSA after bariatric surgery, several analyses were performed. Ravesloot et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> observed that preoperative BMI was not related to OSA remission. However, De Raaff et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> determined that excess weight loss (EWL) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><inline-formula id="ilm0002"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-111-e0002.jpg"/><tex-math id="Tex002">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
${{excess\ weight\ loss = }}{{{{Pre - op\ weight - follow - up\ weight}}} \over {{{pre - op\ weight - ideal\ weight}}}}{\mathrm{ \times 100}}$\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) &lt; 60% was a predictive factor of OSA persistence when Ravesloot et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> showed no linear relationship between the extent of weight loss and improvement in OSA. Pre- and post-operative BMI were relatively similar in both studies.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">de Raaff et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> concluded that severe apnea (AHI ≥ 30) before surgery was a predictive factor of OSA persistence. Yanari et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> also observed that pre-operative AHI was an independent prognostic factor of OSA persistence. In Ravesloot et al,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> age was not a predictive factor of OSA remission, unlike the results from de Raaff et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> in which older age predicted OSA persistence. Regarding comorbidities, Yanari et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> found that high glycated hemoglobin (HbA1c) post-surgery was an independent prognostic factor for OSA persistence. HT was also identified as a predictive factor of OSA persistence by de Raaff et al.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This narrative review highlights the rate of remission of OSA one year after bariatric surgery. This review was strengthened by having selected studies with a significant sample size at the time of follow-up and a homogeneous and accurate assessment of pre- and post-operative OSA. The lack of well-conducted studies in the field is quite surprising considering the volume of bariatric surgery performed each year. Indeed, there were 18,909 procedures in Germany in 2022.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> As obesity is the strongest risk factor for OSA, among the bariatric population, OSA prevalence reaches 45%–70%.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <sec id="s0004-s2001">
        <title>Difficulties Related to the Selection of Studies</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">When collecting literature on cure rates in OSA after bariatric surgery, several difficulties were faced in terms of selection of high-quality studies. Studies on the topic are highly heterogeneous, some were prospective, others were retrospective, and no randomized controlled trials with an adequate sample size were available. There was also high variability in the assessment of OSA patients among the bariatric surgery population, with vague definitions of OSA (eg, self-declaration of suffering from the disorder or self-reported use of CPAP/bilevel positive airway pressure [BiPAP]). A large number of studies were excluded for insufficient number of patients in the final study sample. The “lost to follow-up” category was high in most of the studies. This is also observed in other settings, as seen in a longitudinal study exploring remission of gastroesophageal reflux after a median of 77 months post-Nissen fundoplication, the “lost to follow-up” group was as high as 14%.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The long timing of the post-surgery period and the inconvenience of coming back for PSG could be a possible explanation for the loss of patients. The patients with fewer or no symptoms of OSA after surgery were probably more reluctant to come to the follow-up appointments. Indeed, the self-reported discontinuation of CPAP/BiPAP is an inaccurate way to evaluate OSA remission as 70% of the patients are non-compliant with CPAP after bariatric surgery.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <sec id="s0004-s2001-s3001">
          <title>Heterogeneity of the Definition of OSA and OSA Remission</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Among the selected studies for the present review, OSA definition was also based on two different sleep recordings, PG or PSG, for evaluating AHI. This could be a source of bias for OSA prevalence as diagnosis based on PG can lead to underestimation of OSA severity or false negative results. Indeed, patients diagnosed using PG are likely to have a 30% lower AHI compared to patients undergoing diagnosis by PSG.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Moreover, 14% of patients would be missed for a severe OSA diagnosis with PG instead of PSG.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> The use of different AASM criteria (1999, 2007) can also lead to variability in AHI, especially regarding the number of scored hypopneas, as 2007 criteria are more severe.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> For OSA reassessment after surgery, some study teams have used PSG instead of PG, and this can lead to the reverse, an underestimation of remission rate. Of note, variability of remission rate definition AHI &lt; 5, AHI &lt; 15 or “no more need of CPAP/BiPAP” can also explain the large variation in remission rates among the studies.</citation_analysis></p>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Another concern was related to CPAP wash-out in CPAP users before performing post-surgery PG/PSG. This essential requirement was not applied in any of the studies. The absence of a wash-out period overestimates the real OSA remission rate. When stopping CPAP use, OSA reoccurs after a mean of one week, associated with a sympathetic activity increase, blood pressure increase, relevant cerebral hypoxia, and disturbed cardiac repolarization but without an increased risk of myocardial infarction.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> CPAP withdrawal can, however, increase EDS and reduce driving performance, representing an ethical problem for CPAP/BiPAP withdrawal for the study.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Of note, only 45% of OSA patients suffer from EDS, such that the risk of stopping CPAP one week is low.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Moreover, for the other patients, they can just be asked to avoid driving during the washout period.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2002">
        <title>Influence of Age and Sex</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In all the included studies, except that of Yanari et al,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> there were more women than men in the final study sample. Indeed, the prevalence of obesity is 15% for women and 11% for men.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Moreover, women are more inclined to undergo bariatric surgery.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> According to one study, among 61,708 patients over 10 years, 22% of bariatric surgeries were performed on men and 78% on women.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The predominance of women included in the studies could be a factor related to reduced persistence of OSA after surgery as OSA is mainly related to visceral obesity, typically found in males.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Women are more likely to develop OSA after menopause, due to hormonal changes and increases in visceral deposition of fat.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In the 6 studies selected, the mean age was 47 years and, according to the World Health Organization, most women experience menopause between the age of 45 and 55 years, however, we do not know the menopausal status of these patients and its potential implication in reported OSA remission rates.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2003">
        <title>Choice of Surgical Techniques and Post-Operative Reassessment Period</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The heterogeneity of the studies is also due to the different bariatric surgeries used and the variable post-surgery timing evaluation for persistence/remission of OSA. In a cohort study over 10 years, among 1787 obese patients undergoing RYGB, the patients lost 31% of their baseline weight at one year and 28% at 10 years compared to their nonsurgical matches.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> For SG, the patients lost 23% of their baseline at one year and for LAGB, the patients lost 13% of their baseline weight at one year.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The result at 10 years for SG/LAGB was not available since the patients lost to follow-up was too high after four years. After four years, weight loss was higher with RYGB than SG, which was higher than LAGB.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> A prospective cohort study reported that among 1406 participants undergoing RYGB, the maximal weight loss (37.4% of their baseline) was achieved after a median of two post-operative years. The highest rate of weight regain was during the first year after their nadir weight.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> summarizes the factors possibly linked to variable weight loss after bariatric surgery.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Flow chart of patients included in the six relevant studies. Number at inclusion: total of PSG/PG confirmed OSA patients (AHI&gt;5) that have undergone bariatric surgery. Final number: total of OSA patients with analyzable post-operative PSG/PG. Deaths were reported only in 2 studies (De Raaf et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and Haines et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-111-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: AHI, apnea-hypopnea index; OSA, obstructive sleep apnea; PG, polygraphy; PSG, polysomnography.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Factors Possibly Linked to Variable Weight Loss After Bariatric Surgery</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Factors</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Influence on Weight Loss<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39–41</xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surgical technique</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RYGB&gt;SG&gt;LAGB</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-operative BMI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High&gt;less high</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F&gt;M</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Young&gt;older</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">White, Hispanics&gt;other</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comorbidities</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No&gt;present</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current&gt;non-smoker</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: LAGB, laparoscopic gastric banding; RYGB, Roux-en-Y gastric bypass; SG, sleeve gastrectomy; F, female; M, male.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">According to a randomized controlled trial that followed patients who underwent RYGB vs SG for over 10 years, there were no statistically significant differences in T2D, dyslipidemia (DL), or OSA remission but HT remission rates were higher with RYGB.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Most T2D remission was achieved in two years but no data was presented concerning the best timing for DL/OSA/HTA remission.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> According to this literature review, %EWL was not associated with higher/lower OSA remission rate.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> We hypothesize that the highest OSA remission rate is associated with maximal weight loss, therefore, after one year. In any case, waiting longer for postoperative evaluation of OSA remission rate increases the risk of a higher number of lost to follow-up patients.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2004">
        <title>Factors Associated with Persistence of OSA After Bariatric Surgery</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In the current study, factors associated with persistence of OSA after bariatric surgery included EWL &lt; 60% (de Raaff et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">), but no relationship was identified between pre-operative BMI and the magnitude of weight loss in Ravesloot et al.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> These differences may be related to the sample size of the studies. Ravesloot et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> included fewer patients (n = 171 vs 437) with a high loss to follow-up rate at 12 months of 70%. Other factors, such as pre-operative AHI (de Raaff et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and Yanari et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) and aging (de Raaff et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">), were also not identified by Ravesloot et al.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> However, these risk factors seem to be related to OSA persistence as OSA rate increases with age</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and as the reduction of AHI is linearly associated with BMI, such that if AHI is higher at baseline, the magnitude of the decrease will not be higher than that for less severe OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The fact that these factors were not identified in the study by Ravesloot et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> may also be related to the use of post-operative PG rather than PSG and an underestimation of post-operative AHI.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Regarding comorbidities, Yanari et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> reported that high HbA1c post-surgery was an independent prognostic factor for OSA persistence. A meta-analysis of studies that followed patients up to 24 months indicated that the remission rate of T2D was 63.5%–82%.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Since T2D is a risk factor for OSA,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> persistence of T2D could be an explanation for OSA persistence after bariatric surgery.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">HT was identified as a predictive factor of OSA persistence by de Raaff et al.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The incidence of HT is associated with severe OSA, potentially explaining the remaining presence of post-operative sleep apnea in this specific population.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">One of the lowest remission rates (35%) was observed in Morong et al.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In this study, they used a more restrictive definition of remission: PSG with AHI &lt; 5. Their hypothesis was that positional OSA (POSA) was underestimated among patients after bariatric surgery suggesting that the habit of sleeping in a supine position with CPAP/BiPAP should explain the larger proportion of POSA after surgery. Morong et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> noticed that only low AHI was a significant independent predictor for POSA and that 44% of those who were originally diagnosed with OSA developed POSA after surgery. POSA is associated with backward positioning of the lower jaw, smaller lower facial height, smaller craniofacial volume, and smaller volume of lateral pharyngeal wall soft tissue.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Finally, the lost to follow-up rates in the studies included in this literature review were broadly elevated, from 12% (Peromaa et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) to 70% (Ravesloot et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">), introducing a possible selection bias.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In conclusion, we identified, from this limited sample of bariatric patients, that age, pre-operative OSA severity, proportion of weight loss, and T2D may be factors related to OSA persistence after bariatric surgery but the reported results were inconsistent between studies for age and the magnitude of weight loss. However, several other factors influencing the persistence of OSA should be prospectively explored in adequately powered studies that include strategies to standardize OSA diagnosis and limit loss to follow-up. These include fat distribution, anatomical predispositions and pathophysiological traits, ethnicity, supine position, and rapid eye movement (REM)-predominant hypopnea and apnea.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This could be accomplished by setting up a multicentric prospective study, ideally a randomized controlled trial. Obese patients (BMI &gt; 40), candidates for RYGB, would be randomized in two arms, surgery or behavioral intervention with OSA resolution as primary aim. We would choose RYGB since it is associated with a higher weight loss.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Baseline assessments should include home-PSG before surgery/behavioral intervention, sleep endoscopy, 3-D cone beam computed tomography for extensive anthropometric measurements, waist and neck circumference and fat distribution with free-fat mass component (assessed by dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry). Additional measurements assessing OSA pathophysiological phenotypes, such as Pcrit (H</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">O) and other PSG ventilatory analysis could be performed in patients with confirmed OSA during attended PSG. The better post-operative timing to re-assess patients would be one year because maximal weight loss is observed at this point in long-term prospective studies.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Thus, one year after surgery/behavioral intervention, home-PSG should be repeated (after one-week wash-out of CPAP, if CPAP-treated</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34–36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) together with 3-D cone beam computed tomography, waist and neck circumference, fat distribution with free-fat mass component to understand factors associated with OSA resolution or persistence. Using home-PSG would bring an added value to assessment of sleep position, REM, and supine OSA in the patients’ usual sleep environment. To obtain a population sample that would allow sufficient representation of all the factors possibly associated with the persistence of OSA post-operatively, based on the prevalence of these factors as followed: menopausal women, 20%, ethnicity other than Caucasians, 30%,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> craniofacial anomalies, 30%,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> REM-predominant OSA, 30%,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> T2D, 40% in a bariatric population, the sample size should be 300 patients in each arm (surgery/behavioral intervention). To obtain this population of 600 OSA patients eligible for RYGB, 1200 patients would have to be screened. This type of study could make a major contribution to understanding the evolution of OSA after bariatric surgery in obese patients.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors acknowledge the contribution of a medical writer, Sandy Field, PhD, for English language editing and formatting of the manuscript.</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">AASM, American Academy of Sleep Medicine; AHI, apnea-hypopnea index; AT, arousal threshold; BiPAP, bilevel positive airway pressure; BMI, body mass index; CPAP, continuous positive airway pressure; DL, dyslipidemia; EDS, excessive daytime sleepiness; EWL, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><inline-formula id="ilm0003"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-111-e0003.jpg"/><tex-math id="Tex003">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
${{excess\ weight\ loss = }}{{{{Pre - op\ weight - follow - up\ weight}}} \over {{{pre - op\ weight - ideal\ weight}}}}{{ \times 100}}$\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">; HbA1c, glycated hemoglobin; HT, hypertension; LAGB, laparoscopic gastric banding; LG, loop gain; OA, oral appliance; OAGB, one anastomosis gastric bypass; OSA, obstructive sleep apnea; OSAS, OSA-associated with symptoms and/or comorbidities; PG, polygraphy; PSG, polysomnography; RDI, respiratory disturbance index; REM, rapid eye movement; RYGB, Roux-en-Y gastric bypass; SG, sleeve gastrectomy; T2D, type 2 diabetes; TER, threshold of effective recruitment; UA, upper airway; UAG, muscular upper airway gain; VE, ventilation.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Ethics Approval and Informed Consent</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This review did not require any ethics and informed consent.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0008">
      <title>Consent for Publication</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Authors give consent for the publication of the present material.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0009">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation, or in all these areas; took part in drafting, revising or critically reviewing the article; gave final approval of the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0010">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors have no competing interests to declare for this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Young</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peppard</surname>
<given-names>PE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gottlieb</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Epidemiology of obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>165</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1217</fpage>–<lpage>1239</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.2109080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11991871</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Peppard</surname>
<given-names>PE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Young</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Palta</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prospective study of the association between sleep-disordered breathing and hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>342</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>1378</fpage>–<lpage>1384</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM200005113421901</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10805822</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zinchuk</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yaggi</surname>
<given-names>HK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Phenotypic subtypes of OSA: a challenge and opportunity for precision medicine</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>157</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>403</fpage>–<lpage>420</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chest.2019.09.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31539538</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Akset</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poppe</surname>
<given-names>KG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kleynen</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Endocrine disorders in obstructive sleep apnoea syndrome: a bidirectional relationship</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Endocrinol</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>98</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cen.14685</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Andreozzi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Overstraeten</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ben Youssef</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>African ethnicity is associated with a higher prevalence of diabetes in obstructive sleep apnea patients: results of a retrospective analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>857</fpage>–<lpage>864</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-019-01912-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31410809</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bosi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Vito</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eckert</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Qualitative phenotyping of obstructive sleep apnea and its clinical usefulness for the sleep specialist</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2058</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph17062058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32244892</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pevernagie</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gnidovec-Strazisar</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grote</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>On the rise and fall of the apnea-hypopnea index: a historical review and critical appraisal</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>e13066</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.13066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32406974</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kendzerska</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mollayeva</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gershon</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Untreated obstructive sleep apnea and the risk for serious long-term adverse outcomes: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<page-range>49‑59</page-range>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2013.01.003</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Neelapu</surname>
<given-names>BC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kharbanda</surname>
<given-names>OP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sardana</surname>
<given-names>HK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Craniofacial and upper airway morphology in adult obstructive sleep apnea patients: a systematic review and meta-analysis of cephalometric studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2016.01.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27039222</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Menopause [Internet]</article-title>; <year>2023</year>. <comment>Available from:</comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/menopause" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/menopause</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <day>25</day>, <month>September</month> 2023</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cooper</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gupta</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moustafa</surname>
<given-names>AF</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sex/gender differences in obesity prevalence, comorbidities, and treatment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Obes Rep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<page-range>458‑466</page-range>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13679-021-00453-x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Romero-Corral</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caples</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lopez-Jimenez</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Interactions between obesity and obstructive sleep apnea: implications for treatment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>137</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>711</fpage>–<lpage>719</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.09-0360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20202954</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zeng</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ren</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association between smoking behavior and obstructive sleep apnea: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nicotine Tob Res</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>364</fpage>–<lpage>371</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ntr/ntac126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35922388</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stampfer</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Physical activity, sedentary behaviour and incidence of obstructive sleep apnoea in three prospective US cohorts</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Respir J</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>2100606</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.00606-2021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34289976</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kolla</surname>
<given-names>BP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Foroughi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saeidifard</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The impact of alcohol on breathing parameters during sleep: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2018.05.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30017492</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hariri</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kini</surname>
<given-names>SU</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Herron</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Resolution of symptomatic obstructive sleep apnea not impacted by preoperative body mass index, choice of operation between sleeve gastrectomy and roux-en-Y gastric bypass surgery, or severity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Obes Surg</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1402</fpage>–<lpage>1407</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11695-017-3042-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29204779</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yanari</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sasaki</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Umemura</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Therapeutic effect of laparoscopic sleeve gastrectomy on obstructive sleep apnea and relationship of type 2 diabetes in Japanese patients with severe obesity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Diabetes Investig</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1073</fpage>–<lpage>1085</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jdi.13755</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sarkhosh</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Switzer</surname>
<given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>El-Hadi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The impact of bariatric surgery on obstructive sleep apnea: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Obes Surg</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>414</fpage>–<lpage>423</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11695-012-0862-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23299507</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Al Oweidat</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Toubasi</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tawileh</surname>
<given-names>RBA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Bariatric surgery and obstructive sleep apnea: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2283</fpage>–<lpage>2294</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-023-02840-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37145243</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Peromaa-Haavisto</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tuomilehto</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kössi</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea: the effect of bariatric surgery after 12 months. A prospective multicenter trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2016.12.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28549834</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Timmerman</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Basille</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Basille-Fantinato</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Short-term assessment of obstructive sleep apnea syndrome remission rate after sleeve gastrectomy: a cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Obes Surg</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>3690</fpage>–<lpage>3697</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11695-019-04110-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31346929</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Davidson</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sedgh</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tran</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The anatomic basis for the acquisition of speech and obstructive sleep apnea: evidence from cephalometric analysis supports the great leap forward hypothesis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>497</fpage>–<lpage>505</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2005.03.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15994120</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bruyneel</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea phenotypes eligible for pharmacological treatment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>2</volume>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/frsle.2023.1261276</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Senaratna</surname>
<given-names>CV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perret</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lodge</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence of obstructive sleep apnea in the general population: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>70</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2016.07.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27568340</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>A-M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barnes</surname>
<given-names>HN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Joosten</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The effect of surgical weight loss on obstructive sleep apnoea: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2018.06.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30001806</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Morong</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benoist</surname>
<given-names>LBL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ravesloot</surname>
<given-names>MJL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The effect of weight loss on OSA severity and position dependence in the bariatric population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>851</fpage>–<lpage>856</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-014-0955-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24584563</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>de Raaff</surname>
<given-names>CAL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coblijn</surname>
<given-names>UK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ravesloot</surname>
<given-names>MJL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Persistent moderate or severe obstructive sleep apnea after laparoscopic roux-en-Y gastric bypass: which patients?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Surg Obes Relat Dis</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1866</fpage>–<lpage>1872</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.soard.2016.03.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27234342</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Haines</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nelson</surname>
<given-names>LG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gonzalez</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Objective evidence that bariatric surgery improves obesity-related obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Surgery</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>141</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>354</fpage>–<lpage>358</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.surg.2006.08.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17349847</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ravesloot</surname>
<given-names>MJL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hilgevoord</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van Wagensveld</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Assessment of the effect of bariatric surgery on obstructive sleep apnea at two postoperative intervals</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Obes Surg</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11695-013-1023-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23856989</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Germany bariatric surgery procedures count by segments and forecast to 2030 [Internet]</article-title>. <source>Market Research Reports &amp; Consulting | GlobalData UK Ltd</source>. <comment>Available from:</comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.globaldata.com/store/report/germany-bariatric-surgery-procedures-analysis/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.globaldata.com/store/report/germany-bariatric-surgery-procedures-analysis/</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>October</month>
<day>16</day>, 2023</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Luostarinen</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Nissen fundoplication for reflux esophagitis long-term clinical and endoscopie results in 109 of 127 consecutive patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Surg</italic></source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>217</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>329</fpage>–<lpage>337</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000658-199304000-00004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8466307</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Escourrou</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grote</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Penzel</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The diagnostic method has a strong influence on classification of obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>730</fpage>–<lpage>738</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26511017</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hirotsu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haba-Rubio</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Andries</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of three hypopnea scoring criteria on OSA prevalence and associated comorbidities in the general population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>02</issue>):<fpage>183</fpage>–<lpage>194</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.7612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30736872</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schwarz</surname>
<given-names>EI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stradling</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kohler</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Physiological consequences of CPAP therapy withdrawal in patients with obstructive sleep apnoea—an opportunity for an efficient experimental model</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Thorac Dis</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>S24</fpage>–<lpage>S32</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29445525</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kohler</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stoewhas</surname>
<given-names>A-C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ayers</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of continuous positive airway pressure therapy withdrawal in patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>184</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1192</fpage>–<lpage>1199</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201106-0964OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21836134</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ulander</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hedner</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stillberg</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Correlates of excessive daytime sleepiness in obstructive sleep apnea: results from the nationwide SESAR cohort including 34,684 patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>e13690</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35869576</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kochkodan</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Telem</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghaferi</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Physiologic and psychological gender differences in bariatric surgery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Surg Endosc</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1382</fpage>–<lpage>1388</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00464-017-5819-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28840338</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Palmer</surname>
<given-names>BF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clegg</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The sexual dimorphism of obesity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Cell Endocrinol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>402</volume>:<fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>119</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mce.2014.11.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25578600</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cho</surname>
<given-names>Y-H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Choi</surname>
<given-names>JI</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Weight loss maintenance after bariatric surgery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">World J Clin Cases</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<fpage>4241</fpage>–<lpage>4250</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12998/wjcc.v11.i18.4241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37449236</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Maciejewski</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arterburn</surname>
<given-names>DE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Scoyoc</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Bariatric surgery and long-term durability of weight loss</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Surgery</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>151</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1046</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamasurg.2016.2317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27579793</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Courcoulas</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>King</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Belle</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Seven-year weight trajectories and health outcomes in the Longitudinal Assessment of Bariatric Surgery (LABS) Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Surg</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>153</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>434</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamasurg.2017.5025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29214306</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Salminen</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grönroos</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Helmiö</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of laparoscopic sleeve gastrectomy vs roux-en-Y gastric bypass on weight loss, comorbidities, and reflux at 10 years in adult patients with obesity: the SLEEVEPASS randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Surg</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>157</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>656</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamasurg.2022.2229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35731535</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tahrani</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morton</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Benefits of weight loss of 10% or more in patients with overweight or obesity: a review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Obesity</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>802</fpage>–<lpage>840</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/oby.23371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35333446</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Launois</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pépin</surname>
<given-names>J-L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lévy</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep apnea in the elderly: a specific entity?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2006.08.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17276106</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mitchell</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davidson</surname>
<given-names>ZE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bonham</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Weight loss from lifestyle interventions and severity of sleep apnoea: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1173</fpage>–<lpage>1183</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2014.05.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25192671</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sheng</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Truong</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spitler</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The long-term effects of bariatric surgery on type 2 diabetes remission, microvascular and macrovascular complications, and mortality: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Obes Surg</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2724</fpage>–<lpage>2732</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11695-017-2866-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28801703</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Van Overstraeten</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Andreozzi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Youssef</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea syndrome phenotyping by cluster analysis: typical sleepy, obese middle-aged men with desaturating events are a minority of patients in a multi-ethnic cohort of 33% women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Med Sci</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>729</fpage>–<lpage>736</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11596-021-2388-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34403098</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>S-J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alnakhli</surname>
<given-names>WM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alfaraj</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Multi-perspective clustering of obstructive sleep apnea towards precision therapeutic decision including craniofacial intervention</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-020-02062-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32219710</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Qanash</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mufti</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alhejaili</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The prevalence of rapid eye movement-related obstructive sleep apnea in a sample of Saudi population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Thorac Med</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/atm.atm_388_22</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37323370</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
