<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38410525</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">10895984</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">445469</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S445469</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Development and Validation of a Nomogram for Predicting Obstructive Sleep Apnea Severity in Children</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Liu et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Liu et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4534-5585</contrib-id><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Yue</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Shi Qi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Xia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Jing Lan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Jian Rong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>School of Nursing, Chongqing Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Chongqing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Jian Rong Zhou; Shi Qi Xie, <institution>School of Nursing, Chongqing Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>1 Medical College Road, Yu Zhong District</addr-line>, <addr-line>Chongqing</addr-line>, <addr-line>400016</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, <phone>Tel +86-135 0830 0955</phone>; <phone>+86-156 0833 2043</phone>, <fax>Fax +86-23-63555767</fax>, Email 202028@cqmu.edu.cn; xie47@cqmu.edu.cn</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>07</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Liu et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Liu et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Purpose</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The clinical presentation of Obstructive Sleep Apnea (OSA) in children is insidious and harmful. Early identification of children with OSA, particularly those at a higher risk for severe symptoms, is essential for making informed clinical decisions and improving long-term outcomes. Therefore, we developed and validated a risk prediction model for severity in Chinese children with OSA to effectively identify children with moderate-to-severe OSA in a clinical setting.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Patients and Methods</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">From June 2023 to September 2023, we retrospectively analyzed the medical records of 367 Children diagnosed with OSA through portable bedside polysomnography (PSG). Predictor variables were screened using the least absolute shrinkage and selection operator (LASSO) and logistic regression techniques to construct nomogram to predict the severity of OSA. Receiver operating characteristic curve (ROC), calibration curve, decision curve analysis (DCA), and clinical impact curve (CIC) were used to determine the discrimination, calibration, and clinical usefulness of the nomogram.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">A total of 367 children with a median age of 84 months were included in this study. Neck circumference, ANB, gender, learning problem, and level of obstruction were identified as independent risk factors for moderate-severe OSA. The consistency indices of the nomogram in the training and validation cohorts were 0.841 and 0.75, respectively. The nomogram demonstrated a strong concordance between the predicted probabilities and the observed probabilities for children diagnosed with moderate-severe OSA. With threshold probabilities ranging from 0.1 to 1.0, the predictive model demonstrated strong predictive efficacy and yielded improved net benefit for clinical decision-making. ROC analysis was employed to classify the children into high and low-risk groups, utilizing the Optimal Cutoff value of 0.39.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">A predictive model using LASSO regression was developed and validated for children with varying levels of OSA. This model identifies children at risk of developing OSA at an early stage.</citation_analysis></p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>obstructive sleep apnea</kwd><kwd>children</kwd><kwd>cephalometric</kwd><kwd>prediction nomogram</kwd><kwd>risk prediction model</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>no funding to report</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>There is no funding to report.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="1"/><ref-count count="73"/><page-count count="14"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">A severe form of sleep-disordered breathing (SDB) known as obstructive Sleep Apnea (OSA) is characterized by repeated instances of either partial or complete blockage of the upper airway. This condition leads to compromised breathing, disrupted sleep patterns, and reduced oxygen levels.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Children diagnosed with OSA may experience various complications, including pulmonary hypertension, hypertension,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> maxillofacial developmental malformations, behavioral abnormalities,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> growth and neurodevelopmental delays,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and reduced quality of life</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> if diagnosis, intervention, and treatment are delayed. Children diagnosed with severe OSA are significantly more susceptible, as indicated by multiple studies</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6–9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Furthermore, the treatment approaches for OSA vary depending on the severity of the condition. Early assessment of the severity of OSA in children is crucial for improving prognosis, facilitating targeted treatment, and preventing the progression of the condition.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Pediatric OSA is a challenging disease because OSA severity is associated with age, adenoid size, tonsil size (Hwang,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> 2013), and obesity.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Although nocturnal polysomnography (PSG) is considered the “gold standard” for diagnosing pediatric OSA, its application is constrained.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12–14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The American Academy of Sleep Medicine (AASM)</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and the American Academy of Pediatrics</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> assert that Portable monitors (PM) are suitable for patients with high clinical suspicion of OSA. PM has been shown to be a successful alternative</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> in both retrospective studies</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and systematic reviews,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> particularly in high-risk groups and neglected areas.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The accuracy of PM and their capacity to differentiate between varying degrees of severity in comparison to a full PSG will need to be further investigated.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Clinical prediction models (CPMs) serve as a valuable tool for assessing the advantages and disadvantages of medical interventions. They provide physicians and families of patients with more logical and user-friendly information.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> A three-variable prediction model for OSA in children aged three to six was developed by Certal using the Pediatric Sleep Questionnaire (PSQ) scores, tonsil size, and oxygen desaturation index (ODI).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Wu created a decision tree model to predict the existence of severe OSA in children based on scale scores and demographic analysis.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Si et al developed an identification algorithm based on morphological and positional attention cues for children with moderate to severe OSA using S- magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) data and magnetic resonance imaging data.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Molnar et al investigated the effect of the tongue on upper airway obstruction and OSA</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> using MRI and ultrasound. Their investigation found that anthropometric measurements and MRI AT values both reliably predicted OSA; the most significant predictive criteria were body mass index, age, neck circumference, tongue midline, and parapharyngeal fat levels.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The above studies demonstrate how most contemporary studies on children’s OSA have extensively depended on statistical analysis of clinical examination or questionnaire data, regardless of the data or research methodology used. Due to the paucity of available data on OSA, it is difficult to accurately determine the severity of the disease and accurately depict the patient’s true clinical state.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Nomogram, which is graphical tool based on statistical models, has been widely used to assess disease prognosis or predict disease diagnosis. It visualizes the results of regression equations and allow for the direct computation of variable values. This enables accurate quantification of a variety of risk factors.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Patients with different levels of OSA severity require individualized treatment plans in clinical settings. In this context, quantitative prediction of OSA severity in children holds significant clinical importance.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The quest for the most precise predictive model for OSA has not produced any definitive findings over the past decade. The intricate nature of the diagnostic process required for identifying the condition presents a significant challenge in accurately predicting it. The anthropometric variables (including body mass index and neck/waist circumference), clinical symptoms (snoring and obstructive mouth breathing),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> upper airway soft tissue structure,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and facial measures,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32–34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> have been widely used as the primary factors in regression studies. To the best of our knowledge, there is a lack of documented nomogram that are based on cephalometric, clinical examination (portable PSG) and clinical symptoms (dysphagia, learning problems, sleep problems, and lack of concentration). Additionally, there is currently no established set of standardized screening techniques for OSA in children with different levels of severity.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In this study, we employed the least absolute shrinkage and selection operator (LASSO) regression as a methodology to identify the variables that can be used for quantitative prediction of the severity of OSA in children. The aim was to provide therapeutic assistance and develop tailored treatment programs for children with different levels of OSA.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Study Subjects</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Children with adenoid hypertrophy and or tonsillar hypertrophy who attended the Department of Children’s Ear, Nose and Throat of Chongqing Medical University between June 2023 and September 2023 were included in this study. The inclusion criteria for the retrospective cases were as follows: (1) aged 4–18 years; (2) each child underwent portable PSG, fiberoptic electronic nasopharyngoscopy and lateral nasopharyngeal film, and was diagnosed as having enlarged tonsils or adenoids with varying degrees of OSA; and (3) provided comprehensive clinical information, such as basic information and questionnaires. The study excluded participants who met the following criteria: (1) children with hereditary disorders, neuromuscular disorders, or craniofacial anomalies; (2) children who had undergone previous tonsil or adenoid surgery; (3) children with other sleep disorders, such as insomnia;</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and (4) children who had experienced upper respiratory tract infections within the two weeks before hospital admission; (5) Suffering from mental illnesses such as autism, ADHD, etc.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Sleep Monitoring Method</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The device utilized in this study is referred to as the “Sleep Breathing Preliminary Screen”, which is a type of PM. Machine model: ZG-S01D, voltage: 5V, product number: S01D2211000009; Batch number: 20221109; Production date: 20221114; The manufacturer is Hangzhou Zhaoguan Sensing Technology Co., LTD. This study included apnea hypopnea index (AHI) and lowest oxygen saturation (LSaO2), the two most specific indicators of OSA in children.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Evaluation criteria:</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> an AHI index of less than one, which denotes normal breathing during sleep. AHI &gt; 10 is consistent with severe OSA; 1&lt; AHI &lt; 5 is consistent with a mild OSA diagnostic; and 5 &lt; AHI &lt; 10 is compatible with a moderate OSA diagnosis. Normal nocturnal ventilation is indicated by LSaO2&gt;90%, while moderate hypoxemia is indicated by LSaO2&lt;85%. Severe hypoxemia is indicated by an LSaO2&lt;80%.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Predictor Variables</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We identified 28 potential predictor variables for our study, selected based on existing literature and clinical expertise. These variables included demographic characteristics (age and gender) and clinical symptoms (snoring, obstructive mouth breathing, dysphagia, symptom duration, learning problems, and lack of concentration). Additionally, the study incorporated physical measurements, such as body mass index (BMI) and neck circumference. Clinical examination results, including upper airway level of obstruction, adenoid/nasopharyngeal (A/N) ratio, tonsil size and cephalometric analysis (including SNA, SNB, ANB, NP-FH, NA-PA, UI-LI, UI-SN, MP-SN, MP-FH, Y-axis angle and LI-MP, See </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=445469.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) were also considered. Lastly, we used questionnaires, including obstructive sleep apnea 18 items survey (OSA-18) scores,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> protocol of orofacial myofunctional evaluation with scores (OMES),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and Children’s Sleep Habits Questionnaire (CSHQ).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Study Design</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This study was carried out in compliance with the revised Declaration of Helsinki of 2015 and underwent review by the Ethical Review Committee of the Children’s Hospital of Chongqing Medical University (No. 66, 2023). All youngsters, even those eight years of age and older, had given their informed consent, as did their parents or legal guardians. PSG was conducted in the study to categorize participants into two groups according to the severity of their OSA: mild OSA (1 ≤ AHI ≤ 5 events /h) and moderate to severe OSA (AHI &gt; 5 events /h). The clinical prediction model was then depicted using a nomogram.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Predictive Models</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">LASSO regression is used to compress the coefficients of some variables that are not important to the result to zero, and a finer model is obtained by constructing a penalty function. To construct and validate the nomogram and ensure the robustness of the prediction model, we divided the data into the training set and verification set using the SAMPLE function of R, with a 7:3 ratio. We randomly assigned 70% (n = 256) of children to the training cohort and 30% (n = 111) to the validation cohort. The former was used for developing models, while the latter was used for evaluating the predictive performance of the models. The model’s performance in predicting OSA was evaluated using various metrics, such as the receiver operating characteristic curve (ROC), calibration curve, decision curve analysis (DCA), and clinical impact curve (CIC).</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The ROC is used to illustrate the overall performance of the model, and the area under the curve (AUC) is a measure of the model’s overall performance.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The calibration curve is constructed by visualizing the results of the Hosmer-Lemeshow goodness-of-fit test to assess the agreement between the actual and predicted incidences.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> The DCA is a method used to evaluate the clinical value of a model by considering the potential range of patient risks and benefits, which estimates the net benefit at various risk thresholds to assess the feasibility of a clinical decision.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> The CIC was utilized to assess the clinical relevance of the risk prediction nomogram.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2006">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We analyzed the data using SPSS (Statistical Package for the Social Science 27.0 for Mac) and RV version 4.1.2. Perform the following operations in SPSS software: the Kolmogorov–Smirnov test was used to test the normality of the data; counting data between the two groups are compared using a chi-square test and shown as relative frequencies. The measurement information of a normal distribution is typically expressed as the mean (X) and standard deviation (SD), and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-test is commonly used to compare two groups. We employed the median and interquartile spacing M (P25, P75) to represent the skewed distribution of the data and the Mann–Whitney </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">U</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">-test for between-group comparisons. We use the glmnet package in the R for Logistic LASSO regression. The analysis screened the independent variables to identify risk factors. We assessed nomogram model performance by examining overall accuracy (Brier score),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> calibration (calibration plots and Hosmer–Lemeshow calibration test), and discrimination (AUC);</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> we also plotted decision curves to assess the net benefit of nomogram -assisted decisions.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Basic Characteristics of the Study Population</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We randomly assigned 367 children to the training set (N = 256) and the validation set (N = 111). </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> presents the demographic and clinicopathologic data of the patients. Among children with OSA, 43.1% were diagnosed with moderate to severe OSA. BMI is classified according to percentage, there were 293 normal weight children (79.8%), 19 low body weight children (5.2%); 35 overweight children (9.5%), and 20 obese children (5.4%). Gender, BMI, cervical dimension, and snoring varied statistically significantly amongst children with varying severities in the training cohort. On the other hand, the validation group showed statistically significant variations in terms of Obstructive-mouth breathing (OMB), snoring, OSA-18 and incorrect swallowing. A further study found that mild OSA was the dominant condition in female children, and BMI, neck circumference, snoring, mouth breathing, and nasal congestion were higher in severe OSA children than in mild OSA children.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Baseline Characteristics of All Patients in the Training Cohort and Validation Cohort</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variables</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Training Cohort (n = 256) M (P25, P75)/ N (%)/ X±SD</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Validation Cohort (n = 111) M (P25, P75) / N (%)/ X±SD</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild OSA (n=150)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate to Severe OSA (n=106)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild OSA (n=59)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate to Severe OSA (n=52)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Genders</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002*<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.454<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (51.52%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 (48.48%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31(50%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31(50%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (71.43%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (28.57%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28(57.14%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21(42.86%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Symptom duration</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.062<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.231<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;6 mouths</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (38.89%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (61.11%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7(43.75%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9(56.25%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6–1year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (65.67%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (34.33%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16(25%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8(33.33%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–2years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (59.21%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (40.79%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18(60%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12(40%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;2years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (61.04%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (38.96%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18(43.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23(56.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age (mouth)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84 (60, 108)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88 (60, 120)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.269<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84(60,108)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72(53,96)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.131<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.74 (14.71, 17.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.47 (15.28, 20.47)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001*<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.75(14.54,17.64)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.82(15.03,20.63)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.418<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Neck circumference (cm)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.5 (25.38, 29)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (27, 33)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.5(25.5,30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28(25.5,30.88)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.371<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Snore(0–10 points)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (3, 6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (3, 8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018*<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5(2,6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6(4.25,7.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001*<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>OMB(0–10 points)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (3.75, 8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (4, 8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5(2,8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6(5,8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025*<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Nasalobstruction(0–10 points)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (2, 7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (2, 6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.088<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4(1,6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5(3,6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.199<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Dysphagia(0–10 points)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0, 2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0, 2.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.459<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0,0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0,3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005*<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>OMES</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (86, 91)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (86, 91)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.583<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89(86,92)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88(86,89.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.383<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>OSA-18</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.47±16.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.63±14.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.49±12.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.85±13.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03*<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CSHQ</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (44.75, 56.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.5 (45, 54)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.376<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51(46,57)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.5(47,56.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.878<sup>b</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: *P&lt;0.05 was statistically significant. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>a</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Chi-square test. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>b</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Mann–Whitney </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">U</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-test. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>c</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-test.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: OSA-18, obstructive sleep apnea 18 items survey scores; OMES, protocol of orofacial myofunctional evaluation with scores; CSHQ, Children’s Sleep Habits Questionnaire; BMI, body mass index; OMB, obstructive mouth breathing.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Predictor Variable Screening Using LASSO Regression</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The study measured the severity of OSA as the dependent variable by portable PSG, categorizing it as mild or moderate to severe. It was crucial to reduce the possibility of the model being overfitting because of the covariance and correlation between the 28 independent variables. Filtering and screening the independent variables allowed for the identification of characteristics related to moderate-severe OSA. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> illustrates the progressive compression of the original independent variable coefficients. Eventually, some of the coefficients were compressed to zero, hence avoiding overfitting of the model. The application of the ten-fold cross-validation technique, as shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, demonstrates that the mean square error is lowest when the penalty value is set to 0.04, which is when the model performs ideally. The research revealed that neck circumference, ANB, gender, learning problem, and level of obstruction were the five most promising independent variables for predicting the severity of OSA.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Texture feature selection using the least absolute shrinkage and selection operator (LASSO) binary logistic regression model. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative">) LASSO coefficient profiles of the 28 texture features. 28 factors to the forecast model: age, BMI, neck circumference, snoring, OMB, nasal obstruction, dysphagia, OSA-18, CSHQ, A/N, OMES, SNA, SNB, ANB, NP-FH, NA-PA, UI-LI, UI-SN, MP-SN, MP-FH, LI-MP, Y-axis angle, gender, symptom duration, learning problems, lack of concentration, level of obstruction, and tonsil size. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) The optimal parameter (lambda) is selected using 10-fold cross-validation with minimum criteria in the LASSO logistic regression. Each red dot represents a lambda (λ) value on the path, and confidence intervals for the error rate are indicated. In drawing the black vertical lines, we used the minimum criteria and the one standard error of the minimum criteria (1-SE) to determine the optimal values. 5 factors to the forecast model: Neck circumference, ANB, gender, learning problem, and level of obstruction.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-193-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Construction and Interpretation of the Prediction Model</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We used R software to integrate the five independent predictors mentioned earlier and built a prediction model for OSA severity, which was visualization with nomogram (refer to </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). According to the nomogram model, the likelihood of moderate to severe OSA increases with each child’s overall score. For example, if a child is male, has a wide neck circumference and ANB, and is associated with learning problems and multiplane obstruction of the upper airway, their risk of moderate to severe OSA increases. For example, if a boy, corresponding to Points is 7.5; with both adenoid and tonsillar hypertrophy, corresponding to a score of 32.5; with a neck circumference of 32 cm, corresponding to a score of 25, and an ANB of 5.5, corresponding to a score of 32.5, and always accompanied by learning problems, corresponding to a score of 100, ie, a total score of 197.5, the risk of having moderate to severe OSA is up to 90%. A cumulative score of more than 156 indicated moderate to severe OSA. Moreover, the likelihood of moderate to severe OSA was shown to be 0.95 when the overall score reached 196.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Nomogram for prediction of OSA.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-193-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: OSA, obstructive sleep apnea; AH, Adenoid hypertrophy; TH, Tonsil hypertrophy; ATH, Adenotonsillar hypertrophy.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Evaluation, Analysis, and Validation of the Prediction Model</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The ability of nomogram prediction model to predict moderate to severe OSA was evaluated and validated using ROC. The five included metrics, as well as the overall metrics (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">B</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). The model was internally validated with 500 Bootstrap self-sampling. In the training cohort, the predictive model had an AUC of 0.841 (95% Confidence interval: 0.794–0.888), which is greater than 0.750. The sensitivity was 0.802, specificity was 0.727, Positive Predictive Value (PPV) was 0.675, and Negative Predictive Value (NPV) was 0.838. The AUC of the predictive model in the validation cohort was 0.750 (95% CI: 0.659–0.842). The sensitivity was 0.731, specificity was 0.695, PPV was 0.679, and NPV was 0.745.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">ROC curves for detecting OSA in children. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) ROC curves for the five high-risk factors and overall in the training cohort. 1 represents the overall efficacy of the Nomogram model (Optimal Cutoff value:0.4; ACU: 0.841; Sens:80.2%; Spec:72.7%; PPV:67.5%; NPV:83.8%), 2 represents the predictive efficacy of the neck circumference (Optimal Cutoff value:28.6; ACU: 0.652), 3 represents the predictive efficacy of the ANB (Optimal Cutoff value:4.45; ACU: 0.547), 4 represents the predictive efficacy of the gender (Optimal Cutoff value:1; ACU: 0.594), 5 represents the predictive efficacy of the learning problem (Optimal Cutoff value:5; ACU: 0.558), and 6 represents the predictive efficacy of the level of obstruction (Optimal Cutoff value:3; ACU: 0.753). (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) ROC curves for the five high-risk factors and overall in the validation cohort. 1 (Optimal Cutoff value:0.38; ACU: 0.75; Sens:73.1%; Spec:69.5%; PPV:67.9%; NPV:74.5%), 2 (Optimal Cutoff value:28; ACU: 0.549), 3 (Optimal Cutoff value:4.3; ACU: 0.504), 4 (Optimal Cutoff value:1; ACU: 0.535), 5 (Optimal Cutoff value:6; ACU: 0.519), 6 (Optimal Cutoff value:3; ACU: 0.741). Optimal Cutoff value: A cut-point will be referred to as optimal when the point classifies most of the individuals correctly.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-193-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: AUC, area under the ROC curve; PPV, Positive Predictive Value; NPV, Negative Predictive Value.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The Calibration curve and the Hosmer–Lemeshow test showed a p-value of 0.875, which is greater than the significance level of 0.05, in the validation cohort. This indicates that the predicted probabilities obtained from the nomogram are highly consistent with the observed outcomes, as shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. The accuracy of probabilistic predictions is measured using the Brier score, with a lower score indicating higher accuracy. In both the training and validation cohorts, the Brier scores were 0.162 and 0.207, respectively. The maximum difference in predicted and calibrated probabilities, known as Emax, and the average difference in predicted and calibrated probabilities, known as Eavg, were determined to be 0.029 and 0.011, respectively, in the training cohort. In the validation cohort, these values were 0.174 and 0.063, respectively. It is important to mention that smaller values indicate superior performance. The prediction model shows a high level of efficacy in making accurate predictions. The results are shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">B</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0004" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Calibration curve for predicting probability of OSA. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) Training cohort. Parameter result: Dxy= 0.682; C (ROC) = 0.841; R2= 0.425; D= 0.375; U= −0.008; Q= 0.383; Brier= 0.162; Intercept= 0.000; Slope= 1.000; Emax= 0.029; E90= 0.022; Eavg= 0.011; S:z= 0.157; S:p= 0.875. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) Validation cohort. Parameter result: Dxy= 0.501; C (ROC) = 0.750; R2= 0.127; D= 0.091; U= 0.051; Q= 0.040; Brier= 0.207; Intercept= 0.181; Slope= 0.596; Emax= 0.174; E90= 0.140; Eavg= 0.063; S:z= 2.016; S:p= 0.044. Thick gray line represents a perfect prediction by an ideal model. The Solid black line represents the performance of the nomogram, of which a closer fit to the diagonal dotted line represents a better prediction.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-193-g0004" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The DCA has two reference lines, one reflecting the net benefit without any treatment and the other the net benefit for all patients receiving treatment. When the net benefit of the curve is higher than the two reference lines, it indicates that it has certain clinical application value. The results showed that for both the training group (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5A</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) and the validation group (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5B</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">), with threshold probabilities ranging from 0.1 to 1.0, a greater net benefit could be obtained when making clinical decisions using this predictive model than “no treatment” or “all treatment”. The overall curve of the model exhibits a notable departure from the two extremes, suggesting a high level of predictive accuracy.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0005" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Decision curve analysis in prediction of OSA. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) Training cohort. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) Validation cohort. The y-axis demonstrates the net benefit. The red line indicates the nomogram. The yellow line indicates neck circumference. The green line represents ANB. The fluorescent green line indicates gender. The green dots represent learning problems. The blue dots represent the level of obstruction. The pink line indicates the assumption of no intervention. The intervention-all-patients assumption is represented by the purple line.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-193-g0005" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The CIC demonstrated the clinical validity of the prediction model, as depicted in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6A</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0006" ref-type="fig">B</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. When the threshold probability exceeded 90%, the prediction model concluded that the population identified as high risk for OSA exhibited a high degree of concordance with the actual OSA population. This indicates that the nomogram demonstrates a high overall net benefit across a wide and practical range of threshold probabilities, impacting patient outcomes. This suggests that the predictive model holds significant predictive value.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0006" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Clinical impact curve (CIC) of OSA model. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) Training cohort. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) Validation cohort. The red curve (number of high-risk individuals) indicates the number of people who are classified as positive (high risk) by the model at each threshold probability; the blue curve (number of high-risk individuals with outcome) is the number of true positives at each threshold probability. CIC visually indicated that nomogram conferred high clinical net benefit and confirmed the clinical value of the OSA model.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-193-g0006" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Pediatric OSA has received increasing scientific attention in recent decades, differing from adults in physiology, clinical presentation, polysomnographic features, and outcomes, with adenoidal tonsillar hypertrophy being the main cause, and its high prevalence coinciding with the onset of OSA symptoms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The high prevalence of OSA,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> suboptimal diagnosis rate,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and potential cardiovascular, neurocognitive, and behavioral diseases</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> have driven a great deal of research work in two main directions, one is the search for effective treatments, and the second is to achieve a simplified, objective and low-cost diagnostic method.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Children diagnosed with OSA commonly have their treatment plan determined by the severity of their condition and the expertise of their healthcare providers.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> A rising proportion of individuals displaying symptoms of OSA are experiencing delays in receiving a timely diagnosis and appropriate treatment. This issue arises due to the limitations of current diagnostic methods for OSA, which in turn pose a significant threat to the physical and mental well-being of affected patients.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> If a CPM for OSA of varying severity can be established using general data, clinical tests, and scales, and if children with positive predictions can receive sleep monitoring to assist in the diagnostic process,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> then diagnostic effectiveness will be improved.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">CPM have the potential to offer physicians and patients quantified risk assessments based on their present health condition, as well as predict their future health status. These models use noninvasive, cost-effective, and easily obtainable metrics.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In recent years, there has been a growing interest in Portable PSG, which can be done at home and often uses fewer sensors than PSG (see AASM Scoring Manual for Technical and Digital Specifications).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Use of Portable PSG may provide potential benefits to patients with suspected OSA. Such benefits could include convenience, comfort, increased access to testing, and decreased cost.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Most existing studies on predicting OSA using machine learning methods have focused on the adult population and have shown promising results in predicting OSA in both adults and children. In recent years, machine learning has been used to identify OSA patients based on 2D</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and 3D</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> photos. This demonstrates a link between maxillofacial geometry and the risk of sleep apnea, creating models to predict the most important facial features of AHI, and showing the importance of the neck and jaw region.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Adult-based OSA diagnostic models can predict OSA by considering only simple and readily available predictors, such as BMI, age, sex, or neck circumference, and achieving a high level of sensitivity or specificity.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The child-centered machine learning model demonstrates good diagnostic performance for moderate to severe OSA, and these children greatly benefit from early diagnosis and access to treatment.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Several non-invasive techniques have been developed to diagnose OSA, which provide a certain level of predictability in identifying the condition or its effects.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, the prediction model of OSA severity established by oximeter has great variation and is not enough to diagnose OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The predictive model based on age, weight, height, gender, BMI, Children’s Sleep Questionnaire (PSQ) score, tonsil size, and Oxygen desaturation index (ODI) had good predictive power (AUC: 0.897).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Several craniofacial skeletal variables (eg, SNB angle, branchial height, lower angular angle, and hyoid position) and upper airway morphology</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> are also associated with the severity of OSA and can be used to help identify children at higher risk for OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> He’s photogrammetry-based prediction model was able to identify individuals with and without OSA and had better predictive performance than the general physical examination model.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, Fernandes found that facial stereophotogrammetry had low screening power.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Cheung also found that visual assessments based on front and side photographs were poor at predicting OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Yuen found significant differences in the maxillary-mandibular relationship angle and the ratio of mandibular height to the entire length of the face in prepubertal children as the severity of OSA increased.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The model established by Masoud through three-dimensional airway analysis shows remarkable predictive value.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> In summary, the use of craniofacial anthropometry and photogrammetry to assess facial features has been proposed as an alternative technique for OSA in both adults and children, and very low to moderate quality levels of data, have not been able to support the existence of an association, or lack thereof, between craniofacial morphology and pediatric OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Most clinical signs and symptoms have limited usefulness in screening and predicting OSA, and no single parameter is enough to achieve this goal. Parameters such as age, gender, BMI, and OSA-18 have all been associated with the severity of OSA. The usefulness of these measures as screening assays, however, is still up for discussion. In recent years, there has been a growing emphasis on using a combination of objective and subjective indicators to better identify patients who are at risk for OSA. In an appropriate patient population, and through a rigorous management pathway, the use of portable PSG to diagnose OSA has been shown to provide adequate clinical outcomes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Given the impact of craniofacial features on upper airway collapse during sleep, it is necessary to create predictive models that incorporate craniofacial features and clinical symptoms to evaluate their effectiveness in predicting the severity of the disease. In this study, a total of 28 factors that could potentially impact the severity of the disease were included in the LOSSA regression analysis. In the end, only five variables were used to build the nomogram, including neck circumference, ANB, gender, learning problems, and level of obstruction. The AUC values of the nomogram were greater than 0.75 for both the training and validation cohorts, indicating that the model had a high degree of differentiation. The calibration plots and Hosmer-Lemeshow tests showed a strong agreement between the predicted probabilities of the nomogram and the observed outcomes. Moreover, to assess the clinical validity of the nomogram, we employed the threshold probability-based clinical outcomes provided by the DCA. This approach enabled us to determine a more accurate net clinical benefit. Additionally, the CIC provided intuitive evidence that high-risk populations in real OSA were closely aligned, within a specific range, with severely high-risk populations in OSA. Contrary to previous research, this study found that neck circumference could predict disease severity, and its substance was associated with high BMI.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The results of this study are in concordance with Howard’s study, which found that the upper airway level of obstruction is correlated with the severity of OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Other studies indicate that tonsil/adenoid size does not predict OSA severity based on AHI; however, adenoid size may be related to LSaO2.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> We point out the importance of learning problems in assessing the severity of OSA in children, and the results of this model can be used to guide the risk of neurocognitive impairment in children with severe OSA and determine its efficacy through early intervention.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Men have a higher risk of severe OSA, which may be related to male physiological structure and function. The ANB parameter, which reflects the relationship between the anteroposterior and anteroposterior relative positions of the maxilla and mandible, can also predict the degree of severity to a certain extent, indicating that we can roughly determine the impact and severity of OSA on the maxillofacial region through facial appearance. Most studies indicated that the ability of the questionnaire to screen OSA was low,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> but higher than that of videotape with OSA characteristics</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. It was discovered in this study that neither the CSHQ nor the OSA-18</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> could predict the severity of OSA. According to certain research, identifying and removing duplicate questions from the questionnaire might enhance its prediction performance and increase its prediction efficiency.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68–71</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Low-quality studies have indicated that clinical symptoms can predict OSA severity,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> and although this study included some clinical symptoms, such as snoring and OMB, no association was found. It is positive that OSA-related behavior and quality of life in children can predict improvement after adenotonsillectomy to some extent, and symptoms obtained during the visit can provide auxiliary advice on important comorbidities and possible surgical responses.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our research stands out for its originality and advantages. Our study utilized the primary and objective clinical data to create the first model capable of predicting OSA severity in children. Among the many risk factors taken into consideration, one of the main conclusions is that learning difficulties in kids with OSA can operate as a risk rating indicator, which highlights how crucial it is to evaluate the illness’s significance from a variety of angles. We have also integrated several problems related to OSA and added cephalometric data as a new predictor in risk rating, and These results set our study apart from earlier clinical rating schemes. Compared with the literature of the same type, this study has better prediction performance</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and more comprehensive verification.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Limitations</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This study is subject to certain limitations. First of all, there was only one hospital used for data gathering in this study, and the sample size and coverage were limited. Furthermore, the raw data set is the only one used for training and validation, with no external validation set obtained. Notably, the demographic sample that was used in this investigation was limited to people who were Chinese in origin. For this reason, further research is needed to evaluate whether the model’s conclusions apply to other ethnic groups. Current research on OSA prediction usually uses data from questionnaires and clinical exams. Nonetheless, the quality of data collecting standards affects how reliable the existing prediction models are. In addition, the portable PSG cannot distinguish between sleep and wake cycles, nor can it report the number of apnea and hypopnea times per hour recorded time (as opposed to sleep time), and its ability to distinguish severity also needs to be compared with a professional polysomnography monitor.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The present study has developed a prediction model comprising five variables, namely Neck circumference, ANB, gender, Learning problem, and level of obstruction. This model demonstrates a strong predictive capacity for moderate-to-severe OSA in children. Consequently, it can serve as a valuable tool for clinicians in distinguishing between different severity levels of OSA in children and aiding in clinical decision-making. This model can help physicians diagnose OSA more quickly and reduce the medical expenses for patients compared to PSG monitoring. Further research and validation of the model are necessary before considering practical clinical applications. The application of machine learning and data mining has the potential to improve disease prediction and revolutionize medical decision-making. A more thorough understanding of the screening and diagnosis of OSA in children will only be possible with well-designed, large-scale, controlled, blinded, multicenter prospective studies. Furthermore, more study is required, especially on portable monitoring in kids of different ages.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">OSA, Obstructive sleep apnea; CPM, Clinical predictive models; DCA, Decision Curve Analysis; ROC, Receiver operating characteristic curve; CIC, Clinical impact curve; AUC, Area Under Curve; LASSO, Least Absolute Selection and Shrinkage Operator; OMES, Protocol of orofacial myofunctional evaluation with scores; OSA-18, Obstructive sleep apnea 18 items survey scores; CSHQ, Children’s Sleep Habits Questionnaire; BMI, Body mass index; OMB, Obstructive mouth breathing; ANB, the angle between 3 point landmarks, A point, N and B point, determining the anteroposterior relation between maxilla and the mandible relative to the cranium; PM, Portable monitors.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0008">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0009">
      <title>Ethics Approval and Informed Consent</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The studies involving human participants were reviewed and approved by the Ethics Committee of Children’s Hospital of Chongqing Medical University (No. 66, 2023). China Clinical Trial Registration Center registration number: ChiCTR2300068094. The study was conducted with the informed consent was obtained from all subjects and/or their legal guardian(s) before the investigation, and the study will not cause any harm to the child or his family. Personal information of the children will be kept strictly confidential unless required by law. All data from this study were published with the consent of the participants.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0010">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation, or in all these areas; took part in drafting, revising or critically reviewing the article; gave final approval of the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0011">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ni</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of obstructive sleep apnea in Chinese children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin J Evid Based Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>883</fpage>–<lpage>900</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Celestin</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lockey</surname>
<given-names>RF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pediatric sleep apnea syndrome: an update</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Allergy Clin Immunol Pract</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>852</fpage>–<lpage>861</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaip.2016.02.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27372597</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fernandez-Mendoza</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Calhoun</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vgontzas</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liao</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bixler</surname>
<given-names>EO</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association of pediatric obstructive sleep apnea with elevated blood pressure and orthostatic hypertension in adolescence</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1144</fpage>–<lpage>1151</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamacardio.2021.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34160576</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lamberg</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep-disordered breathing may spur behavioral, learning problems in children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>297</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>2681</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.297.24.2681</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17595262</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hannon</surname>
<given-names>TS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rofey</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ryan</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clapper</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chakravorty</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arslanian</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Relationships among obstructive sleep apnea, anthropometric measures, and neurocognitive functioning in adolescents with severe obesity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Pediatr</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>160</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>732</fpage>–<lpage>735</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpeds.2011.10.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22137667</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Au</surname>
<given-names>CT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ng</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lam</surname>
<given-names>HS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ho</surname>
<given-names>CKW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wing</surname>
<given-names>YK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A 4-year prospective follow-up study of childhood OSA and its association with BP</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>145</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1255</fpage>–<lpage>1263</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.13-1333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24384690</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hinkle</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Connolly</surname>
<given-names>HV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adams</surname>
<given-names>HR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lande</surname>
<given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Severe obstructive sleep apnea in children with elevated blood pressure</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Soc Hypertens</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>204</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jash.2017.12.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29373256</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hunter</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gozal</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Philby</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaylegian</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kheirandish-Gozal</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effect of sleep-disordered breathing severity on cognitive performance measures in a large community cohort of young school-aged children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>194</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>739</fpage>–<lpage>747</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201510-2099OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26930303</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Varlami</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malakasioti</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alexopoulos</surname>
<given-names>EI</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Low-grade albuminuria in children with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>294</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23228180</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hwang</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guilleminault</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>TW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hong</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Usefulness of adenotonsillar size for prediction of severity of obstructive sleep apnea and flow limitation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>149</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>326</fpage>–<lpage>334</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0194599813490892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23715686</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kang</surname>
<given-names>KT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weng</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hsiao</surname>
<given-names>TY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>PL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hsu</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Clinical risk assessment model for pediatric obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Laryngoscope</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>126</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2403</fpage>–<lpage>2409</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lary.25912</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26973061</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ferreira-Santos</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amorim</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Silva Martins</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monteiro-Soares</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pereira Rodrigues</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Enabling early obstructive sleep apnea diagnosis with machine learning: systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Med Internet Res</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e39452</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/39452</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36178720</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yuen</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Au</surname>
<given-names>CT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chu</surname>
<given-names>WCW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>KCC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Reduced tongue mobility: an unrecognized risk factor of childhood obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>zsab217</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsab217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34432065</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Markkanen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rautiainen</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Niemi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Helminen</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peltomäki</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Is securing normal dentofacial development an indication for tonsil surgery in children? A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>133</volume>:<fpage>110006</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijporl.2020.110006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32220727</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Collop</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tracy</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kapur</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea devices for out-of-center (OOC) testing: technology evaluation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>531</fpage>–<lpage>548</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/JCSM.1328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22003351</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Marcus</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brooks</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ward</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Diagnosis and management of childhood obstructive sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatrics</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>130</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e714</fpage>–<lpage>e755</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2012-1672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22926176</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shah</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gurubhagavatula</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Portable monitoring: practical aspects and case examples</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Clin</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>366</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsmc.2011.05.007</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Garg</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rolle</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Prasad</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Home-based diagnosis of obstructive sleep apnea in an urban population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>879</fpage>–<lpage>885</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.3960</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25126034</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Griffiths</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mukushi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adams</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Telehealth-supported level 2 pediatric home polysomnography</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1815</fpage>–<lpage>1821</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.9982</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35393937</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shayeb</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Topfer</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stafinski</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pawluk</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Menon</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Diagnostic accuracy of level 3 portable sleep tests versus level 1 polysomnography for sleep-disordered breathing: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">CMAJ</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>186</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>E25</fpage>–<lpage>E51</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1503/cmaj.130952</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24218531</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Diagnostic accuracy of level IV portable sleep monitors versus polysomnography for pediatric obstructive sleep apnea: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>87</volume>:<fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>137</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2021.08.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34597954</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gu</surname>
<given-names>HQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>ZR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>ZH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Clinical prediction modeling: basic concepts, application scenarios and research ideas</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin J Evid Based Cardiovasc Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1454</fpage>–<lpage>1456+1462</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Certal</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Silva</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carvalho</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Model for prediction of pediatric OSA: proposal for a clinical decision rule</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Laryngoscope</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>125</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2823</fpage>–<lpage>2827</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lary.25438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26154921</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>YX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>YF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>ZF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Clinical prediction modeling of children with severe obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin J Pract Pediatr</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>701</fpage>–<lpage>707</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.19538/j.ek2022090611</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Si</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Magnetic Resonance Imaging-Based Prediction of Obstructive Sleep Apnea in Children</italic></source>. <source>Master</source>. <publisher-name>Beijing Jiaotong University</publisher-name>; <year>2022</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Molnár</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lakner</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Molnár</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Ultrasound and magnetic resonance imaging of the tongue in obstructive sleep apnoea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Appl Sci</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>9583</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/app12199583</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Molnár</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lakner</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Molnár</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The predictive role of the upper-airway adipose tissue in the pathogenesis of obstructive sleep apnoea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Life</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1543</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/life12101543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36294978</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meghji</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Phillips</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Accuracy of clinical scoring tools for the diagnosis of pediatric obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Laryngoscope</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>130</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1034</fpage>–<lpage>1043</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lary.28146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31233218</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>From past to future: bibliometric analysis of global research productivity on nomogram (2000–2021)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>997713</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2022.997713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36203677</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Santaolalla Montoya</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Iriondo Bedialauneta</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aguirre Larracoechea</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martinez Ibargüen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sanchez Del Rey</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sanchez Fernandez</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The predictive value of clinical and epidemiological parameters in the identification of patients with obstructive sleep apnoea (OSA): a clinical prediction algorithm in the evaluation of OSA</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>264</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>637</fpage>–<lpage>643</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00405-006-0241-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17256124</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Keenan</surname>
<given-names>BT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wiemken</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of weight loss on upper airway anatomy and the apnea–hypopnea index. The importance of tongue fat</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>201</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>718</fpage>–<lpage>727</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201903-0692OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31918559</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>DK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rhee</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yun</surname>
<given-names>PY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Adenotonsillar hypertrophy as a risk factor of dentofacial abnormality in Korean children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>272</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>3311</fpage>–<lpage>3316</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00405-014-3407-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25490975</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yuen</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>KCC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chu</surname>
<given-names>WCW</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Craniofacial phenotyping by photogrammetry in Chinese prepubertal children with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>zsac289</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsac289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36462191</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The predictive value of photogrammetry for obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>202</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.8836</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32996460</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yan</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Development and assessment of a risk prediction model for moderate-to-severe obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>936946</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnins.2022.936946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35992917</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sateia</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>International classification of sleep disorders-third edition</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>146</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1387</fpage>–<lpage>1394</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.14-0970</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25367475</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>FH</given-names></string-name>
<article-title>Correlation study of PSG testing with Epworth scale and OSA-18 scale in adult and pediatric OSAHS patients</article-title>. <source>Master</source>. <publisher-name>Guangxi Medical University</publisher-name>; <year>2018</year>. <comment>Available from:</comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://kns.cnki.net/kcms2/article/abstract?v=3uoqIhG8C475KOm_zrgu4lQARvep2SAkWfZcByc-RON98J6vxPv10UKrmgDz2GxQcO1KhxwUektZ8LFwAykjGztcIPfxG-ya%26uniplatform=NZKPT" ext-link-type="uri">https://kns.cnki.net/kcms2/article/abstract?v=3uoqIhG8C475KOm_zrgu4lQARvep2SAkWfZcByc-RON98J6vxPv10UKrmgDz2GxQcO1KhxwUektZ8LFwAykjGztcIPfxG-ya&amp;uniplatform=NZKPT</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>October</month>
<day>27</day>, 2023</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Franco</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosenfeld</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rao</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Quality of life for children with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>123</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/mhn.2000.105254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10889473</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>de Felício</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferreira</surname>
<given-names>CLP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Protocol of orofacial myofunctional evaluation with scores</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>367</fpage>–<lpage>375</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijporl.2007.11.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18187209</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Owens</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spirito</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McGuinn</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Children’s Sleep Habits Questionnaire (CSHQ): psychometric properties of a survey instrument for school-aged children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1043</fpage>–<lpage>1051</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/23.8.1d</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11145319</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Muschelli</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>ROC and AUC with a binary predictor: a potentially misleading metric</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Classif</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>696</fpage>–<lpage>708</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00357-019-09345-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33250548</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Van Calster</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McLernon</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van Smeden</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wynants</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Steyerberg</surname>
<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Calibration: the Achilles heel of predictive analytics</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>230</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12916-019-1466-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31842878</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Van Calster</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nieboer</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vergouwe</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Cock</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pencina</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Steyerberg</surname>
<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A calibration hierarchy for risk models was defined: from utopia to empirical data</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2015.12.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26772608</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vickers</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holland</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Decision curve analysis to evaluate the clinical benefit of prediction models</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Spine J</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1643</fpage>–<lpage>1648</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.spinee.2021.02.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33676020</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hou</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Predicting 30-days mortality for MIMIC-III patients with sepsis-3: a machine learning approach using XGboost</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Transl Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>462</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12967-020-02620-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33287854</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Brier</surname>
<given-names>GW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Verification of forecasts expressed in terms of probability</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mon Weather Rev</italic></source>. <year>1950</year>;<volume>78</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1175/1520-0493(1950)078&lt;0001:VOFEIT&gt;2.0.CO;2</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Núñez</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Steyerberg</surname>
<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Núñez</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Regression modeling strategies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Rev Esp Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>501</fpage>–<lpage>507</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.recesp.2011.01.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21531065</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Su</surname>
<given-names>YX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>YC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>JZC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tu</surname>
<given-names>YK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Management of paediatric obstructive sleep apnoea: a systematic review and network meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Paediatr Dent</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>156</fpage>–<lpage>170</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ipd.12593</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31680340</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kheirandish-Gozal</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>What is “abnormal” in pediatric sleep?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Respir Care</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1366–1374; discussion 1374</fpage>–<lpage>1376</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20875162</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Behar</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roebuck</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Domingos</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gederi</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clifford</surname>
<given-names>GD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A review of current sleep screening applications for smartphones</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiol Meas</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>R29</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/0967-3334/34/7/R29</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23771214</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kapur</surname>
<given-names>VK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Auckley</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chowdhuri</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Clinical practice guideline for diagnostic testing for adult obstructive sleep apnea: an American Academy of Sleep Medicine Clinical Practice Guideline</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>03</issue>):<fpage>479</fpage>–<lpage>504</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.6506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28162150</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bertoni</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Isaiah</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Towards patient-centered diagnosis of pediatric obstructive sleep apnea-a review of biomedical engineering strategies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Expert Rev Med Devices</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>617</fpage>–<lpage>629</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17434440.2019.1626233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31159603</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tsuiki</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nagaoka</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fukuda</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Machine learning for image-based detection of patients with obstructive sleep apnea: an exploratory study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>2297</fpage>–<lpage>2305</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-021-02301-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33559004</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hanif</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leary</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schneider</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Estimation of apnea-hypopnea index using deep learning on 3-D craniofacial scans</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">IEEE J Biomed Health Inform</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>4185</fpage>–<lpage>4194</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/JBHI.2021.3078127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33961569</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0055">
        <label>55.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gutiérrez-Tobal</surname>
<given-names>GC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Álvarez</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kheirandish-Gozal</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Del Campo</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gozal</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hornero</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Reliability of machine learning to diagnose pediatric obstructive sleep apnea: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatr Pulmonol</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1931</fpage>–<lpage>1943</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ppul.25423</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33856128</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0056">
        <label>56.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Slaats</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Hoorenbeeck</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Eyck</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Upper airway imaging in pediatric obstructive sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2014.08.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25438733</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0057">
        <label>57.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vos</surname>
<given-names>WG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Backer</surname>
<given-names>WA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Verhulst</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Correlation between the severity of sleep apnea and upper airway morphology in pediatric and adult patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Opin Allergy Clin Immunol</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ACI.0b013e328334f659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19996963</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0058">
        <label>58.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fagundes</surname>
<given-names>NCF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gianoni-Capenakas</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heo</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Flores-Mir</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Craniofacial features in children with obstructive sleep apnea: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1865</fpage>–<lpage>1875</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.9904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35074045</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0059">
        <label>59.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cheung</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ishman</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benke</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prediction of obstructive sleep apnea using visual photographic analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Anesth</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclinane.2015.12.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27290943</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0060">
        <label>60.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Masoud</surname>
<given-names>AI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alwadei</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gowharji</surname>
<given-names>LF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>CG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carley</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Relating three-dimensional airway measurements to the apnea-hypopnea index in pediatric sleep apnea patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Orthod Craniofac Res</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ocr.12417</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32757439</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0061">
        <label>61.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kirk</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baughn</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>D’Andrea</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>American Academy of Sleep Medicine position paper for the use of a home sleep apnea test for the diagnosis of OSA in children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1199</fpage>–<lpage>1203</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.6772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28877820</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0062">
        <label>62.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Spilsbury</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Storfer-Isser</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosen</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Redline</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Remission and incidence of obstructive sleep apnea from middle childhood to late adolescence</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.4318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25325456</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0063">
        <label>63.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Howard</surname>
<given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brietzke</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pediatric tonsil size: objective vs subjective measurements correlated to overnight polysomnogram</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>140</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>675</fpage>–<lpage>681</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.otohns.2009.01.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19393410</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0064">
        <label>64.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Brockmann</surname>
<given-names>PE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schlaud</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poets</surname>
<given-names>CF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Urschitz</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Predicting poor school performance in children suspected for sleep-disordered breathing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1077</fpage>–<lpage>1083</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2015.03.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26298782</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0065">
        <label>65.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Spruyt</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gozal</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pediatric sleep questionnaires as diagnostic or epidemiological tools: a review of currently available instruments</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2010.07.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20934896</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0066">
        <label>66.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bseikri</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kirley</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Castillo</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feliciano</surname>
<given-names>EMC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Predicting obstructive sleep apnea severity in children referred for polysomnography: use of the pediatric sleep questionnaire and subscales</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>545</fpage>–<lpage>552</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-022-02647-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35633476</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0067">
        <label>67.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>wai</surname>
<given-names>CK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ng</surname>
<given-names>DK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>li</surname>
<given-names>KK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Application of videotape in the screening of obstructive sleep apnea in children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>442</fpage>–<lpage>445</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2007.06.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17761454</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0068">
        <label>68.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Walter</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Biggs</surname>
<given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cikor</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The efficacy of the OSA-18 as a waiting list triage tool for OSA in children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>837</fpage>–<lpage>844</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-015-1289-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26669876</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0069">
        <label>69.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Isaiah</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shikara</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pereira</surname>
<given-names>KD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Das</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Refining screening questionnaires for prediction of sleep apnea severity in children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1349</fpage>–<lpage>1356</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-019-01964-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31776897</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0070">
        <label>70.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kennedy</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Onwumbiko</surname>
<given-names>BE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blake</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pereira</surname>
<given-names>KD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Isaiah</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prospective validation of a brief questionnaire for predicting the severity of pediatric obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>153</volume>:<fpage>111018</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijporl.2021.111018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34973524</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0071">
        <label>71.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Raman</surname>
<given-names>VT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Splaingard</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tumin</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rice</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jatana</surname>
<given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tobias</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Utility of screening questionnaire, obesity, neck circumference, and sleep polysomnography to predict sleep-disordered breathing in children and adolescents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Paediatr Anaesth</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>655</fpage>–<lpage>664</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pan.12911</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27111886</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0072">
        <label>72.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lewis</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schroeder</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ayub</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bhushan</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Clinical symptoms that predict the presence of obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>95</volume>:<fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijporl.2017.02.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28576523</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0073">
        <label>73.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rosen</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>HG</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Utility of symptoms to predict treatment outcomes in obstructive sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatrics</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>135</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e662</fpage>–<lpage>671</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2014-3099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25667240</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
