<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38533251</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">10964089</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">450578</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S450578</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Data Notes</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Chinese Clinical Sleep Database: An Innovative Database System Includes Large-Scale Clinical Data of Chinese Population</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Fang et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Fang et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Ruichen</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Yihong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Fan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Yan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Yuanhui</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Xiang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0009-0001-1530-2154</contrib-id><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Simin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Yuling</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Jinnong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Dan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1303-2397</contrib-id><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Bin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Psychiatry, Sleep Medicine Center, Nanfang Hospital, Southern Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Key Laboratory of Mental Health of the Ministry of Education</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>School of Biomedical Engineering, Faculty of Medicine, Dalian University of Technology</institution>, <addr-line>Dalian</addr-line>, <addr-line>116024</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Adai Technology (Beijing) Co., Ltd</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Bin Zhang, <institution>Department of Psychiatry, Sleep Medicine Center, Nanfang Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>No. 1838 North, Guangzhou Avenue</addr-line>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>510515</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, Email zhang73bin@hotmail.com</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>313</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Fang et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Fang et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Purpose</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In this study, we established the Chinese Clinical Sleep Database (CCSD), aiming to provide a safe, scalable, and user-friendly database that includes high-quality clinical data from Chinese population to facilitate sleep research.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Material and Methods</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We collect individual’s demographic data, scales, anthropometric measurements, clinical diagnosis, and polysomnography (PSG) recordings from the routine medical process of sleep medicine centers using standardized procedures. The distributed cluster storage technology are utilized to store these data. The structured data are stored in a high-performance MySQL database, while the unstructured data are stored in an object storage service. And we have developed an online data platform to share and manage our data.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The data collection has been conducted in three hospitals. In the preliminary stage of data collection (from October 18, 2022 to September 4, 2023), our database included a total of 1183 patients. Among them, 56.8% were male and their ages ranged from 3 to 88 years. These patients were diagnosed with various types of sleep disorders.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Since the CCSD’s inception, it has demonstrated good stability, security, and scalability. As an public database, the CCSD also exhibits user-friendliness. The CCSD contains comprehensive clinical data, which can contribute to the advancement of the diagnosis and treatment strategies for sleep disorders, ultimately promoting sleep health.</citation_analysis></p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>sleep medicine</kwd><kwd>methodology</kwd><kwd>database</kwd><kwd>data collection</kwd><kwd>collaboration tool</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="4"/><ref-count count="33"/><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Humans spend about one-third of their lives sleeping, and sleep is essential for maintaining good mental and physical health. Unhealthy sleep has been shown to be associated with a variety of health conditions, including obesity,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> cardiovascular disease,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> affective disorders,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and neurological disorders.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> With the development of the economy and society, the incidence of sleep disorders increases. According to the survey data from the Chinese Sleep Research Association in 2021, there were over 300 million people in China who suffered from sleep disorders and related issues.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In light of the growing demand for better sleep health, it is essential to conduct in-depth research on sleep. Analyzing and mining large clinical data samples can help advance diagnosis and treatment strategies for sleep disorders and provide information for making public health policies.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In China, despite the gradual accumulation of clinical data in various sleep medicine centers, it has become evident that there are issues such as uneven data quality, diverse data formats, and inconvenient data management among different sleep medicine centers.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Establishing a standardized procedure for data collection and storage can enhance collaboration among different centers, thereby making progress in sleep research.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In order to provide resources for sleep research, public sleep databases, such as Sleep-EDF, ISRUC-sleep, and Sleep Heart Health Study (SHHS), have been established. Public sleep databases contain a vast amount of biophysiological signals and disease-related data. Researchers can use these data to perform secondary analyses. For example, by analyzing data from 1850 participants in the SHHS, Javaheri et al found that a decrease in N3 stage sleep was correlated to a higher prevalence of hypertension in both male and female individuals.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Azarbarzin et al also utilized data from SHHS and found that the hypoxic burden of sleep apnea could predict cardiovascular-related mortality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, the current public sleep databases mainly contain data from European and American populations. There are differences among different populations in terms of sleep structure, sleep quality, and prevalence of sleep disorders.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In order to understand the characteristics of sleep disorders and sleep-related diseases in Chinese population, it is crucial to establish a public sleep database for Chinese population.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In addition, data from public databases are commonly used for training automatic sleep analysis models. For example, Li et al used single-channel electroencephalogram (EEG) signals from SHHS and Sleep-EDF to train and validate an end-to-end deep learning-based automatic sleep staging model.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Prabha et al extracted features from single-channel abdominal respiratory effort signals sourced from the ISRUC-sleep database and constructed a model to automatically detect and classify sleep apnea events.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Because the detailed information about data collection and participants in the public databases is open to investigators, public databases can serve as benchmarks for comparing differences in algorithm performance.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> However, due to the lack of validation with a large number of clinical populations, existing automatic sleep analysis models are rarely used in clinical practice.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Establishing a database with a large number of clinical samples may help developing models that meet clinical practice requirements and have high reliability.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In this study, in collaboration with Adai Technology (Beijing) Ltd., Co, Beijing, China, we established a public sleep database - The Chinese Clinical Sleep Database (CCSD, psg.wangli-tech.com),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> aiming to continuously collect and store the clinical data from routine clinical care and health monitoring processes through standardized procedures.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Population</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The population of CCSD are the individuals presented to the sleep medicine centers. The inclusion criteria are as follows: (1) The individual undergo PSG monitoring (2) No gender or age-based limitations. Before PSG monitoring, individuals are required to sign an informed consent form. The content of the form includes informed consent for PSG, informed consent for synchronous video recording during PSG, and informed consent for making all clinical data (excluding personal private information such as name and phone number) publicly available for research purposes. If there is an occurrence of signal channel detachment or unforeseen interruption during PSG recording, the individual’s data will not be included in the database. To ensure the privacy of each individual, the names and contact information are encrypted in the database. The study was approved by the Medical Ethics Committee of Nanfang Hospital, Southern Medical University (NFEC-2023-371).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>The Procedure of Data Collection</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In order to continuously obtain clinical data from sleep medicine centers, we have designed a set of workflow procedures. As shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, the clinicians make preliminary diagnoses, and arrange PSG for individuals. The nurses assist patients in completing questionnaires and measure their height, weight, neck circumference, and vital sighs. The sleep technicians conduct PSG recordings and score sleep stages and events adhering to the guidelines set forth by the American Academy of Sleep Medicine (AASM).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The clinicians then review the results of examinations and refine their diagnoses. The diagnosis of sleep disorders are made based on the International Classification of Sleep Disorders, third edition (ICSD-3).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The comorbidities of the patient, such as anxiety, depression, hypertension are also recorded. In the end, the clinicians upload the individual’s diagnosis, questionnaire evaluation results, anthropometric measurements, and PSG report to the database. The biophysiological signal recordings, annotation files, audios, and videos of PSG are uploaded by a sleep technician.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Workflow for continuous clinical data collection in sleep medicine centers.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-305-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviation</bold>: PSG, polysomnography.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Measurements</title>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3001">
          <title>Questionnaires</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">A structured questionnaire is used to collect demographic data, including age, gender, ethnicity, residential address, education, marital status, occupation, employment status, frequency of night shift work, and medical history. The questionnaire also includes scales for evaluating various aspects of the individual’s sleep and emotional well-being: Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI), Morning and Evening Questionnaire-5 (MEQ-5), Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS), and Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21–24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> These scales provide information about the patient’s sleep quality, chronotype, daytime sleepiness, as well as the levels of anxiety and depression.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3002">
          <title>Polysomnography</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">PSG recordings can be divided into diagnostic PSG, positive airway pressure (PAP) titration sleep study, and multiple sleep latency test (MSLT). Diagnostic PSG is used to diagnose or exclude sleep disorders. PAP titration sleep study is designed to determine the optimal pressure of PAP devices required to maintain the upper airway opening for obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) patients.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> MSLT is conducted during the daytime after a diagnostic PSG, employing four or five naps to determine daytime sleepiness. It frequently serves as an authoritative examination for narcolepsy.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> According to different diagnostic and therapeutic purposes, at least one of the abovementioned recordings is performed for an individual.</citation_analysis></p>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The channels and sampling rates of different PSG recordings are shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. Diagnostic PSG consists of 6 channels of EEG, 2 channels of electrooculography (EOG), electromyography (EMG) of the mentalis muscle, electrocardiography (ECG), respiratory flow, nasal pressure, respiratory effort, oxygen saturation, snoring, body position, EMG of tibialis anterior muscle, and a time-synchronized video registration. The signal channels of the PAP titration sleep study are the same as those in diagnostic PSG, except that the respiratory airflow is measured using a PAP device.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The MSLT only includes 3 channels of EEG, 2 channels of EOG, chin EMG, and ECG.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Montage and Sampling Rate of Diagnostic PSG, PAP Titration, and MSLT</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnostic PSG</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PAP Titration</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MSLT</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EEG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 channels: F4-M1, C4-M1, O2-M1, F3-M2, C3-M2 and O1-M2; Sampling rate: ≥ 500 Hz.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Same as the Diagnostic PSG; Sampling rate: ≥ 500 Hz.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 channels: F4-M1 or F3-M2, C4-M1 or C3-M2, O2-M1 or O1-M2;<break/>Sampling rate:≥ 500 Hz.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EOG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 channels: E1-M2 (E1:1 cm below and 1 cm lateral to the left outer canthus), E2-M2 (E2: 1 cm above and 1 cm lateral to the right outer canthus); Sampling rate: ≥ 500 Hz.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Same as the Diagnostic PSG; Sampling rate: ≥500 Hz.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Same as the Diagnostic PSG;<break/>Sampling rate: ≥ 500 Hz.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 Chin EMG channels, bilateral anterior tibial EMG;<break/>Sampling rate: ≥ 500 Hz.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Same as the Diagnostic PSG; Sampling rate: ≥ 500 Hz.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 Chin EMG channels;<break/>Sampling rates:≥ 500 Hz.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ECG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sampling rate:≥ 500 Hz.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sampling rate: ≥ 500 Hz.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sampling rate: ≥ 500 Hz.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory flow</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nasal pressure transducer and oronasal thermal flow sensor;<break/>Sampling rate ≥ 100 Hz.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PAP devices flow;<break/>Sampling rate:≥ 100 Hz.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory effort</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory inductive plethysmography (RIP); Sampling rate ≥ 100 Hz.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Same as Diagnostic PSG; Sampling rate: ≥500 Hz.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxygen saturation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pulse oximetry; Sampling rate ≥ 25 Hz.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Same as Diagnostic PSG.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Snoring</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Condenser mic; Sampling rate ≥ 500 Hz.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Same as the Diagnostic PSG.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body position</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gravity-detecting electric sensor; Sampling rate: ≥ 1 Hz.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Same as the Diagnostic PSG.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infrared video</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Camera and infrared light source.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Same as the Diagnostic PSG.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Same as the Diagnostic PSG.</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: EEG, electroencephalography; EMG, electromyogram; EOG, electrooculogram; ECG, Electrocardiogram; NA, not applicable; PSG, polysomnography; PAP, positive airway pressure; MSLT, multiple sleep latency test.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3003">
          <title>Sleep and Related Events Scoring</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Sleep scoring contains various tasks, including sleep staging, identification of arousal events, respiratory events, limb movements, and other sleep-related events. The manual scoring process encompasses sleep stages and respiratory events. Other sleep-related events are automatically identified by the data acquisition software and later reviewed and corrected by a sleep technician.</citation_analysis></p>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep staging involves dividing an overnight into epochs of 30 seconds each and assigning each epoch to one of the five stages: non-rapid eye movement (NREM) sleep (including N1, N2, and N3), rapid eye movement (REM) sleep, and wake. A 5-minute time window is typically used to identify and classify respiratory events, including sleep apnea and hypopnea. Apnea is defined as a drop in the peak airflow signal of at least 90% of the baseline for at least 10 seconds. Hypopnea is defined as a reduction in the amplitude of the airflow signal by at least 30% of the baseline for a period longer than 10 seconds, accompanied by a decrease in blood oxygen saturation of ≥3% or arousal, or with a decrease in blood oxygen saturation of at least 4%.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3004">
          <title>Parameters of PSG Reports</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The diagnostic PSG report includes parameters for sleep scoring, arousal events, respiratory events, sleep stage-related respiratory events, positional respiratory events, limb movement, and cardiac events, as shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. The PAP titration sleep study report includes the same parameters as the diagnostic PSG report, with additional information about the PAP device used for titration, including brand, model, mode, initial pressure, 90% pressure, and leak rate. The MSLT report includes the sleep onset latency and REM onset latency for each nap, and the average sleep onset latency and REM onset latency for the five naps.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Parameters Included in the Diagnostic PSG Report</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep Stage</bold>
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Lighting on/off time</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Total sleep time, Total recording time, Time in Bed</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep onset latency, REM onset latency</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Time of wake after sleep onset, number of wake stages</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep efficiency</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The duration of N1, N2, N3 and REM sleep</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The percentage of N1, N2, N3 and REM sleep in total sleep time</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Arousal events</bold>
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Number and index of arousals during REM, NREM sleep and overnight sleep</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Number and index of respiratory event-related arousals during REM, NREM sleep and overnight sleep</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Number and index of limb movement arousals during REM, NREM sleep and overnight sleep</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Number and index of spontaneous arousal during REM, NREM sleep and overnight sleep</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Respiratory events</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Average duration, number, and index of obstructive, mixed, and central sleep apnea</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Average duration, number, and index of sleep apnea</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Average duration, number, and index of hypopnea</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Apnea-hypopnea index</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Number and index of respiratory effort-related arousal</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Respiratory disturbance index</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Mean and minimum arterial oxygen saturation of sleep</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Number and index of oxygen desaturation of ≥3%</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Respiratory events during REM and NREM sleep</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Respiratory events parameters during REM sleep</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Respiratory events parameters during NREM sleep</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Respiratory events in various positions</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Respiratory events parameters in the supine position</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Respiratory events parameters in the left decubitus position</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Respiratory events parameters in the Right decubitus position</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Limb movement events</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Number and Index of periodic limb movement during overnight sleep</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Number and Index of periodic limb movement during REM and NREM sleep</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Cardiac events</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Average, lowest, and highest heart rate during sleep</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Number of bradycardia or tachycardia episodes</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Number of narrow or wide complex tachycardia episodes</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Number and longest duration of atrial fibrillation episodes</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: PSG, polysomnography; REM, rapid eye movement; NREM, non-rapid eye movement.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3005">
          <title>Database Storage Architecture</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The database employs a distributed cluster storage technology for its storage architecture (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). Structured data (questionnaires, anthropometric measurements, PSG report, etc.) are stored in the MySQL database. The unstructured data (biophysiological recordings, annotation files, videos, audios, etc.) are stored in an object storage service (OSS). The MySQL database storage has the characteristics of high performance, high availability, and easy expansion, which can construct efficient data structures and realize the storage and query of a large number of information. The OSS is a big data storage technology suitable for storing large files. It features automatically scalable storage space that can expand as the amount of data increases.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Storage architecture of the CCSD. MySQL database are designed for the storage of structured data, whereas object storage service is specifically for unstructured data.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-305-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviation</bold>: PSG, polysomnography.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3006">
          <title>Data Platform</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The data in our database can be accessed through a dedicated data platform. Users need to authenticate when they log on to the platform with two-factor authentication (2FA) in order to ensure the security of the data. Users can upload and download data through the platform. We use multithreading and resumable transfer technologies to improve the speed and stability of data transmission. The data platform offers fuzzy retrieval and keyword retrieval capabilities to help users quickly find the information they need.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Result</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Currently, the CCSD is collecting data from Southern Medical University Nanfang Hospital, Taihe Hospital in Shiyan City, and Guizhou Second People’s Hospital. In the preliminary stage of our data collection (from October 18, 2022 to September 4, 2023), a total of 1183 patients were included, with 56.8% of them being males. The age was 42.50 ± 15.44 years (mean ± SD), ranging from 3 to 88 years.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">There were 1535 PSG recordings in our database, including 1214 diagnostic PSG recordings, 293 PAP titration sleep recordings and 28 MSLT recordings. For the diagnostic recordings, 983 patients had recordings for only one night, and 101 patients had recordings for 2 or 3 nights. For the PAP titration sleep study, 194 patients had undergone diagnostic PSG the night before. All patients involved in the MSLT had completed a diagnostic PSG on the previous night. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> lists the detailed number of these recordings.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">PSG Recordings in the CCSD</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of PSG</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of Recordings</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Details of Patients</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnostic PSG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1214</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">983 patients had recordings for one night; 101 had recordings for 2 or more nights</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PAP titration sleep study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">293</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">194 patients had a diagnostic PSG recording from the previous night</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MSLT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All patients had a diagnostic PSG recording from the previous night</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: PSG, polysomnography; PAP, positive airway pressure; MSLT, multiple sleep latency test; CCSD, Chinese Clinical Sleep Database.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> shows the types of sleep disorders that are currently included in our database. Sleep disorders are classified into seven major categories according to ICSD-3.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Our database includes sleep breath disorders, insomnia, sleep-related movement disorders, central disorder of hypersomnolence, parasomnias, and other types of sleep disorders.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The Types of Sleep Disorders Covered in the CCSD</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnosis</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of Cases</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep breath disorders</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">548</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insomnia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">276</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep-related movement disorders</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Narcolepsy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parasomnias</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other sleep disorders</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">210</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comorbid sleep disorders</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal population</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviation</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: CCSD, Chinese Clinical Sleep Database.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The CCSD is the first sleep database for Chinese population. We continuously collect clinical data from multiple centers using a standardized data collection method. We have successfully included over 1000 clinical samples, and the data in the database are still growing. Our plan for the future is to expand the number of cases to ten thousands in two years.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">With innovative data storage design and efficient data management platform, our database exhibits the following characteristics: 1) Accessibility and usability: The data platform includes user-friendly web interface features for data entry, retrieval, management, sharing, and reporting. 2) Privacy and Security: The database uses state-of-The-art authentication and encryption systems to ensure privacy and security. The database includes a robust disaster recovery system, ensuring that the data is protected against unforeseen circumstances. Regular backups and redundant systems are in place to provide a fail-safe against data loss. 3) Scalability: The use of distributed cluster storage technology can help to store structured and unstructured data, ensuring a high availability and reliability of the data. The database is scalable to accommodate increasing volumes of data as more patients are included.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The CCSD is pooled from sleep medicine centers in grade-A tertiary hospitals, which have a wide range of patient sources. By combining data collection with the routine clinical work of these sleep medicine centers, our database has included various sleep disorders. As the number of patients increases, the data scale of our database will continue to expand. Our database can provide valuable resources for research on rare sleep disorders such as narcolepsy; it can be also used for research on comorbid sleep disorders and sleep disorders combined with other systemic diseases.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">When collecting data for the CCSD, each sleep medicine center followed a standardized procedure and recorded PSG according to the guidance of the AASM. The standardized data collection procedure not only guarantees the integrity and reliability of the data, but also ensures comparability and consistency across different centers.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In addition, adopting a unified data format also helped strengthening the cooperation among various sleep medicine centers and promoting the data sharing and technological exchange. With the advancement of database construction, we hope to establish a nationwide sleep research system to delve into the sleep issues faced by different regions, age groups, and populations with different lifestyles. This will provide stronger support for improving people’s sleep health.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The utilization of distributed cluster storage technology enabled the inclusion of diverse unstructured data in our database, such as videos and audios. Video and audio recordings captured during sleep are necessary for diagnosing some sleep disorders, such as REM sleep behavior disorder (RBD). RBD is a type of parasomnia that is characterized by REM sleep without atonia (RWA), accompanied by dream-related speech and/or complex motor behaviors.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Videos and PSG recordings are the gold standard for diagnosing RBD.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Some sleep-related movement disorders, such as sleep bruxism, also require video and audio assistance for diagnosis.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Our database can provide resources for the research of these diseases.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">PAP titration sleep study and MSLT are also common examinations in sleep medicine centers. However, the two types of PSG recordings are not currently available in the existing public database. Our database include both PAP titration sleep study and MSLT recordings. The PAP titration study can be used to investigate the efficacy of continuous positive airway pressure therapy, and the MSLT recordings can be used to explore biomarkers for excessive daytime sleepiness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">There are still some limitations in our current work. Firstly, due to the impact of the COVID-19 epidemic, the data collection in the early stage has been limited, resulting in a sample size smaller than we expected. Secondly, despite our strict control over the data collection procedure, there are still some individuals with missing data due to technical issues or lack of cooperation from the individuals. Lastly, it is currently not possible to directly conduct statistical analysis on the data platform.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The CCSD contains comprehensive clinical data. Since its inception, this database has demonstrated good stability, security, and scalability. As an public database, the CCSD also exhibits user-friendliness. The database can contribute to the advancement of the diagnosis and treatment strategies for sleep disorders, ultimately promoting sleep health.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In the future, we plan to recruit more institutions to participate in data collection. Additionally, we will conduct follow-ups with individuals in the database. We will also enhance the functionality of the data platform to provide investigators with greater convenience.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This work was supported by the National Key R&amp;D Program of China [grant number 2021YFC2501500],National Natural Science Foundation of China [grant number 82271525], Nanfang Hospital Clinical Research Project of Southern Medical University [grant number 2021CR009], and National Natural Science Foundation of China [grant number 82071488].</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The author would like to express gratitude to the Chinese Sleep Research Society for their support of this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The data of CCSD can be accessed through </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">psg.wangli-tech.com</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. In order to obtain the data, researchers need to contact the Department of Psychiatry (Sleep Medicine Center) of Nanfang Hospital and submit a research protocol with a clear scientific question. After internal review, researchers can be provided with the necessary account and password to access the database.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0007">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Yuanhui Li, Xiang Liu, and Simin Guo are affiliated with Adai Technology (Beijing) Co., Ltd. The authors report no other conflicts of interest in this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chaput</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McHill</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cox</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The role of insufficient sleep and circadian misalignment in obesity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Endocrinol</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>82</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41574-022-00747-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36280789</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mariani</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Redline</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep irregularity and risk of cardiovascular events: the multi-ethnic study of atherosclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>991</fpage>–<lpage>999</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2019.12.054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32138974</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pearson</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Uglik-Marucha</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miskowiak</surname>
<given-names>KW</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The relationship between sleep disturbance and cognitive impairment in mood disorders: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Affect Disord</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>327</volume>:<fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>216</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2023.01.114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36739007</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bishir</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bhat</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Essa</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep deprivation and neurological disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biomed Res Int</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>2020</volume>:<fpage>5764017</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2020/5764017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33381558</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Xin</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suning</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Junxiang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Research status of and recommendations for prevention and control of sleep disorders in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sichuan Univ</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>226</fpage>–<lpage>230</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Benke</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benke</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Artificial intelligence and big data in public health</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2796</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph15122796</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30544648</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pastorino</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Vito</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Migliara</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Benefits and challenges of big data in healthcare: an overview of the European initiatives</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>Supplement_3</issue>):<fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurpub/ckz168</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jiahui</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xiaolin</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xiaoxing</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Past, present and future of sleep medicine in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of Peking University</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>567</fpage>–<lpage>573</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Javaheri</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>YY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Punjabi</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quan</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gottlieb</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Redline</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Slow-wave sleep is associated with incident hypertension: the sleep heart health study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>1</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsx179</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Azarbarzin</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sands</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stone</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The hypoxic burden of sleep apnoea predicts cardiovascular disease-related mortality: the osteoporotic fractures in men study and the sleep heart health study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Heart J</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>1149</fpage>–<lpage>1157</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehy624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30376054</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ancoli-Israel</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and ethnicity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>193</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15402002.2010.509186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20924832</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yan</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mahini</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>End-to-end sleep staging using convolutional neural network in raw single-channel EEG</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biomed Signal Process Control</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>:<fpage>63</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bspc.2020.102203</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Prabha</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yadav</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Singh</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Respiratory effort signal based sleep apnea detection system using improved random forest classifier</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">IETE J Res</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03772063.2021.1999864</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Khalighi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sousa</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Santos</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nunes</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>ISRUC-sleep: a comprehensive public dataset for sleep researchers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Comp Metho Prog Bio</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>124</volume>:<fpage>180</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmpb.2015.10.013</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The application and prospects of artificial intelligence technology in the field of sleep medicine</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Natl Med J China</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>1710</fpage>–<lpage>1716</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nath</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rahimy</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kras</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Korot</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Toward safer ophthalmic artificial intelligence via distributed validation on real-world data</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Opin Ophthalmol</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>459</fpage>–<lpage>463</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ICU.0000000000000986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37459329</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>BS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mun</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lim</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>An accurate deep learning model for wheezing in children using real world data</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>22465</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-25953-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36577766</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Chinese Clinical Sleep Database</collab>. <article-title>Department of psychiatry, sleep medicine center, Nanfang hospital</article-title>. <publisher-loc>China</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Chinese Clinical Sleep Database</publisher-name>; <year>2023</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xlink:href="http://psg.wangli-tech.com" ext-link-type="uri">psg.wangli-tech.com</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>November</month>
<day>19</day>, 2023</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Berry</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abreu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">The AASM Manual for the Scoring of Sleep and Associated Events: Rules, Terminology and Technical Specifications</italic></source>. <edition>2.6.</edition> ed. <publisher-loc>Darien</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</publisher-name>; <year>2023</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">International Classification of Sleep Disorders</italic></source>. <edition>third edition</edition> ed. <publisher-loc>Darien</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</publisher-name>; <year>2014</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>CFR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monk</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berman</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kupfer</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Pittsburgh sleep quality index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0165-1781(89)90047-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2748771</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Weixia</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aizezi</surname>
<given-names>MUYESE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhitao</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Validity and reliability of the Chinese version of morningness/eveningness questionnaire-5 items (MEQ-5) in students of technical schools</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin Mental Health J</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>406</fpage>–<lpage>412</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Johns</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A new method for measuring daytime sleepiness: the Epworth sleepiness scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>540</fpage>–<lpage>545</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/14.6.540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1798888</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhenxiao</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huaxue</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Linying</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Reliability and validity of Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin J Clinicians</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>198</fpage>–<lpage>201</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kushida</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chediak</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berry</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Clinical guidelines for the manual titration of positive airway pressure in patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>171</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18468315</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Krahn</surname>
<given-names>LE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arand</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Avidan</surname>
<given-names>AY</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Recommended protocols for the multiple sleep latency test and maintenance of wakefulness test in adults: guidance from the American Academy of Sleep Medicine</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2489</fpage>–<lpage>2498</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.9620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34423768</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Patil</surname>
<given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ayappa</surname>
<given-names>IA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caples</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kimoff</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harrod</surname>
<given-names>CG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Treatment of adult obstructive sleep apnea with positive airway pressure: an American Academy of Sleep Medicine clinical practice guideline</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>343</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.7640</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30736887</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bhatt</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Data quality - The foundation of real-world studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Perspect Clin Res</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>92</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/picr.picr_12_23</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37325580</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>REM sleep behavior disorder (RBD)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurobiol Dis</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>143</volume>:<fpage>104996</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nbd.2020.104996</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32599063</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Antelmi</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lippolis</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Biscarini</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tinazzi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Plazzi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>REM sleep behavior disorder: mimics and variants</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>101515</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2021.101515</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34186416</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Manfredini</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ahlberg</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Winocur</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lobbezoo</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Management of sleep bruxism in adults: a qualitative systematic literature review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Oral Rehabil</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>862</fpage>–<lpage>874</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/joor.12322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26095208</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Brillante</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cossa</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>PY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laks</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Rapid eye movement and slow-wave sleep rebound after one night of continuous positive airway pressure for obstructive sleep apnoea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Respirology</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>547</fpage>–<lpage>553</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1843.2012.02147.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22309157</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dietmann</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gallino</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wenz</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mathis</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bassetti</surname>
<given-names>CLA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Multiple sleep latency test and polysomnography in patients with central disorders of hypersomnolence</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.12.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33453460</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
