<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38646463</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">11032107</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">449305</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S449305</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Changes in the Objective Measures of Sleep in Association with Menses Among Female Athletes with Poor Subjective Sleep Quality: Female Athletes with Poor Subjective Sleep Quality Have More Sleep Arousals During Menses</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Kawasaki et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Kawasaki et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1205-5477</contrib-id><name><surname>Kawasaki</surname><given-names>Yu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5747-7668</contrib-id><name><surname>Kasai</surname><given-names>Takatoshi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sakurama</surname><given-names>Yuko</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0006" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kawana</surname><given-names>Fusae</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shiroshita</surname><given-names>Nanako</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koikawa</surname><given-names>Natsue</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0006" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0007" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Juntendo University Graduate School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Tokyo</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Cardiovascular Respiratory Sleep Medicine, Juntendo University Graduate School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Tokyo</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Cardiovascular Management and Remote Monitoring, Juntendo University Graduate School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Tokyo</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Cardiovascular Biology and Medicine, Juntendo University Graduate School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Tokyo</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label><institution>Sleep and Sleep-Disordered Breathing Center, Juntendo University Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Tokyo</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="aff0006"><label>6</label><institution>Japanese Center for Research on Women in Sport, Juntendo University</institution>, <addr-line>Tokyo</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="aff0007"><label>7</label><institution>Graduate School of Health and Sports Science, Juntendo University</institution>, <addr-line>Chiba</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Takatoshi Kasai, Department of Cardiovascular Biology and Medicine, Juntendo University Graduate School of Medicine, <addr-line>3-1-3 Hongo, Bunkyo-ku</addr-line>, <addr-line>Tokyo</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country>, <phone content-type="general">Tel +81-33813-3111</phone>, <fax>Fax +81-5689-0627</fax>, Email kasai-t@mx6.nisiq.net</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>388</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Kawasaki et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kawasaki et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Purpose</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Female athletes with menstrual abnormalities have poor sleep quality. However, whether female athletes with poor sleep quality based on subjective assessment have distinctive changes in objective measures of sleep in association with menses remains unclear. This study aimed to compare changes in objective sleep measurements during and following menses between collegiate female athletes with and without poor subjective sleep quality.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Patients and Methods</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Female collegiate athletes (age range/mean ± standard deviation: 18–22/ 22.2±1.1) with regular menstrual cycles were recruited. The participants underwent home electroencephalogram monitoring during the first and second nights after the onset of menses and one night between the seventh and 10th nights after menses onset (mid-follicular phase). The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) was used to assess the subjective sleep quality. Interactions between the presence of poor subjective sleep quality (ie, PSQI ≥6) and changes in objective measures of sleep in association with menses were analyzed.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Data of 45 athletes, including 13 with poor subjective sleep quality, showed that changes in arousal index in athletes with poor subjective sleep quality were distinctive from those in athletes without poor subjective sleep quality (p = 0.036 for interaction). In athletes with poor subjective sleep quality, the arousal index was significantly increased in menses (p for analysis of variance, 0.015), especially on the first night after the onset of menses compared with during the mid-follicular phase (p = 0.016).</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Collegiate female athletes with regular menstrual cycles are likely to have poor subjective sleep quality in association with more frequent arousal during the first night after the onset of menses than during the mid-follicular phase.</citation_analysis></p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>electroencephalogram</kwd><kwd>menstruation</kwd><kwd>Pittsburgh sleep quality index</kwd><kwd>sports</kwd><kwd>women</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Strategic Research Foundation at Private Universities, 2014–2018</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Japanese Center for Research on Women in Sport, Juntendo University</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Project for Fostering, Survey research for the strategic strengthening of female athletes 2017–2018 by the Japan Sports Agency</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>the Juntendo University Young Investigator Joint Project Award 2015 (K1517)</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>a Grant-in-Aid for Scientific Research</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>JSPS KAKENHI</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>The Intractable Respiratory Diseases and Pulmonary Hypertension Research Group from the Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This study was supported by the MEXT*-Supported Program for the Strategic Research Foundation at Private Universities, 2014–2018 (*Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology); Japanese Center for Research on Women in Sport, Juntendo University; Project for Fostering, Survey research for the strategic strengthening of female athletes 2017–2018 by the Japan Sports Agency; the Juntendo University Young Investigator Joint Project Award 2015 (K1517), a Grant-in-Aid for Scientific Research (Grant Number, 26507010); JSPS KAKENHI (Grant Number, JP17K09527; JP18K15904; JP21K08116; JP21K16034; JP21K17604); and a grant to The Intractable Respiratory Diseases and Pulmonary Hypertension Research Group from the Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare (20FC1027). These funding sources do not have any other roles in this study.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="2"/><ref-count count="39"/><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Despite the crucial role of sleep in recovery after training,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> few studies have investigated sleep and sleep issues in athletes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Women are likely to be dissatisfied with their sleep quality,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and this is true in female athletes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The reasons for such poor “self-reported/subjective” sleep quality in women remain unclear but could be multifactorial. One reason may include menstruation and its related issues.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Indeed, in our previous study, menstrual abnormality was associated with poor subjective sleep quality in female athletes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In terms of objectively evaluating sleep, in women, electroencephalogram (EEG)-based sleep parameters during the mid-follicular (MF) phase and those during the mid- or late-luteal phase were generally compared, and no differences were noted in most sleep parameters except for a minor reduction in rapid eye movement (REM) sleep during the mid- or late-luteal phase.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10–12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> However, sleep disturbances were reported during the initial few days after menses onset,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> and comparisons of objective measures of sleep during and following menses should be considered. Thus, we previously assessed changes in objective sleep measures based on EEG monitoring during and after menses in athletes and found that female collegiate athletes were likely to have poor objective sleep quality during menses.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">In general, despite the likelihood of poor subjective sleep quality in women,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5–8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> results are not always bad when sleep quality is assessed objectively.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16–19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Thus, there are some discrepancies between subjective and objective sleep quality, particularly in women. Whether female athletes with poor sleep quality, based on subjective assessments, have distinctive changes in objective measures of sleep in association with menses remains unclear. Therefore, we conducted subgroup analyses of our previous study, in which changes in objective sleep measures based on EEG monitoring during and following menses in collegiate female athletes were assessed by comparing changes in objective sleep measures in association with menses between those with and without poor subjective sleep quality.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Details were described elsewhere.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Briefly, healthy female collegiate athletes (age range/mean: 18–22/ 22.2±1.1) with regular menstrual cycles, defined according to the Japanese Society of Obstetrics and Gynecology (ie, menstrual cycles between 25 and 38 days long with a variation of each cycle within 6 days), were recruited from the Juntendo University School of Health and Sports Science. The exclusion criteria were the use of any drugs, including hormonal contraceptives, premenstrual dysphoric disorder, dysmenorrhea, and other gynecological pathologies that may interfere with sleep patterns, shift work, and transmeridian travel within the past 3 months and during the study period. This study adhered to the Declaration of Helsinki and was approved by the Research Ethics Committee of Juntendo University. Informed consent was obtained from all the participants.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Sleep-Related Baseline Assessments</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Sleep-related baseline assessments using the following tools were conducted once at the time of enrollment of all participants. The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) was used to assess self-reported sleep quality over a 1-month period.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The total score of the seven components ranges from 0 to 21. The Japanese version (PSQI-J)</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> was used, with a cutoff point of 5.5, rounded up to &gt;6, to indicate poor subjective sleep quality in this study. The Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS)</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> is an established tool for evaluating self-reported sleepiness over a few weeks to months.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The ESS has been translated into Japanese (JESS) and validated.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In this study, significant self-reported sleepiness was defined as a JESS score of ≥11.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Restless legs syndrome was assessed based on the international criteria and a positive answer to all five interview questions.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Moreover, the participants were asked the following questions: (1) Have you snored during the past 1 month? “No”, “&lt;1 night per week”, “1–2 nights per week”, or “&gt;2 nights per week”; and (2) Have you displayed apneas during sleep? “No”, “&lt;1 night per week”, “1–2 nights per week”, or “&gt;2 nights per week”.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Sleep Monitoring</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Details were shown elsewhere.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Briefly, all participants underwent overnight home sleep monitoring using a two-channel portable EEG device (ZA-9. Proassist, Ltd., Osaka, Japan), which consists of two pairs of electrodes connected to a transmitter and receiver and provides EEG, electrooculogram, and submental electromyogram. The portable EEG device has only two input channels; however, it can display EEG, electrooculogram (EOG), and electromyogram (EMG). The first channel recorded brain waves from electrodes above the right eye and left mastoid, and the second channel recorded the low-frequency band (EOG) and high-frequency band (EMG) from the left eye and jaw muscle input signals. It is possible to separate and display the data by changing the band filter. After receiving instructions on the portable EEG device, the participants set it up themselves in the four situations described below. All data were manually scored by an experienced sleep technologist based on widely used criteria.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The participants underwent EEG monitoring on the following four occasions: (1) the first night at any time during the menstrual cycle to adapt to the EEG monitoring system; the obtained data were not scored or used (TEST); (2) the first night after menses onset (M1); (3) the second night after menses onset (M2); and (4) one night between the seventh and tenth nights after menses onset (MF). Daily entries of the menstrual data were collected. The MF phase was chosen because, in previous studies, while objectively evaluating sleep in women, EEG-based sleep parameters during the MF and mid-luteal phases were generally compared, and no differences were noted except for a minor reduction in REM sleep during the mid-luteal phase;</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10–12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> moreover, it is generally easier to capture than the mid-luteal phase. Following the TEST, the order of starting from MF to M1/2 (ie, MF first) or from M1/2 to MF (ie, menses first) depended on the participants. All participants were asked to undergo EEG monitoring during the league’s regular season.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Continuous variables are summarized as mean and standard deviation or median (interquartile range), as appropriate. Categorical variables are presented as numbers (percentages). Changes in sleep parameters across occasions were assessed using repeated-measures one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) and Tukey’s test for multiple comparisons. Sleep-onset latency (SOL) and wake after sleep onset were naturally log-transformed because they were not normally distributed. To assess the effect of poor subjective sleep quality on changes in sleep parameters, first-order interactions in two-way repeated-measures ANOVA models were examined by entering interaction terms between the instances of EEG monitoring and PSQI subgroups (ie, time-by-subgroup interaction). Repeated-measures ANOVA was performed for each subgroup if significant time-by-subgroup interactions were found. If the within-subgroup ANOVA was significant, post hoc Bonferroni pairwise comparisons were performed. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. All statistical analyses were performed using SPSS version 23 (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, USA).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Participant Characteristics</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Overall, 52 healthy female collegiate athletes with regular menstrual cycles were enrolled. All participants were instructed by their team to record their menstrual cycles regularly, allowing us to confirm regular menstrual cycles and non-use of oral contraceptives. The data of seven female athletes could not be used because they could not complete all the EEG monitoring occasions for personal reasons. No differences in age, type of competition, or PSQI score were found between the dropouts and completers (data not shown). Thus, data from 45 female athletes were analyzed. Among them, 32 (71.1%) had PSQI &lt;6 (ie, without poor subjective sleep quality), and 13 (28.9%) had PSQI ≥6 (ie, with poor subjective sleep quality). Regarding the PSQI subscale, significant differences were observed in subjective sleep quality, sleep latency, sleep duration, and daytime dysfunction between female athletes with and without poor subjective sleep quality (p=0.001, p&lt;0.001, p=0.004, and p&lt;0.001, respectively). Their characteristics are summarized in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. None of the patients had any symptoms of restless legs syndrome. Two in each group (6.3% in PSQI &lt;6 and 15.4% in PSQI ≥6) reported snoring &lt;1 night per week, one in each group (3.1% in PSQI &lt;6 and 7.7% in PSQI ≥6) reported snoring 1–2 nights per week (p = 0.472) for the previous 1 month, and none reported experiencing apnea during sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Subject Characteristics</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Without Poor Subjective Sleep Quality N=32</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">With Poor Subjective Sleep Quality N=13</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.3 ± 1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.2 ± 1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.800</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height, cm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">162.0 ± 5.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">161.9 ± 6.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.969</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight, kg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.3 ± 4.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.2 ± 7.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.135</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, kg/m<sup>2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1 ± 1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.1 ± 1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Menstrual cycle, days</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.6 ± 4.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.2 ± 3.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.416</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of menses, days</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7 ± 1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6 ± 1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.752</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of sports</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.546</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soccer, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (34.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (30.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Track and field, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (28.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (23.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kendo, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (21.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (15.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basketball, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (15.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (23.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Softball, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (7.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6 ± 1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9 ± 1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESS score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1 ± 3.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7 ± 2.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.585</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">% of athletes with sleepiness, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (46.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (46.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.999</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Note</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: Continuous data are summarized using the mean ± SD.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: BMI, body mass index; PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index; ESS, Epworth Sleepiness Scale.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Interactions Between Poor Subjective Sleep Quality and Changes in Objective Measures of Sleep in M1, M2, and MF</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">No time-by-subgroup interactions were found between changes in the objective measures of sleep other than the arousal index and the presence or absence of poor subjective sleep quality (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). However, a significant interaction was found between changes in the arousal index and the presence or absence of poor subjective sleep quality (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative">), indicating that changes in the arousal index across the menstrual cycle in athletes with poor subjective sleep quality were different from those in athletes without poor subjective sleep quality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Changes in Objective Measures of Sleep Other Than Arousal Index in Participants with and without Poor Subjective Sleep Quality</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI Category</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">M1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">M2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MF</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P for Interaction</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TIB, min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;6 (N = 32)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">395.6 ± 64.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">357.6 ± 76.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">394.0 ± 77.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.812</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥6 (N = 13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">404.6 ± 57.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">382.9 ± 55.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">408.5 ± 66.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TST, min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;6 (N = 32)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">359.4 ± 62.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">328.9 ± 73.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">365.9 ± 74.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.696</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥6 (N = 13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">350.9 ± 62.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">337.3 ± 60.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">376.5 ± 56.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOL, min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;6 (N = 32)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.3 (16.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.0 (11.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8 (12.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.353</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥6 (N = 13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.0 (41.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0 (21.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0 (19.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;6 (N = 32)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.0 ± 6.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.0 ± 5.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.4 ± 5.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.363</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥6 (N = 13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.8 ± 9.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.1 ± 8.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.6 ± 5.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WASO, min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;6 (N = 32)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8 (12.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3 (9.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8 (9.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.157</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥6 (N = 13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5 (11.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0 (11.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0 (7.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">% of REM sleep, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;6 (N = 32)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.4 ± 5.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.8 ± 5.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.8 ± 4.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.568</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥6 (N = 13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.3 ± 8.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.9 ± 6.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.0 ± 4.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">% of N3 sleep, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;6 (N = 32)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.2 ± 8.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.1 ± 8.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.2 ± 6.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.610</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥6 (N = 13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.0 ± 9.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.3 ± 7.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.4 ± 6.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Note</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: Continuous data are summarized using the mean ± SD or median (interquartile range).</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: M1/2, 1</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>st</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and 2</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>nd</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> night after menses onset; MF, mid-follicular phase; N3, deep non-REM sleep; REM, rapid eye movement; SE, sleep efficiency; SOL, sleep onset latency; TST, total sleep time; WASO, wake after sleep onset.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Changes in arousal index across M1/2 and MF. The changes in the arousal index across the menstrual cycle in athletes with poor subjective sleep quality differed from those in athletes without poor subjective sleep quality (p = 0.036). In athletes with poor subjective sleep quality, the arousal index was significantly higher at M1 than at MF (p = 0.015 for ANOVA, p = 0.016 for comparison between M1 and MF, p = 0.111 for comparison between M2 and MF, and p &gt; 0.999 for comparison between M1 and M2). In athletes without poor subjective sleep quality, the arousal index was similar across menstrual cycles (p for ANOVA, 0.131; p = 0.531 for comparison between M1 and MF, p &gt; 0.999 for comparison between M2 and MF, and p = 0.147 for comparison between M1 and M2).</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-381-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Note</bold>: Values represent the mean ± SD.</attrib><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: ANOVA, analysis of variance; M1/2, 1<sup>st</sup> and 2<sup>nd</sup> night after menses onset; MF, mid-follicular phase.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Changes in Arousal Index in M1, M2, and MF Within Athletes with and without Poor Subjective Sleep Quality</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">In athletes without poor subjective sleep quality, the arousal index was similar across the menstrual cycle (p for ANOVA, 0.131). In athletes with poor subjective sleep quality, the arousal index varied significantly across the menstrual cycle (p for ANOVA, 0.015; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) and was significantly increased in M1 compared with MF (p = 0.016), while no difference was observed between M2 and MF (p = 0.111) and between M1 and M2 (p &gt; 0.999) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">These findings provide novel insights into the relationship between menstruation and sleep quality in female athletes. First, 28.9% of the female athletes with regular menstrual cycles had poor subjective sleep quality, as assessed using the PSQI. Second, changes in one objective measure of sleep (arousal index) differed between participants with and without poor subjective sleep quality. Finally, the arousal index increased during menses, particularly at M1, which increased significantly compared to MF in female athletes with poor subjective sleep quality, whereas no such variation was observed in female athletes without poor subjective sleep quality. These findings suggest that a substantial number of female athletes have poor subjective sleep quality even when only female athletes with regular menstrual cycles were enrolled, and that poor subjective sleep quality may be partially explained by the contrast of the arousal index between menses and the MF phase (ie, increase in menses, but decrease in MF). Therefore, greater cortical arousal was observed during menses in female athletes with poor sleep than in those with good sleep quality.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">The percentage of female athletes with poor subjective sleep quality (PSQI ≥6) in previous studies</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> ranged from 48.8% to 50.0%. The 28.9% of female athletes who reported poor subjective sleep quality in this study was less than that in previous studies. This may be because only female athletes without menstrual irregularities were included in this study, confirming the association between subjective sleep quality and menstrual abnormalities, as shown in a previous study.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> It is difficult to compare female athletes with other populations regarding the percentage of athletes with poor subjective sleep quality. The applicability of this method to other populations and variations in the cutoff values for PSQI</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> in various populations remain to be elucidated. However, approximately one in three healthy female athletes who do not have menstrual cycle problems remain dissatisfied with their sleep; thus, sleep interventions in female athletes are an urgent issue.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In the present study, a significant increase in the arousal index was observed during menstruation compared with the follicular phase in female athletes who showed poor subjective sleep quality. The accentuated arousal response during menstruation may be due to discomfort during menstrual sleep. Sleep-disordered breathing, represented by obstructive sleep apnea syndrome, is the leading disorder that causes sleep fragmentation,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> but it is also known to cause sleep fragmentation in discomfort due to restless leg syndrome</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and discomfort due to the external environment, such as the intensive care unit,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> which can also cause sleep fragmentation. Furthermore, an interventional study that used gonadotropin-releasing hormone agonists to mimic menopause in healthy women and evaluated the association between nighttime discomfort and objective sleep measures reported that nighttime discomfort was associated with sleep fragmentation.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Koikawa et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> showed a significant association between sanitary products and the percentage of N3 sleep during menstruation. This finding suggests that discomfort during menstruation may affect sleep quality.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Furthermore, changes in the core body temperature (CBT) due to fluctuations in sex hormones may explain this increased arousal response. Increased CBT owing to fluctuations in sex hormones during the menstrual cycle increases arousal during sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32–34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> An increase in progesterone levels contributes to an increase in CBT, and a decrease in estradiol levels leads to a decrease in CBT; the progesterone/estradiol ratio influences CBT variability.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Therefore, CBT tends to drop during the menstrual and follicular phases of the menstrual cycle and rises during the luteal phase. Particularly, women in the follicular phase performed less during the day than those in the luteal phase when exposed to transient sleep deprivation.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Increased deep body temperature is potentially protective against disturbances in arousal levels.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Consequently, female athletes who perceived poor subjective sleep quality may have had CBT-related sleep vulnerabilities.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In the present study, poor objective sleep quality, as indicated by an increase in the arousal index, was associated with poor subjective sleep quality. Objective and subjective sleep outcomes may reflect the different aspects of sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Some reports have shown that there is usually a discrepancy between the subjective and objective measures of sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Despite this, in female athletes with regular menstrual cycles, poor subjective sleep quality is associated with an increased arousal index during menstruation. Sleep fragmentation is reported to be more strongly perceived as poor subjective sleep quality than as poor objective sleep quality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> It is likely that sleep fragmentation, expressed as an increase in the arousal index during menstruation, causes subjective sleep quality deterioration. In addition, a recent scoping review investigating how various physiological signals recorded during sleep relate to subjectively perceived sleep quality reported that increased sleep fragmentation was associated with poor subjective sleep quality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In sleep interventions for female athletes, particular attention should be paid to the increased arousal index during menstruation. Further studies are warranted to determine how sleep fragmentation during menses can be improved in athletes.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our study had some limitations. First, the lack of overnight polysomnography is a major limitation. Although nobody in each group reported experiencing apnea during sleep, only one participant in each group reported snoring for 1–2 nights per week. However, no significant difference in terms of snoring between the two groups was found, which might be due to snoring or other forms of sleep-disordered breathing on objective sleep measures. In addition, the presence or absence of other sleep disorders such as periodic leg movements was not formally confirmed. Second, we lacked data on productive hormone levels and body temperatures. Because all our participants had regular menstrual cycles based on regularly recorded cycles and because we focused on the first and second days after menses onset and the seventh and tenth nights after menses onset, their phases were adequately captured. Third, the participants were not controlled for physical activity, diet, caffeine intake, or daytime naps on the day of measurement. All participants were recruited from the Juntendo University School of Health and Sports Science, and their competition levels and lifestyle rhythms were considered consistent. This study aimed to assess the natural sleep patterns of female collegiate athletes.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">An increased arousal response during menstrual sleep in female athletes was shown to be an important factor causing both objective and subjective sleep quality impairments. Although further research is needed to determine the causes of increased arousal response during menstruation, efforts to reduce nighttime discomfort during menstruation (eg, proper use and selection of sanitary products) may improve objective and subjective sleep quality.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0006">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Fusae Kawana and Takatoshi Kasai are affiliated with a department endowed by Philips Respironics, ResMed, Teijin Home Healthcare, and Fukuda Denshi. Nanako Shiroshita and Takatoshi Kasai are affiliated with a department endowed by Paramount Bed. The authors report no other conflicts of interest in this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Myllymaki</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rusko</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Syvaoja</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Juuti</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kinnunen</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kyrolainen</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of exercise intensity and duration on nocturnal heart rate variability and sleep quality</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Appl Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>112</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>801</fpage>–<lpage>809</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00421-011-2034-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21667290</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Samuels</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep, recovery, and performance: the new frontier in high-performance athletics</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurol Clin</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>169–80; ix</fpage>–<lpage>x</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ncl.2007.11.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18295089</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Simpson</surname>
<given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gibbs</surname>
<given-names>EL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matheson</surname>
<given-names>GO</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Optimizing sleep to maximize performance: implications and recommendations for elite athletes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Scand J Med Sci Sports</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>266</fpage>–<lpage>274</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/sms.12703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27367265</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Leeder</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Glaister</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pizzoferro</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dawson</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pedlar</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep duration and quality in elite athletes measured using wristwatch actigraphy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sports Sci</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>541</fpage>–<lpage>545</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02640414.2012.660188</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22329779</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Akerstedt</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knutsson</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Westerholm</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Theorell</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alfredsson</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kecklund</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disturbances, work stress and work hours: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychosom Res</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>741</fpage>–<lpage>748</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12217447</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lindberg</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Janson</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gislason</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bjornsson</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hetta</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boman</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disturbances in a young adult population: can gender differences be explained by differences in psychological status?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>387</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9302720</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Koikawa</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shimada</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suda</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Murata</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kasai</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sex differences in subjective sleep quality, sleepiness, and health-related quality of life among collegiate soccer players</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Biol Rhythms</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>386</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s41105-016-0068-4</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kawasaki</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kasai</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koikawa</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sex differences in factors associated with poor subjective sleep quality in athletes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sports Med Phys Fitness</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>140</fpage>–<lpage>151</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.23736/s0022-4707.19.09875-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31640313</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baker</surname>
<given-names>FC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Menstrual cycle effects on sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Clin</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>283</fpage>–<lpage>294</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsmc.2018.04.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30098748</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baker</surname>
<given-names>FC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sassoon</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kahan</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Perceived poor sleep quality in the absence of polysomnographic sleep disturbance in women with severe premenstrual syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>535</fpage>–<lpage>545</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.2012.01007.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22417163</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shechter</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boivin</surname>
<given-names>DB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep, hormones, and circadian rhythms throughout the menstrual cycle in healthy women and women with premenstrual dysphoric disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Endocrinol</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>2010</volume>:<fpage>259345</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2010/259345</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20145718</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Driver</surname>
<given-names>HS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Werth</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dijk</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Borbély</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The menstrual cycle effects on sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Clin</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsmc.2007.10.003</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baker</surname>
<given-names>FC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Driver</surname>
<given-names>HS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Self-reported sleep across the menstrual cycle in young, healthy women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychosom Res</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>243</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-3999(03)00067-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15016584</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kravitz</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Janssen</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Santoro</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Relationship of day-to-day reproductive hormone levels to sleep in midlife women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>165</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>2370</fpage>–<lpage>2376</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.165.20.2370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16287766</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Koikawa</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Takami</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kawasaki</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Changes in the objective measures of sleep between the initial nights of menses and the nights during the midfollicular phase of the menstrual cycle in collegiate female athletes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1745</fpage>–<lpage>1751</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.8692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32666918</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Krishnan</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Collop</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Gender differences in sleep disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Opin Pulm Med</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>383</fpage>–<lpage>389</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.mcp.0000245705.69440.6a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17053485</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>van den Berg</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miedema</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tulen</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hofman</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Neven</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tiemeier</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sex differences in subjective and actigraphic sleep measures: a population-based study of elderly persons</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1367</fpage>–<lpage>1375</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/32.10.1367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19848365</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ehlers</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kupfer</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Slow-wave sleep: do young adult men and women age differently?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>215</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2869.1997.00041.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9358400</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Walsleben</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kapur</surname>
<given-names>VK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Newman</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep and reported daytime sleepiness in normal subjects: the sleep heart health study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>293</fpage>–<lpage>298</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/27.2.293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15124725</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>CF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monk</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berman</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kupfer</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Pittsburgh sleep quality index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2748771</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Doi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Minowa</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Uchiyama</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Psychometric assessment of subjective sleep quality using the Japanese version of the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI-J) in psychiatric disordered and control subjects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>97</volume>(<issue>2–3</issue>):<fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>172</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11166088</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Johns</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A new method for measuring daytime sleepiness: the Epworth sleepiness scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>540</fpage>–<lpage>545</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1798888</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Takegami</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suzukamo</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wakita</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Development of a Japanese version of the Epworth Sleepiness Scale (JESS) based on item response theory</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>556</fpage>–<lpage>565</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2008.04.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18824408</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fukuhara</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Takegami</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suzukamo</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>[The Japanese version of the Epworth Sleepiness Scale (JESS): major differences and revisions from previously used ‘Japanese’ versions] Nihonngoban the Epworth Sleepiness Scale (JESS): koremade shiyousareteita ookuno nihonngoban tono omona sai to kaitei (in Japanese)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nihon Kokyuki Gakkai Zasshi</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>896</fpage>–<lpage>898</lpage>. <comment>Japanese</comment>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Picchietti</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garcia-Borreguero</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Restless legs syndrome/Willis-Ekbom disease diagnostic criteria: updated International Restless Legs Syndrome Study Group (IRLSSG) consensus criteria--history, rationale, description, and significance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>860</fpage>–<lpage>873</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2014.03.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25023924</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Berry</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brooks</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gamaldo</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>AASM scoring manual updates for 2017 (Version 2.4)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>665</fpage>–<lpage>666</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.6576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28416048</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fabbri</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beracci</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martoni</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meneo</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tonetti</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Natale</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Measuring subjective sleep quality: a review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>3</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph18031082</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Punjabi</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The epidemiology of adult obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Am Thorac Soc</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>136</fpage>–<lpage>143</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1513/pats.200709-155MG</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18250205</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Trenkwalder</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paulus</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Restless legs syndrome: pathophysiology, clinical presentation and management</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>346</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrneurol.2010.55</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20531433</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pisani</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>D’Ambrosio</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and delirium in adults who are critically Ill: a contemporary review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>157</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>977</fpage>–<lpage>984</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chest.2019.12.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31874132</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Joffe</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crawford</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Economou</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A gonadotropin-releasing hormone agonist model demonstrates that nocturnal hot flashes interrupt objective sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1977</fpage>–<lpage>1985</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.3244</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24293774</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vidafar</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gooley</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burns</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Increased vulnerability to attentional failure during acute sleep deprivation in women depends on menstrual phase</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>8</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsy098</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wright</surname>
<given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Badia</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of menstrual cycle phase and oral contraceptives on alertness, cognitive performance, and circadian rhythms during sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Brain Res</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>103</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>185</fpage>–<lpage>194</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0166-4328(99)00042-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10513586</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Grant</surname>
<given-names>LK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gooley</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>St Hilaire</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Menstrual phase-dependent differences in neurobehavioral performance: the role of temperature and the progesterone/estradiol ratio</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>2</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsz227</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shuster</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simon</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Good sleep is a mood buffer for young women during menses</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsad072</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kaplan</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hirshman</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hernandez</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>When a gold standard isn’t so golden: lack of prediction of subjective sleep quality from sleep polysomnography</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biol Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>123</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsycho.2016.11.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27889439</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Edinger</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fins</surname>
<given-names>AI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Glenn</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia and the eye of the beholder: are there clinical markers of objective sleep disturbances among adults with and without insomnia complaints?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Consult Clin Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>586</fpage>–<lpage>593</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10965634</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Herbert</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pratt</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Emsley</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kyle</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Predictors of nightly subjective-objective sleep discrepancy in poor sleepers over a seven-day period</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Sci</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/brainsci7030029</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McCarter</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hagen</surname>
<given-names>PT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>St Louis</surname>
<given-names>EK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Physiological markers of sleep quality: a scoping review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>101657</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2022.101657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35753151</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
