<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38706925</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">11069370</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">448579</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S448579</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Compromised Dynamic Cerebral Autoregulation in Patients with Restless Legs Syndrome</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Zhang et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Zhang et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yanan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Qianqian</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Qingqing</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0009-0001-3775-5517</contrib-id><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Mingyang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Yi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Zhen-Ni</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Zan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0002" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Sleep Center, Department of Neurology, The First Hospital of Jilin University</institution>, <addr-line>Chang Chun</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Stroke Center, Department of Neurology, The First Hospital of Jilin University</institution>, <addr-line>Chang Chun</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Zhen-Ni Guo, Stroke Center, Department of Neurology, The First Hospital of Jilin University, <addr-line>Xinmin Street 1#</addr-line>, <addr-line>Chang Chun</addr-line>, <addr-line>130021</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, <phone content-type="general">Tel +86-431-88782378</phone>, Email zhen1ni2@jlu.edu.cn</corresp><corresp id="an0002">Zan Wang, Sleep Center, Department of Neurology, The First Hospital of Jilin University, <addr-line>Xinmin Street 1#</addr-line>, <addr-line>Chang Chun</addr-line>, <addr-line>130021</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, <phone content-type="general">Tel +86-431-88782378</phone>, Email wangzan@jlu.edu.cn</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>443</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>07</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Zhang et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Zhang et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Restless legs syndrome (RLS) is a prevalent sensorimotor nervous system disorder in patients accompanied with insomnia, blood pressure fluctuation, and sympathetic dysfunction. These symptoms may disrupt cerebral hemodynamics. Dynamic cerebral autoregulation (dCA) describes the temporary response of cerebrovascular system to abrupt fluctuations in blood pressure, which keep cerebral blood flow stable and serve as a marker of cerebrovascular system ability.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Objective</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This research aimed to assess dCA in RLS patients.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In this study, RLS patients were recruited and subsequently classified into four groups (mild, moderate, severe, and very severe) based on the International RLS Rating Scale (IRLS). Healthy controls matched for age and sex were enrolled. All participants were evaluated dCA by assessing phase difference (PD). A portion of patients with RLS was reassessed for dCA after one month of medication therapy (pramipexole [0.125 mg/day] and gabapentin [300 mg/day]).</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">There were altogether 120 patients with RLS and 30 controls completed the polysomnography and dCA assessment. PD was lower in the moderate, severe, and very severe RLS groups than that in the controls and mild RLS groups. Periodic limb movement index (PLMI), arousal index, and IRLS all showed a linear correlation with PD in RLS patients. Additionally, PD increased in RLS patients after therapy.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The dCA was compromised in moderate, severe, and very severe RLS patients and was negatively correlated with the IRLS, arousal index, and PLMI. After 1 month of therapy, dCA improved in RLS patients.</citation_analysis></p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>restless legs syndrome</kwd><kwd>dynamic cerebral autoregulation</kwd><kwd>autonomic nerve dysfunction</kwd><kwd>dopaminergic</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="open-funder-registry">10.13039/501100001809</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Scientific and Technological Innovation 2030</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>The article was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (Grant No: 82071489), and the Scientific and Technological Innovation 2030 (Grant No: 2021ZD0204303) to ZW.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="4"/><ref-count count="61"/><page-count count="13"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Restless legs syndrome (RLS) is a sensorimotor nervous system disorder marked by extreme discomfort in both lower limbs, with irresistible movement impulses in the evening or when it is quiet, and continuous movement could partially or completely alleviate this impulse.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> It may cause insomnia, fatigue, blood pressure fluctuation, and sympathetic dysfunction.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> A series of trends appeared suggesting that the risk variables for stroke and RLS interacted.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Several studies have found that people with RLS who had periodic limb movements in sleep (PLMS) have cerebral hemodynamic disturbances.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Byun et al used near-infrared spectroscopy to find that there were no changes in the low-frequency oscillations between oxyhemoglobin concentration and deoxyhemoglobin concentration during the different sleep stages, which shows that RLS patients with PLMS had cerebral hemodynamic disturbances, and sympathetic hyperactivity has been suggested as the underlying mechanism.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> RLS patients are prone to erectile dysfunction, and the risk increases with a higher frequency of RLS symptoms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Shneyder et al found that more autonomic complaints were present in RLS patients, mainly in sialorrhea, heat intolerance, dizziness on standing, early abdominal fullness, and constipation.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Furthermore, patients with RLS have been shown to have decreased nitric oxide (NO) levels, elevated nitrite oxide synthase expression, compromised vascular endothelial function, and increased arterial stiffness,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8–11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> which may disturb cerebral hemodynamics and increase the risk of cerebrovascular disease.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, it is not easy to determine the underlying functional alterations of cerebrovascular disease.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Dynamic cerebral autoregulation (dCA), is the brain’s natural ability to sustain cerebral blood flow under conditions of rapid and significant variations in arterial blood pressure. It is defined as the instantaneous rate of change of cerebral blood flow to cerebral perfusion pressure.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Among the evaluation parameters were phase difference (the primary metric, indicates the phase change angle between 0° and 90°), gain (the variation in arterial blood pressure and cerebral blood flow velocity amplitude), and the coherence function (the signal-to-noise ratio) were among the evaluation parameters.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> A decreased phase difference often reflects a compromised dCA. The mechanism of dCA is complex and still unclear; four theories are widely accepted: endothelial, myogenic, metabolic, and neurogenic mechanisms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The dCA could be vital to sustaining steady cerebral blood flow in patients with RLS because RLS has potential effects on cerebral hemodynamics; however, few studies have assessed dCA in RLS patients.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">One of the primary theories for the etiology of RLS is a dopaminergic deficiency in the central nervous system (CNS).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The most widely used medication is dopamine agonists (DAs), which lessen both PLMS and the main symptoms of RLS.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Pramipexole, a high-affinity D3 receptor agonist, enhances objective sleep parameters and subjective RLS symptoms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Winkelman et al found that pramipexole significantly decreased periodic limb movement index (PLMI) and increased total sleep time and sleep efficiency in RLS patients.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Trenkwalder et al demonstrated a highly significant deterioration of subjective RLS indicators in the group that stopped pramipexole after six months of treatment in a withdrawal experiment.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Pramipexole may diminish autonomic responses and re-establish appropriately responsive sympathovagal homeostasis by acting on the same D3 receptors in the dorsal and intermediolateral gray matter of the spinal cord, which may affect dCA. The voltage-dependent calcium channel’s α2δ-1 subunit is highly-affinity bound by gabapentin, an analog of gamma aminobutyric acid, which additionally inhibits the release of neurotransmitters and postsynaptic excitability.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Gabapentin improved sleep architecture and reduced PLMS score and symptoms across all rating scales as compared to placebo in a double-blind, cross-over trial.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Gabapentin inhibits the release of serotonin, norepinephrine, and dopamine via engaging in a voltage-dependent calcium channel interaction with the α2δ-1 subunit.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> These neurotransmitters may affect the dCA.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Autoregulatory parameters of patients with RLS were obtained using transfer function analysis (TFA) to assess dCA function in this study. We speculate that RLS patients have compromised dCA, and find the relationship between dCA parameters and clinical data, and access the function of pramipexole and gabapentin in dCA of RLS after therapy, providing more evidence for evaluating RLS and accompanying symptoms.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The study recruited participants from the Department of Neurology at the First Hospital of Jilin university between March 2020 and November 2022. The following were the inclusion criteria for each of the groups: Control group: age- and sex-matched individuals without neurological disease and sleep disorders and the IRLS scores were zero; RLS group: according to the International Restless Legs Syndrome Study Group (IRLSSG), the following were the diagnostic criteria for RLS: an irresistible urge to move the legs, typically but not constantly accompanied by unpleasant and uncomfortable feelings in the legs; symptoms that start or get worse during lying down or sitting down; Movement could either totally or partially relieve symptoms; symptoms are either exclusive to the evening or night and worsen there than during the day; and the presence of the aforementioned characteristics cannot be completely explained by the fact that they are signs of a different medical or behavioral condition;</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> excellent bilateral temporal window penetration. The IRLS was used to further categorize the patients into four categories: mild, moderate, severe, and very severe, Mild ranging from 1 to 10, moderate ranging from 11 to 20, severe ranging from 21 to 30, and very severe ranging from 31 to 40. Exclusion criteria were: age more than 65 years; medical or neurological disorders (including diabetes mellitus, liver or kidney disease, Parkinson’s disease, stroke, epilepsy, narcolepsy, other movement disorder and psychiatric disease); hyperthyroidism, arrhythmia, and other hemodynamic factors; dopaminergic, adrenergic, or cholinergic medication for up to 4 weeks before enrollment; and vascular ultrasound (EMS-9 PB, Delica, Shenzhen, China) with the diagnosis of intracranial and extracranial vascular stenosis or occlusion. If symptoms are moderate or above, pharmacological therapy was required. Non-dopaminergic drugs like gabapentin are the first-line treatment, and avoid augmentation. Dopaminergic therapies may develop augmentation syndrome and dose-related adverse effects (such as dizziness, drowsiness, nausea, or headache), so a lowest-effective dose was prescribed for DAs in patients with RLS.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Since DAs and gabapentin utilize distinct pharmacological processes via which they achieve their therapeutic effects, combination treatment can be more effective at controlling symptoms than monotherapy.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Gabapentin is preferential for pain and paresthesia, while dopaminergic therapy is primarily used to improve motor symptoms in patients with RLS.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Considering co-morbidities and symptom intensity of patients with moderate or above symptoms, we chose pramipexole and gabapentin. It is advised to take 0.125 mg of pramipexole once day, 2–3 h before bedtime, the advised conventional dosage for gabapentin is 300mg given 2–3 h before bedtime.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Age, sex, medical history, Cambridge-Hopkins questionnaire for RLS, IRLS, and neurological examination were obtained from all participants. All participants underwent polysomnography (PSG), dCA measurements, and blood tests, including serum iron, ferritin, creatinine, urea nitrogen, alanine aminotransferase, and aspartate aminotransferase levels. The dCA was examined again after one month of therapy with pramipexole (0.125 mg/day) and gabapentin (300 mg/day) in some patients with RLS.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Questionnaires</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The aim of the Cambridge-Hopkins questionnaire for RLS (CH-RLSq) is to evaluate RLS symptoms using patient-administered diagnostic questionnaires, which includes 6 items for diagnostic symptoms and 1 item for differential diagnosis. The CH-RLSq was validated in the general population by Allen et al, with 87.2% sensitivity and 94.4% specificity for ascertainment of RLS.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">As the first-choice method to assess the subjective severity of RLS, IRLS was developed by the IRLSSG through questions posed to its membership, consisting of 10 elements scored from 0 (none) to 4 (very severe), concerning the frequency, severity, and effects of RLS symptoms on mood, sleep, and daily activities.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> IRLS categories have been defined as follows: mild (0–10), moderate (11–20), severe (21–30), and very severe (31–40). The IRLS was validated in 20 centers from six countries by Walters et al, possessing high levels of convergence, reliability for test-retests over an interval of 2–4 weeks, internal coherence, and inter-examiner reliability.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Polysomnography</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All subjects were required to be monitored for at least 8 hours in a typical sleep-laboratory room using PSG recording (Compumedics, Abbotsford, Australia). Caffeinated beverages were not allowed for participants in the afternoon before the recordings. The research adhered to the American Academy of Sleep Medicine (AASM) with regards to electroencephalography, electrooculography, chin muscle electromyography, electrocardiography, nasal pressure, finger oximetry, and respiratory bands on the chest and abdomen. The AASM version 2.3 were applied by professional PSG technologists to assess the PSG findings.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Dynamic Cerebral Autoregulation Assessment and Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">For at least 12 hours before measurement, participants were instructed to refrain from using nicotine, alcohol, and caffeinated drinks, and physical activity. The experiments were carried out at a consistent temperature of 22–24°C in a dedicated laboratory. An expert operator conducted all measurements. Before the baseline arterial blood pressure and heart rate were measured (Omron 711; Omron, Kyoto, Japan, the participants were required to spend 15 minutes lying down in a comfortable supine position). We spontaneously recorded beat-to-beat arterial blood pressure (Finometer Model 1; Finapres Medical Systems, Enschede, Netherlands) and Continuous bilateral middle cerebral artery blood flow velocity (MultiDop X2, DWL, Sipplingen, Germany) for 10 minutes. We further analyze dCA through the obtained data. A facemask connected to a nasal tube and a capnograph were used to measure end-tidal CO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> levels. Every participant was asked to remain awake throughout.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The dCA data were processed using MATLAB software (MathWorks, Natick, MA, USA). TFA was used to analyze dCA. The cross-correlation function was used to eliminate the delay between the Doppler cerebral blood flow velocity and the arterial blood pressure, and align the signal with heart rate beat by beat. The signal was filtered using a third-order Butterworth low-pass filter (with a cutoff frequency of 0.5 Hz) and reduced to 1Hz. TFA was used to analyze and calculate the quotient of the cross-correlation spectrum and autocorrelation spectrum between the cerebral blood flow velocity (CBFV) and arterial blood pressure (ABP), and derive relevant parameters for evaluating dCA function in the low-frequency domain (0.06–0.12 Hz).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The degree of a linear relationship between </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">oscillations</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> in CBFV and ABP was reflected by coherence. When the coherence was &gt; 0.5, statistical analysis was performed.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The SPSS software (version 23.0) was used to analyze data statistics. The normal distribution of continuous variables was evaluated using the Shapiro–Wilk test. The mean and standard deviation were used to represent measurement data with a normal distribution, which included IRLS, mean arterial pressure (MAP), iron, ferritin, PD, heart rate, end-tidal CO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">, total sleep time (TST), sleep efficiency (SE), sleep onset latency (SOL), stage 1 non-REM (stage N1), stage 2 NREM (stage N2), stage 3 NREM (stage N3), rapid eye movement (REM) sleep, arousal index, periodic limb movement index (PLMI) and apnea-hypopnea index (AHI). Male sex, age, body mass index (BMI), IRLS, hypertension, hyperlipidemia, and smoking were examples of categorical variables that were reported as percentages and absolute numbers. The variations between various independent samples (IRLS, PD, iron, ferritin, age, BMI, MAP, heart rate, end-tidal CO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">, TST, SOL, SE, stage N1-N3, REM sleep, arousal index, AHI, PLMI, male sex, hypertension, hyperlipidemia, and smoking) were compared using one-way analysis of variance or the chi-square test. The Spearman-test was used to analyze the correlations between PD and IRLS, arousal index, and PLMI. An independent sample </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">-test was used to assess the differences in age, TST, SOL, SE, stage N1-N3, REM sleep, arousal index, AHI, PLMI, and PD, and the chi-square test was used to assess the differences in IRLS and male between the RLS group with ferritin &lt; 45 µg/L and the RLS group with ferritin ≥ 45 µg/L. Pre- and post- therapy PD in RLS patients were compared using a non-parametric Wilcoxon signed-rank test. Univariate and multivariate linear regressions were used to assess the association between PD and clinical parameters, including male sex, age, BMI, MAP, heart rate, hypertension, hyperlipidemia, smoking, end-tidal CO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">, IRLS, iron, ferritin, TST, SOL, SE, stage N1-N3, REM sleep, arousal index, AHI, and PLMI. The relationship between PD and clinical factors, including male, age, BMI, MAP, heart rate, hypertension, hyperlipidemia, smoking, end-tidal CO2, IRLS, iron, ferritin, TST, SOL, SE, stage N1–N3, REM sleep, arousal index, AHI, and PLMI, was examined using univariate and multivariate linear regressions. The adjusted P-value was calculated using Bonferroni corrected post hoc analysis. The statistical significance level was set at </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.05.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Participant Characteristics</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In total, there were 142 RLS patients and 43 age- and sex-matched normal controls were included, and 120 RLS patients (30 with mild, 30 with moderate, 30 with severe RLS, and 30 with very severe) and 30 controls completed PSG and dCA assessments. All parameters from all groups were compared (see </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). Male sex, age, BMI, hypertension, hyperlipidemia, and smoking were very similar among the five groups and were not statistically different. MAP, heart rate, end-tidal CO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">, and iron and ferritin levels among the groups showed no statistically significant differences.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Clinical Characteristics and Phase Difference in Mild, Moderate, Severe, Very Severe RLS Patients and Controls</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Controls (n = 30)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild RLS (n = 30)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate RLS (n = 30)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe RLS (n = 30)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very Severe RLS (n = 30)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">χ<sup>2</sup>/F</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (40.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (40.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (43.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (33.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (33.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.907</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.124</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.775</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (10.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (3.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (10.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (3.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (10.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 &lt;= Age &lt; 45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (13.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (13.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (13.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (23.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (10.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 &lt;= Age &lt; 55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (50.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (33.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (33.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (33.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (40.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥ 55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (26.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (50.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (43.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (40.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (40.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.449</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.071</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 18.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (6.67)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (6.67)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (3.33)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5 &lt;= BMI &lt; 24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (43.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (43.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (80.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (56.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (56.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥ 24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (50.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (50.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (16.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (43.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (43.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAP (mmHg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.03 ± 14.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.00 ± 9.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.10 ± 9.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.23 ± 7.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.17 ± 8.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.300</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.273</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart rate (beats/min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.5 ± 8.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.6 ± 7.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.7 ± 9.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.7 ± 6.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.6 ± 7.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.640</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.635</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IRLS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.73 ± 2.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.96 ± 2.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.30 ± 2.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.73 ±2.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (16.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (13.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (13.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (16.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (20.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.694</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.952</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hyperlipidemia, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (13.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (13.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (16.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (13.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (10.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.577</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.966</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (10.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (6.67)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (13.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (16.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (10.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.725</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.786</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iron (µmol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.10 ± 4.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.72 ± 4.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.14 ± 4.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.38 ±7.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.97 ± 8.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.544</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.193</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin (µg/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">130.25 ± 52.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128.65 ± 57.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">116.56 ± 77.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109.43 ± 38.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109.52 ± 73.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.801</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.526</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phase difference (degree)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.37 ± 9.39<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.58 ± 10.00<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.34 ± 10.11<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.54 ± 7.20<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.48 ± 7.82<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.353</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">End-tidal CO<sub>2</sub> (mmHg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.65 ± 4.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.84 ± 4.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.00 ± 4.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.81 ± 4.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.64 ± 5.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.364</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.834</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: *</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> value &lt; 0.05 (statistically different in one-way analysis of variance and the chi-square test). Similar superscript letters indicate no significant difference, while different superscript letters indicate significant difference in Bonferroni’s post-hoc test.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: RLS, restless legs syndrome; BMI, body mass index; MAP, mean arterial pressure; IRLS, International restless legs syndrome severity scale.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>PSG Parameters</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Among the PSG parameters, TST, SOL, SE, REM sleep, stage N1, stage N3, arousal index, and PLMI showed significant variations in the RLS groups and controls (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> = 0.004, &lt; 0.001, &lt; 0.001, = 0.005, &lt; 0.001, &lt; 0.001, &lt; 0.001, &lt; 0.001, respectively). Regarding TST, the level was significantly decreased in patients with severe (337.80 ± 70.04) and very severe RLS groups (330.27 ± 90.18) compared to controls (400.40 ± 34.72); sleep onset latency was significantly longer in severe (22.41 ± 9.14) and very severe RLS groups (27.89 ± 10.85) than those in controls (15.53 ± 3.03), mild RLS group (15.53 ± 3.33) and moderate RLS groups (17.11 ± 4.10), with statistically significant difference between severe and very severe RLS groups; sleep efficiency was significantly decreased in patients with moderate (71.06 ± 13.37), severe (63.34 ± 11.44), and very severe RLS groups (58.13 ± 14.19) than those in controls (86.50 ± 8.72), and sleep efficiency was statistically different in very severe RLS groups than those in mild and moderate RLS groups. The arousal index was significantly increased in the mild (16.01 ± 4.86), moderate (22.56 ± 11.65), severe (19.92 ± 8.47), and very severe RLS groups (25.10 ± 7.71) versus controls (6.00 ± 3.58), and the arousal index in mild patients was significantly increased compared to those in moderate and very severe RLS groups. PLMI was significantly increased in mild (16.89 ± 6.40), moderate (18.93 ± 5.86), severe (35.70 ± 2.83) and very severe RLS groups (79.73 ± 25.08) versus controls (0.89 ± 0.77), and PLMI was significantly increased in very severe RLS groups versus mild to severe RLS groups, and PLMI was significantly increased in the severe RLS group compared to the moderate RLS group (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Polysomnography Parameters in Mild, Moderate, Severe, Very Severe RLS Patients and Controls</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Controls (n = 30)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild RLS (n = 30)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate RLS (n = 30)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe RLS (n = 30)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very Severe RLS (n = 30)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total sleep time (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">400.40 ± 34.72<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">377.99 ± 89.39<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">386.96 ± 114.52<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">337.80 ± 70.04<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">330.27 ± 90.18<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.069</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep onset latency (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.53 ± 3.03<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.53 ± 3.33<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.11 ± 4.10<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.41 ± 9.14<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.89 ± 10.85<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.240</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep efficiency (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.50 ± 8.72<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.46 ± 15.66<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.06 ± 13.37<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.34 ± 11.44<sup>bc</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.13 ± 14.19<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.977</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage N1 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.42 ± 1.24<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.06 ± 6.68<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.47 ± 9.04<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.47 ± 8.69 <sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.43 ± 11.77<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.086</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage N2 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.47 ± 6.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.29 ± 10.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.82 ± 7.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.93 ± 10.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.63 ±12.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.490</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.743</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage N3 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.20 ± 5.02<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.92 ± 7.46<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.68 ± 4.82<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.02 ± 3.92 <sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.43 ± 3.12<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.748</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM sleep (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.90 ± 8.59<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.38 ± 7.49<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.82 ± 7.78<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.81 ± 9.77<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.52 ± 10.02<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.861</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arousal index (events/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00 ± 3.58<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.01 ± 4.86<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.56 ± 11.65<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.92 ± 8.47<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.10 ± 7.71<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.559</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI (events/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.12 ± 1.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.31 ± 0.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.56 ± 1.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30 ± 1.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.22 ± 1.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.437</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.781</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLMI (events/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 ± 0.77<sup>d</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.89 ± 6.40<sup>bc</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.93 ± 5.86<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.70 ± 2.83<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.73 ± 25.08<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.534</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001*</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: *</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> value &lt; 0.05 (statistically different in one-way analysis of variance). Similar superscript letters indicate no significant difference, while different superscript letters indicate significant difference in Bonferroni’s post-hoc test.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: RLS, restless legs syndrome; REM, rapid eye movement; Stage N1, stage 1 non-REM; Stage N2, stage 2 non-REM; Stage N3, stage 3 non-REM; AHI, apnea-hypopnea index; PLMI, periodic limb movement index.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>DCA Parameters</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We used the average values in the following analyses because there were no discernible differences in the right and left dCA parameters (PD). The PD was significantly decreased in the moderate (39.34 ± 10.11), severe (39.54 ± 7.20), and very severe RLS groups (37.48 ± 7.82) versus controls (52.37± 9.39, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.001) and mild RLS groups (50.58 ± 10.00, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.001) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The autoregulatory parameter and statistical distributions in each group. Statistical distributions of average phase difference (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) and its transfer function (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) in each group. Similar lowercase letters indicate no significant difference, while different lowercase letters indicate significant difference (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.001) (One-way analysis of variance and Bonferroni’s post-hoc test). The dashed frame represents a specific frequency domain (0.06–0.12Hz).</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-431-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Comparison of IRLS, PD, and PSG Parameters Between RLS Patients with Ferritin &lt; 45 µg/L and Ferritin ≥ 45 µg/L</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">A total of 120 RLS patients were separated into ferritin &lt; 45 µg/L (25 patients) and ≥ 45 µg/L (95 patients) groups in accordance with ferritin levels. The IRLS, PD, and PSG parameters of the two groups are shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. There was a statistically significant difference in IRLS between the two groups (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.003). The group with ferritin &lt; 45 µg/L had a significantly higher arousal index (24.89 ±12.76) than the group with ferritin &gt; 45 µg/L (19.85 ± 7.56, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.013) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The IRLS, Phase Difference and Polysomnography Parameters in RLS Patients with Ferritin &lt;45 µg/L and Ferritin ≥45 µg/L</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin &lt; 45 µg/L (n=25)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin ≥ 45 µg/L (n=95)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">χ<sup>2</sup>/t</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (40.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (36.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.084</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.772</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.8 ± 8.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.9 ± 8.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.095</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IRLS, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.198</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (16.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (44.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11–20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (32.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (17.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21–30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (12.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (22.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31–40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (40.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (15.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total sleep time (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">364.92 ± 122.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">356.50 ± 86.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.395</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.694</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep onset latency (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.14 ± 9.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.37 ± 8.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.885</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.378</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep efficiency (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.70 ±15.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.19 ± 14.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.049</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.296</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage N1 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.50 ± 10.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.49 ±10.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.358</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.721</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage N2 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.70 ±7.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.66 ±10.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.985</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage N3 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.82 ± 5.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.07 ± 6.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">− 0.118</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.851</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM sleep (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.46 ± 6.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.70 ± 9.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">− 0.274</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.784</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arousal index (events/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.89 ±12.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.85 ± 7.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.530</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLMI (events/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.99 ± 24.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.71 ± 29.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.820</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.414</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phase difference (degree)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.07 ± 9.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.91 ± 10.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">− 0.364</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.717</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: *</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> value &lt; 0.05 (statistically different in one-way analysis of variance and the chi-square test).</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0006"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: RLS, restless legs syndrome; IRLS, International restless legs syndrome severity scale; REM, rapid eye movement; Stage N1, stage 1 non-REM; Stage N2, stage 2 non-REM; Stage N3, stage 3 non-REM; PLMI, periodic limb movement index.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2005">
        <title>Correlation Analysis for IRLS with PD, Arousal Index, and PLMI in RLS</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Spearman correlation analysis revealed a significant relationship between the PD value of RLS patients and IRLS (r = - 0.343, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.0001), arousal index (r = - 0.213, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.0193), and PLMI (r = - 0.230, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.0113) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Relations between phase difference and IRSL (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">), arousal index (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">), and PMLI (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>C</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) in patients with RLS (Spearman correlation test).</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-431-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2006">
        <title>Univariable and Multivariable Analysis of dCA-Influencing Factors</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> reports the univariate and multivariate regression analysis of PD. In the univariate model, there was a positive correlation between PD and IRLS stage N3 (β = 0.292, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.001), and a negative correlation between PD and IRLS (β = - 0.359, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.001), sleep onset latency (β = - 0.336, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.001), stage N1 (β = - 0.183, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.046), arousal index (β = - 0.218, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.017), and PLMI (β = - 0.240, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.008). Clinical data including IRLS, TST, SOL, SE, stage N1, stage N3, arousal index, and PLMI with </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.1 in the univariate analysis were analyzed in the multivariate model, and no factors associated with dCA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Univariable and Multivariable Analysis for the Phase Difference</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">Factors</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Phase Difference, Degree</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Univariable Analysis</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Multivariable Analysis</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">β</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">β</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.086</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.349</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">− 0.046</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.576</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.894</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">− 0.119</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.195</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart Rate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.886</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.721</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hyperlipidemia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.103</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.263</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">− 0.096</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.297</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">End-tidal CO<sub>2</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.036</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.390</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IRLS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">− 0.359</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">− 0.193</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.140</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iron (µmol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">− 0.032</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.730</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferritin (µg/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.118</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.198</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Sleep Time (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.160</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.081<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.064</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5443</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep onset latency (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">− 0.336</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">− 0.164</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.129</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Efficiency (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.172</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.896</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage N1 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">− 0.183</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">− 0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.983</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage N2 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.756</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage N3 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.292</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.142</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.164</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM Sleep(%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.769</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arousal Index (events/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">− 0.218</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">− 0.091</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.324</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI (events/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.444</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLMI (events/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">− 0.240</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.854</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0007"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>a</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Nominally significant values (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> &lt; 0.1) included in the multivariable model; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>b</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> value &lt; 0.05 (statistically different).</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0008"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: BMI, body mass index; MAP, mean arterial pressure. IRLS, International restless legs syndrome severity scale; REM, rapid eye movement; Stage N1, stage 1 non-REM; Stage N2, stage 2 non-REM; Stage N3, stage 3 non-REM; AHI, apnea-hypopnea index; PLMI, periodic limb movement index.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2007">
        <title>DCA Parameters of 35 Patients with RLS Before and After Treatment</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Out of 120 patients with RLS, only 35 patients (12 with moderate, 11 with severe, and 12 with very severe RLS) were examined with IRLS and dCA after one month of standardized therapy with pramipexole (0.125 mg/day) and gabapentin (300 mg/day). The IRLS decreased after treatment (24.91 ± 8.27 versus 20.26 ± 8.89, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.001), the PD increased after the treatment [36.41 (33.05–40.45) versus 48.56 (39.99–54.35), </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.001] (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The autoregulatory parameter and statistical distributions in RLS patients before and after treatment. Statistical distributions of phase difference (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) and its transfer function (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) in RLS patients before and after treatment (Wilcoxon signed-rank test).</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-431-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The current study showed that dCA was compromised in patients with moderate, severe, and very severe RLS and was negatively correlated with the IRLS severity scale, arousal index, and PLMI in PSG. After 1 month of medical therapy with pramipexole (0.125 mg/day) and gabapentin (300 mg/day), the dCA improved in patients with RLS.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Studies have reported cerebral hemodynamic changes in patients with RLS. The case of a father and daughter with familial RLS was reported in 1998 by San et al; hyperperfusion in the thalamus and anterior cingulate and hypoperfusion in the caudate nuclei were found using positron emission tomography and single-photon emission computed tomography.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Byun et al reported cerebral hemodynamic disorder in RLS patients and PLMS using near-infrared spectroscopy, which could be an important mechanism that increase the risk of cerebrovascular disease.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Our results appear to be consistent with those of other studies on RLS, supporting an association between cerebral hemodynamics and RLS.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> We recruited patients with RLS in the absence of known risk diseases (previous stroke, previous heart disease, arrhythmia, and sleep-disordered breathing). Our study showed no significant differences between the RLS patients and the control group with regard to demographics and vascular risk factors (including hypertension, hyperlipidemia, and smoking), indicating that dCA was compromised in moderate to very severe patients with RLS, which suggests that RLS may be an influencing factor for preclinical evidence of cerebrovascular disease by affecting dCA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The potential mechanisms of impaired dCA in patients with RLS are unclear; however, there are theoretical explanations that patients with RLS have impaired dCA. First, sympathetic hyperactivity was widely present in patients with RLS. Chenini et al reported that untreated patients with RLS had more autonomic symptoms in evaluated cardiovascular, gastrointestinal, urinary, thermoregulatory, pupillomotor, and sexual dysfunctions using the SCOPA-AUT questionnaire, which were without effect of PLMS, sleep fragmentation and medication.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Izzi et al discovered that patients with RLS tend to have hypertension, the ability to regulate vasodilation or vasoconstriction was reduced and the autonomous nervous system was imbalanced.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In addition, PLMS is observed in up to 80% of RLS patients and is often accompanied by hyperarousal, sleep fragmentation, significant transient increases in heart rate and blood pressure, which suggests sympathetic activation and autonomic arousal exited in patients with RLS.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Sympathetic hyperactivity could modulate cerebral flow through vasodilation or vasoconstriction and has an important impact on dynamic cerebral autoregulation.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Second, the disturbed sleep architecture and sleep continuity in RLS patients have been demonstrated in several studies.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Most patients with RLS reported sleep disturbances, including decreased total sleep time, difficulties in sleep onset and maintenance, reduced sleep efficiency, and frequent arousal in a questionnaire and PSG studies.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> A study by Winkelman et al demonstrated that RLS patients exhibited higher arousal index and longer mean sleep latency in PSG, more continual RLS symptoms, and greater sleep latency than those without RLS.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The comparative observational study of Hornyak et al found that RLS patients experience a reduction in both REM and non-REM sleep, as well as a shorter total sleep time, longer sleep onset latencies, poorer sleep efficiency, a higher arousal index, and sleep stage changes. Furthermore, RLS patients showed substantially increased PLMS and sleep fragmentation indices compared to controls.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Our study discovered that RLS patients experienced disrupted sleep structure, which mainly manifests as increased arousal index, prolonged sleep latency, worse sleep efficiency, and decreased sleep efficiency, which was consistent with the above results. It is widely known that there may be a link between sleep loss and sleep disturbance and a higher risk of type 2 diabetes, obesity, hypertension, and coronary artery disease.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39–42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> An elevated risk of stroke and cardiovascular disease was associated with sleep loss and disturbance.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The elevated activity of the sympathetic system, dysfunction of vascular endothelial cells, and dyslipidemia may be the underlying mechanisms,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> which have a significant association with dCA. Our study found that dCA in RLS patients was correlated with the arousal index and PLMI in PSG, which may also suggest that the mechanics of impaired dCA in RLS patients may be involved in sleep-related arousal. The acute phase of a stroke was accompanied by changes in sleep structure, such as a decrease in total sleep time and sleep efficiency,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> which may prove that the dCA impairment caused by disruption of sleep structure and sleep loss may be a crucial intermediary mechanism of stroke in RLS patients.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Moreover, the impaired dCA in RLS patients was also explained by the vascular variables, including impaired cerebral vascular endothelial dysfunction and increased arterial stiffness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Decreased NO levels, increased oxidative stress, and sympathetic activation are the underlying systemic pathophysiologies of impaired endothelial function in patients with RLS.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Reduced NO production could promote vascular endothelial dysfunction, which can result in reduced local blood flow and hypoxia,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> which may affect dCA. Moreover, oxidative stress is associated with endothelial dysfunction, leading to impaired perfusion and/or vascular tone.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> These findings suggest that the impaired dCA may be caused by these pathological alterations.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Furthermore, we found that the arousal index in RLS patients with ferritin &lt; 45 µg/L was higher than that in RLS patients with ferritin ≥ 45 µg/L, which suggests that nocturnal arousal and sleep fragmentation are more prone to occur in patients with low ferritin levels. Ferritin levels are a reflection of iron supply; iron is a part of the rate-limiting enzyme tyrosine hydroxylase and a cofactor in dopamine synthesis.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> It has been suggested that iron metabolism may influence the dopamine of the CNS and sympathetic nervous system and impact the potential effects of dCA. Although the results of IRLS and PLMI did not show any significant differences, there was an increasing trend in the ferritin &lt; 45 µg/L group, which further supports the theory that iron deficiency correlates with both PLMI and the intensity of RLS symptoms. Cerebral iron deficiency is the critical pathophysiology of RLS rather than peripheral iron status, which may occur despite normal peripheral iron stores.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, we detected serum iron and ferritin levels rather than brain iron levels. Further work is required to examine brain iron levels and to analyze their relationship with dCA in RLS patients.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">One of the main hypotheses for the etiology of RLS is a dopaminergic deficiency in the CNS.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> As a monoamine neurotransmitter, dopamine affects cerebral circulation and vasomotor function by direct and intricate vasoactive actions,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> which can modulate dCA. Several dopaminergic pathways have been found in the cerebrum, including the striatonigral, mesolimbic, mesocortical, tuberoinfundibular, and supraspinal A11 dopamine cell groups.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Patients with RLS may also have an increase in sympathetic impulses due to decreased dopamine levels, while decreased A11 dopaminergic diencephalospinal pathway function results in increased peripheral sympathetic outflow.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Medical therapies for RLS in this study included pramipexole and gabapentin. Pramipexole is a dopamine agonist with selective action upon dopamine D3 receptors, which can reverse RLS symptoms, reduce PLMI, and improve subjective sleep quality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Gabapentin is a derivative of γ-aminobutyric acid that decreases glutamate release. These trials have demonstrated improvements for PLMS, sleep architecture, and RLS symptoms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> After 1 month of therapy, dCA was higher than that before treatment in 35 patients with RLS. We hypothesized that as a high-affinity D3 receptor agonist, pramipexole may diminish autonomic responses and re-establish appropriately responsive sympathovagal homeostasis by acting on the same D3 receptors in the dorsal and intermediolateral gray matter of the spinal cord, which may affect dCA. Gabapentin interacts with the α2δ-1 subunit of voltage-dependent calcium channels, which antagonizes the release of dopamine, norepinephrine, and serotonin.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> These neurotransmitters may affect the dCA. The response of dCA to dopaminergic medications further demonstrated that dysfunction of the neurotransmitter dopamine is one of the pathogenesis of RLS. However, it’s possible that the improvement in sleep structure disturbance is an underestimated factor in the elevated dCA in RLS patients after therapy. But we did not reexamine PSG monitoring for patients, we will focus on this in following days.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">This study had several limitations. First, the duration of RLS plays an important role in cerebrovascular alertness; however, we failed to consider the exact duration of RLS. Second, the inability to successfully penetrate the temporal bone window in elderly patients may limit their inclusion. Third, we lack PSG data after therapy, which limited our analysis of possible factors for impaired dCA. In addition, we choose a ferritin of 45 µg/L rather than the international recommendation of 75 µg/L, and our sample size was relatively small, and there may be some data bias; future studies will be done with a larger sample size.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In conclusion, this study demonstrated that dynamic cerebral autoregulation was compromised in patients with moderate, severe, and very severe RLS, which was negatively correlated with the IRLS severity scale, arousal index, and PLMI in PSG. After 1 month of medication therapy, dCA improved in patients with RLS. Further studies are needed to probe the in-depth mechanisms of RLS, its relationship with dCA, and the mechanism of its therapeutic effect, providing a new approach for clinical diagnosis and treatment.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The deidentified data used and analyzed during this study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Ethics Approval and Consent to Participate</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The First Hospital of Jilin University Ethics Committee has approved the study (Approval No: 2016-294) and followed the guidelines of the Declaration of Helsinki (1964). All the participants gave an informed consent.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0008">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors declare that they have no competing interests in this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gossard</surname>
<given-names>TR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trotti</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Videnovic</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Restless legs syndrome: contemporary diagnosis and treatment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurotherapeutics</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>140</fpage>–<lpage>155</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13311-021-01019-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33880737</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Trenkwalder</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Högl</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Comorbidities, treatment, and pathophysiology in restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>994</fpage>–<lpage>1005</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(18)30311-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30244828</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Katsanos</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kosmidou</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Konitsiotis</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Restless legs syndrome and cerebrovascular/cardiovascular events: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Neurol Scand</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>137</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>142</fpage>–<lpage>148</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ane.12848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28948600</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Byun</surname>
<given-names>JI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jung</surname>
<given-names>KY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>GT</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Spontaneous low-frequency cerebral hemodynamics oscillations in restless legs syndrome with periodic limb movements during sleep: a near-infrared spectroscopy study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>114</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3988/jcn.2016.12.1.107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26754783</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cho</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duffy</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep, sleep disorders, and sexual dysfunction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">World J Mens Health</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>261</fpage>–<lpage>275</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5534/wjmh.180045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30209897</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schwarzschild</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Reilly</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Restless legs syndrome and erectile dysfunction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/33.1.75</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20120623</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shneyder</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adler</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hentz</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Autonomic complaints in patients with restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1413</fpage>–<lpage>1416</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2013.08.781</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24152795</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yoon</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Impaired endothelial function may predict treatment response in restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neural Transm</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>126</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1051</fpage>–<lpage>1059</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00702-019-02031-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31218470</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chenini</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rassu</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guiraud</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Blood pressure profile and endothelial function in restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>15933</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-52401-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31685922</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Patton</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ponnuru</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Snyder</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Hypoxia-inducible factor pathway activation in restless legs syndrome patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1329</fpage>–<lpage>1335</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1468-1331.2011.03397.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21985026</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baskol</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Korkmaz</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Erdem</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Assessment of nitric oxide, advanced oxidation protein products, malondialdehyde, and thiol levels in patients with restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>414</fpage>–<lpage>418</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2011.11.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22469072</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aries</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elting</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Keyser</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cerebral autoregulation in stroke: a review of transcranial Doppler studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Stroke</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2697</fpage>–<lpage>2704</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/STROKEAHA.110.594168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20930158</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Claassen</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meel-van den Abeelen</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simpson</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>International Cerebral Autoregulation Research Network (CARNet). Transfer function analysis of dynamic cerebral autoregulation: a white paper from the International Cerebral Autoregulation Research Network</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cereb Blood Flow Metab</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>665</fpage>–<lpage>680</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0271678X15626425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26782760</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Qu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>QY</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The impact of serial remote ischemic conditioning on dynamic cerebral autoregulation and brain injury related biomarkers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>835173</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphys.2022.835173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35273521</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ekbom</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ulfberg</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>266</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>419</fpage>–<lpage>431</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2796.2009.02159.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19817966</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Winkelman</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Armstrong</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Practice guideline summary: treatment of restless legs syndrome in adults: report of the guideline development, dissemination, and implementation subcommittee of the American Academy of Neurology</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>87</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>2585</fpage>–<lpage>2593</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000003388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27856776</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Partinen</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hirvonen</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jama</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Efficacy and safety of pramipexole in idiopathic restless legs syndrome: a polysomnographic dose-finding study – the PRELUDE study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>407</fpage>–<lpage>417</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2006.03.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16815748</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Winkelman</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sethi</surname>
<given-names>KD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kushida</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Efficacy and safety of pramipexole in restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1034</fpage>–<lpage>1039</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/01.wnl.0000231513.23919.a1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16931507</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Trenkwalder</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stiasny-Kolster</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kupsch</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Controlled withdrawal of pramipexole after 6 months of open-label treatment in patients with restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mov Disord</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1404</fpage>–<lpage>1410</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mds.20983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16755554</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sills</surname>
<given-names>GJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The mechanisms of action of gabapentin and pregabalin</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Opin Pharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>108</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coph.2005.11.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16376147</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Garcia-Borreguero</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Larrosa</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de la Llave</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Treatment of restless legs syndrome with gabapentin: a double-blind, cross-over study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1573</fpage>–<lpage>1579</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.59.10.1573</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12451200</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fink</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dooley</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meder</surname>
<given-names>WP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Inhibition of neuronal Ca (2<sup>+</sup>) influx by gabapentin and pregabalin in the human neocortex</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropharmacology</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>236</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0028-3908(01)00172-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11804619</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Picchietti</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garcia-Borreguero</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Restless legs syndrome/Willis-Ekbom disease diagnostic criteria: updated International Restless Legs Syndrome Study Group (IRLSSG) consensus criteria-history, rationale, description, and significance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>860</fpage>–<lpage>873</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2014.03.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25023924</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wijemanne</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jankovic</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Restless legs syndrome: clinical presentation diagnosis and treatment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>678</fpage>–<lpage>690</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2015.03.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25979181</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Trenkwalder</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hening</surname>
<given-names>WA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Montagna</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Treatment of restless legs syndrome: an evidence-based review and implications for clinical practice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mov Disord</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>2267</fpage>–<lpage>2302</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mds.22254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18925578</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burchell</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>MacDonald</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Validation of the self-completed Cambridge–Hopkins questionnaire (CH-RLSq) for ascertainment of restless legs syndrome (RLS) in a population survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1097</fpage>–<lpage>1100</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2008.10.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19195928</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Abetz</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arbuckle</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The reliability, validity and responsiveness of the International Restless Legs Syndrome Study Group rating scale and subscales in a clinical trial setting</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>340</fpage>–<lpage>349</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2005.12.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16713344</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Walters</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>LeBrocq</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dhar</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Validation of the International Restless Legs Syndrome Study Group rating scale for restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>132</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14592342</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>van Beek</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Claassen</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rikkert</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cerebral autoregulation: an overview of current concepts and methodology with special focus on the elderly</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cereb Blood Flow Metab</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1071</fpage>–<lpage>1085</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jcbfm.2008.13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18349877</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>van Beek</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Claassen</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rikkert</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Frequency domain analysis of cerebral blood flow velocity and its correlation with arterial blood pressure</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cereb Blood Flow Metab</italic></source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>311</fpage>–<lpage>318</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004647-199803000-00010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9498848</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>San Pedro</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mountz</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mountz</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Familial painful restless legs syndrome correlates with pain dependent variation of blood flow to the caudate, thalamus, and anterior cingulate gyrus</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Rheumatol</italic></source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2270</fpage>–<lpage>2275</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9818676</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chenini</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barateau</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rassu</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Systematic assessment of autonomic symptoms in restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>80</volume>:<fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2021.01.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33548567</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Izzi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Placidi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Romigi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Is autonomic nervous system involved in restless legs syndrome during wakefulness?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1392</fpage>–<lpage>1397</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2014.06.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25266501</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ferri</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zucconi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rundo</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Heart rate and spectral EEG changes accompanying periodic and non-periodic leg movements during sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Neurophysiol</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>118</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>438</fpage>–<lpage>448</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinph.2006.10.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17140849</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Montplaisir</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boucher</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poirier</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Clinical, polysomnographic, and genetic characteristics of restless legs syndrome: a study of 133 patients diagnosed with new standard criteria</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mov Disord</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mds.870120111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8990055</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hamner</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tan</surname>
<given-names>CO</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Relative contributions of sympathetic, cholinergic, and myogenic mechanisms to cerebral autoregulation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Stroke</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1771</fpage>–<lpage>1777</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/STROKEAHA.114.005293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24723314</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Winkelman</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Redline</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baldwin</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Polysomnographic and health-related quality of life correlates of restless legs syndrome in the sleep heart health study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>772</fpage>–<lpage>778</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19544754</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hornyak</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feige</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Voderholzer</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Polysomnography findings in patients with restless legs syndrome and in healthy controls: a comparative observational study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>861</fpage>–<lpage>865</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/30.7.861</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17682656</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stang</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moebus</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Möhlenkamp</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Gender-specific associations of short sleep duration with prevalent hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e15</fpage>–<lpage>e16</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.107.108456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18227401</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kowall</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lehnich</surname>
<given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Strucksberg</surname>
<given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Associations among sleep disturbances, nocturnal sleep duration, daytime napping, and incident prediabetes and type 2 diabetes: the Heinz Nixdorf recall study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2015.12.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27448469</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cappuccio</surname>
<given-names>FP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>D’Elia</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Strazzullo</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Quantity and quality of sleep and incidence of type 2 diabetes: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes Care</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>414</fpage>–<lpage>420</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc09-1124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19910503</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cappuccio</surname>
<given-names>FP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cooper</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>D’Elia</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration predicts cardiovascular outcomes: a systematic review and meta-analysis of prospective studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Heart J</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1484</fpage>–<lpage>1492</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehr007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21300732</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Phillips</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mannino</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Do insomnia complaints cause hypertension or cardiovascular disease?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>489</fpage>–<lpage>494</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.26913</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17803012</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chandola</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferrie</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perski</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The effect of short sleep duration on coronary heart disease risk is greatest among those with sleep disturbance: a prospective study from the Whitehall II cohort</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>739</fpage>–<lpage>744</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/33.6.739</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20550013</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Carreras</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>SX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peris</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Chronic sleep fragmentation induces endothelial dysfunction and structural vascular changes in mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1817</fpage>–<lpage>1824</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.4178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25364077</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Clark</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salo</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lange</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Onset of impaired sleep and cardiovascular disease risk factors: a longitudinal study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1709</fpage>–<lpage>1718</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.6098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27397560</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bassetti</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aldrich</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep electroencephalogram changes in acute hemispheric stroke</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>185</fpage>–<lpage>194</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1389-9457(00)00071-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11311681</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gottselig</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bassetti</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Achermann</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Power and coherence of sleep spindle frequency activity following hemispheric stroke</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>125</volume>(<issue>Pt 2</issue>):<fpage>373</fpage>–<lpage>383</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awf021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11844737</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Green</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dawson</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Groenewoud</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Is flow-mediated dilation nitric oxide mediated? A meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>376</fpage>–<lpage>382</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.113.02044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24277765</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Heitzer</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schlinzig</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krohn</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Endothelial dysfunction, oxidative stress, and risk of cardiovascular events in patients with coronary artery disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circulation</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>22</issue>):<fpage>2673</fpage>–<lpage>2678</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/hc4601.099485</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11723017</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Daiber</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Steven</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weber</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Targeting vascular (endothelial) dysfunction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Br J Pharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>174</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1591</fpage>–<lpage>1619</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bph.13517</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27187006</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Beard</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Connor</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Iron status and neural functioning</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Annu Rev Nutr</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.nutr.23.020102.075739</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12704220</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Earley</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Connor</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beard</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Abnormalities in CSF concentrations of ferritin and transferrin in restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1698</fpage>–<lpage>1700</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.54.8.1698</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10762522</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Earley</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Connor</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beard</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Ferritin levels in the cerebrospinal fluid and restless legs syndrome: effects of different clinical phenotypes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1069</fpage>–<lpage>1075</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/28.9.1069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16268375</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0055">
        <label>55.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Trenkwalder</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paulus</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Restless legs syndrome: pathophysiology, clinical presentation and management</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>346</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrneurol.2010.55</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20531433</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0056">
        <label>56.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Martens</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McConnell</surname>
<given-names>FK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Filippini</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Dopaminergic modulation of regional cerebral blood flow: an arterial spin labelling study of genetic and pharmacological manipulation of COMT activity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroimage</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>234</volume>:<fpage>117999</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2021.117999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33789133</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0057">
        <label>57.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Connor</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>XS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Altered dopaminergic profile in the putamen and substantia nigra in restless leg syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>132</volume>(<issue>Pt9</issue>):<fpage>2403</fpage>–<lpage>2412</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awp125</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19467991</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0058">
        <label>58.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Clemens</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rye</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hochman</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Restless legs syndrome: revisiting the dopamine hypothesis from the spinal cord perspective</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>130</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/01.wnl.0000223316.53428.c9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16832090</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0059">
        <label>59.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Högl</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garcia-Borreguero</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trenkwalder</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Efficacy and augmentation during 6 months of double-blind pramipexole for restless legs syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>351</fpage>–<lpage>360</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2010.12.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21354368</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0060">
        <label>60.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Adler</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Treatment of restless legs syndrome with gabapentin</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Neuropharmacol</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>148</fpage>–<lpage>151</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00002826-199704000-00006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9099467</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0061">
        <label>61.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pugsley</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whetzel</surname>
<given-names>SZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dooley</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Reduction of 3,4-diaminopyridine-induced biogenic amine synthesis and release in rat brain by gabapentin</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychopharmacology</italic></source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>137</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>74</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002130050595</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9631959</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
