<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39050365</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">11268851</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">472014</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S472014</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Causal Association Between Obstructive Sleep Apnea and Child-Onset Asthma Come to Light: A Mendelian Randomization Study</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Gan et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Gan et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0009-0003-5773-9033</contrib-id><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>Qiming</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Quanzhen</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Yanjuan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Xiaofeng</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Jingcun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6354-5794</contrib-id><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Xiaofen</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Dongxing</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1998-9958</contrib-id><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Nuofu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Kang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>State Key Laboratory of Respiratory Disease, National Clinical Research Center for Respiratory Disease, National Center for Respiratory Disease, Department of Sleep Medicine Center, Guangzhou Institute of Respiratory Health, The First Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Guangdong</addr-line>, <addr-line>510160</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Nanshan School, Guangzhou Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Guangdong</addr-line>, <addr-line>511436</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Kang Wu; Nuofu Zhang, <institution>Department of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, Sleep Medicine Center, Guangzhou Institute of Respiratory Health, The First Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>No. 28 Qiaozhong Mid Road</addr-line>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Guangdong</addr-line>, <addr-line>510160</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, Email d102_wk@126.com; nfzhanggird@163.com</corresp><fn id="ft0001"><label>*</label><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">These authors contributed equally to this work</citation_analysis></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>979</fpage><lpage>987</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>03</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Gan et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Gan et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Purpose</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) had been associated with asthma in observational studies, but the effect of OSA on the onset of asthma in childhood or adulthood remains unclear, and the causal inferences have not been confirmed. This study aims to investigate the potential causal association between OSA with asthma, including different age-of-onset subtypes, providing reliable basis for the clinical treatment of OSA and asthma.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Patients and Methods</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Causality between OSA and asthma was assessed using a two-sample bi-directional Mendelian randomization (MR) analysis. OSA data were obtained from the FinnGen consortium R9, while asthma and its subtypes (adult-onset asthma, child-onset asthma, and moderate-to-severe asthma) were sourced from the IEU OpenGWAS project. The inverse-variance weighted (IVW) method was chosen as the primary analysis and was complemented by various sensitivity analyses. The MR-PRESSO outlier test was employed to systematically identify and remove outlier variants, mitigating heterogeneity and potential effects of horizontal pleiotropy.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The MR analyses provided evidence of genetically predicted OSA having a promoting effect on child-onset asthma (OR,1.49; 95% CI, 1.05–2.11; P=0.025) and moderate-to-severe asthma (OR,1.03; 95% CI, 1.00–1.06; P=0.046). However, no causal association between OSA with asthma and adult-onset asthma was observed.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our study revealed a causal association between OSA and child asthma, but not in adults. Moderate-to-severe asthma may have a potential promoting effect on OSA. These findings underscore the importance of age-specific considerations in managing asthma and suggests the need for personalized approaches in clinical practice.</citation_analysis></p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>asthma</kwd><kwd>obstructive sleep apnea</kwd><kwd>Mendelian randomization</kwd><kwd>genetic</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>the Young Scientist Fund of National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>school-enterprise cooperation funding project of Guangzhou</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the Young Scientist Fund of National Natural Science Foundation of China (NO. 82100062) and school-enterprise cooperation funding project of Guangzhou (NO. SL2023A03J01372).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="1"/><ref-count count="38"/><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) and asthma are widespread respiratory conditions that have significant health implications. OSA is a sleep-related breathing disorder characterized by recurrent episodes of complete or partial upper airway obstruction, leading to intermittent hypoxia, hypercapnia, or arousals during sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> On the other hand, asthma is distinguished by chronic airway inflammation and bronchial hyperresponsiveness, and it affects individuals of all ages. The prevalence of asthma of around 10% in children and adolescents,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and 6–7% in adults, thus impacting approximately 300 million people worldwide.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Although there has been extensive individual research into asthma and OSA, their potential relationship remains a topic of ongoing investigation. Several studies have attempted to establish a link between the two diseases. For instance, a 2008–2009 national survey analysis found the prevalence of asthma with OSA to be 2.7 times higher than that without OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> A recent mate-analysis has shown that difficult-to-control asthma was independently associated with OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">While previous studies have suggested a possible association between asthma and OSA, the impact of OSA on the onset of asthma in childhood or adulthood is unclear. Moreover, current evidence is largely limited to observational studies, which complicates establishing a cause-and-effect relationship. Tao and colleges’ study shown that compared to those without OSA, allergic rhinitis, chronic tonsillitis and adenoid hypertrophy were independent risk factors for OSA in children with asthma.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Moreover, studies had shown that the asthma symptoms can be relieved after treating OSA,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> especially in patients with uncontrolled asthma. A recent study has demonstrated that frequent asthma in childhood is associated with OSA in middle‐age.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> All of these indicated the potential relationship between OSA and asthma. However, Jose et al aimed to explore the causality between OSA and asthma, but the result was inconclusive.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Thus, it is crucial to understand the potential causal association between these two conditions as a step towards improving therapeutic approaches and patient outcomes. In recent years, the use of Mendelian randomization (MR) analysis as a method to assess causality in observational studies by leveraging genetic variants as instrumental variables has gained prominence.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> This analytical approach enables the investigation of causal associations between exposures and outcomes, providing a more reliable estimate of causality compared to traditional observational studies.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Therefore, we sought to examine the causal influence of asthma on the development of OSA and vice versa by employing a bi-directional MR approach, considering potential confounders and genetic predisposition as well. Furthermore, we aimed to investigate whether the causal association between asthma and OSA varies between childhood and adult asthma, which could aid in tailoring treatment strategies for specific age groups.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">By unraveling the causal pathways between asthma and OSA, our findings can potentially contribute to clinical practice, early prevention strategies, and treatment interventions for both conditions. Ultimately, such knowledge has the potential to enhance health outcomes and improve quality of life for individuals affected by these respiratory conditions.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Study Design</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The MR design was summarized in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. Single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) were used as the instrumental variables (IVs) in the MR analysis to estimate the causal association between exposure and development of disease. The IVs must base on three critical assumptions: (1) IVs must be strongly associated with exposure; (2) IVs are not related to confounding factors; (3) IVs affect outcome risk only through the risk factor rather than any other ways.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Overview of the bidirectional two-sample Mendelian randomization (MR) study design. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) MR analysis illustration. There are three principal assumptions in MR design: ① Instrumental variables (IVs) must be strongly associated with exposure; ② IVs are not related to confounding factors; and ③ IVs affect outcome risk only through the risk factor rather than any other ways; (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) The forward and reverse stages of MR analysis between OSA and asthma and three subtypes asthma.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-979-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: OSA, obstructive sleep apnea; MR, Mendelian randomization; IVs, Instrumental variables; SNP, single-nucleotide polymorphisms; LD, Linkage disequilibrium.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Data Source</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">All the datasets used are publicly available. The genome-wide association study (GWAS) summary-level data for OSA comes were obtained from the FinnGen biobank (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="http://www.finngen.fi/en" ext-link-type="uri">www.finngen.fi/en</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">), which contains information from 41,704 patients and 335,573 controls. The database integrates imputed genotype data from Finnish biobanks, and Finnish health registries.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> For asthma and its subtypes, namely adult-onset asthma and child-onset asthma, the datasets were extracted from UK Biobank (UKBB, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="http://www.ukbiobank.ac.uk" ext-link-type="uri">www.ukbiobank.ac.uk</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). The asthma GWAS data comprised 56,167 asthma patients and 352,255 controls. The adult-onset asthma dataset, defined as asthma onset after the age of 26, contained 22,296 cases and 347,481 controls. The child-onset asthma dataset, defined as asthma onset before the age of 12, included 9676 cases and 347,481 controls. Additionally, data for moderate-to-severe asthma, defined by patients taking medication or being diagnosed by a doctor, consisted of 5135 cases and 25,675 controls. Detailed information about the data sources is presented in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Characteristics of GWAS Consortiums Used for Each Variable</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traits</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample Size(Cases/Controls)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Consortium</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PMDI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Obstructive sleep apnea</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41,704/335,573</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FINNGen</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Asthma</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56,167/352,255</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UKBB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34103634</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Adult-onset asthma</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,296/347,481</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UKBB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31619474</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Child-onset asthma</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,676/347,481</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UKBB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31619474</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Moderate-to-severe asthma</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,135/25,675</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">European</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UKBB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30552067</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: GWAS, genome-wide association studies; UKBB, UK Biobank; FINNGen, Finnish Gene.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>The Selection of Genetic Instrumental Variables (IVs)</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">MR analysis used IVs as mediators between exposure factors and outcomes to explore causal association. Firstly, the genome-wide significance level is set at p&lt;5×10</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>–8</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, which is commonly accepted in the MR analysis.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> All selected IVs must meet the criteria of being meaningfully associated with exposure and unrelated to outcome. Secondly, to ensure the independence, IVs clumping is performed using a cutoff of R</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;0.001 within a genetic window of 10,000 kb. R</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">, which represents the proportion of exposure explained by IVs, can be calculated using the formula: R</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = β</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> / (SE</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> *N+β</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> For a strong association between IVs and exposure, the F statistic is calculated using the formula F = R</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">/ (1 − R</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative">) × (N–2), where N represents the sample size. To avoid bias from weak instruments, IVs with an F-statistic &lt;10 are removed.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Finally, the use of PhenoScanner V2, an expanded tool for searching human genotype–phenotype associations, helps exclude IVs related to outcome traits.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Mendelian Randomization Analyses</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The multiplicative random-effect inverse variance-weighted (IVW) method is considered to have the highest ability to detect causal associations in MR analysis, which regarded as the primary criterion for assessing the result. The weighted median and the MR-Egger are used as supplementary methods.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The statistical significance threshold is commonly set 0.05. To assess heterogeneity among individual SNPs, Cochran’s Q test is employed. If significant heterogeneity is observed, the random-effects model is chosen.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Stability of the results is evaluated using MR–Egger regression and MR pleiotropy residual sum and outlier (MR-PRESSO). MR-Egger regression can detect directional pleiotropy, accounting for the possibility of non-zero intercepts.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> MR-PRESSO is used to identify and remove any horizontal pleiotropic outlier by calculating p-values for each SNP.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> These outliers are eliminated prior to each MR analysis. The leave-one-out sensitivity method is employed to assess if the results are influenced by the removal of any single SNP. Scatterplots, forest plots, and funnel plots are generated to further examine the sensitivity of the results. All analyses are conducted using the TwoSampleMR and MR-PRESSO packages in R Software 4.3.1. The forest plot is created using ggplot2 package.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Causal Effect of Obstructive Sleep Apnea on Asthma</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">At first, we conducted the MR analyses to investigate the causal effect of OSA on asthma and its subtypes. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472014.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Figure S1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> show the main flowcharts of genetic instrument screening. We identified 22, 12, 12, and 19 SNPs as IVs for asthma, adult-onset asthma, child-onset asthma, and moderate-to-severe asthma, respectively. To account for the influence of BMI as a confounding factor, we excluded SNPs associated with BMI by PhenoScanner. We further used the MR-PRESSO method to detect and remove any outliers, resulting in a final set of 12, 7, 7 and 12 SNPs for the MR analyses. Detailed information on the selected SNPs is provided in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472014.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Table S1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. Using the IVW method, we found that genetically predicted OSA was significantly associated with an increased incidence of child-onset asthma (IVW OR,1.49; 95% CI, 1.05–2.11; P=0.025) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). Similar results were observed when applying the weighted median method (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472014.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Table S2</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). However, none of the three methods provided causal association evidence between OSA with asthma (IVW OR,1.08; 95% CI, 0.97–1.19; P=0.148), adult-onset asthma (IVW OR,1.03; 95% CI, 0.82–1.30; P=0.784), or moderate-to-severe asthma (IVW OR,0.93; 95% CI,0.60–1.46; P=0.761) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472014.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Table S2</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). Heterogeneity was observed in the results of OSA on moderate-to-severe asthma, as indicated by Cochran’s Q statistical test (P=0.029), thus supporting the use of the random-effects IVW method (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472014.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Table S3</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). The MR-Egger intercept analysis did not reveal any evidence of pleiotropy, except the moderate-to-severe asthma (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472014.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Table S3</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). Forest plots and scatter plots depicting the results are shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472014.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Figure S2</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> respectively. Leave-one-out analysis confirmed the robustness of the positive results (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472014.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Figure S3</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). Funnel plots indicated little evidence of heterogeneity (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472014.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Figure S4</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The forest plot of the MR analysis results about causal associations of OSA on asthma, adult-onset asthma, child-onset asthma and moderate-to-severe asthma. Significant threshold was set at p-value &lt; 0.05 for the inverse variance weighted method (IVW).</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-979-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: OSA, obstructive sleep apnea; MR, Mendelian randomization; SNP, single-nucleotide polymorphisms; OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The scatter plots of SNP effect. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) the scatter plots of SNP effect about OSA on asthma, (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) the scatter plots of SNP effect about OSA on adult -onset asthma, (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>C</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) the scatter plots of SNP effect about OSA on child-onset asthma, (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>D</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) the scatter plots of SNP effect about OSA on moderate-to-severe asthma.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-979-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: OSA, obstructive sleep apnea; SNP, single-nucleotide polymorphisms; MR, Mendelian randomization.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Causal Effect of Asthma on Obstructive Sleep Apnea</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We conducted a reverse MR study to explore the causal effect of asthma on OSA, using the same methodology to screen SNPs (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472014.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Figure S5</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). Finally, we identified 66, 13, 41, and 14 SNPs linked to asthma, adult-onset asthma, child-onset asthma, and moderate-to-severe asthma respectively. Details of SNPs can be found in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472014.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Table S4</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. Based on IVW method, only moderate-to-severe asthma was found to have a significant causal effect on OSA (IVW OR,1.03; 95% CI, 1.00–1.06; P=0.046), as shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. However, we did not observe significant causal effects of asthma or the other two subtypes on OSA (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472014.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Table S2</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). Furthermore, the results of asthma and adult-onset asthma on OSA showed heterogeneity tested by Cochran’s Q statistical (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472014.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Table S3</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). We presented the forest plots, leave-one-out analysis, scatter plots and funnel plots in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472014.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Figures S6</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">–</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=472014.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">S9</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> respectively to provide more detailed information.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0004" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The forest plot of the MR analysis results about causal associations of asthma, adult-onset asthma, child-onset asthma and moderate-to-severe asthma on OSA. Significant threshold was set at p-value &lt; 0.05 for the inverse variance weighted method (IVW).</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-979-g0004" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: OSA, obstructive sleep apnea; MR, Mendelian randomization; SNP, single-nucleotide polymorphisms; OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We investigated the causal association between OSA and asthma, including some of its subtypes, using bi-directional MR analysis. To our knowledge, it is the first MR study on this topic, providing valuable insights into the causality between asthma and OSA. Our results indicate that OSA is a risk factor for the development of childhood asthma at the genetic level, and moderate-to-severe asthma may serve as potential risk factors for OSA. However, our forward and reverse MR analyses did not find a significant causal association between OSA and asthma, including adult-onset asthma.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Based on previous studies, the relationship between asthma and OSA appears to be bidirectional. The prevalence of OSA is higher in patients with asthma compared to those without OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> A randomized population-based prospective study showed that participants with asthma had a significantly increased risk of OSA (RR=2.72, P=0.045) compared to those without asthma.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Asthma and OSA share similar pathophysiological mechanisms. The intermittent hypoxia in OSA can lead to oxidative stress and systemic inflammation, ultimately leading to airway hyperreactivity.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Then, chronic airway inflammation caused by asthma can lead to the infiltration of inflammatory cells,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> attenuates the force generated by respiratory muscles,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and undermine protective mechanisms of pharyngeal upper-airway (pUAW) patency.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Long-term use of inhaled corticosteroid (ICS) for asthma also can potentially lead to upper airway collapse during sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> These factors may contribute to the development of OSA in asthmatic patients. However, current researches on OSA combined with asthma consists of observational or cross-sectional studies, which without discussing the causal association in depth. Additionally, the heterogeneity of the two diseases suggests that they are strongly influenced by similar acquired factors, such as occupational exposures, smoking, air pollution and hormonal changes, which may overshadow the potential impact of OSA on asthma development.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Furthermore, the persistent airway inflammation characteristic of adult-onset asthma may have a complex etiology, involving multiple genetic and environmental factors that mitigate the causal effect of OSA. However, our study, while excluding the interference of acquired environmental factors, found no causal association between OSA and asthma at the genetic level. This finding does not conflict with the results of current observational studies but further emphasizes the important role of environmental factors in the occurrence and development of the two diseases. On the other hand, the result indicating that moderate-to-severe asthma may have a potential promoting effect on OSA suggest that individuals with more severe asthma may have more “fragile” airways, with more intense inflammation responses and increased airway hyperresponsiveness,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> which is more likely to lead to the production of OSA.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Most importantly, the significant causal association between OSA and child-onset asthma is intriguing. Our study demonstrates that OSA contributes to the development of child-onset asthma at a genetic level. Child-onset asthma is mostly associated with genetic factors, including lung growth and development, and immune system development.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Therefore, chronic airway inflammation in early life can increase the respiratory system’s plasticity, leading to impaired lung function and eventually resulting in various respiratory diseases. Pediatric OSA is most commonly observed in children aged 2 to 8 years old, and is mostly associated with tonsillar and adenoid hypertrophy.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> A study demonstrated that tonsillar hypertrophy (OR=3.15; 95% CI 2.04–4.88) and adenoidal hypertrophy (OR=1.89; 95% CI 1.19–3.00) significantly increased OSA risk, and this influence decreases in adolescence.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Thus, adenotonsillectomy (AT) be considered as the first-line therapy for pediatric OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Rakesh et al research shown that after 1 year following, the control of asthma symptoms had significantly improved in children who underwent AT, indicating that the presence of OSA in children may aggravate underlying asthma.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Chronic inflammation caused by allergic rhinitis, enlarged tonsils and adenoids results in an overexpression of leukotrienes and their receptors. This overexpression can promote the proliferation of adenotonsillar cells, forming a vicious circle that affects the occurrence and development of asthma and OSA in children.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Another study shown that montelukast, a cysteinyl-leukotriene receptor antagonist, could effectively reduce the severity of pediatric OSA and adenoidal size.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Substantially, compared with adults, children’s respiratory system function and immune respiratory response are still developing and may be more susceptible to chronic airway inflammation, which may the main reason for asthma in children with OSA and aggravation of asthma symptoms. Thus, our findings are consistent with previous studies highlighting the potential impact of OSA on childhood respiratory health. The results also provided reliable clinical evidences that screening for OSA in children with asthma and early treatment of OSA are meaningful for reducing the incidence of asthma and optimizing asthma symptom control, consistent with previous conclusions.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The findings of our study suggest that chronic, low-grade inflammation in the early life can lead to impaired lung function and have long-term effects on the development and progression of chronic respiratory diseases, such as asthma.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Additionally, recurrent hypoxemia and hypercapnia induced by OSA can worsen airway hyperreactivity and cause airway inflammation.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> These effects may be more pronounced in children compared to adults. It has been observed that children have more active upper airway reflexes during sleep, which decrease during adolescence, which can result in a stronger response to hypoxemia and hypercapnia,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and may leading to more frequent alternations between phases of hypoxemia and hyperventilation. Consequently, the airway inflammatory response may be more intense in children with OSA. Identifying OSA as a potential causal factor for childhood asthma highlights the importance of early intervention and management of OSA in pediatric populations to prevent the development of asthma.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">It is worth noting that the MR analysis used in this study relies on certain assumptions, including the validity of instrumental variables and the absence of pleiotropy. Although we rigorously accounted for potential confounders and employed robust sensitivity analyses, we did not find age-stratified OSA databases and sex-stratified OSA and asthma databases, so the possibility of unmeasured confounding or pleiotropy cannot be completely ruled out. Additionally, we exclusively enrolled individuals of European descent in our study population, indicating that our findings might not be generalizable to individuals of other ethnic ancestries. Finally, limited by the current genome-wide association studies (GWAS) studies, we were unable to get detailed gender-specific and age-stratified information, which prevented us from conducting in-depth subtype analyses.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In conclusion, our study using a comprehensive MR approach provides evidence of a causal association between OSA and childhood asthma, implying that OSA acts as a risk factor for asthma development in early life. However, no significant causal association was observed between OSA and adult-onset asthma. These findings underscore the importance of considering developmental factors and age-specific mechanisms in the understanding the interactions between asthma and OSA. Further research is needed to unravel the underlying mechanisms governing these relationships and to guide the development of personalized interventions for individuals affected by asthma and OSA.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our Mendelian randomization study revealed a causal association between OSA and childhood asthma, as well as a potential promoting effect of moderate-to-severe asthma on OSA. However, we observed no causal association between OSA and asthma in adults. These findings emphasize the significance of early intervention and targeted treatments for childhood asthma induced by OSA and pay more attention to the influence of moderate and severe asthma. Further research is needed to uncover the underlying mechanisms and explore other factors influencing this relationship. Overall, our study highlights the importance of age-specific considerations in managing asthma and suggests the need for personalized approaches in clinical practice.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We gratefully acknowledge the IEU OpenGWAS project for access to their data. We are very thankful to the participants and investigators of the FinnGen study.</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s0006">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All data are publicly available GWAS summary data. The website of datasets using in this research shown in method part of this paper.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Ethics Declaration</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The ethics committee of the First Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou Medical University strictly follows the Declaration of Helsinki and International Ethical Guidelines for Health-related Research Involving Humans, etc, to perform independent ethical review duties. All genome-wide association studies included in this study all originate from publicly published GWAS summary databases, which complies with the conditions for exemption from review as stated in the “Ethical Review Measures for Life Sciences and Medical Research Involving Humans”.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0008">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors declare no conflicting interest associated with this manuscript.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Veasey</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosen</surname>
<given-names>IM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Solomon</surname>
<given-names>CG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive Sleep Apnea in Adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>380</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>1442</fpage>–<lpage>1449</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMcp1816152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30970189</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>García-Marcos</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Asher</surname>
<given-names>MI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pearce</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The burden of asthma, hay fever and eczema in children in 25 countries: GAN Phase I study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Respir J</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>2102866</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.02866-2021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35144987</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stern</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pier</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Litonjua</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Asthma epidemiology and risk factors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Semin Immunopathol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00281-020-00785-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32020334</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bhattacharyya</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kepnes</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Ambulatory office visits and medical comorbidities associated with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>147</volume>:<fpage>1154</fpage>–<lpage>1157</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0194599812459850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22951431</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The relationship between obstructive sleep apnea and asthma severity and vice versa: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Med Res</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>139</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40001-023-01097-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36998095</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tao</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ding</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Risk factors of sleep-disordered breathing and poor asthma control in children with asthma</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Pediatr</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>288</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12887-024-04762-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38689232</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bhattacharjee</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Choi</surname>
<given-names>BH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gozal</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mokhlesi</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association of adenotonsillectomy with asthma outcomes in children: a longitudinal database analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e1001753</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1001753</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25369282</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Serrano-Pariente</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Plaza</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Soriano</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Asthma outcomes improve with continuous positive airway pressure for obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Allergy</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>802</fpage>–<lpage>812</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/all.13070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27732758</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Senaratna</surname>
<given-names>CV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lowe</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Walters</surname>
<given-names>EH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Associations of early life and childhood risk factors with obstructive sleep apnoea in middle-age</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Respirology</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/resp.14592</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37733623</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Castro-Rodriguez</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brockmann</surname>
<given-names>PE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marcus</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Relation between asthma and sleep disordered breathing in children: is the association causal</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Paediatr Respir Rev</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>72</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.prrv.2016.08.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27818068</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Evans</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davey Smith</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mendelian Randomization: new Applications in the Coming Age of Hypothesis-Free Causality</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Annu Rev Genomics Hum Genet</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>327</fpage>–<lpage>350</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-genom-090314-050016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25939054</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Davies</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holmes</surname>
<given-names>MV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davey Smith</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Reading Mendelian randomisation studies: a guide, glossary, and checklist for clinicians</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>362</volume>:<fpage>k601</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.k601</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30002074</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kurki</surname>
<given-names>MI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Karjalainen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Palta</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>FinnGen provides genetic insights from a well-phenotyped isolated population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nature</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>613</volume>:<fpage>508</fpage>–<lpage>518</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-022-05473-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36653562</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Larsson</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Butterworth</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burgess</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mendelian randomization for cardiovascular diseases: principles and applications</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Heart J</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>4913</fpage>–<lpage>4924</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehad736</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37935836</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lai</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mendelian randomization study reveals the relationship between dietary factors and respiratory diseases</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>22601</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-50055-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38114639</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Burgess</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thompson</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Avoiding bias from weak instruments in Mendelian randomization studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>755</fpage>–<lpage>764</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyr036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21414999</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kamat</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blackshaw</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Young</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>PhenoScanner V2: an expanded tool for searching human genotype-phenotype associations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>4851</fpage>–<lpage>4853</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btz469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31233103</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hartwig</surname>
<given-names>FP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davey Smith</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bowden</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Robust inference in summary data Mendelian randomization via the zero modal pleiotropy assumption</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>1985</fpage>–<lpage>1998</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyx102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29040600</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bowden</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Del Greco</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Minelli</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davey Smith</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sheehan</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thompson</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A framework for the investigation of pleiotropy in two-sample summary data Mendelian randomization</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Stat Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>1783</fpage>–<lpage>1802</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/sim.7221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28114746</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bowden</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davey Smith</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burgess</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mendelian randomization with invalid instruments: effect estimation and bias detection through Egger regression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>512</fpage>–<lpage>525</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyv080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26050253</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Verbanck</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>CY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Neale</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Do</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Detection of widespread horizontal pleiotropy in causal relationships inferred from Mendelian randomization between complex traits and diseases</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Genet</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>693</fpage>–<lpage>698</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-018-0099-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29686387</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Alharbi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Almutairi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alotaibi</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alotaibi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shaikh</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bahammam</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The prevalence of asthma in patients with obstructive sleep apnoea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Prim Care Respir J</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>328</fpage>–<lpage>330</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4104/pcrj.2009.00020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19407917</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Teodorescu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barnet</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hagen</surname>
<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Palta</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Young</surname>
<given-names>TB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peppard</surname>
<given-names>PE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between asthma and risk of developing obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>313</volume>:<fpage>156</fpage>–<lpage>164</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2014.17822</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25585327</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Prasad</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nyenhuis</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weaver</surname>
<given-names>TE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea and asthma: associations and treatment implications</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>171</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2013.04.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23890469</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pinyochotiwong</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chirakalwasan</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Collop</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Nocturnal Asthma</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Asian Pac J Allergy Immunol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>78</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12932/AP-231020-0986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34174807</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Saxena</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Imayama</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adrish</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Revisiting Asthma obstructive sleep apnea overlap: current knowledge and future needs</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Med</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>6552</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm12206552</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37892689</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Prasad</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nyenhuis</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Imayama</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Siddiqi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Teodorescu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Asthma and obstructive sleep apnea overlap: what has the evidence taught us</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>201</volume>:<fpage>1345</fpage>–<lpage>1357</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201810-1838TR</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31841642</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>King</surname>
<given-names>GG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>James</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harkness</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wark</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pathophysiology of severe asthma: we’ve only just started</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Respirology</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>262</fpage>–<lpage>271</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/resp.13251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29316003</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Asthma in children and adolescents: a comprehensive approach to diagnosis and management</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Rev Allergy Immunol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>98</fpage>–<lpage>137</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12016-011-8261-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22187333</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Garza</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Witmans</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salud</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lagera</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Co</surname>
<given-names>VA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tablizo</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Association between Asthma and OSA in Children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Children</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1430</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/children9101430</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36291366</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kang</surname>
<given-names>KT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chou</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weng</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>PL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hsu</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Associations between adenotonsillar hypertrophy, age, and obesity in children with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e78666</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0078666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24205291</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ishman</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maturo</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schwartz</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Expert consensus statement: management of pediatric persistent obstructive sleep apnea after adenotonsillectomy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>168</volume>:<fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>130</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ohn.159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36757810</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mussi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Forestiero</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zambelli</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The first-line approach in children with Obstructive Sleep Apnea Syndrome (OSA)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Med</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>7092</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm12227092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38002704</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ji</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Qiu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The efficacy and safety of montelukast in children with obstructive sleep apnea: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>201</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.11.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33465554</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ross</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep-disordered breathing and childhood asthma: clinical implications</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Opin Pulm Med</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MCP.0b013e32835b11a1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23114562</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Decrue</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gorlanova</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Usemann</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frey</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Lung functional development and asthma trajectories</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Semin Immunopathol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00281-020-00784-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31989229</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mihaicuta</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tiotiu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Corlateanu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ioan</surname>
<given-names>IC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bikov</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Asthma and obstructive sleep apnoea in adults and children - an up-to-date review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>101564</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2021.101564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34902822</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Alsubie</surname>
<given-names>HS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>BaHammam</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive Sleep Apnoea: children are not little Adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Paediatr Respir Rev</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>72</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.prrv.2016.02.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27262609</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
