<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39050367</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">11268715</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">467516</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S467516</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Sex Differences in the Relationship Between Self-Reporting of Snoring and Cardiovascular Risk:An Analysis of NHANES</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Wang et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Wang et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2426-8944</contrib-id><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Junwen</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Yuyang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Xuefeng</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Xinru</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9562-4622</contrib-id><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Yong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Cardiology, West China Hospital, Sichuan University</institution>, <addr-line>Chengdu</addr-line>, <addr-line>610041</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Yong Peng, <institution>Department of Cardiology, West China Hospital, Sichuan University</institution>, <addr-line>37 Guoxue Street</addr-line>, <addr-line>Chengdu</addr-line>, <addr-line>610041</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, Email pengyong@scu.edu.cn</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>965</fpage><lpage>977</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>06</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Wang et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Wang et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Identifying risk factors for cardiovascular disease (CVD) is critical for effective prevention and management. While classic CVD risk factors have been extensively studied, there is a scarcity of research on the association between snoring and CVD risk, particularly in the context of sex differences.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This study utilized data from the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES) conducted between 2015 and 2020. Participants were initially categorized based on the severity of snoring or the presence of snoring.Within the snoring group, they were further classified by sex. Analysis was carried out using multivariate logistic regression.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our study included 12,681 participants aged 18 years or older. When compared to the non-snoring group, individuals in the moderate snoring group had a higher odds ratio (OR) of 1.418 (95% CI 1.083 to 1.857, p = 0.011), while those in the severe snoring group had a higher OR of 1.882 (95% CI 1.468 to 2.409, p &lt; 0.001). In the snoring group, individuals were further categorized by gender: 4527 males and 4131 females. Importantly, male patients showed a higher OR for atrial fibrillation (4.945, 95% CI 1.187 to 20.598, p = 0.028) compared to females. Additionally, male patients had a higher OR for coronary heart disease (2.002, 95% CI 1.152 to 3.479, p = 0.014) compared to females.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Sex plays a significant role in the relationship between snoring and CVD risk. Males with snoring have a higher risk of developing CVD compared to females. In particular, male snorers are nearly five times more likely to develop atrial fibrillation and about twice as likely to experience coronary artery disease in comparison to female snorers. It is recommended that healthcare providers and public health officials prioritize cardiovascular risk assessments for male individuals who exhibit symptoms of snoring.</citation_analysis></p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>gender differences</kwd><kwd>snoring</kwd><kwd>cardiovascular risk</kwd><kwd>atrial fibrillation</kwd><kwd>coronary artery disease</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Sichuan Provincial Cadre Health Research Project, China</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>135 project for disciplines of excellence–Clinical Research Incubation Project, West China Hospital, Sichuan University</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This study was supported by Sichuan Provincial Cadre Health Research Project, China (Sichuan Ganyan ZH2024-101) and by 135 project for disciplines of excellence–Clinical Research Incubation Project, West China Hospital, Sichuan University (Grant number: 2021HXFH061, Sichuan, China).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="3"/><ref-count count="56"/><page-count count="13"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Cardiovascular disease (CVD) is the leading cause of death, accounting for one-third of all mortality causes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> CVD remains the leading cause of death in the United States population, and over the past 18 years, CVD has claimed the lives of more than 10 million individuals.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> CVD pose a significant health burden globally, accounting for a substantial number of deaths and disabilities.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Identifying and understanding the risk factors and management of these conditions.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The relationship between sleep apnea and cardiovascular disease is well established.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> However, studies on the relationship between snoring and cardiovascular disease are relatively scarce. Among patients with sleep apnea, 94% experience snoring, while approximately 43% of snorers are at risk for sleep apnea.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4–6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> A substantial proportion of the general population (10% to 60%) are habitual snorers, but most do not have sleep apnea.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Compared to sleep apnea, snoring is easier to diagnose and more readily accepted by the public.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Therefore, exploring the relationship between snoring and cardiovascular disease may be more meaningful. Hence, our study is conducted among snorers. Previous studies have confirmed that snoring can increase the risk of endothelial dysfunction and diabetes, as well as elevate sympathetic nervous system excitability.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8–10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> This may be a significant reason why snoring raises the risk of cardiovascular diseases. Moreover, even among the existing studies that have examined the association between snoring and CVD risk, the findings are contradictory.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Therefore, it is essential to explore the relationship between snoring and CVD.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Disparities between men and women persist in the diagnosis, treatment, and prognosis of CVD.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The in-hospital mortality rate for female patients with acute coronary syndrome is significantly higher than that of male patients.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Research has indicated that women are more likely to experience complications, including bleeding, associated with coronary revascularization procedures.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> During midlife, around the time of peri- and post-menopause, sleep quality deteriorates, while CVD risk significantly increases in women compared to earlier decades.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> One of the most notable biological differences is the influence of sex hormones. Estrogen, which is more prevalent in premenopausal women, has been shown to have protective effects against CVD.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> It helps to maintain healthy lipid profiles, reduces inflammation, and improves endothelial function.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Males tend to accumulate visceral fat, which is associated with a higher risk of metabolic syndrome and cardiovascular complications.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The findings of these studies underscore the significant role of sex in CVD. Moreover, socioeconomic status and lifestyle have an impact on cardiovascular disease.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Lower socioeconomic status is associated with higher rates of smoking, obesity, and limited access to healthcare services, all of which contribute to increased CVD risk.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Men are more likely to engage in behaviors that increase CVD risk, such as heavy drinking and unhealthy eating patterns.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Therefore, exploring gender differences in the association between snoring and cardiovascular disease risk can inform the development of health policies and guidelines, thereby improving overall cardiovascular disease outcomes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> However, there is a lack of research examining sex differences in the connection between snoring and CVD risk. Therefore, it is particularly important to investigate these sex differences.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The present study aimed to investigate the sex differences in the association between snoring and CVD risk using data from the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES), a nationally representative sample in the United States.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Method</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Study Population</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The NHANES is an ongoing research program that provides population estimates related to the nutrition and health of adults and children in the United States. The survey utilizes a stratified, multistage probability design to recruit a representative sample of the U.S population. Data for the survey are obtained through personal structured interviews conducted at participants’ homes, health examinations conducted at a mobile examination center, and laboratory analysis of specimens.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> All data can be found on the NHANES website (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhanes.htm" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhanes.htm</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). The study protocols were approved by the Institutional Review Board (IRB) of the National Center for Health Statistics, and written informed consent was obtained from each participant. Due to the combination of data from 2017–2018 with that of 2019–2020, the 2017–2018 data has been excluded. Our study included all participants in the NHANES from 2015 through 2020 who were 18 years of age or older and had available sleep data that included information on snoring. We were excluded participants under the age of 18 and those with incomplete key data.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Grouping Methods</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In this study, we employed two grouping methods. The first method involved dividing participants into two groups based on the presence or absence of snoring. The second method involved classifying participants into five groups based on the severity of snoring: non-snoring group, mild snoring group, moderate snoring group, severe snoring group, and unclear snoring group. Within the population of individuals who reported snoring, we divided them into two groups based on their gender: male snorers and female snorers.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Medication Usage and Disease Definition</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Participants were queried about their recent use of prescription medications within a 30-day period. Respondents who acknowledged taking such medications were asked to furnish the interviewers with the respective containers. If the containers were not accessible, participants were requested to disclose the names of the medications to the researchers. In this study, the presence of atrial fibrillation was determined if the investigator reported taking atrial fibrillation medication and provided evidence. For diabetes, the diagnosis was based on medication usage, blood glucose and HbA1c values, and past medical history. Hypertension was considered present if the blood pressure was consistently equal to or greater than 140/90 mmHg on three times or if the patient was currently taking hypertension medication or had a documented history of hypertension.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Sociodemographic Characteristics and Snore Status</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The study collected data on various sociodemographic characteristics and weight status of the participants. These included:1.Age: Participants reported their age. 2. Sex: Participants identified themselves as male or female. 3. Race and Ethnic Group: Participants identified their racial and ethnic background, including options such as Mexican American, Other Hispanic, non-Hispanic White, non-Hispanic Black, Non-Hispanic Asian, or other.4. Education: Participants reported their educational attainment, categorized as less than 11th grade, high school, some college, college graduate, or other.5. Family Income: Participants provided information about their family income, categorized as less than 1.3 of the federal poverty level, 1.3 to 3.49 of the federal poverty level, or equal to or greater than 3.5 of the federal poverty level.6.Drinking Status: Participants reported their smoking status as nondrinker, low-to-moderate drinker (&lt;=2 drinks/day in men and &lt;=1 drink/day in women), or heavy drinker (&gt;2 drinks/day in men and &gt;1 drinks/day in women).7.Smoking Status: Participants reported their smoking status as current smoker, former smoker, or never smoked. Individuals who reported smoking more than 100 cigarettes in their lifetime were classified as current smokers, while those who reported smoking more than 100 cigarettes but had quit smoking were classified as former smokers. 8. Snore Status: Participants were queried about the frequency of their snoring over the past 12 months during sleep. In cases where participants were unable to provide an answer, inquiries were made to other household members, including bed partners, regarding the snoring behavior. Participants reported their snore status as never, rarely snore, occasionally snore, frequently snore, or do not know snore. Individuals who reported snoring 1–2 nights a week were classified as rarely snore, while those who reported snoring 3–4 nights a week were classified as occasionally snore. Those who reported snoring 5 or more nights a week were classified as frequently snore, and those who reported not knowing whether they snore were classified as do not know snore. In addition to sociodemographic characteristics, weight status was assessed using body mass index (BMI), calculated as the weight in kilograms divided by the square of the height in meters. Participants were then classified into three weight-status groups: normal weight (BMI &lt; 25), overweight (BMI 25 to &lt;30), or obese (BMI ≥ 30).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Outcome Events</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This study defined CVD events as including coronary heart disease, angina, atrial fibrillation, heart failure, stroke, heart attack, and hypertension.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2006">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Percentages, means, and 95% confidence interval of key variables were calculated to describe the sample at each level of snoring. Logistic regression model was employed to examine the association between snoring and the outcome variables, while accounting for potential confounding variables. This logistic regression aimed to address any imbalances in potential confounding variables between the groups, thereby reducing their influence on the outcome measures.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The data analysis was conducted using V.15.1 (Stata Corp LP), incorporating survey analysis procedures to account for the complex sampling design. The survey examination weights were applied as appropriate to ensure the obtained estimates were nationally representative. In instances where data was absent for the primary variable, snoring, cases were excluded. For missing data pertaining to covariates, categorical variables with missing data were consolidated into a single category, while multiple imputation was employed for continuous variables. The utilization of multiple imputation was intended to enhance the comprehensiveness and precision of the analysis, while mitigating potential biases stemming from missing data. All statistical tests conducted were two-sided, and a significance level of P &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. To ensure adequate statistical power, we estimated the sample size. Statistical analyses were conducted using appropriate tests, and corrections for multiple hypothesis testing were implemented. Effect sizes were estimated based on findings from previous similar studies. The probabilities of type II errors were set at 0.20. Special attention was paid to subgroups, where the risk of Type II errors might be elevated, to ensure the robustness of the analysis.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Study Population</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Out of the 12,681 participants, a total of 3113 individuals who reported no snoring were included in the study based on the questionnaire survey regarding the presence of snoring in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. Among the participants, there were 3009 individuals categorized as mild snorers, 2245 individuals categorized as moderate snorers, 3404 individuals categorized as severe snorers, and 910 individuals categorized as unclear snorers. The baseline data divided into two groups based on the presence or absence of snoring is presented in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=467516.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Table S1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. A total of 4023 individuals were classified as the non-snoring group, while 8658 individuals were classified as the snoring group. In the snoring group, individuals were further categorized by gender: 4527 males and 4131 females (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=467516.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Table S2</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Baseline Characteristics of Study Participants in NHANES 2015–2020 Grouped According to Snoring Severity</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Snoring</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">P</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Snoring</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild Snoring</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate Snoring</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe Snoring</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear Snoring</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total No. of participants</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3113</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3009</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2245</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3404</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">910</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Creatinine(mmol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.958 (72.112 to 73.814)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.302 (73.499 to 75.114)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.383 (74.514 to 76.262)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.569 (75.777 to 77.370)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.819 (75.202 to 78.471)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sodium(mmol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">139.656 (139.560 to 139.752)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">139.807 (139.714 to 139.899)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">139.748 (139.633 to 139.863)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">139.803 (139.711 to 139.896)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">139.658 (139.477 to 139.840)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.121</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triglyceride(mmol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.220 (1.195 to 1.246)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.304 (1.276 to 1.333)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.398 (1.365 to 1.432)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.565 (1.533 to 1.597)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.356 (1.305 to 1.409)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uric acid(mmol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">293.005 (289.967 to 296.074)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">305.642 (302.571 to 308.744)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">315.724 (312.182 to 319.307)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">326.499 (323.545 to 329.481)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">310.745 (305.170 to 316.423)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total cholesterol(mmol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.637 (4.600 to 4.675)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.738 (4.700 to 4.776)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.742 (4.698 to 4.785)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.812 (4.775 to 4.849)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.750 (4.681 to 4.820)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High-density lipoprotein cholesterol(mmol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.407 (1.392 to 1.423)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.359 (1.345 to 1.374)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.322 (1.306 to 1.339)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.236 (1.224 to 1.248)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.354 (1.327 to 1.381)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low-density lipoprotein cholesterol(mmol/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.585 (2.538 to 2.633)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.691 (2.644 to 2.739)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.719 (2.663 to 2.777)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.795 (2.748 to 2.843)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.695 (2.606 to 2.787)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1838 (59.043%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1583 (52.609%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1110 (49.443%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1438 (42.244%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">503 (55.275%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1275 (40.957%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1426 (47.391%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1135 (50.557%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1966 (57.756%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">407 (44.725%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 18–44 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1530 (49.149%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1451 (48.222%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">831 (37.016%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1216 (35.723%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">253 (27.802%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 45–64 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">842 (27.048%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1012 (33.632%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">868 (38.664%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1470 (43.184%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">311 (34.176%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥65 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">741 (23.803%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">546 (18.146%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">546 (24.321%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">718 (21.093%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">346 (38.022%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mexican American</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">330 (10.601%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">411 (13.659%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">284 (12.650%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">567 (16.657%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">133 (14.615%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other Hispanic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">333 (10.697%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">310 (10.302%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">247 (11.002%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">466 (13.690%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95 (10.440%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Non-Hispanic White</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1130 (36.299%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1046 (34.762%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">791 (35.234%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1074 (31.551%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">334 (36.703%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Non-Hispanic Black</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">784 (25.185%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">711 (23.629%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">582 (25.924%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">797 (23.414%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">237 (26.044%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Non-Hispanic Asian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">410 (13.171%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">385 (12.795%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">242 (10.780%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">344 (10.106%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 (8.791%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">126 (4.048%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">146 (4.852%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99 (4.410%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">156 (4.583%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (3.407%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Less than 11th grade</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">611 (19.627%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">507 (16.849%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">360 (16.036%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">806 (23.678%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">249 (27.363%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> High school</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">721 (23.161%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">679 (22.566%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">529 (23.563%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">805 (23.649%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">224 (24.615%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Some college</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">987 (31.706%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">941 (31.273%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">744 (33.140%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1087 (31.933%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">267 (29.341%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> College graduate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">785 (25.217%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">879 (29.212%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">610 (27.171%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">705 (20.711%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">165 (18.132%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (0.289%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (0.100%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0.089%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.029%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (0.549%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marital status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Never married</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1477 (47.446%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1796 (59.688%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1371 (61.069%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2087 (61.310%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">259 (28.462%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Married or living with partner</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">524 (16.833%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">378 (12.562%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">325 (14.477%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">548 (16.099%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">306 (33.626%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Divorced, separated, or widowed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">597 (19.178%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">474 (15.753%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">307 (13.675%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">421 (12.368%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">213 (23.407%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">515 (16.544%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">361 (11.997%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">242 (10.780%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">348 (10.223%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">132 (14.505%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ratio of family income to poverty level</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≤1.3 of the federal poverty line</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">902 (28.975%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">694 (23.064%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">483 (21.514%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">949 (27.879%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">314 (34.505%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;1.3≤3.49 of the federal poverty line</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1063 (34.147%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1027 (34.131%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">835 (37.194%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1187 (34.871%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">289 (31.758%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;3.5 of the federal poverty line</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">753 (24.189%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">968 (32.170%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">683 (30.423%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">875 (25.705%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">158 (17.363%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">395 (12.689%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">320 (10.635%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">244 (10.869%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">393 (11.545%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">149 (16.374%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">717 (23.032%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">667 (22.167%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">695 (30.958%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1194 (35.076%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">316 (34.725%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1251 (40.186%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">915 (30.409%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">482 (21.470%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">468 (13.749%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">248 (27.253%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 25 to 30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">939 (30.164%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">996 (33.101%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">772 (34.388%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">997 (29.289%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">289 (31.758%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">884 (28.397%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1082 (35.959%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">967 (43.073%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1909 (56.081%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">363 (39.890%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (1.253%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (0.532%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (1.069%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (0.881%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (1.099%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cigarette use</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Never smoked</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1928 (61.934%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1867 (62.047%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1313 (58.486%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1757 (51.616%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">469 (51.538%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Former smoker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">179 (5.750%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">151 (5.018%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">124 (5.523%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">223 (6.551%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (5.824%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Current smoker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">312 (10.022%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">301 (10.003%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">261 (11.626%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">407 (11.957%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">124 (13.626%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">694 (22.294%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">690 (22.931%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">547 (24.365%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1017 (29.877%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">264 (29.011%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol use</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Never drinker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1206 (38.741%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">956 (31.771%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">706 (31.448%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1135 (33.343%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">388 (42.637%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Low-to-moderate drinker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">954 (30.646%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1013 (33.666%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">817 (36.392%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1144 (33.608%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">283 (31.099%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Heavy drinker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">953 (30.614%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1040 (34.563%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">722 (32.160%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1125 (33.049%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">239 (26.264%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Relationship of Snoring to Cardiovascular Risks</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In the unadjusted logistic regression model1, the odds ratios (OR) for moderate snoring (OR 1.569, 95% CI 1.335 to 1.843, P &lt; 0.001), and severe snoring (OR 2.199, 95% CI 1.900 to 2.545, P &lt; 0.001) are presented in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. In the adjusted logistic regression Model 2, which controlled for variables such as sex, race, age, education, and marital status, the odds ratios (OR) for mild snoring, moderate snoring, and severe snoring were 1.096 (95% CI 0.934 to 1.286, P = 0.262), 1.382 (95% CI 1.161 to 1.644, P &lt; 0.001), and 1.937 (95% CI 1.646 to 2.279, P &lt; 0.001) respectively (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> - Model 2). In the multivariable logistic regression Model 3, adjusted for variables including sex, race, age, education, marital status, creatinine (Cr), triglyceride (TG), uric acid (UA), total cholesterol (TC), high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL), and low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL), individuals in the moderate snoring group had an odds ratio (OR) of 1.418 (95% CI: 1.083 to 1.857, p = 0.011) compared to the non-snoring group. Similarly, individuals in the severe snoring group had an odds ratio (OR) of 1.882 (95% CI: 1.468 to 2.409, p &lt; 0.001) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-Model 3). Individuals who snored had a higher odds ratio compared to non-snorers (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=467516.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Table S3</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Snoring and Indicators of Cardiovascular Disease Risk Grouped According to the Severity of Snoring</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 1 OR (95% CI) P</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 2 OR (95% CI) P</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 3 OR (95% CI) P</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Snoring</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Non-snoring</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mild snoring</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.086(0.934 to 1.261)0.284</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.096(0.934 to 1.286)0.262</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.066(0.836 to 1.361)0.606</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Moderate snoring</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.569(1.335 to 1.843) &lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.382(1.161 to 1.644) &lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.418(1.083 to 1.857)0.011</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Severe snoring</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.199(1.900 to 2.545) &lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.937(1.646 to 2.279) &lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.882(1.468 to 2.409) &lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Nuclear snoring</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.575(1.271 to 1.951) &lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.088(0.867 to 1.366)0.467</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.959(0.673 to 1.368)0.817</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: Model1: unadjusted. Model2: means adjusted for sex, race, age, education, marital. Model3: means adjusted for sex, race, age, education, marital, creatinine, triglyceride, uric acid, total cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Gender Differences in the Association Between Snoring and Cardiovascular Risk</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Males with snoring demonstrated a higher incidence rate of CVD (OR 1.414, 95% CI 1.099–1.819, p=0.007) in comparison to females (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). The odds ratios (OR) for male patients with snoring were higher than those for females in various CVDs, including atrial fibrillation (OR 3.441, 95% CI 1.513 to 7.827, p = 0.003), coronary heart disease (OR 2.019, 95% CI 1.409 to 2.892, p &lt; 0.001), heart disease (OR 1.682, 95% CI 1.207 to 2.344, p = 0.002), angina (OR 1.468, 95% CI 0.990 to 2.175, p = 0.055), hypertension (OR 1.159, 95% CI 1.022 to 1.314, p = 0.021), and heart failure (OR 1.225, 95% CI 0.879 to 1.707, p = 0.229) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). However, for stroke patients, the odds ratio (OR) for males was lower than that for females (OR 0.850, 95% CI 0.609 to 1.186, p = 0.339) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Logistic Regression Analysis of the Association Between Snoring and Various Cardiovascular Diseases Stratified by Sex</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 1 OR (95% CI) P</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 2 OR (95% CI) P</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 3 OR (95% CI) P</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Cardiovascular disease<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.271(1.122 to 1.442) &lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.444(1.260 to 1.654) &lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.414(1.099 to 1.819) 0.007</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hypertension<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.159(1.022 to 1.314)0.021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.279(1.117 to 1.464) &lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.358(1.051 to 1.755)0.019</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Atrial fibrillation<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.441(1.513 to 7.827)0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.213(1.474 to 7.006)0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.945(1.187 to 20.598)0.028</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Heart failure<sup>d</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.225(0.879 to 1.707)0.229</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.676(1.203 to 2.334)0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.812(0.399 to 1.651)0.566</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Coronary heart disease<sup>e</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.019(1.409 to 2.892) &lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.639(1.759 to 3.957) &lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.002(1.152 to 3.479)0.014</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Stroke<sup>f</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.850(0.609 to 1.186)0.339</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.987(0.689 to 1.415)0.945</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.866(0.504 to 1.487)0.601</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Angina<sup>g</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.468 (0.990 1to 2.175)0.055</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.877(1.244 to 2.833)0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.625(0.697 to 3.779)0.261</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Heart attack<sup>h</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.682(1.207 to 2.344)0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.209(1.532 to 3.187) &lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.723(1.054 to 2.817)0.030</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: Model 1: unadjusted. Model 2: adjusted for race, age, education, marital. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>a</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Cardiovascular diseases model 3 adjusted for sex, race, age, education, marital, body mass index (BMI), creatinine (Cr), triglyceride (TG), uric acid (UA), total cholesterol (TC), high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL), low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL). </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>b</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Hypertension adjusted for race, age, education, marital, BMI, Cr, TG, UA, TC, LDL, LDL. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>c</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Atrial fibrillation model 3 adjusted for race, age, income, marital, diabetes, education, hypertension (HTN), heart failure (HF), angina, marital, BMI, coronary heart disease (CHD), heart attack (HA), Cr, TG, UA, TC, HDL, LDL. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>d</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Heart failure model 3 adjusted for race, age, income, marital, diabetes, education, angina, marital, HTN, BMI, HA, Cr, TG, UA, TC, HDL, LDL. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>e</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Coronary heart disease model 3 adjusted for race, age, income, marital, diabetes, education, angina, marital, HF, BMI, HA, Cr, TG, UA, TC, HDL, LDL. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>f</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Stork model 3 adjusted for race, age, income, marital, education, diabetes, HTN, BMI, Cr, TG, UA, TC, HDL, LDL. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>g</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Angina model 3 adjusted for race, age, income, marital, education, diabetes, HTN, BMI, TG, UA, TC, HDL, LDL. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>h</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Heart attack model 3 adjusted for race, age, income, marital, diabetes, education, angina, marital, HTN, HF, BMI, CHD, Cr, TG, UA, TC, HDL, LDL.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1
</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Unadjusted Logistic Regression Analysis of the Association Between Snoring and Various Cardiovascular Diseases Stratified by Sex.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-965-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">After adjusting for variables such as race, age, education, and marital status, male patients exhibited a higher odds ratio (OR 1.444, 95% CI 1.260 to 1.654, p &lt;0.001) for CVD compared to females (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). The odds ratios (OR) for male patients with snoring were higher than those for females in various CVD, including atrial fibrillation (OR 3.213, 95% CI 1.474 to 7.006, p = 0.003), coronary heart disease (OR 2.639, 95% CI 1.759 to 3.957, p &lt; 0.001), heart disease (OR 2.209, 95% CI 1.532 to 3.187, p &lt; 0.001), angina (OR 1.877, 95% CI 1.244 to 2.833, p = 0.003), hypertension (OR 1.279, 95% CI 1.117 to 1.464, p &lt; 0.001), and heart failure (OR 1.676, 95% CI 1.203 to 2.334, p = 0.002) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). However, for stroke patients, the odds ratio (OR) for males was lower than that for females (OR 0.987, 95% CI 0.689 to 1.415, p = 0.945) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2
</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Adjusting for Race, Age, Education, and Marital Status: Association Between Snoring and Various Cardiovascular Diseases Stratified by Sex.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-965-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">After adjusting for race, age, education, marital status, Cr, TG, UA, TC, HDL, and LDL, male patients exhibited a higher odds ratio (OR 1.414, 95% CI 1.099–1.819, p = 0.007) for CVD compared to females (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). After adjusting for race, age, education, marital status, Cr, TG, UA, TC, HDL, and LDL, male patients showed a higher odds ratio for hypertension (HTN) (1.358, 95% CI 1.051 to 1.755, p = 0.021) compared to females (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). After adjusting for race, age, income, marital status, diabetes, education, heart failure (HF), angina, BMI, coronary heart disease (CHD), heart attack (HA), HTN, Cr, TG, UA, TC, HDL, and LDL, male patients exhibited a higher odds ratio for atrial fibrillation (4.945, 95% CI 1.187 to 20.598, p = 0.028) compared to females (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). After adjusting for race, age, income, marital, diabetes, education, angina, marital, HTN, BMI, HA, Cr, TG, UA, TC, HDL, and LDL, Male patients exhibited a lower odds ratio for heart failure (0.812, 95% CI 0.399 to 1.651, p = 0.566) compared to females (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). Adjusted for race, age, income, marital status, diabetes, education, angina, BMI, heart attack, Cr, TG, UA, TC, HDL, and LDL, male patients exhibited a higher odds ratio for coronary heart disease (2.002, 95% CI 1.152 to 3.479, p = 0.014) compared to females (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).After adjusting for variables including race, age, income, marital, education, diabetes, HTN, BMI, Cr, TG, UA, TC, HDL, and LDL, male patients showed a decreased odds ratio for stroke (0.866, 95% CI 0.504 to 1.487, p = 0.601) in comparison to females (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). Adjusted for race, age, income, marital, education, diabetes, HTN, BMI, TG, UA, TC, HDL, and LDL, male patients exhibited a lower odds ratio for angina (1.625, 95% CI 0.697 to 3.779, p = 0.261) compared to females (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). Adjusted for race, age, income, marital, diabetes, education, angina, HTN, HF, BMI, CHD, Cr, TG, UA, TC, HDL, and LDL, male patients exhibited a lower odds ratio for heart attack (1.723, 95% CI 1.054 to 2.817, p = 0.261) compared to females (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3
</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Adjusting for Potentially Relevant Variables: Association Between Snoring and Various Cardiovascular Diseases Stratified by Sex.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-965-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Notes:</bold> a: cardiovascular diseases model 3 adjusted for sex, race, age, education, marital, body mass index (BMI), creatinine (Cr), triglyceride (TG), uric acid (UA), total cholesterol (TC), high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL), low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL). b: hypertension adjusted for race, age, education, marital, BMI, Cr, TG, UA, TC, LDL, LDL. c: atrial fibrillation model 3 adjusted for race, age, income, marital, diabetes, education, hypertension (HTN), heart failure (HF), angina, marital, BMI, coronary heart disease (CHD), heart attack (HA), Cr, TG, UA, TC, HDL, LDL. d: heart failure model 3 adjusted for race, age, income, marital, diabetes, education, angina, marital, HTN, BMI, HA, Cr, TG, UA, TC, HDL, LDL. e: coronary heart disease model 3 adjusted for race, age, income, marital, diabetes, education, angina, marital, HF, BMI, HA, Cr, TG, UA, TC, HDL, LDL. f: stork model 3 adjusted for race, age, income, marital, education, diabetes, HTN, BMI, Cr, TG, UA, TC, HDL, LDL. g: angina model 3 adjusted for race, age, income, marital, education, diabetes, HTN, BMI, TG, UA, TC, HDL, LDL. h: heart attack model 3 adjusted for race, age, income, marital, diabetes, education, angina, marital, HTN, HF, BMI, CHD, Cr, TG, UA, TC, HDL, LDL.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Notably, our study revealed that male patients who snore have a notably higher prevalence of CVD, including hypertension, atrial fibrillation, coronary heart disease, and heart disease, in comparison to their female counterparts. Specifically, the risk of atrial fibrillation in male snorers is almost five times greater than in female snorers. The risk of coronary heart disease is twice as high in male snorers compared to females. Additionally, male snorers have a higher risk of developing hypertension and heart disease compared to their female counterparts. These findings emphasize the importance of considering sex-specific factors in assessing CVD risk associated with snoring. This novel contribution expands our understanding of the complex relationship between snoring and CVD risk and highlights the need for further research to explore the underlying mechanisms driving these gender-specific differences.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our study’s findings are consistent with previous research, which underscores the potential role of snoring as a risk factor for CVD events.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23–25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Snoring, a common sleep disorder, is characterized by loud and intermittent sounds produced during sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> It has been linked to various health implications, including CVD such as HTN, CHD, and stroke.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Our study contributes to the existing literature by providing further evidence of the association between snoring and CVD risk. Snoring may predispose individuals to AF, which is the most common cardiac arrhythmia.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> This can occur through various mechanisms, such as hypoxemia, hypercapnia, and subsequent increases in blood pressure and heart rate.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Snoring can lead to intermittent hypoxia, resulting in oxidative stress and inflammatory responses in the body.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Snoring may consequently result in endothelial dysfunction and organ dysfunction.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Snoring can impact lipid and protein metabolism at the genetic level, potentially leading to an elevated CVD risk.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, these results have paid little attention to the difference sex.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Sex differences in the association between snoring and CVD risk were also evident in our study. Male participants demonstrated a higher risk of CVD events compared to females. This finding highlights the importance of considering gender-specific factors when assessing the relationship between snoring and CVD health. The overactivation of the sympathetic nervous system is not only crucial in the early stages of hypertension development, but is also associated with several comorbidities commonly linked to hypertension.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Males have higher sympathetic nervous system activity than females, which may explain the higher risk of hypertension in male patients with similar snoring conditions.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> This is consistent with our research findings. Hormonal differences, anatomical variations, and sleep patterns may contribute to the observed gender disparities.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Indeed, estrogen has been found to have the ability to modulate the excitability of the sympathetic nervous system and regulate endothelial function.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Sex hormones have been suggested to influence the reabsorption of renal sodium and vascular resistance, which could potentially explain the differences in hypertension observed between men and women.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> This might partially explain the gender difference in hypertension among patients with snoring.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Our study has identified a correlation between snoring and an elevated risk of atrial fibrillation (AF). Previous studies have also established a link between sleep apnea and an increased risk of AF.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> The co-occurrence of snoring and sleep apnea in some of our patients suggests a potential explanation for the heightened risk observed in our study. We found that the risk of AF in male snoring patients is nearly five times that of females. Although previous studies have confirmed the association between snoring and AF,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> there have been no studies that have examined whether this association differs by sex. Differences in atrial anatomy or tissue fibrosis may be involved in sex-specific responses to snoring in the development of AF.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Females exhibit a greater anti-inflammatory profile as a compensatory mechanism, mediated by the angiotensin type 2 receptor.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Postmenopausal women face an elevated risk of AF.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Cardiac fibrosis is crucial for the development of AF.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The more pronounced fibrosis in women may be associated with the upregulation of the TGFβ/Smad3 pathway and older age.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In our study, female patients had an average age of approximately 47 years, which may, in part, account for the gender disparities in the link between snoring and AF. Male cardiomyocytes exhibited greater late sodium current, calcium transients, and sarcoplasmic reticulum calcium content in the left atrial posterior wall than female cardiomyocytes, potentially contributing to increased ectopic activity.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Male mice had faster spontaneous beating rates in the pulmonary veins, greater burst firing, and longer periods of delayed afterdepolarizations compared to female mice.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Sympathetic stimulation can also contribute to the promotion of AF through various mechanisms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> This includes increasing the release of calcium ions (Ca2+), which can influence the conduction properties and refractoriness of cardiac tissue.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Additionally, sympathetic stimulation can lead to the formation of afterdepolarizations, which are abnormal electrical events in cardiac cells, and these afterdepolarizations can trigger or sustain AF.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Males have higher sympathetic nervous system activity than females.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> This may potentially explain the elevated risk of AF in male patients with snoring. It has been confirmed that female snoring patients have a higher risk of CVDs compared to males in this study. Currently, there appears to be a tendency to focus more on the CVD health of male snoring patients, which includes healthcare professionals, while potentially overlooking the significance of snoring in female patients.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Similarly, male snoring patients have a significantly higher rate of referrals to higher-level hospitals compared to female snoring patients, enabling them to receive better treatment.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, women with AF were more frequently symptomatic than men, and they experienced more severe symptoms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In previous studies, women with AF exhibited notably higher rates of life-threatening adverse events, such as the development of acquired long QT syndrome when treated with class Ia or III antiarrhythmic drugs.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Compared to male patients, female atrial fibrillation patients have a higher rate of surgical complications, and the surgical outcomes are also less favorable.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Therefore, it’s crucial to also pay attention to female snorers.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Our study underscores the distinct gender disparities in the connection between snoring and CVDs, notably atrial fibrillation. Nonetheless, the underlying mechanisms and clinical characteristics are intricate. Further research into gender variations in the correlation between snoring and CVDs is imperative. Additional cohort studies or interventional studies are required to investigate the potential causal association between snoring and CVDs. Nevertheless, these discoveries carry substantial implications for the implementation of clinical practices for preventing CVDs. There is a need for increased clinical awareness and focused screening for snoring and cardiovascular risk factors in male. Moreover, it is imperative to advocate for the implementation of routine screening for snoring in primary care settings, with a particular focus on male individuals who snore. Simultaneously, public health initiatives should focus on increasing awareness and providing community-based screening programs to facilitate early detection and management of CVDs in this male. Developing targeted clinical guidelines and health policies specifically for men may be more effective in reducing the cardiovascular disease risks associated with snoring.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Limitations</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Limitations to the present study deserve attention. Firstly, despite adjusting for numerous potential confounders in the statistical models, the outcomes of the current study, being observational in nature, may have been influenced by unaccounted-for cardiovascular disease and snoring risk factors. Secondly, the reliance on self-reported data, particularly regarding snoring frequency and CVD risk factors, may introduce recall bias and misclassification. Finally, our findings can only demonstrate the existence of an association between snoring and CVD, rather than a causal relationship between the two. Further longitudinal studies are needed to investigate whether duration of increased snoring has cumulative effects on CVD.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our study has revealed a significant correlation between snoring and CVD, with notable differences observed between sexes. Among snoring patients, males demonstrated a higher CVD risk compared to females. Male snorers have approximately five times the risk of developing AF and roughly double the risk of CAD compared to female patients. Increased clinical awareness and targeted screening for snoring in men can help reduce cardiovascular disease risks. Developing specific guidelines and policies for men may be more effective in addressing this issue.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Ethics Approval</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The NHANES study received approval from the Institutional Review Board of the National Center for Health Statistics (No. Continuation of Protocol #2011-17 and Protocol #2018-01). More information can be found at </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhanes/irba98.htm" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nhanes/irba98.htm</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. Due to the NHANES data being publicly available, this study is exempted by our institutional ethics committee.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0008">
      <title>Consent to Participate</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">All participants provided written informed consent.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0009">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation, or in all these areas; took part in drafting, revising or critically reviewing the article; gave final approval of the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0010">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Benjamin</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Muntner</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alonso</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Heart disease and stroke statistics-2019 update: a report from the American heart association</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circulation</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>139</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e56</fpage>–<lpage>e528</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIR.0000000000000659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30700139</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Roth</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mensah</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>CO</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Global burden of cardiovascular diseases and risk factors, 1990-2019: update from the gbd 2019 study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>76</volume>(<issue>25</issue>):<fpage>2982</fpage>–<lpage>3021</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2020.11.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33309175</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lloyd-Jones</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huffman</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Karmali</surname>
<given-names>KN</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Estimating longitudinal risks and benefits from cardiovascular preventive therapies among medicare patients: the million hearts longitudinal ASCVD risk assessment tool: a special report from the American heart association and American college of cardiology</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circulation</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>135</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>e793</fpage>–<lpage>e813</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIR.0000000000000467</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27815375</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mokhlesi</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Varga</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea and cardiovascular disease. rem sleep matters!</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>197</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>554</fpage>–<lpage>556</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201710-2147ED</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29141154</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Alshaer</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hummel</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mendelson</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marshal</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bradley</surname>
<given-names>TD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Objective relationship between sleep apnea and frequency of snoring assessed by machine learning</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>463</fpage>–<lpage>470</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.7676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30853041</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Al Shaikh</surname>
<given-names>YG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haytham Shieb</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koruturk</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alghefari</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hassan</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mussa</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The symptoms and risk of sleep apnea among adults in the United Arab Emirates</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Thorac Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>168</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/atm.ATM_245_17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30123336</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Teculescu</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hannhart</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cornette</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Montaut-Verient</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Virion</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Michaely</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalence of habitual snoring in a sample of French males. role of ”minor” nose-throat abnormalities</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Respiration; Intl Rev Thorac Dis</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>365</fpage>–<lpage>370</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000050528</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Michalek-Zrabkowska</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martynowicz</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wieckiewicz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smardz</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poreba</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mazur</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cardiovascular implications of sleep bruxism-a systematic review with narrative summary and future perspectives</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2245</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm10112245</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34064229</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baguet</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Courand</surname>
<given-names>PY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lequeux</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Snoring but not sleepiness is associated with increased aortic root diameter in hypertensive patients. The SLEEPART study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>202</volume>:<fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>132</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijcard.2015.03.319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26397400</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Xiong</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhong</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between self-reported habitual snoring and diabetes mellitus: a systemic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Diabetes Res</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>2016</volume>:<fpage>1958981</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2016/1958981</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26904689</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ikehara</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Iso</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Date</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>JS: association of sleep duration with mortality from cardiovascular disease and other causes for Japanese men and women: the JACC study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>295</fpage>–<lpage>301</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/32.3.295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19294949</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Marshall</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cullen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knuiman</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grunstein</surname>
<given-names>RJS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep apnea as an independent risk factor for all-cause mortality: the Busselton health study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1079</fpage>–<lpage>1085</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18714779</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Holtzman</surname>
<given-names>JN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaur</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hansen</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bushana</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gulati</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sex differences in the management of atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Atherosclerosis</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>384</volume>:<fpage>117268</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.atherosclerosis.2023.117268</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37723005</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Champney</surname>
<given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frederick</surname>
<given-names>PD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bueno</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The joint contribution of sex, age and type of myocardial infarction on hospital mortality following acute myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Heart</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>95</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>895</fpage>–<lpage>899</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/hrt.2008.155804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19147625</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ahmed</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dauerman</surname>
<given-names>HL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Women, bleeding, and coronary intervention</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circulation</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>127</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>641</fpage>–<lpage>649</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.112.108290</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23381962</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mong</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cusmano</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sex differences in sleep: impact of biological sex and sex steroids</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Philos Trans R Soc London, Ser B</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>371</volume>(<issue>1688</issue>):<fpage>20150110</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2015.0110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26833831</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Garcia</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mulvagh</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Merz</surname>
<given-names>CN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buring</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Manson</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cardiovascular disease in women: clinical perspectives</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circ Res</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>118</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1273</fpage>–<lpage>1293</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.116.307547</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27081110</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Karastergiou</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Greenberg</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fried</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sex differences in human adipose tissues - the biology of pear shape</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biol Sex Differ</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>13</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2042-6410-3-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22651247</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kaplan</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Keil</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Socioeconomic factors and cardiovascular disease: a review of the literature</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circulation</italic></source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>88</volume>(<issue>4 Pt 1</issue>):<fpage>1973</fpage>–<lpage>1998</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.CIR.88.4.1973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8403348</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Emslie</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hunt</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macintyre</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>How similar are the smoking and drinking habits of men and women in non-manual jobs?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurpub/12.1.22</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11968516</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Everett</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brooks</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vlachos</surname>
<given-names>HEA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chaitman</surname>
<given-names>BR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frye</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bhatt</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sex differences in cardiac troponin and the risk of death or major cardiovascular events</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>978</fpage>–<lpage>980</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2016.06.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27561773</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Akinbami</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davy</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey, 2017-March 2020 Prepandemic File: Sample Design, Estimation, and Analytic Guidelines</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vital Health Stat</italic></source>. <volume>2022</volume>(<issue>190</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aljawadi</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khoja</surname>
<given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>BaHammam</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alyahya</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alkhalifah</surname>
<given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>AlGhmadi</surname>
<given-names>OK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Determining the prevalence of symptoms and risk of obstructive sleep apnoea among old Saudis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Taibah Univ Sci</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>402</fpage>–<lpage>412</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtumed.2020.10.024</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration, snoring habits and risk of acute myocardial infarction in China population: results of the INTERHEART study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>531</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-14-531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24885282</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nagayoshi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tanigawa</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yamagishi</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Self-reported snoring frequency and incidence of cardiovascular disease: the circulatory risk in communities study (CIRCS)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>295</fpage>–<lpage>301</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2188/jea.JE20110109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22447210</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Palinkas</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marrara</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bataglion</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Analysis of the sleep period and the amount of habitual snoring in individuals with sleep bruxism</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Med Oral Patologia Oral y Cirugia Bucal</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e782</fpage>–<lpage>e786</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4317/medoral.23136</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Endeshaw</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rice</surname>
<given-names>TB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schwartz</surname>
<given-names>AV</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Snoring, daytime sleepiness, and incident cardiovascular disease in the health, aging, and body composition study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1737</fpage>–<lpage>1745</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.3140</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24179308</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shivalkar</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van de Heyning</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kerremans</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea syndrome: more insights on structural and functional cardiac alterations, and the effects of treatment with continuous positive airway pressure</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1433</fpage>–<lpage>1439</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2005.11.054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16580533</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Titova</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yuan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baron</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lindberg</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Michaëlsson</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Larsson</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Self-reported symptoms of sleep-disordered breathing and risk of cardiovascular diseases: observational and Mendelian randomization findings</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e13681</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.13681</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35869582</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Marulanda-Londoño</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chaturvedi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The interplay between obstructive sleep apnea and atrial fibrillation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>668</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fneur.2017.00668</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29312113</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lavie</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Intermittent hypoxia: the culprit of oxidative stress, vascular inflammation and dyslipidemia in obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Expert Rev Respir Med</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1586/17476348.2.1.75</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20477224</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Loke</surname>
<given-names>YK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kwok</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Niruban</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Myint</surname>
<given-names>PK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association of obstructive sleep apnea with risk of serious cardiovascular events: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circ Cardiovasc Qual Outcomes</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>720</fpage>–<lpage>728</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCOUTCOMES.111.964783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22828826</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wain</surname>
<given-names>LV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shrine</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Artigas</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Genome-wide association analyses for lung function and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease identify new loci and potential druggable targets</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nature Genet</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>416</fpage>–<lpage>425</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3787</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28166213</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>DeLalio</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sved</surname>
<given-names>AF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stocker</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sympathetic nervous system contributions to hypertension: updates and therapeutic relevance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Can J Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>712</fpage>–<lpage>720</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cjca.2020.03.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32389344</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Du</surname>
<given-names>XJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dart</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Riemersma</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sex differences in the parasympathetic nerve control of rat heart</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Exp Pharmacol Physiol</italic></source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>485</fpage>–<lpage>493</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1681.1994.tb02545.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7982279</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Raymond</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Norton</surname>
<given-names>GR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Woodiwiss</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brooksbank</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Impact of gender and menopausal status on relationships between biological aging, as indexed by telomere length, and aortic stiffness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Hypertens</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>623</fpage>–<lpage>630</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ajh/hpu212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25413841</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mercuro</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Podda</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pitzalis</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Evidence of a role of endogenous estrogen in the modulation of autonomic nervous system</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am j Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>85</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>787</fpage>–<lpage>789</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0002-9149(99)00865-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12000064</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schulman</surname>
<given-names>IH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aranda</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raij</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Veronesi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aranda</surname>
<given-names>FJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Surgical menopause increases salt sensitivity of blood pressure</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1168</fpage>–<lpage>1174</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.HYP.0000218857.67880.75</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16618835</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ashraf</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vongpatanasin</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Estrogen and hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Hypertens Rep</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>368</fpage>–<lpage>376</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11906-006-0080-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16965722</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mehra</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benjamin</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shahar</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of nocturnal arrhythmias with sleep-disordered breathing: the sleep heart health study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>173</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>910</fpage>–<lpage>916</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.200509-1442OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16424443</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Colangelo</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lloyd-Jones</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of sleep apnea and snoring with incident atrial fibrillation in the multi-ethnic study of atherosclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>182</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwv004</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Forleo</surname>
<given-names>GB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tondo</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Luca</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Gender-related differences in catheter ablation of atrial fibrillation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">EP Europace</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>613</fpage>–<lpage>620</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/europace/eum144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17636302</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cochet</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mouries</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nivet</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Age, atrial fibrillation, and structural heart disease are the main determinants of left atrial fibrosis detected by delayed-enhanced magnetic resonance imaging in a general cardiology population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>484</fpage>–<lpage>492</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jce.12651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25727248</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gillis</surname>
<given-names>EE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sullivan</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sex differences in hypertension: recent advances</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1322</fpage>–<lpage>1327</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.116.06602</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27777357</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ko</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rahman</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martins</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Atrial fibrillation in women: treatment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>124</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrcardio.2016.171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27786235</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pfannmüller</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boldt</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reutemann</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Gender-specific remodeling in atrial fibrillation?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>61</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>66</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0032-1332795</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tsai</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>YC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kao</surname>
<given-names>YH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>YY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>YJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Distinctive sodium and calcium regulation associated with sex differences in atrial electrophysiology of rabbits</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>168</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>4658</fpage>–<lpage>4666</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijcard.2013.07.183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23953257</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tsai</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>YC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>YK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>YJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sex differences in the electrophysiological characteristics of pulmonary veins and left atrium and their clinical implication in atrial fibrillation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circ Arrhythm Electrophysiol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>550</fpage>–<lpage>559</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCEP.111.961995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21659634</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Insulander</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Juhlin-Dannfelt</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Freyschuss</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vallin</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Electrophysiologic effects of mental stress in healthy subjects: a comparison with epinephrine infusion</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Electrocardiol</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>301</fpage>–<lpage>309</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-0736(03)00078-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14661166</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sawatari</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chishaki</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ando</surname>
<given-names>SI</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The epidemiology of sleep disordered breathing and hypertension in various populations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Hypertens Rev</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>12</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1573402112666160114093307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26778203</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Larsson</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lindberg</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Franklin</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lundbäck</surname>
<given-names>BJC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Gender differences in symptoms related to sleep apnea in a general population and in relation to referral to sleep clinic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>124</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>204</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.124.1.204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12853524</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Linde</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bongiorni</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Birgersdotter-Green</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sex differences in cardiac arrhythmia: a consensus document of the European heart rhythm association, endorsed by the heart rhythm society and Asia Pacific heart rhythm society</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Europace</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1565</fpage>–<lpage>1565ao</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/europace/euy067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29961863</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rienstra</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Veldhuisen</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hagens</surname>
<given-names>VE</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Gender-related differences in rhythm control treatment in persistent atrial fibrillation: data of the rate control versus electrical cardioversion (RACE) study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1298</fpage>–<lpage>1306</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2005.05.078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16198847</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lehmann</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Timothy</surname>
<given-names>KW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frankovich</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Age-gender influence on the rate-corrected QT interval and the QT-heart rate relation in families with genotypically characterized long QT syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0735-1097(96)00454-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8996300</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0055">
        <label>55.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deshmukh</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thakkar</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Gender, race, and health insurance status in patients undergoing catheter ablation for atrial fibrillation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am j Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>117</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1117</fpage>–<lpage>1126</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjcard.2016.01.040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26899494</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0056">
        <label>56.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>YT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>YL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kang</surname>
<given-names>HY</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Revealing the influences of sex hormones and sex differences in atrial fibrillation and vascular cognitive impairment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Mol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>8776</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms22168776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34445515</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
