<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39100907</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">11298188</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">466283</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S466283</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Associations Between Sleep Duration and Cardiometabolic Diseases Among Residents in Southwest China</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Li et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Li et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0009-0007-3098-7570</contrib-id><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Jinxi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Yiduo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0009-0003-4117-148X</contrib-id><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xuyun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Gang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>International Medical College, Chongqing Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Chongqing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>College of Basic Medical Sciences, Naval Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Cardiology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Chongqing Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Chongqing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Gang Liu, Email 203745@hospital.cqmu.edu.cn</corresp><fn id="ft0001"><label>*</label><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">These authors contributed equally to this work</citation_analysis></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>1121</fpage><lpage>1130</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Li et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Li et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">The burden of cardiometabolic diseases (CMDs), defined as stroke, coronary artery disease, and diabetes mellitus, continues to pose a global challenge. Sleep duration has been linked to cardiovascular health. However, there is a lack of focused investigations on CMDs in underdeveloped areas of China.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Purpose</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This study aimed to examine the relationship between sleep duration and CMDs among residents from southwest China.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Patients and Methods</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This large cross-sectional study screened data from the National Key Research and Development Program (2018YFC1311400). Based on sleep duration reported through a standardized questionnaire, encompassing the sleep patterns of the past five years, participants were classified into three groups: &lt;6, 6–8, &gt;8 hours. Baseline characteristics were compared, and Poisson regression models were used to assess the relationship between sleep duration and CMDs. Subgroup analysis was conducted based on age and gender.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This study included 28,908 participants with an average age of 65.6 ± 10.0 years, of whom 57.6% were female. The overall prevalence of CMDs was 22.6%. After multivariate adjustments, the prevalence ratios (PR) (95% CI) for CMDs across the three groups (6–8h, &lt;6h and &gt;8h) were: reference, 1.140 (1.068–1.218), 1.060 (0.961–1.169) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P <sub>for trend</sub></italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> =0.003), respectively. The subgroup analysis revealed that among older females, a longer sleep duration (&gt;8h) was also associated with an increased prevalence risk of CMDs, with PR 1.169 (1.001–1.365) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=0.049).</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">A shorter sleep duration (&lt;6 hours) was associated with an increased risk of CMDs in the general population, while a longer sleep duration (&gt;8 hours) also raised the prevalence risk among older females.</citation_analysis></p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>cardiometabolic disease</kwd><kwd>sleep duration</kwd><kwd>Southwest China</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>the cultivation fund of the First Affiliated Hospital of Chongqing</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This study is supported by the cultivation fund of the First Affiliated Hospital of Chongqing Medical University, No. PYJJ2019-25.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="3"/><ref-count count="33"/><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Cardiometabolic diseases (CMDs), including stroke, coronary artery disease (CAD), and diabetes mellitus (DM), have significantly contributed to the escalating global burden of disease and disability in recent years.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In China, stroke has emerged as the leading cause of both mortality and morbidity, with a pooled annual prevalence rate of 1.33%.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Moreover, CAD had a prevalence rate exceeding 0.81% in 2022, playing a prominent role in cardiovascular-related mortality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> DM, driven by the surge in obesity rates, stands out as another notable chronic condition projected to affect approximately 45.86% of individuals by 2040.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In recent decades, there has been a decline in individuals’ sleep duration attributed to shifts in personal lifestyles, socio-economic factors, work patterns, and global development.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5–7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Existing research has indicated that reduced sleep duration is associated with an increased incidence of stroke, cardiovascular diseases, and DM.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8–10</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Some studies have demonstrated a U-shaped relationship between sleep duration and the occurrence of DM and cardiovascular events, suggesting that both insufficient and excessive sleep can lead to adverse health outcomes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10–12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, no association between sleep duration and cardiometabolic outcomes in adolescents was also reported.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">China is currently facing a formidable challenge in terms of managing cardiovascular disease, as the incidence and mortality rates continue to rise annually. Furthermore, since 2012, rural areas have experienced significantly higher mortality rates from cardiovascular disease compared to urban areas.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Despite numerous studies having explored the impact of sleep duration on specific diseases globally, especially in developed country, investigations focusing on the concept of CMDs remain limited, especially among Chinese population and in low-income area of the country. Therefore, this study aims to investigate associations between sleep duration and CMDs among residents in southwest China.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Material and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Study Design</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This project is a sub-project of the National Key Research and Development Program (2018YFC1311400) aimed at establishing a solid foundation for the prevention and treatment of chronic cardiovascular diseases. Under the guidance of Chongqing Municipal Health Commission and local Centers for Disease Control, from August 2018 to December 2020, the Cardiovascular Department of the First Affiliated Hospital of Chongqing Medical University conducted a comprehensive cross-sectional investigation by employing phased stratified random sampling on community residents in 16 districts or counties located in southwest China.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The study flow chart was presented in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative">, with local community doctors serving as the investigators. The survey primarily consisted of face-to-face questionnaires and a few telephone interviews. Data were entered into the research system by skilled data entry clerks, who conducted stratified sampling checks to ensure the authenticity and reliability of the data.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The study flow chart.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1121-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Residents aged 18 years or older who had been registered residents in their respective communities for a minimum of 6 months were enrolled. A total of 32,709 participants were assessed, with 3,801 excluded due to (1) missing or inaccurate sleeping data (n=2687), and (2) missing CMDs data (n=1114). Ultimately, the analysis was conducted on a cohort of 28,908 residents.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Definition of Terms</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The dataset comprised demographic information, family medical history, dietary and lifestyle factors, sleep duration, physical examinations, and serum biochemical tests. Participants were asked to recall their living conditions over the past five years.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Both alcohol consumption and smoking were habitual practices that occurred at least three times per week. The term “well-educated” referred to individuals who had completed at least a high school education or higher. “High income” was defined as an average personal income exceeding 5000 RMB per month. “Physical inactivity” was characterized by engaging in outdoor activities less than 20 hours per week. “Vegetables insufficiency” indicated a weekly intake of vegetables less than three days. “Fruits consumption habit” was defined as a weekly intake of fruits for more than five days. Finally, the term “cardiac-cerebral vascular disease (CCVD) family history” encompassed any documented occurrence of cardiovascular or cerebrovascular diseases in a first-degree relative.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The investigators conducted physical examinations and performed serum biochemical tests. Height and weight measurements were taken with lightweight clothing, while heart rate and blood pressure were recorded as an average from three readings after a five-minute rest. The heart rate was measured using a stethoscope to record the number of heart beats per minute, while the blood pressure was measured using an electronic or mercury sphygmomanometer. Both blood lipid and glucose tests were carried out following a minimum fasting period of seven hours. All measuring instruments and equipment were provided by the community doctors’ units.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">DM was defined as the presence of at least one of the following criteria:</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> (a) Fasting plasma glucose (FPG) level of ≥7.0 mmol/L, (b) 2 hours- post challenge plasma glucose level of ≥11.1 mmol/L, (c) pharmacologically treated with glucose-lowering medications.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The definition of CAD included coronary artery stenosis exceeding 50%, which was confirmed by documented medical records through computed tomography angiography (CTA) or percutaneous coronary angiography (CAG), regardless of the presence of ischemic symptoms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Stroke includes ischemic or hemorrhagic stroke as demonstrated by cranial imaging.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">CMDs were defined as any one of DM, CAD or stroke.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The three conditions must be supported by clear medical records from a secondary or higher-level medical institutions.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep duration refers to the total amount of time obtained during the nocturnal sleep episode.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Participants were categorized into three groups based on their self-reported average daily sleep duration pattern over the past five years: &lt;6 hours, 6–8 hours, and &gt;8 hours. The primary outcomes examined were CMDs and its components.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Continuous variables following a normal distribution were expressed as mean ± standard deviation (SD). Differences between groups were compared using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) if the variances were uniformed. Otherwise, skewed distributions were expressed as the median and quartile ranges (25%-75%), and the Kruskal–Wallis test was utilized. Categorical variables were represented by cases with percentages, and differences between groups were compared using the Pearson chi-square test.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The Poisson regression models were utilized to ascertain the association between sleep duration and CMDs as well as its components. These models were adjusted for disease-related variables, and each prevalence ratio (PR) value along with its 95% confidence interval (CI) was computed. We initially performed univariate regression analysis to identify the factors influencing the outcome variables in the baseline data (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> &lt; 0.05), and subsequently included them individually for multivariate regression analysis. Furthermore, considering the close association of CMDs with age and gender, subgroup analyses based on age and sex were conducted to validate the robustness of our findings. The demarcation between the younger and older age was set at 65 years.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The data were analyzed using SPSS version 25.0 (IBM, USA), and GraphPad Prism 8.4.3 was utilized for generating the figures. All statistical tests were two-tailed, and a significance level of </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.05 was applied.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The present study was a retrospective cross-sectional analysis that included 28,908 participants ranging in age from 20 to 98 years old, with a mean age of 65.6 ± 10.0 years. Among the participants, 57.6% were female. The data presented in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> indicates that only 29.0% of the general population slept for a duration of 7 hours per day, with proportions of the three groups (6–8h, &lt;6h, &gt;8h) being 74.9%, 18.6%, and 6.5% respectively.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The distribution of sleep duration among the general population (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) and three groups (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1121-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">According to </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">, individuals with a sleep duration of less than 6 hours tended to be older, more likely to have a family history of CCVD, lower income, physical inactivity, and insufficient vegetable intake. They also exhibited higher systolic and diastolic blood pressure levels but had lower weight and body mass index. Additionally, they had slower heart rates and lower levels of triglycerides and fasting glucose.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Baseline Data at Enrollment Grouped by Sleeping Duration</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Characteristics at enrollment</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Overall N=28,908</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Sleeping duration, hrs/day</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">6–8 h n=21,662</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 6 h n=5375</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; 8h n=1871</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, yrs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.6 ± 10.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.8 ± 10.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.3 ± 7.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.6 ± 11.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female gender, n%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,660 (57.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,585 (58.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2994 (55.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1081(57.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rural residents, n%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8378 (29.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5792 (26.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2052 (38.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">534 (39.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Well educated, n%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2773 (9.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2330 (10.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">196 (3.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">247 (13.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCVD family history, n%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1874 (6.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">775 (3.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1059 (19.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (2.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High income, n%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3598 (12.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3160 (14.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">167 (3.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">271 (14.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Lifestyles</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Alcohol consumption, n%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3704 (12.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2804 (12.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">690 (12.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">210 (11.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.102</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Smoking, n%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4345 (15.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3304 (15.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">803 (14.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">238 (12.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sleeping duration, hrs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0 (6.0–8.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0 (6.0–8.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0 (5.0–5.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0 (9.0–10.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Physical inactivity, n%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3639 (12.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2395 (11.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1072 (19.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">172 (9.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Vegetables insufficiency, n%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1451 (5.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1103 (5.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">301 (5.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Fruits consumption habit, n%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,649 (43.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,210 (47.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1402 (26.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1037 (55.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Physical examinations</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Height, cm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">155.4 ± 8.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">155.7 ± 8.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">154.1 ± 8.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">155.9 ± 8.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Weight, kg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.9 ± 10.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.3 ± 10.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.9 ± 9.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.3 ± 10.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> BMI, kg/m<sup>2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.3 ± 3.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.4 ± 3.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.9 ± 3.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.3 ± 3.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Heart rate, bpm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.4 ± 10.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.5 ± 10.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.0 ± 10.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.0 ± 10.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> SBP, mmHg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">138.9 ± 19.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">138.3 ± 19.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">140.9 ± 18.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">138.9 ± 19.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> DBP, mmHg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.0 ± 11.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.6 ± 11.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.3 ± 11.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.8 ± 11.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Serum biochemical tests</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> TG, mmol/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (0.9–1.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (0.9–1.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (0.90–1.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (0.9–2.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> TC, mmol/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0 (4.3–5.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0 (4.3–5.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1 (4.4–5.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8 (4.1–5.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HDL-C, mmol/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5 (1.3–1.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5 (1.3–1.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 (1.3–1.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 (1.2–1.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> LDL-C, mmol/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6 (2.0–3.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6 (2.0–3.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7 (2.1–3.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4 (1.9–3.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Fasting glucose, mmol/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7 ± 1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8 ± 1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6 ± 1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7 ± 1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: CCVD, cardiac-cerebral vascular disease; BMI, body mass index; SBP: systolic blood pressure; DBP, diastolic blood pressure; TG, triglycerides; TC, total cholesterol; HDL-C, high density lipoprotein cholesterol; LDL-C, low density lipoprotein cholesterol.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">On the other hand, residents with a sleep duration exceeding 8 hours were slightly more educated, less likely to smoke, and more inclined towards consuming fruits. They also had greater height but lower cholesterol levels.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The overall prevalence rates of CMDs, DM, stroke, and CAD were 22.6%, 18.6%, 1.6%, and 3.7% respectively (displayed in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). Residents with a sleep duration of less than 6 hours had the highest prevalence rate. After multivariate adjustments (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">), the PR (95% CI) for CMDs across the three sleep duration groups (6–8h, &lt;6h, and &gt;8h) were: reference, 1.140 (1.068–1.218), 1.060 (0.961–1.169) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P <sub>for trend</sub></italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> =0.003), respectively.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Prevalence of Cardiometabolic Diseases Among Different Groups</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Comorbidity</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Overall N=28,908</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Sleeping duration, hrs/day</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">6–8 h n=21,662</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 6 h n=5375</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; 8hn=1871</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMDs, n%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6521 (22.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4730 (21.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1352 (25.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">439 (23.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> DM, n%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5365 (18.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3917 (18.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1081 (20.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">367 (19.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Stroke, n%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">475 (1.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">320 (1.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">126 (2.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (1.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Ischemic stroke, n%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">408 ((1.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">276 (1.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109 (2.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (1.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Hemorrhagic stroke, n%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93 (0.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (0.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (0.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (0.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.232</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> CAD, n%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1077 (3.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">763 (3.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">240 (4.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 (4.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: CMDs, cardiometabolic diseases; DM, diabetes mellitus; CAD, coronary artery disease.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Associations Between Sleep Duration with Cardiometabolic Diseases After Adjustments</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Models</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">6–8h</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;6h PR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P value</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;8h PR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P value</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P <sub>for trend</sub></italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crude</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.152 (1.084–1.224)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.075 (0.974–1.185)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.150</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.103 (1.038–1.173)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.077 (0.976–1.187)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.139</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.123 (1.056–1.194)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.073 (0.973–1.183)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.159</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.140 (1.068–1.218)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.060 (0.961–1.169)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.244</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: The Poisson regression was employed. Crude: univariate adjustment by group of sleeping duration. Model 1: adjusted by crude + age (continuous variable). Model 2: adjusted by model 1 + female gender + height (continuous variable). Model 3: adjusted by model 2 + rural residents + well educated + CCVD family history + high income + smoking + physical inactivity + vegetables insufficiency + fruits consumption habit.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: PR, prevalence ratio; CCVD, cardiac-cerebral vascular disease.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">As displayed in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">, except for the older male subgroup, the association between shorter sleep duration (&lt;6h) and an increased risk of CMDs remained consistent across all subgroup analyses based on age and gender. In the gender subgroup analysis, it was found that among females, particularly older females, a longer sleep duration (&gt;8h) also significantly elevated the prevalence risk of CMDs, with PR 1.169 (1.001–1.365) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=0.049) (refer to </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=466283.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Tables 1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=466283.docx" ext-link-type="uri">2</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">)
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The relationship between sleep duration with CMD among general population (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) and different subgroups (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1121-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In analyses of CMD subcomponents, a shorter sleep duration (&lt;6 h) was associated with an increased risk of DM across all subgroups, including women who slept for longer durations (&gt;8 h). Additionally, among women, a shorter sleep duration (&lt;6 h) was also linked to an elevated risk of CAD. On the other hand, a longer sleep duration (&gt;8 h) was associated with an increased risk of hemorrhagic stroke in the elderly population (aged ≥65 years old). Conversely, no statistically significant correlation between stroke or CAD and sleep duration was observed in the subgroups of individuals aged younger than 65 years or among males (refer to </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=466283.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This study examined the association between self-reported sleep duration and CMDs among adults in southwest China. Epidemiological data from the sample revealed that 74.9% of the population in southwest China reported sleeping for 6 to 8 hours, while the overall prevalence of CMDs was found to be 22.6%, which closely aligns with the prevalence of 24.2% observed in the UK Biobank population.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> In comparison to residents who slept for 6–8 hours, those who slept less than 6 hours exhibited an increased risk of CMDs. Additionally, this elevated CMDs risk was also observed specifically in older females who slept over 8 hours.</citation_analysis></p>
      <sec id="s0004-s2001">
        <title>Sleep Duration and CMDs</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Previous research conducted in various global contexts consistently reveals a U-shaped relationship, whereby both short and long sleep durations are associated with an increased risk of cardiovascular diseases, stroke, and DM.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10–12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> The impact of sleep duration on the risk factors and outcomes of these CMDs remains consistent.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Furthermore, there exists a mutual influence and reciprocal relationship among CMDs that renders them interrelated risk factors to one another.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">The complex interrelation is exemplified by instances such as cardiovascular diseases and DM, collectively constituting risk factors for stroke, as evidenced in existing literature.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In the context of cardiovascular diseases, age plays a crucial role as the U-shaped curve becomes more pronounced with advancing age.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> However, certain studies have not verified the impact of prolonged sleep duration on the risk of CAD and hypertension, which are key factors for CMDs.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This research demonstrated that in southwestern China, a sleep duration of less than 6 hours was associated with an increased risk of CMDs across the general population, consistent with findings from other investigations.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Furthermore, it was also observed that a sleep duration exceeding 8 hours was associated with an elevated risk of CMDs in women, as well as an increased susceptibility to hemorrhagic stroke in the elderly population. This finding suggests the possible presence of a U-shaped curve relationship between sleep duration and CMDs.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Interestingly, in the subgroup analysis, no statistically significant correlation between stroke or CAD and sleep duration was observed in the subgroups of young and male individuals. This finding is consistent with some research on cardiometabolic risks in adolescents before.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> However, although sleep duration was not shown to directly affect cardiovascular health when people were young, some risk factors such as sleep quality, life and diet behaviors can be influenced. Research with longer follow-up is needed to explore whether there is future impact.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2002">
        <title>Potential Mechanisms and Intervention</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The mechanisms by which sleep duration influences CMDs are intricate and diverse. Short sleep duration is implicated in the alteration of leptin and ghrelin levels, subsequently affecting appetite and energy balance within the human body, leading to obesity, which is a risk factor for CMDs.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Conversely, respiratory disorders and inflammatory markers associated with obesity can also impact both the duration and quality of sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Furthermore, there is evidence suggesting a causal relationship between stroke and the development of sleep disorders, accompanied by changes in circadian rhythm dynamics.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> As a result, CMDs and sleep duration mutually influence each other.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">In terms of blood pressure regulation, insufficient sleep duration can contribute to hypertension by affecting muscle relaxation and sympathetic tone modulation.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Additionally, inadequate sleep duration can lead to abnormal lipid metabolism, glucose intolerance, insulin resistance, and vascular calcification—significant factors contributing to stroke, CAD, and DM.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Disease such as obstructive sleep apnea, which has an impact on both sleep duration and quality, was reported as an independent risk factor of CMDs. The underlying mechanism including hypoxia, generation of reactive oxygen species, inflammation, and sympathetic activation.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21–23</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In the intervention and prevention of CMDs and their associated risk factors, evidence suggests that systematically screening and managing sleep disorders can significantly contribute to primary and secondary prevention of CMDs, improve prognosis, and reduce overall mortality rates.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Improving sleep duration and quality reduces the threat of CMDs risk factors by enhancing the effectiveness of weight loss interventions and promoting healthy blood pressure conditions.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Therefore, strategically addressing sleep conditions and targeting diseases such as sleep apnea through improving daily habits and clinical therapy is crucial for both the general population and patients with CMDs in terms of prevention and treatment.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2003">
        <title>Sleep Status Among Chinese Population</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The average sleep duration among the Chinese population in 2022 was recorded at 7.4 hours per night.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> A significant majority of Chinese adults, over 64.8%, reported sleeping less than 8 hours.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Findings from a study conducted between 2008 and 2018 revealed an increase in both poor sleep quality and short sleep duration among the elderly population.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In 2022, it was demonstrated that approximately 41.3% of older individuals in China slept less than 6 hours per day, with an overall average of 6.5 hours.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Research conducted specifically in rural areas of China identified that 52.4% of older people slept less than seven hours.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep duration variation exhibited correlations with various factors including gender, educational attainment, socioeconomic status, familial composition, presence of chronic illnesses, and overall quality of life.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Furthermore, social issues arising from recent socioeconomic development in China such as higher divorce rates, increase smoking and alcohol abuse, weakened family bonds, and widening socioeconomic disparity between rich and poor also have a notable impact on sleep duration.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The findings of this study revealed a higher prevalence of individuals sleeping for less than 6 hours per night compared to the national average, while a lower prevalence was observed for those sleeping more than 8 hours per night. These results indicated regional disparities in sleep patterns within southwestern China when compared to the national level.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The duration of sleep has been found to be associated with various diseases affecting the neurological, cardiovascular, and endocrine systems.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Furthermore, decreased sleep duration has been linked to certain risk factors such as obesity, hypertension, and high blood lipid level.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The prevalence of obesity in 2018 in China was 51.2% and was predicted to be 70.5% in 2030, while the prevalence of hypertension in China was predicted to increase 7.9% from 2018 to 2030.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In China, the prevalence of CAD in rural area has surpassed urban area since 2016. The mortality rates of cardiovascular and cerebrovascular disease in rural area were higher than in urban region.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The observed regional disparities in sleep duration may contribute to variations in disease prevalence across distinct regions, which shows the importance of paying attention to the sleep duration of residents in economically underdeveloped areas.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Limitation</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">This study has several limitations. Firstly, it should be noted that this was a cross-sectional retrospective study, meaning that follow-up data was not available. Secondly, the reliance on self-reported sleep duration data introduces a potential source of bias as participants may exhibit variability and subjectivity in reporting their sleep habits.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Also, various factors such as illness and social-psychological state may impact sleep duration. Thirdly, the identification of patients with stroke and CAD relied solely on examining existing medical records which inherently limits the accuracy of determining prevalence and incidence rates. Latent or asymptomatic cases may have been overlooked, leading to an underestimation of true prevalence and incidence rates within the study population.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">To address these limitations, large-scale prospective studies on a selected population with documented evidence of CMDs and objective measurements of sleep durations can be conducted in the future.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Our study is among the few that directly investigate the association between sleep duration and CMDs, thereby updating the existing literature on limited Asian data, particularly in economically underdeveloped Southwestern China. Additionally, we perform subgroup analyses based on age and gender to enhance the credibility of our findings.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">In conclusion, this study demonstrates that a sleep duration (&lt;6 hours) is associated with an increased risk of CMDs in the general population, while a longer sleep duration (&gt;8 hours) also raises the prevalence risk specifically among older females. Considering the crucial role of sleep duration in lifestyle, it is imperative to implement health education and interventions targeting optimal sleep duration for primary prevention of CMDs.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors would like to express their sincere gratitude to all the participants for generously sharing their personal data, the diligent efforts of the data investigators, as well as the invaluable cooperation and assistance provided by the local hospitals and governments.</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s0007">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The data that support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0008">
      <title>Ethics Approval and Consent to Participate</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This study complies with the Declaration of Helsinki and was approved by the ethics committee of the First Affiliated Hospital of Chongqing Medical University, No. 2020-23. All the participants were informed of the study content and signed informed consent.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0009">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">All authors have no conflicts of interest to declare for this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cao</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cardiometabolic diseases, total mortality, and benefits of adherence to a healthy lifestyle: a 13-year prospective UK Biobank study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Transl Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>234</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12967-022-03439-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35590361</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hua</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ren</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Increasing burden of stroke in China: a systematic review and meta-analysis of prevalence, incidence, mortality, and case fatality</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Stroke</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>267</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/17474930221135983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36274585</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>-S-S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Epidemiology and current management of cardiovascular disease in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Geriatr Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>387</fpage>–<lpage>406</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/JAHA.117.005947</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38800543</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>YL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The prevalence, awareness, management and influencing factors of diabetes in middle-aged and elderly in China, evidence from the CHARLS in 2015</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Medicine</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>101</volume>(<issue>50</issue>):<fpage>e32348</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaneurol.2021.2876</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36550904</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cappuccio</surname>
<given-names>FP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and Cardio-Metabolic Disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Cardiol Rep</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>110</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11886-017-0916-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28929340</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Longitudinal study of the relationship between sleep duration and hypertension in Chinese adult residents (CHNS 2004-2011)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>88</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2019.01.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31132577</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Relationship of Sleep Duration with Sociodemographic Characteristics, Lifestyle, Mental Health, and Chronic Diseases in a Large Chinese Adult Population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>384</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.6484</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27998377</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kwok</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kontopantelis</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuligowski</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Self-reported sleep duration and quality and cardiovascular disease and mortality: A dose-response meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Heart Assoc</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>e008552</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/jaha.118.008552</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30371228</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lao</surname>
<given-names>XQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deng</surname>
<given-names>H-B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep quality, sleep duration, and the risk of coronary heart disease: A prospective cohort study with 60,586 adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.6894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29198294</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yin</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jin</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shan</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>relationship of sleep duration with all-cause mortality and cardiovascular events: A systematic review and dose-response meta-analysis of prospective cohort studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Heart Assoc</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>9</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/jaha.117.005947</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association between sleep duration and incidence of type 2 diabetes in China: the REACTION study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin Med J</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>135</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1242</fpage>–<lpage>1248</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/cm9.0000000000001835</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35568995</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shan</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration and risk of type 2 diabetes: a meta-analysis of prospective studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes Care</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>529</fpage>–<lpage>537</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc14-2073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25715415</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Confortin</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aristizábal</surname>
<given-names>LYG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>da Silva Magalhães</surname>
<given-names>EI</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association between sleep duration and cardiometabolic factors in adolescents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>686</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-022-13119-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35395941</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dutil</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Podinic</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sadler</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep timing and health indicators in children and adolescents: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Health Promot Chronic Dis Prev Can</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>150</fpage>–<lpage>169</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24095/hpcdp.42.4.04</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35481337</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Summary of the 2022 Report on Cardiovascular Health and Diseases in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin Med J</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>136</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>2899</fpage>–<lpage>2908</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/cm9.0000000000002927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38018129</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>ElSayed</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aleppo</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aroda</surname>
<given-names>VR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>2. classification and diagnosis of diabetes: standards of care in diabetes-2023</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes Care</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>S19</fpage>–<lpage>s40</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc23-S002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36507649</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sulava</surname>
<given-names>EF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Confortin</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Management of coronary artery disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Surg Clin North Am</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>102</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>449</fpage>–<lpage>464</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.suc.2022.01.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35671766</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hankey</surname>
<given-names>GJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Stroke</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>389</volume>(<issue>10069</issue>):<fpage>641</fpage>–<lpage>654</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0140-6736(16)30962-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27637676</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between sleep duration and hypertension among adults in Southwest China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Glob Heart</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>10</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5334/gh.1100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35342697</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hepburn</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bollu</surname>
<given-names>PC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>French</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep medicine: Stroke and sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Missouri Medicine</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>115</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>527</fpage>–<lpage>532</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30643347</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Arnaud</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bochaton</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pépin</surname>
<given-names>J-L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnoea and cardiovascular consequences: pathophysiological mechanisms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Cardiovasc Dis</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>113</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>350</fpage>–<lpage>358</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.acvd.2020.01.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32224049</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of obstructive sleep apnea with cardiometabolic diseases and cardiovascular mortality</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Respir J</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>764</fpage>–<lpage>770</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/crj.13666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37482921</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Destors</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tamisier</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Galerneau</surname>
<given-names>L-M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Physiopathologie du syndrome d’apnées-hypopnées obstructives du sommeil et de ses conséquences cardio-métaboliques</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Presse Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>395</fpage>–<lpage>403</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lpm.2016.09.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28126503</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cassidy</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trenell</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stefanetti</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Physical activity, inactivity and sleep during the diabetes remission clinical trial (DiRECT)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diabet Med</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e15010</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/dme.15010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36398460</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>St-Onge</surname>
<given-names>M-P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grandner</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration and quality: impact on lifestyle behaviors and cardiometabolic health: A scientific statement from the American Heart Association</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circulation</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>134</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<fpage>e367</fpage>–<lpage>e386</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/cir.0000000000000444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27647451</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name><surname>Shuo</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>
<article-title>Half of Chinese adults not getting 8 hours of sleep, report shows</article-title>. <year>2023</year>; <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.chinadaily.com.cn/a/202303/17/WS6413f48aa31057c47ebb512e.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.chinadaily.com.cn/a/202303/17/WS6413f48aa31057c47ebb512e.html</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>July</month>
<day>26</day>, 2024.</date-in-citation></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>eBioMedicine</collab>. <article-title>A good night’s sleep is more important than you think</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">EBioMedicine</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>90</volume>:<fpage>104575</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ebiom.2023.104575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37059495</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tao</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Trends and disparities in sleep quality and duration in older adults in China from 2008 to 2018: a national observational study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>998699</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2023.998699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36875376</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pan</surname>
<given-names>X-B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>H-X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cao</surname>
<given-names>Y-J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Secular trends in sleep conditions in Chinese elderly individuals: a national population-based study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Sci Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>555</fpage>–<lpage>566</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/nss.S416084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37441269</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between social capital and sleep duration among rural older adults in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>12</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-021-12441-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34986811</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Winer</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deters</surname>
<given-names>KD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kennedy</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of short and long sleep duration with amyloid-β burden and cognition in aging</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>78</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1187</fpage>–<lpage>1196</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaneurol.2021.2876</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34459862</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yan</surname>
<given-names>AF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. et al. <article-title>Health consequences of obesity and projected future obesity health burden in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Obesity</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1724</fpage>–<lpage>1751</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/CM9.0000000000001835</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36000246</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Svensson</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saito</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Svensson</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of sleep duration with all- and major-cause mortality among adults in Japan, China, Singapore, and Korea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Net Open</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e2122837</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.suc.2022.01.005</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
