<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39131166</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">11314433</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">468522</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S468522</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Healthy Sleep Pattern, Metabolic Diseases, and Risk of Stroke: The Kailuan Cohort Study</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Huang et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Huang et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Lili</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Yesong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>Tingting</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Nannan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Liang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7095-6022</contrib-id><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Shouling</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0002" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Xiang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Nutrition and Food Hygiene, School of Public Health, Institute of Nutrition, Fudan University</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Neurology, Kailuan General Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Tangshan</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Cardiology, Kailuan General Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Tangshan</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Xiang Gao, <institution>Department of Nutrition and Food Hygiene, School of Public Health, Institute of Nutrition, Fudan University</institution>, <addr-line>130 Dongan Road</addr-line>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <addr-line>200032</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, Email xiang_gao@fudan.edu.cn</corresp><corresp id="an0002">Shouling Wu, <institution>Department of Cardiology, Kailuan General Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>57 Xinhua East Road</addr-line>, <addr-line>Tangshan</addr-line>, <addr-line>063000</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, <phone content-type="general">Tel +86 315 3025655</phone>, <fax>Fax +86 315 3725312</fax>, Email drwusl@163.com</corresp><fn id="ft0001"><label>*</label><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">These authors contributed equally to this work</citation_analysis></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>1169</fpage><lpage>1178</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Huang et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Huang et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Sleep complaints were reported to be associated with stroke, however, the evidence on the association between healthy sleep pattern and stroke risk in Chinese is limited.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Objective</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The aim of this study was to investigate the association between healthy sleep pattern and stroke in Chinese, and the influence of metabolic diseases on the association.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">A total of 11,851 participants from the Kailuan study in China without stroke at baseline were included. We calculated a healthy sleep score according to four sleep factors, and defined the low-risk groups as follows: no insomnia, no excessive daytime sleepiness, no frequent snoring, and sleep 7–8h/d. Each low-risk sleep factor was assigned a score of 1. Cox proportional hazard models were used to assess the association between healthy sleep score and stroke. Mediation analysis was used to estimate the role of metabolic diseases (obesity, diabetes, and hypertension) in the healthy sleep score-stroke association.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">During a mean follow-up period of 7.7 years, 504 cases of stroke were identified. A higher healthy sleep score was associated with a lower risk of stroke in a dose-response manner (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">-trend=0.03). The adjusted hazard ratio (HR) for participants with a healthy sleep score of 4 versus ≤2 was 0.75 (95% confidence interval [CI]: 0.56, 0.96). In addition, obesity, diabetes, and hypertension collectively explained 21.9% (95% CI: 17.2, 26.5) of the association between healthy sleep score and stroke.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Adherence to healthy sleep pattern was associated with a lower risk of stroke, and the favorable association was partially mediated by metabolic diseases.</citation_analysis></p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>healthy sleep pattern</kwd><kwd>metabolic disease</kwd><kwd>stroke</kwd><kwd>mediation</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>This study was supported by the Startup grant at Fudan University JIF201036Y</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This study was supported by the Startup grant at Fudan University JIF201036Y.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="4"/><ref-count count="40"/><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Evidence has demonstrated that sleep complaints, including short or long sleep duration, insomnia, frequent snoring, and excessive daytime sleepiness, have an impact on the risk of stroke.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> This could be due to their effects on sympathetic nervous system activity,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> glucose homeostasis,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and vascular structure and function.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> These sleep behaviors do not occur in isolation, and modifications in one sleep behavior usually lead to compensatory changes in other sleep behaviors.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Therefore, combining various sleep behaviors into sleep patterns could reflect real-world sleep conditions. However, data on relationship between sleep pattern and risk of stroke are limited and mainly conducted in Western populations.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8–10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Moreover, the association between sleep complaints and stroke subtypes has not been well-studied,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> and few studies were conducted in Asian populations.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In addition, the associations between individual sleep complaints and metabolic diseases, including obesity, diabetes, and hypertension, have been well-established.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Furthermore, these metabolic diseases are also risk factors for stroke</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15–17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> and thus may be involved in the association between sleep and stroke risk. To date, no data have explored to which extent the association between sleep pattern and stroke risk could be interpreted by these metabolic abnormalities.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">To address these research gaps, we used data from the Kailuan study, a large community-based cohort in China, to examine the association of a healthy sleep score (combination of major sleep behaviors) with the risk of total stroke and subtypes of stroke. We also examined the role of metabolic diseases in the relationship between sleep pattern and risk of stroke.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In this analysis, participants were derived from the Kailuan study, an ongoing cohort from 2006–2007 with 101,510 Chinese adults aged 18–98 years recruited. The study design has been described in detail in previous studies.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18–20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Participants were recruited from Kailuan general hospital and 10 hospitals responsible for the healthcare of the community. All participants completed questionnaire assessments (ie socioeconomic status, lifestyles, and history of diseases), clinical, and laboratory examinations. The same assessments were conducted every two years afterwards. In 2012, information on sleep complaints was collected among 12,990 participants;</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> thus, the survey in 2012 was regarded as the baseline survey in this study.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We excluded those with cancer and cardiovascular disease (n=504) at baseline, without completed sleep data (n=265) or covariates (n=370), resulting in 11,851 participants for the present analysis. The study was approved by the Ethics Committee of the Kailuan General Hospital (approval number: 2006-05), and all participants provided written informed consent.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Assessment of Sleep Complaints</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep complaints, including insomnia, daytime sleepiness, sleep duration, and snoring, were collected via questionnaires. The detailed information has been described in previous studies.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Insomnia was assessed using the Chinese version of the Athens Insomnia Scale (AIS), comprising eight items evaluating insomnia symptoms over the past three months. Each item was scored from 0 to 3 (0=no event, 1= mild, 2= moderate, and 3= severe), with a total AIS score of ≥6 indicating insomnia. Daytime sleepiness was assessed via the Chinese version of the Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS) with eight items. Each item scored 0–3, representing the probability of falling asleep while engaged in specific daily life situations, with a total ESS score ≥10 indicating excessive daytime sleepiness. Sleep duration was collected via the question “usual total hours of actual sleep during the night over the past one month”. Snoring was collected by self-reported snoring frequency as never/rare, occasional, or frequent during the last month.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Definition of Healthy Sleep Score</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We then constructed a healthy sleep score using the above four sleep behaviors. According to the previous studies</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and the recommendation of the American Academy of Sleep Medicine and Sleep Research Society,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> we defined low-risk sleep factors as follows: no excessive daytime sleepiness, no insomnia, sleep 7–8 h per day, and no frequent snoring. Each low-risk sleep factor was assigned a score of 1 and 0 otherwise. Then, all component scores were summed to obtain a healthy sleep score ranging from 0 to 4, with higher scores indicating a healthier sleep pattern. The healthy sleep score was categorized into three groups according to the data distribution: healthy sleep score≤2, healthy sleep score of 3, and healthy sleep score of 4.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Assessment of Outcome-Incident Stroke Cases</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The outcome was the first occurrence of stroke, including ischemic stroke and hemorrhagic stroke, according to the World Health Organization criteria.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The detailed adjudication of incident stroke in the Kailuan study was described previously.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In brief, participants were followed up by face-to-face interviews at biennial routine medical examinations until 31 December, 2020. The outcome was further confirmed by checking discharge summaries from the 11 hospitals and medical records from medical insurance. Outcome information was obtained directly by checking death certificates from provincial vital statistics offices, discharge summaries, and medical records for the participants without face-to-face follow-ups.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Assessment of Metabolic Conditions and Other Related Factors</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The weight and height of each participant were measured by trained study staff. Body mass index (BMI) was calculated as weight in kilograms divided by height in meters squared. Obesity was defined as BMI≥28kg/m</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, aligning with the Chinese criteria.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The blood pressure (BP) was taken using a calibrated mercury sphygmomanometer, with at least two readings after 5 minutes of rest; the average value was used for hypertension diagnosis. Following the Seventh Report of the Joint National Committee recommendation,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> hypertension was defined as BP measurement ≥140/90 mmHg or the self-reported use of antihypertensive medication. Fasting (8–12h) blood samples were collected in the morning and then stored at −80°C at the central laboratory of Kailuan general hospital. An auto-analyzer (Hitachi 747; Hitachi, Tokyo) was used to measure fasting blood glucose (FBG) with the hexokinase/glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase method. The coefficient of variation using blind quality control specimens was &lt;2.0%.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Diabetes was defined as an FBG value ≥7.0 mmol/L, use of hypoglycemic drugs, or self-reported physician-diagnosed diabetes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> We also combined obesity, diabetes, and hypertension, and defined a composite index with values ranging from 0 to 3, representing the range from no disease to the presence of the three metabolic diseases.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Information on age, sex, education, average income per month, occupation, alcohol consumption, smoking, and physical activity were also obtained via a questionnaire by well-trained health workers.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Serum creatinine was measured using the sarcosine oxidase assay method (creatinine kit; BioSino Bio-technology and Science Inc., Beijing, China), with ≤6% intra- and inter-assay variable coefficients. The estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) was computed according to the chronic kidney disease (CKD) Epidemiology Collaboration equation.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Proteinuria was assessed using the dry-chemistry method (H12-MA test strips; Changchun Dirui Medical Technology Co., Ltd., Changchun, China). In this study, participants with eGFR &lt;60mL/min per 1.73 m</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> or proteinuria ≥2+ (&gt;300mg/dl) were considered to have CKD.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2006">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Baseline characteristics were described across healthy sleep score, and differences among groups were tested by one-way ANOVA, Kruskal–Wallis test, or chi-square tests where appropriate. Person years were calculated from baseline until the date of stroke diagnosis, death, or 31 December 2020, whichever occurred first. Cox proportional hazards regression was used to estimate the hazard ratios (HRs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) of total stroke and stroke subtypes (ischemic and hemorrhagic stroke). The linear trend in risk across healthy sleep pattern groups was tested by using the median value for each group and treating them as continuous variables.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Based on existing literature, we adjusted for age and sex in Model 1; occupation (coal miners, other blue miners, white miners), education (illiterate and primary, middle school, high school and above), average income per month (≤1000, 1000–3000, &gt;3000RMB), alcohol consumption (never and past, current and light drink, current and moderate and above), smoking (never, past, current), physical activity (no, occasional, frequent), use of sleep medication (no, yes) and CKD (no, yes) were further adjusted in Model 2. Obesity (no, yes), hypertension (no, yes), and diabetes (no, yes) were further adjusted in Model 3 to examine the influence of these metabolic diseases on the association between healthy sleep score and stroke. We also analyzed the association of individual low-risk sleep factors with total stroke and its subtypes.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">To investigate the consistency of our findings across different demographics, subgroup analyses were performed based on age (&lt;60 and ≥60 years), sex (men and women), education (illiterate and primary, middle school, high school and above), average income per month (≤1000, 1000–3000, &gt;3000RMB), physical activity (no, occasional, frequent), alcohol consumption (never and past, current and light drink, current and moderate and above), smoking status (never, past, current), and CKD (no, yes). An interaction analysis between healthy sleep score and metabolic diseases was conducted using likelihood ratio tests.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Mediation effects of metabolic diseases on the association between healthy sleep score and stroke risk were evaluated using mediation package in R. Indirect, direct, and total effects for each mediator were computed via combining the mediator and outcome models with the adjustment of all the covariates in Model 2. The joint associations were also assessed. The participants were classified into nine groups according to number of healthy sleep factors (≤2, 3, 4) and the number of metabolic diseases (0, 1, and ≥2), with number of healthy sleep factors≤2 and metabolic diseases≥2 as the reference group.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We performed several sensitivity analyses to test the robustness of our findings. First, we excluded incident cases during the first two years of follow-up, considering the possibility of reverse causality. Second, we excluded participants with CKD. Third, we excluded coal miners (41.3%), considering the generalization of results.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">All analyses were conducted by R (version 4.2.0), and a two-sided </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> value&lt;0.05 was considered significant.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Characteristics of the Study Population</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Among the 11,851 participants (mean age: 53.8±10.4 years; 82.4% of men), 1468 (12.4%) participants had ≤2 healthy sleep factors, 6349 (53.6%) had 4 healthy sleep factors (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). Participants with higher healthy sleep score were younger, more likely to be women, White-collar workers, and less likely to consume alcohol or smoke, and had a lower proportion of obesity, hypertension, and diabetes compared to those with lower healthy sleep score (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Baseline Characteristics Across Healthy Sleep Score</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">All</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Healthy Sleep Score</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11851</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1468</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4034</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6349</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.8±10.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.5±10.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.7±10.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.6±11.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9764 (82.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1262 (86.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3398 (84.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5104 (80.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education level, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Illiterate and primary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">748 (6.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99 (6.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">260 (6.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">389 (6.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Middle school</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10036 (84.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1279 (87.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3425 (84.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5332 (84.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> High school and above</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1067 (9.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90 (6.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">349 (8.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">628 (9.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Occupation, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Coalminers</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4890 (41.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">716 (48.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1830 (45.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2344 (36.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other blue collars</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6106 (51.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">687 (46.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,986 (49.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3433 (54.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> White collars</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">855 (7.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (4.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">218 (5.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">572 (9.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average income per month, RMB, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≤1000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3473 (29.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">346 (23.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1081 (26.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2046 (32.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1001–3000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7612 (64.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1060 (72.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2705 (67.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3847 (60.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;3000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">766 (6.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (4.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">248 (6.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">456 (7.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol consumption, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Never</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7046 (59.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">661 (45.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2140 (53.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4245 (66.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Current, light</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3475 (29.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">539 (36.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1290 (32.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1646 (25.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Current, moderate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1033 (8.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">205 (14.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">456 (11.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">372 (5.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Current, heavy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">179 (1.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (2.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (0.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Current, unknown</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (0.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (0.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (0.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (0.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Past</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (0.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (1.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (0.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (0.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoke, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Never</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6661 (56.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">612 (41.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1962 (48.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4087 (64.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Past</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">664 (5.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128 (8.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">249 (6.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">287 (4.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Current</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4526 (38.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">728 (49.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1823 (45.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1975 (31.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical activity, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5622 (47.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">720 (49.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1921 (47.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2981 (47.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Occasional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4467 (37.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">433 (29.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1356 (33.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2678 (42.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Frequent</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1762 (14.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">315 (21.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">757 (18.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">690 (10.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Use of sleep medication</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1260 (10.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">167 (11.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">315 (7.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">778 (12.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, kg/m<sup>2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0±3.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.6±3.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.1±3.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.8±3.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CKD, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">451 (3.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (3.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">149 (3.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">245 (3.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obesity, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1891 (15.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">327 (22.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">681 (16.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">883 (13.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4905 (41.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">681 (46.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1683 (41.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2541 (40.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1332 (11.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">211 (14.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">458 (11.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">663 (10.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Continuous variables were expressed as: mean ±SD, Categorical variables were expressed as: n (%).</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: BMI, body mass index; CKD:, chronic kidney disease.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Association Between Healthy Sleep Pattern and Stroke Risk</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">During a mean follow-up period of 7.7±1.0 years, 504 incident cases of stroke were identified. We observed a higher healthy sleep score was associated with a lower risk of stroke in a dose-response manner. The adjusted HR of stroke was 0.86 (95% CI: 0.70, 0.94) for each healthy sleep score increment based on Model 2 (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). Compared to healthy sleep score≤2, the adjusted HR of stroke was 0.71 (95% CI: 0.55, 0.91) for healthy sleep score of 4. The association (HR: 0.75, 95% CI: 0.56, 0.96) was slightly attenuated when further adjusting for obesity, diabetes, and hypertension. The associations were also observed in stroke subtype, with the estimated effect on hemorrhagic stroke (each healthy sleep score increment, HR: 0.62, 95% CI: 0.46, 0.83) were more pronounced than ischemic stroke (each healthy sleep score increment, HR: 0.88, 95% CI: 0.78, 0.99; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The Association Between Healthy Sleep Score and Risk of Stroke</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="5" rowspan="1">Healthy Sleep Score, HR (95% CI)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Each Score Increase</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for Trend</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Total stroke</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case/person-year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84/11,368</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">177/31,278</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">243/48,720</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Model 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (reference)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 (0.60, 1.01)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68 (0.53, 0.88)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 (0.76, 0.94)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Model 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (reference)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 (0.60, 1.01)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 (0.55, 0.91)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 (0.70, 0.94)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Model 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (reference)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.63, 1.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75 (0.56, 0.96)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88 (079, 0.98)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Ischemic stroke</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case/person-year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72/11,418</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">166/31,322</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">225/48,806</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Model 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (reference)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 (0.65, 1.13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76 (0.58, 0.99)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88 (0.78, 0.99)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hemorrhagic stroke</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case/person-year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15/11,617</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20/31,879</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23/49,566</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Model 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (reference)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49 (0.25, 0.95)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35 (0.18, 0.68)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62 (0.46, 0.83)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: Model 1: adjusted for age, sex (men or women); Model 2: model 1 additionally adjusted for education (illiterate and primary, middle school, high school and above), average income per month (≤1000, 1000–3000, &gt;3000RMB), occupation (coalminers, other blue collars, white collars), physical activity (no, occasion, frequent), alcohol drinking (never and past, light drinking, moderate-heavy drinking), smoking (never, past, current), use of sleep medication (no or yes), and CKD (no, yes). Model 3: model 2 additionally adjusted for obesity (no, yes), hypertension (no, yes) and diabetes (no, yes).</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Association Between Low-Risk Sleep Factors and Stroke Risk</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">The analyses of individual low-risk sleep factors showed that no excessive daytime sleepiness (HR: 0.60, 95% CI: 0.37, 0.97) and no frequent snoring (HR: 0.69, 95% CI: 0.56, 0.86) were associated with lower risk of total stroke (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). The two sleep factors were also associated with stroke subtypes, with the estimated effect on hemorrhagic stroke (no excessive daytime sleepiness, HR: 0.28, 95% CI: 0.10, 0.79; no frequent snoring, HR: 0.46, 95% CI: 0.25, 0.83) were more pronounced compared to ischemic stroke (no excessive daytime sleepiness, HR: 0.64, 95% CI: 0.38, 1.05; no frequent snoring, HR: 0.73, 95% CI: 0.58, 0.92).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The Association Between Low-Risk Sleep Factors and Risk of Stroke</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Low-Risk Sleep Factors</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">HR (95% CI)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Stroke</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ischemic Stroke</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemorrhagic Stroke</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No excessive daytime sleepiness</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60 (0.37, 0.97)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64 (0.38, 1.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28 (0.10, 0.79)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No insomnia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 (0.65, 1.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (0.66, 1.15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 (0.34, 1.52)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep 7–8h/day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 (0.80, 1.18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (0.82, 1.22)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62 (0.36, 1.06)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No frequent snoring</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 (0.56, 0.86)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73 (0.58, 0.92)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46 (0.25, 0.83)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: Model was adjusted for age, sex (men or women), education (illiterate and primary, middle school, or high school and above), average income per month (≤1000, 1000–3000, &gt;3000RMB), occupation (coalminers, other blue collars, white collars), physical activity (no, occasion, frequent), alcohol drinking (never and past, light drinking, moderate-heavy drinking), smoking (never, past, current), use of sleep medication (no or yes) and CKD (no, yes).</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Subgroup Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The association between healthy sleep score and stroke risk remained consistent in participants aged ≥60, men, those with low income, no physical activity, no alcohol drinking and smoking, and without CKD, but the interaction test did not reach statistical significance (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> for interaction&gt;0.05 for all; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=468522.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Figure S1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2005">
        <title>Mediation Analysis and Joint Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In the mediation analysis, the association between healthy sleep score and stroke risk was mediated by obesity, diabetes, and hypertension with the proportion of mediation effect ranging from 4.4% to16.1%. Collectively, the three mediators explained 21.9% (95% CI: 17.2, 26.5) of the association between healthy sleep score and stroke risk (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative">). The joint analysis showed that compared with participants with number of healthy sleep factors≤2 and metabolic diseases≥2, participants with 4 healthy sleep factors and no metabolic diseases had a substantially lower risk of stroke (HR: 0.27, 95% CI: 0.16, 0.44; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Association of Healthy Sleep Score with Total Stroke Mediated by Metabolic Diseases</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Effect</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Natural Direct Effect</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Natural Indirect Effect</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion Eliminated</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">% (95% CI)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obesity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.855 (0.781, 0.930)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.879 (0.797, 0.960)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.973 (0.968, 0.979)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.1 (12.7, 24.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.863 (0.783, 0.943)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.872 (0.793, 0.951)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.990 (0.988, 0.992)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2 (3.0, 9.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.856 (0.728, 0.984)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.862 (0.740, 0.984)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.992 (0.984, 0.998)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4 (3.1, 5.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total mediation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.9 (17.2, 26.5)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: Model was adjusted for age, sex (men or women), education (illiterate and primary, middle school, or high school and above), average income per month (≤1000, 1000–3000, &gt;3000RMB), occupation (coalminers, other blue collars, white collars), physical activity (no, occasion, frequent), alcohol drinking (never and past, light drinking, moderate-heavy drinking), smoking (never, past, current), use of sleep medication (no or yes) and CKD (no, yes).</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The joint association of healthy sleep score and metabolic diseases with stroke. Model was adjusted for age, sex (men or women), education (illiterate and primary, middle school, high school or college and above), average income per month (≤1000, 1000–3000, &gt;3000RMB), occupation (coalminers, other blue collars, white collars), physical activity (no, occasion, frequent), alcohol drinking (never and past, light drinking, moderate-heavy drinking), smoking (never, past, current), use of sleep medication (no or yes), and CKD (no, yes).</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1169-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In the sensitivity analyses, the results were generally robust when excluding incident cases occurring during the first two years of follow-up, coal miners, patients with CKD (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=468522.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Table S1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In this large-scale community-based study conducted in China, we found that higher healthy sleep score (combination of no insomnia, no excessive daytime sleepiness, sleep 7–8h/d, and no frequent snoring), was associated with lower total stroke and its subtypes risk. For each number increment in low-risk sleep factor, there was an 14% lower risk of total stroke. In addition, the metabolic disease, including obesity, diabetes, and hypertension, collectively explained 21.9% of the association between healthy sleep score and stroke. In addition, individuals with 4 healthy sleep factors and no metabolic diseases had approximately 70% lower risk of stroke than those with number of healthy sleep factors≤2 and metabolic diseases≥2.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our study contributes to the literature regarding the influence of sleep patterns on stroke risk, which were mainly conducted in Western populations. A study using data from the UK Biobank creating a healthy sleep score using chronotype, duration, insomnia, snoring, and excessive daytime sleepiness, also found that participants with higher sleep pattern scores (healthy sleep pattern) had a 34% (95% CI: 25%, 42%) lower risk of stroke.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> A recent retrospective case-control study also found a graded association between the accumulation of sleep disturbance symptoms (included extreme sleep duration, sleep onset latency, waking more than once, napping for &gt;1h, unplanned napping and presence or uncertainty surrounding snorting, snorting or gasping and breathing cessation or choking) and stroke risk.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Compared with participants with 0–1 sleep disturbance symptoms, participants with an increased number of sleep disturbance symptoms had a graded increase in stroke risk (2–3: OR: 1.63, 95% CI: 1.36–1.96; 4–5: OR: 3.08, 95% CI: 2.49–3.80; &gt;5: OR: 5.38, 95% CI: 4.03–7.18).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Our findings, together with these studies, suggest that the comprehensive index constructed using multi-dimensional sleep parameters could be useful to identify high-risk populations for stroke event.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The association between individual sleep complaints and stroke has been widely discussed. However, the conclusions were still controversial. Our study found that participants without excessive daytime sleepiness or frequent snoring were associated with a lower risk of stroke, while we did not observe significant associations of insomnia or sleep duration with risk of stroke, which were found in other studies.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Nevertheless, this also provides evidence to support the notion that using a sleep pattern may help us find a stable estimate of the sleep-stroke relationship.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Few studies have specifically explored the relationship between sleep and stroke subtypes. The Dongfeng-Tongji cohort, using a single question to assess sleep quality over the past six months, found a significant association between poor sleep quality and increased risk of ischemic and hemorrhagic strokes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Similarly, a large retrospective case-control study found a dose-response association of sleep disturbance symptoms with ischemic and hemorrhagic stroke.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Consistent with these studies, our study also found an association of healthy sleep score with ischemic and hemorrhagic stroke. Notably, our study, together with the above-mentioned studies, observed the effect of sleep on hemorrhagic stroke was more pronounced than ischemic stroke. The pathogenesis of stroke may provide some insight. The increased risk of hemorrhagic stroke induced by sleep disturbances may be largely attributed to its direct impact on blood pressure, as hypertension is a major risk factor for cerebral hemorrhage.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, due to the small sample size of incident hemorrhagic stroke cases, we cannot exclude the possibility of chance findings, and the results should be interpreted with caution.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our mediation analyses contribute to better understanding the lower risk of stroke associated with healthy sleep pattern. Our data showed that the association between healthy sleep pattern and stroke may be explained by metabolic disease, including obesity, hypertension, and diabetes. These metabolic conditions are well-established risk factors of stroke.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Sleep complaints were also reported to be associated with these chronic conditions.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Experimental studies demonstrated that poor sleep quality might induce leptin production, insulin resistance, and increased sympathetic nervous system activity, which could result in the aforementioned metabolic abnormalities.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3–5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37–39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> However, the moderate mediation proportion (21.9%) in this study indicated other crucial factors need to be identified. Nevertheless, in joint associations, we found that the individuals with 4 healthy sleep factors and no metabolic diseases had approximately 70% lower risk of stroke. Our findings support the importance of maintaining healthy sleep pattern and metabolic health simultaneously in stroke prevention.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Several limitations in this study should be noted. Firstly, the incident case number of hemorrhagic stroke were small, and future studies with a larger sample size are required to replicate our findings. Secondly, information on chronic conditions was collected at baseline, which may affect the inference of causal association. Thirdly, we evaluated the association between baseline sleep patterns and future stroke risk without accounting for changes in sleep habits, potentially leading to non-differential misclassification.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Additionally, sleep complaints were self-reported via questionnaire, introducing the possibility of measurement errors. Fourthly, because most of the participants from the Kailuan study were men (82.4%), they cannot be viewed as a representative sample of the general Chinese population. However, studying such a population could reduce residual confounding due to diverse socioeconomic factors and lifestyle patterns. Finally, residual confounding cannot be completely ruled out because of the limitation of observational study design, despite comprehensive adjustment for the potential confounders.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In this large cohort study in China, our findings suggested that adherence to a healthy sleep pattern, including no insomnia, no excessive daytime sleepiness, sleep 7–8h/d, and no frequent snoring, was associated with a lower risk of stroke. In addition, our data showed significant mediation effect of metabolic diseases on the association between healthy sleep pattern and stroke risk. Our findings highlight the importance of maintaining both healthy sleep pattern and normal metabolism to reduce the risk of stroke.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We thank all study participants, their relatives, the members of the survey teams at the 11 regional hospitals of the Kailuan Medical Group, and the project development and management teams at the Beijing Tiantan Hospital and the Kailuan Group.</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s0006">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The data are available from the corresponding authors upon reasonable request.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Ethics Approval and Informed Consent</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The study was approved by the Ethics Committee of the Kailuan General Hospital (approval number: 2006-05) and conformed to the tenets of the Declaration of Helsinki. All data from this study were published with the consent of the participants.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0008">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation, or in all these areas; took part in drafting, revising or critically reviewing the article; gave final approval of the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0009">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ke</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruan</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Short sleep duration associated with the incidence of cardio-cerebral vascular disease: a prospective cohort study in Shanghai, China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Cardiovasc Disord</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>177</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12872-023-03205-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37003977</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of sleep duration and napping with stroke mortality in older Chinese: a 14-year prospective cohort study of the Guangzhou Biobank Cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>384</fpage>–<lpage>391</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2022.11.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36512889</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Coy</surname>
<given-names>TV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dimsdale</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ancoli-Israel</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clausen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep apnoea and sympathetic nervous system activity: a review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>42</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2869.1996.00006.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8795801</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schmid</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hallschmid</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jauch-Chara</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Disturbed glucoregulatory response to food intake after moderate sleep restriction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>371</fpage>–<lpage>377</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/34.3.371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21358855</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buxton</surname>
<given-names>OM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pavlova</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reid</surname>
<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simonson</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adler</surname>
<given-names>GK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep restriction for 1 week reduces insulin sensitivity in healthy men</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2126</fpage>–<lpage>2133</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/db09-0699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20585000</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Calvin</surname>
<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Covassin</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kremers</surname>
<given-names>WK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Experimental sleep restriction causes endothelial dysfunction in healthy humans</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Heart Assoc</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e001143</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/jaha.114.001143</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25424573</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wallace</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stone</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smagula</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Which sleep health characteristics predict all-cause mortality in older men? An application of flexible multivariable approaches</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>1</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsx189</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fan</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep patterns, genetic susceptibility, and incident cardiovascular disease: a prospective study of 385 292 UK biobank participants</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Heart J</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1182</fpage>–<lpage>1189</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehz849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31848595</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yin</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of healthy sleep pattern with the risk of cardiovascular disease and all-cause mortality among people with diabetes: a prospective cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diabet Res Clin Pract</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>186</volume>:<fpage>109822</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.diabres.2022.109822</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mc Carthy</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yusuf</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Judge</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep patterns and the risk of acute stroke: results from the INTERSTROKE International Case-Control Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>100</volume>(<issue>21</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/wnl.0000000000207249</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration, midday napping, and sleep quality and incident stroke: the Dongfeng-Tongji cohort</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>94</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e345</fpage>–<lpage>e356</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/wnl.0000000000008739</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31827003</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brunner</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ren</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration and risk of ischemic stroke in postmenopausal women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Stroke</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>3185</fpage>–<lpage>3192</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/strokeaha.108.521773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18635832</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Reutrakul</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Cauter</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep influences on obesity, insulin resistance, and risk of type 2 diabetes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Metabolism</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>84</volume>:<fpage>56</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.metabol.2018.02.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29510179</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rahim</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McIsaac</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aronson</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tranmer</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The associations of shift work, sleep quality, and incidence of hypertension in Ontario adults: a population-based study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Can J Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>513</fpage>–<lpage>518</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cjca.2020.09.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32927020</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hajifathalian</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ezzati</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Woodward</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rimm</surname>
<given-names>EB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Danaei</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Metabolic mediators of the effects of body-mass index, overweight, and obesity on coronary heart disease and stroke: a pooled analysis of 97 prospective cohorts with 1·8 million participants</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>383</volume>(<issue>9921</issue>):<fpage>970</fpage>–<lpage>983</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0140-6736(13)61836-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24269108</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Peters</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huxley</surname>
<given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Woodward</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Diabetes as a risk factor for stroke in women compared with men: a systematic review and meta-analysis of 64 cohorts, including 775,385 individuals and 12,539 strokes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>383</volume>(<issue>9933</issue>):<fpage>1973</fpage>–<lpage>1980</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0140-6736(14)60040-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24613026</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Turin</surname>
<given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Okamura</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Afzal</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Hypertension and lifetime risk of stroke</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Hypertens</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>116</fpage>–<lpage>122</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/hjh.0000000000000753</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26556566</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Ideal cardiovascular health metrics and the risks of ischemic and intracerebral hemorrhagic stroke</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Stroke</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2451</fpage>–<lpage>2456</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/STROKEAHA.113.678839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23868276</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lichtenstein</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The risk of ischemic stroke and hemorrhagic stroke in Chinese adults with low-density lipoprotein cholesterol concentrations &lt; 70 mg/dL</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>142</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12916-021-02014-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34130689</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A prospective study of waist circumference trajectories and incident cardiovascular disease in China: the Kailuan Cohort Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Clin Nutr</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>113</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>338</fpage>–<lpage>347</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ajcn/nqaa331</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pavlova</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Risk factors for probable REM sleep behavior disorder: a community-based study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>86</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>1306</fpage>–<lpage>1312</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/wnl.0000000000002414</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26819459</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pavlova</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Probable REM sleep behavior disorder and risk of stroke: a prospective study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>88</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>1849</fpage>–<lpage>1855</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/wnl.0000000000003902</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28389588</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hou</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep and CKD in Chinese adults: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin J Am Soc Nephrol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>885</fpage>–<lpage>892</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2215/cjn.09270816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28389618</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>FW</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Poor sleep quality is associated with altered taste perception in Chinese adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Acad Nutr Diet</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>121</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>435</fpage>–<lpage>445</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jand.2020.06.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32828739</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Watson</surname>
<given-names>NF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Badr</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Belenky</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Joint consensus statement of the American Academy of Sleep Medicine and Sleep Research Society on the recommended amount of sleep for a healthy adult: methodology and discussion</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1161</fpage>–<lpage>1183</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.4886</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26194576</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>WHO Task Force</collab>. <article-title>Stroke--1989. Recommendations on stroke prevention, diagnosis, and therapy. Report of the WHO Task Force on Stroke and other Cerebrovascular Disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Stroke</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1407</fpage>–<lpage>1431</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.str.20.10.1407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2799873</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jin</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Longitudinal change of perceived salt intake and stroke risk in a Chinese population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Stroke</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1332</fpage>–<lpage>1339</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/strokeaha.117.020277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29739913</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obesity prevalence and risks among Chinese adults: findings from the China PEACE Million Persons Project, 2014–2018</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circ Cardiovasc Qual Outcomes</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e007292</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/circoutcomes.120.007292</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34107739</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chobanian</surname>
<given-names>AV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bakris</surname>
<given-names>GL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Black</surname>
<given-names>HR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The seventh report of the Joint National Committee on Prevention, Detection, Evaluation, and Treatment of High Blood Pressure: the JNC 7 report</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>289</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>2560</fpage>–<lpage>2572</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.289.19.2560</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12748199</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jin</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rexrode</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prospective study of fasting blood glucose and intracerebral hemorrhagic risk</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Stroke</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/strokeaha.117.019189</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29229723</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weng</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ho</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hsu</surname>
<given-names>YW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia subtypes and the subsequent risks of stroke: report from a nationally representative cohort</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Stroke</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1349</fpage>–<lpage>1354</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/strokeaha.113.003675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24699057</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Titova</surname>
<given-names>OE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Michaëlsson</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Larsson</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep duration and stroke: prospective cohort study and Mendelian randomization analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Stroke</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>3279</fpage>–<lpage>3285</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/strokeaha.120.029902</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32895015</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Magid-Bernstein</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Girard</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Polster</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cerebral hemorrhage: pathophysiology, treatment, and future directions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circ Res</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>130</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1204</fpage>–<lpage>1229</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/circresaha.121.319949</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35420918</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Curioni</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>André</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Veras</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Weight reduction for primary prevention of stroke in adults with overweight or obesity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cochrane Database Syst Rev</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>2006</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>Cd006062</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD006062.pub2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17054273</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bradley</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spring</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beran</surname>
<given-names>RG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chatzis</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Killingsworth</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bhaskar</surname>
<given-names>SMM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Role of diabetes in stroke: recent advances in pathophysiology and clinical management</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes Metab Res Rev</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e3495</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dmrr.3495</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34530485</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mansukhani</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Covassin</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Somers</surname>
<given-names>VK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Apneic sleep, insufficient sleep, and hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>73</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>744</fpage>–<lpage>756</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/hypertensionaha.118.11780</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30776972</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Broussard</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kilkus</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Delebecque</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Elevated ghrelin predicts food intake during experimental sleep restriction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Obesity</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>132</fpage>–<lpage>138</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/oby.21321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26467988</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stern</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grant</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thomson</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Short sleep duration is associated with decreased serum leptin, increased energy intake and decreased diet quality in postmenopausal women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Obesity</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>E55</fpage>–<lpage>E61</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/oby.20683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24347344</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cui</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>López</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rahmouni</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The cellular and molecular bases of leptin and ghrelin resistance in obesity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Endocrinol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>338</fpage>–<lpage>351</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrendo.2016.222</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28232667</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Leng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cappuccio</surname>
<given-names>FP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wainwright</surname>
<given-names>NW</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration and risk of fatal and nonfatal stroke: a prospective study and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>84</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1072</fpage>–<lpage>1079</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/wnl.0000000000001371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25716357</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
