<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39184949</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">11342950</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">470557</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S470557</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Self-Compassion as a Mediator Linking Sleep Disturbances with Non-Suicidal Self-Injury: A Four-Wave, Cross-Lagged Study</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Shi et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Shi et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6234-5456</contrib-id><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Xuliang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Miaomiao</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Xiaoyan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Ya</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>College of Education, Hebei University</institution>, <addr-line>Baoding</addr-line>, <addr-line>Hebei Province</addr-line>, <addr-line>071002</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Applied Social Sciences, The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</institution>, <country>Hong Kong</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Center for Mental Health Education and Counseling, Guangdong University of Science and Technology</institution>, <addr-line>Dongguan</addr-line>, <addr-line>Guangdong Province</addr-line>, <addr-line>523083</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Xuliang Shi, <institution>Associate professor at the College of Education, Hebei University</institution>, <addr-line>Baoding</addr-line>, <addr-line>071002</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, Email shixl163@163.com</corresp><fn id="ft0001"><label>*</label><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">These authors contributed equally to this work</citation_analysis></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>1221</fpage><lpage>1233</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Shi et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Shi et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="s2001"><title>Objective</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This longitudinal study examined the reciprocal relationship between sleep disturbances with non-suicidal self-injury and whether self-compassion mediates these associations.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec id="s2002"><title>Methods</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">A total of 5785 freshmen were sampled from a large-scale health-related cohort among Chinese college students at the baseline. This study spanned six waves with a six-month interval between each wave. Data from the last four waves were used because self-compassion or non-suicidal self-injury was not measured in the first two waves. The cross-lagged panel models were used to examine the longitudinal dynamic relationships between sleep disturbances, self-compassion, and non-suicidal self-injury.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec id="s2003"><title>Results</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The results showed that all the auto-regressive paths were significant. For the cross-lagged paths, there was a reciprocal relation between sleep disturbances and self-compassion. Importantly, self-compassion played a longitudinal mediating role in the prediction from sleep disturbances to non-suicidal self-injury (indirect effect = 0.007 to 0.009, all </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> values &lt; 0.001).</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec id="s2004"><title>Conclusion</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Psychological interventions targeting improved sleep quality and self-compassion may hold great promise for reducing the incidence of non-suicidal self-injury.</citation_analysis></p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>sleep disturbances</kwd><kwd>self-compassion</kwd><kwd>NSSI</kwd><kwd>longitudinal design</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Open Experimental Project of Hebei University</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Higher Education Teaching Reform Project of Hebei Province</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This study was supported from the Open Experimental Project of Hebei University (Grant No. sy202201), and Higher Education Teaching Reform Project of Hebei Province (Grant No. 2021GJJG684).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="3"/><ref-count count="70"/><page-count count="13"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Non-suicidal self-injury (NSSI) is a growing clinical and public health problem.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1–3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> NSSI was defined as the deliberate damage to body tissue without suicidal intent, and it is not socially or culturally sanctioned.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Examples of NSSI behaviors include cutting or carving the skin, self-battery, and severe scratching.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4–6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> College students, who are in the transition from adolescence to emerging adulthood, are particularly vulnerable to engaging in self-injury.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Previous studies have shown that approximately one in five students reported lifetime NSSI at college entrance,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and 15% of students initiate NSSI during the first two years of university.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> NSSI has been associated with various adverse outcomes, including impaired academic functioning,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> emotional disorders,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and increased suicidal ideation and attempts.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Sleep problems, such as insomnia, irregular sleep patterns, and insufficient sleep duration, are prevalent among college students.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Previous research has shown that about 18.5% of college students reported insomnia, a rate higher than the rate of 7.4% reported in the general population.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Sleep problems, as a potential modifiable risk factor, have been evidenced to be associated with self-harming thoughts and behaviors in numerous cross-sectional and longitudinal studies.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15–18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> A systematic review and meta-analysis have found that sleep problems including short sleep duration, sleep disturbances, and poor sleep quality were associated with non-suicidal self-injury.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In addition, some clinical intervention studies have suggested that cognitive-behavioral therapy for insomnia (CBT-I) can be beneficial in reducing self-harming thoughts and behaviors.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Despite accumulating evidence establishing the relationship between sleep problems and NSSI, there are several limitations in the literature. First of all, most extant research has examined the directional path from sleep problems to NSSI, with limited evidence regarding whether NSSI affects sleep problems. NSSI does not effectively address the issues that cause emotional distress, leading individuals to feel powerless and experience an increased sense of hopelessness, which may increase their risk of sleep disturbances. Secondly, most previous studies have relied on cross-sectional or two-wave longitudinal designs, which provide limited insight into the long-term dynamic relationship between sleep problems and NSSI. Finally, although the relationship between sleep problems and NSSI has been established, the potential mechanisms underlying this relationship were understudied. Revealing these mechanisms would have important clinical significance in understanding the occurrence of NSSI.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Self-compassion refers to the practice of treating oneself with kindness and non-judgmental understanding when experiencing suffering or pain, which is an effective approach to deal with distressing thoughts and emotions.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Some studies have explored the relationship between sleep problems and self-compassion. On the one hand, accumulated experience of stressful life events over time is likely to have a deteriorating effect on one’s ability to maintain self-compassion.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22–24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Chronic sleep disturbances, an important stressor, have been shown to be negatively associated with self-compassion. For instance, a cross-sectional study have found that fears of self-compassion and self-criticism mediated the relationship between poor sleep quality and mental health wellbeing.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> On the other hand, individuals with high levels of self-compassion may have better sleep quality compared to those with low self-compassion. Self-compassionate individuals are less likely to repress or avoid painful feelings when facing inadequacies or challenges as they acknowledge that others may also experience similar situations.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Thus, self-compassion contributes to a more accepting and gentle attitude towards oneself, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> which may foster better sleep hygiene practices and promote healthier sleep patterns.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In recent decades, self-compassion has gained significant attention in the field of self-injury. The benefits and barriers model of NSSI</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> proposes five barriers that prevent most people from engaging in self-injury: lack of awareness of NSSI, a positive view of the self, aversion to physical pain, aversion to NSSI stimuli, and social norms. For emerging adults, a positive view of self is considered the most significant barrier for preventing NSSI.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Self-compassion can be seen as a healthy way to value oneself. Self-compassionate individuals can process and accept emotional pain by paying full attention to thoughts and feelings, and treating them with understanding.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Increasing evidence has shown that self-compassion is a significant protective factor against NSSI. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30–33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Furthermore, self-compassion was positively related with adaptive coping and negatively related with maladaptive coping.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Extending from this notion, individuals with low self-compassion are more likely to rely on avoidance and maladaptive coping,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> which ultimately leads to more NSSI behaviors.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, previous studies have mainly relied on cross-sectional to examine the relationships between self-compassion and NSSI.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> More longitudinal studies are needed to explore the dynamic relationship between these variables.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">External stressors typically contribute to negative outcomes indirectly through individual psychological factors. Therefore, self-compassion may be an important potential mechanism linking external stressors and mental health problems.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37–39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> For example, researchers have found that negative life events can diminish positive self-compassion processes (eg, self-kindness, common humanity, and mindfulness), which in turn puts students at greater suicidal risk.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Chronic sleep disturbances, an important negative life event, have been shown to be negatively associated with self-compassion. Currently, only one study has assessed the mediating effects of self-compassion between sleep problems and NSSI. Kim and coworkers in their cross-sectional study found that fears of self-compassion partially mediated the relationship between poor sleep quality and mental health wellbeing.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Thus, the pathways from sleep problems to NSSI through self-compassion are plausible. However, given that these potential mediating pathways have not been extensively examined, a more rigorous investigation of these proposed relationships is warranted. The cross-lagged panel model (CLPM) has been proven to be an effective technique for examining reciprocal causal effects using longitudinal data. Such an analysis could ultimately aid in the creation and execution of effective, targeted interventions to reduce the incidence of NSSI in young adults.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Previous findings have shown a close relationship between sleep problems, self-compassion, and NSSI.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15–19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30–33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, longitudinal studies examining the dynamic relationships between these variables are limited. To address this gap, the present study employed a multi-wave longitudinal design to examine the dynamic longitudinal relationships between sleep disturbances, self-compassion, and NSSI. Based on the literature, three hypotheses were examined: 1) Sleep disturbances and NSSI would bidirectionally and positively predict each other; 2) Sleep disturbances and self-compassion would bidirectionally and negatively predict each other; 3) Self-compassion would mediate the longitudinal link from sleep disturbances to NSSI.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants and Procedures</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Participants were selected from a large-scale health-related cohort among Chinese college students. This cohort was a six-wave prospective study from 2019 to 2022 in south China. Detailed sampling and data collection have been described in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. Briefly, at baseline (T</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>0</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, May 2020), 5608 freshmen (51.8% male, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">M</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>age</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=18.63, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">SD</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=0.88) from two public universities were identified for subsequent follow-up investigations. Of the participants at baseline, 5497 (2.0% attrition rate), 5363 (4.4% attrition rate), 5239 (6.6% attrition rate), 4326 (22.8% attrition rate), and 4312 (23.1% attrition rate) provided valid responses at Time 1 (T</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>1</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, October 2020), Time 2 (T</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, May 2021), Time 3 (T</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>3</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, October 2021), Time 4 (T</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>4</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, May 2022), and Time 5 (T</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>5</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, October 2022) respectively. The main reason for attrition was that students were absent from class on the day of the assessment. In the current study, we used data from T</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> to T</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>5</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> because self-compassion or non-suicidal self-injury was not measured at the baseline and Time 1. Ultimately, 4303 students (48.4% male, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">M</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>age</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=18.50, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">SD</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">=0.80) who completed at least three waves were included in this study.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sampling procedure for the current study.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1221-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: “less than 10 minutes means” means that if the time it took to complete the survey was less than 10 minutes, the questionnaire was considered to be invalid.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The missing completely at random (MCAR) test was used on all variables across the four waves of the study. The result showed that the data were not missing at a random (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">χ</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=585.81, df =197, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p&lt;</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> 0.001). According to Goodman and Blum,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> chi-square tests and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> tests were conducted to compare demographic characteristics and outcome variables at baseline for participants who completed four surveys with those who did not. The results found that males (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">χ</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 63.97, df = 1, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p &lt;</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> 0.001) were more likely to drop out. As for the outcome variables, students with higher self-compassion at T</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> were more likely to drop out (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=3.15, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p &lt;</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> 0.01). No significant differences were found in other outcome variables. Therefore, the full information maximum likelihood (FIML) method was used in subsequent model estimations.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Every academic year, Chinese universities organize mental health surveys for college students, and students were approached through these surveys. This organized questionnaire survey effectively reduces the rate of dropout. All participants completed an online mental health survey using mobile phones in a regular classroom environment with the help of trained teachers and graduate assistants. It took approximately 30 mins to complete the questionnaire. Before collecting data, we obtained permission from the principals of two schools and obtained informed consent from students. All participants were informed that their participation in the study was voluntary and that they could withdraw from the study at any time without repercussions. The present study protocol was reviewed and approved by the Research Ethics Committee of Hebei University.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Questionnaire Measures</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Sleep Disturbances</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Sleep disturbances were measured using the Youth Self-Rating Insomnia Scale (YSIS).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The YSIS consists of 8 items assessing insomnia symptoms, perceived sleep quality, sleep insufficiency, sleep dissatisfaction, and interference of sleep difficulties with daytime functioning. Insomnia symptoms were measured with three items: “Trouble falling asleep”, “Wake up frequently during the night”, and “Wake up very early and cannot get back to sleep”. Perceived sleep quality, sleep dissatisfaction, and sleep insufficiency were each assessed with one item: “During the past month, how would you rate the quality of your sleep overall?” “During the past month, how satisfied were you with your sleep overall?” “Do you feel that you do not have enough sleep”. Impaired daytime functioning was measured using two items: “Feel unrested and unrestored upon waking” and “Sleep disturbances interfere with your daily activities”. Perceived sleep quality is rated from 1=very good to 5=very poor and sleep dissatisfaction is rated from 1= very satisfied to 5=very unsatisfied. The remaining 6 items are rated on a five-point scale from 1 = never, 2 = rarely (&lt;1 time/week), 3 = sometimes (1–2 times/week), 4 = often (3–5 times/week), to 5 = almost every day (6–7 times/week). The total score of YSIS ranges from 8 to 40, with a higher score reflecting more severe sleep disturbances during the past month. The YSIS has been found to have appropriate internal consistency and test-retest reliability,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and has been adopted in some studies.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In this study, Cronbach’ s alpha values were 0.86, 0.75, 0.76, and 0.87 for T</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> to T</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>5</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, respectively.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Self-Compassion</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Self-compassion was measured using the Self-Compassion Scale-Short Form (SCS-SF).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The SCS-SF is a short-form version of the original Self-Compassion Scale (SCS),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> which has demonstrated adequate internal consistency (Cronbach’ s alpha ≥ 0.86) and a near-perfect correlation (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">=0.97) with the original scale. The SCS-SF includes 12-item items, and all items are answered on a 5-point Likert scale ranging from 1 (almost never) to 5 (almost always). This scale comprises six dimensions measuring self-kindness, self-judgment, common humanity, isolation, mindfulness, and over-identification. After recoding the reversed items, all items are summed to get a total score ranging from 12 to 60. A higher total score indicates a higher level of self-compassion. The SCS-SF has demonstrated good psychometric properties in the Chinese college students.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In this study, Cronbach’ s alpha values were 0.68, 0.71, 0.72, and 0.70 for T</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> to T</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>5</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, respectively.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Non-Suicidal Self-Injury</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Non-suicidal self-injury was measured using seven items from the Deliberate Self-harm Inventory.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Participants were asked, “During the past six months, have you ever engaged in the following behaviors to hurt yourself deliberately without intention to kill yourself”. These behaviors included cutting, burning, hitting, etc. Participants rated their engagement in these behaviors on a 7-point scale from 1=never to 7=six times or more. The score is calculated by summing all responses, with higher scores indicating higher levels of NSSI. According to previous study,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> NSSI was categorized into two groups: sporadic (ie, 1–4 times) and repetitive NSSI (ie, ≥ 5 times), based on the frequency of NSSI. Deliberate Self-harm Inventory has been widely used in previous studies.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In this study, Cronbach’ s alpha values were 0.96, 0.92, 0.90, and 0.86 for T</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> to T</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>5</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, respectively.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Covariates</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Several demographic covariates were reported by the students at baseline, including students’ gender (0 = female, 1 = male), age, and family economic status (0 = good, 1 = fair, 2 = poor).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2005">
        <title>Data Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Data analyses were divided into the following steps. First, descriptive statistics and zero-order correlation analysis were performed on the main variables. Second, confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) was adopted to evaluate the longitudinal measurement invariance for all measures across four measurement occasions. Measurement invariance was established when the model fit of different constraint models did not deteriorate significantly according to the changes in Comparative Fit Index (ΔCFI ≤ 0.010) and Root Mean Square Error of Approximation (ΔRMSEA ≤ 0.015) and Standardized Root Mean Squared Residual (ΔSRMR ≤ 0.010).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Third, two cross-lagged panel models were conducted to examine the hypothesized relationships among sleep disturbance, self-compassion, and NSSI. The first model tested the association between sleep disturbance and NSSI by including the stability paths, within-wave associations, and cross-lagged effects. In the second model, we added self-compassion to the first model as a possible mediator to test the hypothesized full model. Participants’ gender, age and family SES were entered in all models as time-invariant covariates across four time points. Due to the nonnormally distribution of NSSI, we used the maximum likelihood robust estimator (MLR) to obtain a more accurate parameter estimation. Multiple indicators were used to evaluate model fit: the comparative fit index (CFI; acceptable &gt; 0.90), the root mean square error of approximation (RMSEA; acceptable &lt; 0.08), and the standardized root mean square residual (SRMR; acceptable &lt; 0.08). The significance of the mediated effects was tested using the bias-corrected percentile bootstrap method with 1000 samples. The effect is significant if the confidence intervals did not include zero. Fourth, a multi-group approach was applied to test invariance across gender for the two cross-lagged panel models. All analyses in this study were performed using IBM SPSS version 26.0 and Mplus 8.4.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0004-s2001">
        <title>Descriptive Analyses</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> displays descriptive statistics and bivariate correlations about sleep disturbances, self-compassion, and NSSI. Sleep disturbances were significantly negatively correlated with self-compassion and positively correlated with NSSI at each time point. Self-compassion was significantly negatively correlated with NSSI at each time point. The ranges for skewness of sleep disturbances, self-compassion, and NSSI at the four time points were 0.68 to 0.82, 0.35 to 0.76, and 5.69 to 9.81, respectively, and the ranges for kurtosis of these variables were 0.29 to 1.21, 0.14 to 0.36, 36.05 to 125.23, respectively. As shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">, 9.2%, 8.3%, 7.2%, and 10.2% of college students reported at least one self-injury behavior. More specifically, 6.7%, 5.8%, 5.1%, and 5.3% reported sporadic NSSI, and 2.5%, 2.6%, 2.1%, and 4.9% reported repetitive NSSI.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Zero-Order Correlations Among Main Variables</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1. Sleep disturbances (T<sub>2</sub>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2. Sleep disturbances (T<sub>3</sub>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3. Sleep disturbances (T<sub>4</sub>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4. Sleep disturbances (T<sub>5</sub>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5. Self-compassion (T<sub>2</sub>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6. Self-compassion (T<sub>3</sub>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7. Self-compassion (T<sub>4</sub>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8. Self-compassion (T<sub>5</sub>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9. NSSI (T<sub>2</sub>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10. NSSI (T<sub>3</sub>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11. NSSI (T<sub>4</sub>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12. NSSI (T<sub>5</sub>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.55</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Note</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: All correlation coefficients are significant at 0.001 (two-tailed). NSSI = Non-suicidal self-injury.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The prevalence of non-suicidal self-injury among college students.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1221-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2002">
        <title>Longitudinal Measurement Invariance</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Longitudinal measurement invariance was tested to determine the degree of consistent measurement across time. As shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">, scalar invariance was established for self-compassion and NSSI measures, and metric invariance was established for sleep disturbances. These results indicated that observed changes in these variables over time were meaningful rather than reflecting measurement artifacts.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Fit Indices for Measurement Invariance of Sleep Disturbances, Self-Compassion and Non-Suicidal Self-Injury</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model Tested</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">χ</italic><sup>2</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">df</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CFI</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TLI</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RMSEA</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SRMR</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ CFI</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ RMSEA</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ SRMR</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Sleep disturbances</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Configural MI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1171.203</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">188</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.977</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.966</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Metric MI</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1317.749</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>200</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.974</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.964</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.036</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.042</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.003</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.007</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scalar MI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4758.488</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">218</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.893</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.865</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.170</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.081</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.128</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Self-compassion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Configural MI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8241.925</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">732</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.943</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.912</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.050</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.054</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metric MI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8278.493</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">750</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.943</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.914</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.049</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.054</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Scalar MI</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>8664.897</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>786</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.940</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.914</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.049</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.055</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.003</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Non-suicidal self-injury</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Configural MI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7455.807</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">302</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.916</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.894</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.075</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metric MI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8774.571</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">320</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.910</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.890</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.077</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.006</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Scalar MI</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>8943.120</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>341</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.905</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.888</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.077</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.044</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.005</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.002</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Note</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Bold type indicates established model of measurement invariance.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2003">
        <title>The Results of Cross-Lagged Panel Models</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">After controlling for gender, age and FES, the first CLPM was conducted to test the association between sleep disturbances and NSSI. The result showed that the model fitted the data well, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">χ</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 454.56, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">df</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> =12, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.001, CFI = 0.92, SRMR = 0.06, and RMSEA = 0.071. As depicted in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, all the auto-regressive paths for sleep disturbances and NSSI were significant. For the cross-lagged paths, sleep disturbances at prior time points predicted NSSI at subsequent time points but not vice versa. These results indicated that sleep disturbances may have a greater impact on subsequent NSSI.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Cross-Lagged Panel Model for sleep disturbances and non-suicidal self-injury.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1221-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Note</bold>: *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05; *** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001.</attrib><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: SD, Sleep disturbances; NSSI, non-suicidal self-injury.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In the second CLPM, we added self-compassion to the first model as a possible mediator. The result showed that the model fitted the data best, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">χ</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 984.15, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">df</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> =27, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.001, CFI = 0.93, SRMR = 0.062, and RMSEA = 0.061. As depicted in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">, all the auto-regressive paths were significant. Analyses of indirect effects revealed a significant indirect path from sleep disturbances to NSSI through self-compassion over time (see </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). More specifically, the path from sleep disturbances at T</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> to NSSI at T</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>4</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> via self-compassion at T</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>3</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> was significant (indirect effect = 0.007, 95% CI = 0.004–0.011); and the path from sleep disturbances at T</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>3</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> to NSSI at T</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>5</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> via self-compassion at T</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>4</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> was significant (indirect effect = 0.009, 95% CI = 0.006–0.013). Additionally, bidirectional relationships between sleep disturbances and self-compassion were also found.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Significant Indirect Paths Between Sleep Disturbances, Self-Compassion, and NSSI for the Final CLPM</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Indirect Effects</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">β</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">SE</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Bootstrapped 95% CI</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD T<sub>2</sub> → SCT<sub>3</sub> → NSSI T<sub>4</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD T<sub>3</sub> → SCT<sub>4</sub> → NSSI T<sub>5</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Note</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: ***</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.001. Standardized coefficients.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: NSSI, Non-suicidal self-injury; T, Time. are presented, CLPM, Cross-Lagged Panel Model; SD, Sleep disturbances; SC, Self-compassion.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0004" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Cross-Lagged Panel Model for sleep disturbances, self-compassion, and non-suicidal self-injury.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1221-g0004" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Note</bold>: *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05**<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01; ***<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001.</attrib><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: SD, Sleep disturbances; SC, self-compassion; NSSI, non-suicidal self-injury.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2004">
        <title>Gender Invariance Analyses</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">A multi-group approach was adopted to test invariance across gender, and the results suggested that these associations did not have significant gender differences. Therefore, gender did not moderate the relationships among the three variables.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The current study is the first to use the cross-lagged panel models (CLPMs) to more thoroughly and rigorously examine the longitudinal relationship between sleep disturbances and NSSI, and the mediating role of self-compassion in a large sample of college students. The main results are as follows: 1) prior sleep disturbances predicted subsequent NSSI after adjusting for covariates; 2) self-compassion mediated the longitudinal relationship between sleep disturbances and NSSI after adjusting for covariates; 3) there is a bidirectional and negative effect between sleep disturbances and self-compassion.</citation_analysis></p>
      <sec id="s0005-s2001">
        <title>The Prevalence Rates of NSSI</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The overall prevalence of NSSI among college students varies from 7.2% to 10.2% across different time points, with 5.1–6.7% of students reporting sporadic NSSI and 2.1–4.9% reporting repetitive NSSI, which is consistent with some previous studies.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> For instance, using data from the Leuven College Surveys, Kiekens et al found that a one-year incidence of first onset NSSI was 10.3%, with a total of 8.6% of participants reporting sporadic NSSI and 7.0% reporting repetitive NSSI during the first two years of college.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, some studies found higher or lower prevalence of NSSI compared with our results. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> These variations may be influenced by factors such as cultural and socioeconomic differences, as well as variations in screening methods, sample characteristics, and timeframe used to estimate prevalence (lifetime, last year, or last month).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0005-s2002">
        <title>The Mediating Role of Self-Compassion Between Sleep Disturbances and NSSI</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">As a crucial strategy for emotional regulation, self-compassion was incorporated into the cross-lagged mediation model to explore its potential mediating role between sleep disturbances and NSSI. Our hypothesis was supported showing that self-compassion indeed played a longitudinal mediating role in linking sleep disturbances and NSSI. More specifically, individuals with more severe sleep disturbances tended to have lower levels of self-compassion, thereby increasing their risk of engaging in NSSI. These findings extended the literature that has identified self-compassion as a mediator between negative life events (eg, peer victimization and traumatic stress) and self-injury (or other psychological maladjustment). </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37–39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">On the one hand, we found that sleep disturbances were negatively predictive of self-compassion. This aligns with the principles of Compassion-focused therapy (CFT), which proposes that individuals have three affect-regulating systems: 1) the threat system (functions to protect individuals from harm), 2) the drive system (functions to seek resources and achieve goals), and 3) the soothing system (functions to promote rest and digest, ease, and calmness).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Based on this model, stressful life events, such as chronic sleep disturbances, may trigger a defense response through the threat system, thereby disrupting their soothing system. Consequently, individuals experiencing sleep disturbances may struggle to show compassion towards their own distress and utilize compassionate self-regulation skills.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In addition, self-compassion is believed to encompass the ability to perceive life experiences more “objectively”.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Individuals with sleep disturbances, in contrast to those without, often exhibit negative cognition,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> such as self-criticism and catastrophic thoughts. These negative thought patterns may undermine an individual’s capacity to provide themselves with emotional care.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> On the other hand, our results suggested that self-compassion had a longitudinal effect on NSSI, which was consistent with previous cross-sectional</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31−33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and longitudinal studies. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Several possible explanations can be proposed for these associations. Firstly, according to the benefits and barriers model of NSSI,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> people have to overcome several instinctive “barriers” before experiencing the “benefits” of NSSI. Having a positive self-view (eg, self-compassion) may create an environment where it is difficult to deliberately self-injure because individuals with high levels of self-compassion may view themselves favorably and have a protective attitude towards their bodies, making it less likely for them to engage in self-injury as a means of coping with negative emotions.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> When the “barrier” of a positive self-view is weakened, individuals may start to believe that they deserve pain and punishment, leading to a stronger identification with NSSI.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,60 Secondly, the social mentality theory of self-compassion and self-reassurance posit that self-compassion can enhance individuals’ ability to seek support and assistance from others.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Therefore, individuals with higher levels of self-compassion may be more likely to communicate their need for help and respond positively to support from others.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> As a result, others may be more willing to provide additional support, leading to a greater sense of social support, which may prevent the occurrence of NSSI. Thirdly, previous research has found a positive association between self-compassion and adaptive coping, as well as a negative correlation with maladaptive coping.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Maladaptive coping strategies have been shown to be associated with NSSI.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Overall, self-compassion may be a potential mediating mechanism linking sleep disturbances and NSSI.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0005-s2003">
        <title>The Bidirectional Relationship Between Sleep Disturbances and Self-Compassion</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our results suggested a bidirectional relationship between sleep disturbances and self-compassion, which was consistent with previous empirical research.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0063" ref-type="bibr">63–65</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The predictive effects of sleep disturbances on self-compassion have been discussed earlier. This section focuses on the predictive effect of self-compassion on sleep disturbances. Self-compassion can contribute to nighttime relaxation, but self-critical thoughts may fuel restlessness and agitation, leading to poorer sleep quality. Emerging studies have suggested that self-compassion may play a protective role in ameliorating the negative effects of stressors on sleep quality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In addition, self-compassion-based interventions have shown effectiveness in improving sleep quality. For instance, in an experiment conducted by Butz and Stahlberg,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> compared to students in the control group, those in the self-compassion intervention groups (a 20-min brief self-compassion meditation vs a self-compassionate writing task) reported significantly better sleep quality. In short, self-compassion is amenable and that improved self-compassion can promote better sleep quality.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0005-s2004">
        <title>Strengths and Limitations</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Compared to previous cross-sectional designs or shorter-term longitudinal studies, this study used a large-sample longitudinal design to comprehensively examine the temporal associations between sleep disturbances, self-compassion, and NSSI from a developmental perspective. Although this study contributes to the literature, the findings need to be interpreted with consideration of several limitations. First, all data were assessed by self-report measures, which may be affected by social desirability and recall bias. Structured diagnostic interviews and behavioral measures should be used in future studies to provide a comprehensive understanding of the variables under investigation. Second, due to data fitting, random intercept cross-lagged panel models (RI-CLPMs) were not use in this study. This means that we did not disentangle between-person variance and within-person variance.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Future studies could use RI-CLPMs to explore longitudinal relationships between the aforementioned variables at the within-person level. Third, we used a convenience sample of college students in the southern provinces of China, which made it difficult to generalize our findings to other regions or cultural contexts. Future studies in a larger and more diverse samples would help to enhance the external validity of our findings. Finally, the validity of the SCS as a measure of self-compassion has long been debated. The SCS scale measures both positive and negative components simultaneously. Thus, there is a growing trend to separate the SCS into two independent factors in research. However, Neff indicted that self-compassion represents movement along a continuum from uncompassionate self-responding to compassionate self-responding, and separating the SCS into two separate factors is problematic.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0005-s2005">
        <title>Clinical Implications</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">From a practical perspective, these findings indicated that clinicians and school counselors should incorporate the assessment and intervention of sleep disturbances, self-compassion, and NSSI into their practice. Psychological interventions aimed at improving sleep quality, such as cognitive-behavioral therapy (CBT) and dialectical behavioral therapy (DBT), could be considered.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In addition, self-compassion-oriented prevention and intervention programs, such as compassion-focused therapy (CFT) and mindful self-compassion (MSC), may hold great promise in reducing the incidence of NSSI.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Meta-analyses have shown that self-compassion interventions are effective in promoting self-compassion and reducing psychopathology in clinical and subclinical populations.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Therefore, schools and mental health professionals should encourage college students who are experiencing sleep problems to participate in self-compassion courses.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The current study utilized CLPMs to theoretically test the longitudinal dynamic relationships between these variables. The results revealed a bidirectional association between sleep disturbances and self-compassion, with self-compassion mediated the association between sleep disturbances and NSSI.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We thank all the project participants in this study.</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s0007">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The data are not publicly available due to privacy and research ethical restrictions.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0008">
      <title>Statement of Ethics</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This study complies with the Declaration of Helsinki. The present study protocol was reviewed and approved by the Research Ethics Committee of Hebei University.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0009">
      <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">All participants provided written informed consent prior to their study enrolment.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0010">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors declare no conflicts of interest in this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Klonsky</surname>
<given-names>ED</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Non-suicidal self-injury in United States adults: prevalence, sociodemographics, topography and functions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Med</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1981</fpage>–<lpage>1986</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/s0033291710002497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21208494</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jomar</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dhingra</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Forrester</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shahmalak</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dickson</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A meta-analysis of the prevalence of different functions of non-suicidal self-injury</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Affect Disord</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>227</volume>:<fpage>759</fpage>–<lpage>769</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2017.11.073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29689691</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Whitlock</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Muehlenkamp</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Purington</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Nonsuicidal self-injury in a college population: general trends and sex differences</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Health</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>691</fpage>–<lpage>698</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07448481.2010.529626</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21950249</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nock</surname>
<given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Self-injury</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Annu Rev Clin Psycho</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>339</fpage>–<lpage>363</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.clinpsy.121208.131258</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buelens</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luyckx</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kiekens</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gandhi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Muehlenkamp</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Claes</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Investigating the DSM-5 criteria for non-suicidal self-injury disorder in a community sample of adolescents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Affect Disord</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>260</volume>:<fpage>314</fpage>–<lpage>322</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2019.09.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31521868</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zetterqvist</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lundh</surname>
<given-names>LG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dahlström</surname>
<given-names>Ö</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Svedin</surname>
<given-names>CG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalence and function of non-suicidal self-injury (NSSI) in a community sample of adolescents, using suggested DSM-5 criteria for a potential NSSI disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Abnorm Child Psych</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>759</fpage>–<lpage>773</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10802-013-9712-5</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Alonso</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Auerbach</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bantjes</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Non-suicidal self-injury among first-year college students and its association with mental disorders: results from the world mental health international college student (WMH-ICS) initiative</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>875</fpage>–<lpage>886</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0033291721002245</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34140062</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kiekens</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hasking</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Claes</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Predicting the incidence of non-suicidal self-injury in college students</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Psychiat</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>44</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eurpsy.2019.04.002</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kiekens</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Claes</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hasking</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A longitudinal investigation of non-suicidal self-injury persistence patterns, risk factors, and clinical outcomes during the college period</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Med</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>6011</fpage>–<lpage>6026</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/s0033291722003178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36325723</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kiekens</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Claes</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Demyttenaere</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Lifetime and 12-month nonsuicidal self-injury and academic performance in college freshmen</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Suicide Life-Threat</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>563</fpage>–<lpage>576</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/sltb.12237</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bentley</surname>
<given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cassiello-Robbins</surname>
<given-names>CF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vittorio</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sauer-Zavala</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barlow</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The association between nonsuicidal self-injury and the emotional disorders: a meta-analytic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Psychol Rev</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>72</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cpr.2015.02.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25771494</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Paul</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsypes</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eidlitz</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ernhout</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whitlock</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Frequency and functions of non-suicidal self-injury: associations with suicidal thoughts and behaviors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiat Res</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>225</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>276</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2014.12.026</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Becker</surname>
<given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jarrett</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luebbe</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garner</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burns</surname>
<given-names>GL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kofler</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep in a large, multi-university sample of college students: sleep problem prevalence, sex differences, and mental health correlates</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Health</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>174</fpage>–<lpage>181</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleh.2018.01.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29555131</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A systematic review of studies on the prevalence of Insomnia in university students</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>129</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1579</fpage>–<lpage>1584</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.puhe.2015.07.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26298588</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Russell</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beattie</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bohan</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>MacMahon</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rasmussen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep problem, suicide and self-harm in university students: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>58</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2018.12.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30721844</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Burke</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hamilton</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seigel</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep irregularity and nonsuicidal self-injurious urges and behaviors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>zsac084</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsac084</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Latina</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bauducco</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tilton-Weaver</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia symptoms and non-suicidal self-injury in adolescence: understanding temporal relations and mechanisms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>e13190</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.13190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32893426</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bandel</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brausch</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Poor sleep associates with recent non-suicidal self-injury engagement in adolescents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15402002.2018.1545652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30472890</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Khazaie</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zakiei</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCall</surname>
<given-names>WV</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Relationship between sleep problems and self-injury: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>689</fpage>–<lpage>704</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15402002.2020.1822360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32991212</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Asarnow</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bai</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Babeva</surname>
<given-names>KN</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep in youth with repeated self-harm and high suicidality: does sleep predict self-harm risk?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Suicide Life-Threat</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1189</fpage>–<lpage>1197</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/sltb.12658</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Neff</surname>
<given-names>KD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The development and validation of a scale to measure self-compassion</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Self Identity</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>250</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15298860309027</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of childhood maltreatment on self-compassion: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Trauma Violence Abuse</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>873</fpage>–<lpage>885</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/15248380211043825</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34510982</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Miron</surname>
<given-names>LR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seligowski</surname>
<given-names>AV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boykin</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Orcutt</surname>
<given-names>HK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The potential indirect effect of childhood abuse on posttrauma pathology through self-compassion and fear of self-compassion</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mindfulness</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>596</fpage>–<lpage>605</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12671-016-0493-0</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Long</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ren</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Bullying victimization and depression among left-behind children in rural China: roles of self-compassion and hope</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Child Abuse Neglect</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>104072</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chiabu.2019.104072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31319239</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oldham</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fernando</surname>
<given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kirby</surname>
<given-names>JN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Compassion mediates poor sleep quality and mental health outcomes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mindfulness</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1252</fpage>–<lpage>1261</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12671-021-01595-8</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Neff</surname>
<given-names>KD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Self-compassion: theory, method, research, and intervention</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Annu Rev Psycho</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>74</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>218</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-psych-032420-031047</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Neff</surname>
<given-names>KD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Self-compassion, self-esteem, and well-being</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Soc Personal Psychol Compass</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1751-9004.2010.00330.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Neff</surname>
<given-names>KD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rude</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>An examination of self-compassion in relation to positive psychological functioning and personality traits</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Res Pers</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>908</fpage>–<lpage>916</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jrp.2006.08.002</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hooley</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Franklin</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Why do people hurt themselves? A new conceptual model of nonsuicidal self-injury</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Psychol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>428</fpage>–<lpage>451</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2167702617745641</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Xavier</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pinto Gouveia</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cunha</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Non-suicidal self-injury in adolescence: the role of shame, self-criticism and fear of self-compassion</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Child Youth Care For</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>571</fpage>–<lpage>586</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10566-016-9346-1</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Xavier</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pinto Gouveia</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cunha</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The protective role of self-compassion on risk factors for non-suicidal self-injury in adolescence</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sch Ment Health</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>476</fpage>–<lpage>485</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12310-016-9197-9</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cleare</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gumley</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Connor</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Self-compassion, self-forgiveness, suicidal ideation, and self-harm: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Psychol Psychot</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>511</fpage>–<lpage>530</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cpp.2372</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Per</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schmelefske</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brophy</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Austin</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khoury</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mindfulness, self-compassion, self-injury, and suicidal thoughts and behaviors: a correlational meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mindfulness</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>821</fpage>–<lpage>842</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12671-021-01815-1</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ewert</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vater</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schröder-Abé</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Self-compassion and coping: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mindfulness</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1063</fpage>–<lpage>1077</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12671-020-01563-8</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leary</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Self-compassion, stress, and coping</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Soc Personal Psychol Compass</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>118</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1751-9004.2009.00246.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20686629</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wan</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Associations of coping styles with nonsuicidal self-injury in adolescents: do they vary with gender and adverse childhood experiences?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Child Abuse Neglect</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>104</volume>:<fpage>104470</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chiabu.2020.104470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32234639</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Játiva</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cerezo</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The mediating role of self-compassion in the relationship between victimization and psychological maladjustment in a sample of adolescents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Child Abuse Neglect</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1180</fpage>–<lpage>1190</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chiabu.2014.04.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24811571</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Múzquiz</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pérez-García</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bermúdez</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Relationship between direct and relational bullying and emotional well-being among adolescents: the role of self-compassion</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<fpage>15874</fpage>–<lpage>15882</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12144-022-02924-3</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Najarian</surname>
<given-names>ASM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Understanding the association between negative life events and suicidal risk in college students: examining self-compassion as a potential mediator</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>73</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>745</fpage>–<lpage>755</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jclp.22374</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27716911</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Goodman</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blum</surname>
<given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Assessing the non-random sampling effects of subject attrition in longitudinal research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Manage</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>627</fpage>–<lpage>652</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0149-2063(96)90027-6</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Allison</surname>
<given-names>PD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Missing data techniques for structural equation modeling</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Abnorm Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>112</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>545</fpage>–<lpage>557</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0021-843x.112.4.545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14674868</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fan</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jia</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Psychometric properties of youth self-rating insomnia scale (YSIS) in Chinese adolescents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Biol Rhythms</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>339</fpage>–<lpage>348</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s41105-019-00222-3</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia and other sleep-related problems during the remission period of the COVID-19 pandemic: a large-scale survey among college students in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiat Res</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>304</volume>:<fpage>114153</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2021.114153</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chi</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liang</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>S-T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Mental health problems among Chinese adolescents during the COVID-19: the importance of nutrition and physical activity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Clin Hlth Psyc</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>100218</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijchp.2020.100218</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Raes</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pommier</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Neff</surname>
<given-names>KD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Gucht</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Construction and factorial validation of a short form of the self-compassion scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Psychol Psychot</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>250</fpage>–<lpage>255</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cpp.702</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chi</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Trajectories of complex posttraumatic stress symptoms among Chinese college students with childhood adversities: the role of self-compassion</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Child Abuse Neglect</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>150</volume>:<fpage>106138</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chiabu.2023.106138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36948929</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gratz</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Measurement of deliberate self-harm: preliminary data on the deliberate self-harm inventory</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychopathol Behav Assess</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>263</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1012779403943</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>You</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ying</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Emotion reactivity, nonsuicidal self-injury, and regulatory emotional self-efficacy: a moderated mediation model of suicide ideation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Affect Disord</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>266</volume>:<fpage>82</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2020.01.083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32056950</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>You</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Different profiles with multiple risk factors of nonsuicidal self-injury and their transitions during adolescence: a person-centered analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Affect Disord</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>295</volume>:<fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2021.08.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34416619</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>FF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sensitivity of goodness of fit indexes to lack of measurement invariance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Struct Equation Model</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>464</fpage>–<lpage>504</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10705510701301834</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Qu</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wen</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Non-suicidal self-injury in Chinese population: a scoping review of prevalence, method, risk factors and preventive interventions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Reg Health-Western Pac</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lanwpc.2023.100794</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Swannell</surname>
<given-names>SV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>GE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Page</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hasking</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>St John</surname>
<given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalence of nonsuicidal self-injury in nonclinical samples: systematic review, meta-analysis and meta-regression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Suicide Life-Threat</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>303</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/sltb.12070</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kiekens</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hasking</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boyes</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The associations between non-suicidal self-injury and first onset suicidal thoughts and behaviors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Affect Disord</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>239</volume>:<fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>179</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2018.06.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30014957</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Taliaferro</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Muehlenkamp</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Risk factors associated with self-injurious behavior among a national sample of undergraduate college students</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Health</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07448481.2014.953166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25144520</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0055">
        <label>55.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Boyne</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hamza</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Depressive symptoms, perceived stress, self-compassion and nonsuicidal self-injury among emerging adults: an examination of the between and within-person associations over time</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Emerg Adulthood</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1269</fpage>–<lpage>1285</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/21676968211029768</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36111318</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0056">
        <label>56.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gilbert</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The origins and nature of compassion focused therapy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brit J Clin Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>6</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bjc.12043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24588760</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0057">
        <label>57.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Neff</surname>
<given-names>KD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Self-compassion: an alternative conceptualization of a healthy attitude toward oneself</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Self Identity</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15298860309032</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0058">
        <label>58.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ballesio</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bacaro</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vacca</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Does cognitive behaviour therapy for insomnia reduce repetitive negative thinking and sleep-related worry beliefs? A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>101378</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2020.101378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32992228</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0059">
        <label>59.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ding</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The mutual relationship between self-compassion, perceived social support, and adolescent NSSI: a three-wave longitudinal study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mindfulness</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1940</fpage>–<lpage>1950</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12671-023-02169-6</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0060">
        <label>60.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hooley</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>St Germain</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Nonsuicidal self-injury, pain, and self-criticism: does changing self-worth change pain endurance in people who engage in self-injury?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Psychol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>305</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2167702613509372</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0061">
        <label>61.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hermanto</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zuroff</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The social mentality theory of self-compassion and self-reassurance: the interactive effect of care-seeking and caregiving</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Soc Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>156</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>523</fpage>–<lpage>535</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00224545.2015.1135779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26736073</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0062">
        <label>62.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cawood</surname>
<given-names>CD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huprich</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Late adolescent nonsuicidal self-injury: the roles of coping style, self-esteem, and personality pathology</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Pers Disord</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>765</fpage>–<lpage>781</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1521/pedi.2011.25.6.765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22217223</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0063">
        <label>63.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arteta-Garcia</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Purol</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Diary study: the protective role of self-compassion on stress-related poor sleep quality</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mindfulness</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1931</fpage>–<lpage>1940</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12671-018-0939-7</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0064">
        <label>64.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Butz</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stahlberg</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Can self-compassion improve sleep quality via reduced rumination?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Self Identity</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>666</fpage>–<lpage>686</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15298868.2018.1456482</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0065">
        <label>65.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Houston</surname>
<given-names>EE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amonoo</surname>
<given-names>HL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bryant</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Is self-compassion associated with sleep quality? A meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mindfulness</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>82</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12671-020-01498-0</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0066">
        <label>66.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hamaker</surname>
<given-names>EL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuiper</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grasman</surname>
<given-names>RPPP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A critique of the cross-lagged panel model</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Methods</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>102</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0038889</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25822208</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0067">
        <label>67.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Calvo</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>García-González</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perez-Galbarro</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Psychotherapeutic interventions specifically developed for NSSI in adolescence: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Neuropsychopharm</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>86</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.euroneuro.2022.02.009</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0068">
        <label>68.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Turner</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Austin</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chapman</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Treating nonsuicidal self-injury: a systematic review of psychological and pharmacological interventions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Can J Psychiat</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>576</fpage>–<lpage>585</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/070674371405901103</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0069">
        <label>69.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Hasking</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <part-title>Self-compassion and non-suicidal self-injury</part-title>. In: <string-name><surname>Finlay-Jones</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bluth</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Neff</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, editors. <source><italic toggle="yes">Handbook of Self-Compassion</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name>; <year>2023</year>:<fpage>369</fpage>–<lpage>378</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0070">
        <label>70.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wilson</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mackintosh</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Power</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>SWY</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effectiveness of self-compassion related therapies: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mindfulness</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>979</fpage>–<lpage>995</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12671-018-1037-6</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
