<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39282468</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">11401520</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">456025</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S456025</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Sex Differences in the Associations Between Chronic Diseases and Insomnia Symptoms Among Older Adults in India</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Muhammad et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Muhammad et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1486-7038</contrib-id><name><surname>Muhammad</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>Milan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5377-4614</contrib-id><name><surname>Jana</surname><given-names>Arup</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7623-3770</contrib-id><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Soomi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Center for Healthy Aging, The Pennsylvania State University</institution>, <addr-line>University Park</addr-line>, <addr-line>PA</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Population &amp; Development, International Institute for Population Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Mumbai</addr-line>, <addr-line>Maharashtra</addr-line>, <country>India</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Arup Jana; T Muhammad, Email arupjana0000@gmail.com; mkt5742@psu.edu</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>1339</fpage><lpage>1353</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Muhammad et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Muhammad et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Sleep problems are a critical issue in the aging population, affecting quality of life, cognitive efficiency, and contributing to adverse health outcomes. The coexistence of multiple diseases is common among older adults, particularly women. This study examines the associations between specific chronic diseases, multimorbidity, and insomnia symptoms among older Indian men and women, with a focus on the interaction of sex in these associations.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Data were drawn from 31,464 individuals aged 60 and older in the Longitudinal Ageing Study in India, Wave-1 (2017–18). Insomnia symptoms were assessed using four questions adapted from the Jenkins Sleep Scale (JSS-4), covering difficulty falling asleep, waking up, waking too early, and feeling unrested during the day. Multivariable logistic regression models, stratified by sex, were used to analyze the associations between chronic diseases and insomnia symptoms.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Older women had a higher prevalence of insomnia symptoms than men (44.73% vs 37.15%). Hypertension was associated with higher odds of insomnia in both men (AOR: 1.20) and women (AOR: 1.36). Women with diabetes had lower odds of insomnia (AOR: 0.80), while this association was not significant in men. Neurological or psychiatric disorders, stroke, and bone and joint diseases were linked to higher odds of insomnia in both sexes. Chronic lung disease was associated with insomnia in men (AOR: 1.65), but not in women. Additionally, having three or more chronic diseases significantly increased the odds of insomnia in both men (AOR: 2.43) and women (AOR: 2.01).</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Hypertension, bone and joint diseases, lung diseases, stroke, neurological or psychiatric disorders, and multimorbidity are linked to insomnia symptoms in older Indian adults. Disease-specific management and routine insomnia screening are crucial for promoting healthy aging in this vulnerable population.</citation_analysis></p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>chronic conditions</kwd><kwd>India</kwd><kwd>insomnia symptoms</kwd><kwd>multimorbidity</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="2"/><ref-count count="88"/><page-count count="15"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The prevalence of sleep complaints and multimorbidity increases with aging.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Sufficient rest plays a crucial role in promoting the holistic wellbeing of the broader community, encompassing physical, social, and mental dimensions of health.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, the swiftly expanding elderly demographic in low- and middle-income countries (LMICs) including India, coupled with a notable incidence of non-communicable diseases (NCDs) and symptoms of insomnia, presents an escalating obstacle for policymakers and researchers. This trend augments the demands on caregiving within households and communities.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4–6</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">It has been found that the overall health of an older adult declines when they experience sleep disorders.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> According to prior studies, many factors have been connected to insomnia symptoms in the aged population. Age-related medical and psychiatric conditions, for instance, raise the likelihood of insomnia symptoms, especially in the 60-year-old population.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Furthermore, several chronic diseases, including hypertension, diabetes, stroke, obesity, and coronary artery diseases are significant risk factors for clinical symptoms of insomnia.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8–10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, insomnia symptoms are not always related to getting older, for example, in the United States, it has been found that being older was not associated with self-reported insomnia symptoms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Similarly, one study reveals that about 71% of older person in Nepal had insomnia, which was associated not just to age but also to illiteracy, unemployment, economic dependence, and most notably the existence of comorbidities.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The literature shows close relationships between insomnia and chronic diseases. Specifically, persons with hypertension were more likely to have shorter sleep duration</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and sleep problems/disorders including obstructive sleep apnea (OSA), and restless legs syndrome and narcolepsy.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Likewise, diabetes was found to be associated with chronic insomnia, with a 2.95-fold increased risk for those who slept less than 6 hours a night.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> It is well established by previous studies that there is a direct link between insomnia and depression</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and comorbid nature of psychiatric disorders with sleep disturbances.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Additionally, those with arthritis were 23% more likely than people without arthritis to experience insomnia symptoms,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) was shown to be related to poor sleep quality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Another study among older Chinese adults found that heart disease, COPD and gastroenteritis were associated with short sleep, whereas hypertension was associated with long sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Besides, systematic reviews and several longitudinal studies have suggested a strong link between cardiovascular diseases and insomnia and/or sleep disorders.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24–28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Yet, there has been limited research thus far on chronic diseases and associated insomnia symptoms in LMICs including India because of the lack of population-based data.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">When examining the risk of insomnia symptoms associated with chronic conditions in Indian older adults, it is important to consider potential sex differences. Previous studies on Indian older adults found that women reported significantly higher odds of sleep problems than their men counterparts,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and women had greater impairments in quality of life related to insomnia symptoms compared to older men.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> In the larger literature, many studies have examined sex differences in the chronic disease-insomnia link, while results are mixed depending on specific chronic diseases examined. Some studies report that older men suffer from insomnia more frequently than women and that this is related to poor health, depression, angina pectoris and limitations in daily activities.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> On the other hand, daytime sleeplessness, one of the symptoms of insomnia, has been linked to a range of psychosocial health issues and has been proven to be more prevalent in older women and people with low educational attainment in urban areas.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Importantly, biological differences between male and female sexes may explain the variations in the associations between chronic diseases and insomnia symptoms among older men and women. For instance, sex hormones like oestrogen and progesterone, which decrease during menopause, significantly influence sleep architecture and vulnerability to insomnia in women.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Conversely, testosterone levels, which impact muscle tone and breathing, may contribute to sleep apnea and subsequent insomnia in men.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> These hormonal influences, along with physiological, and psychosocial factors, underscore the necessity of sex-specific analyses in examining the relationships between chronic diseases and insomnia symptoms.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In this study, we examined the associations of chronic diseases (specific types, number) with insomnia symptoms with a specific focus on sex differences using large a nationally representative sample of older adults in India. We hypothesised significant sex differences in the prevalence of insomnia symptoms with a higher prevalence among older women than men. We also hypothesized that each type of and a greater number of chronic conditions would be positively associated with insomnia symptoms among older adults and women in particular.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Data</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The data for this research was sourced from the wave 1 of the Longitudinal Ageing Study in India (LASI), conducted during 2017–18. It encompasses a sample of more than 72,000 individuals aged 45 and above, representing all states and union territories of India. LASI utilized a multistage stratified area probability cluster sampling approach to select the final units of observation, which included individuals aged 45 years and older, as well as their spouses, regardless of age.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The survey utilized a three-stage sampling strategy in rural regions and a four-stage sampling approach in urban areas. A comprehensive methodology, providing full details on the survey design and data collection, was made available in the survey report.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The Indian Council of Medical Research (ICMR) provided the requisite guidelines and ethical approval for conducting the LASI survey. The survey agencies responsible for fieldwork obtained informed consent from the participants prior to data collection. The current study specifically focuses on respondents aged 60 years and older and the total sample comprises 31,464 older adults in this age group (15,098 men and 16,366 women).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Outcome Variables</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The LASI survey evaluated insomnia symptoms using four questions, which were adapted from the Jenkins Sleep Scale (JSS-4).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The JSS scale was developed as a brief questionnaire to recognize sleep difficulties in the last month and is most commonly used sleep-related scale in epidemiological studies.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The items read: 1) “How often do you have trouble falling asleep?“ 2) “How often do you have trouble with waking up during the night?“ 3) “How often do you have trouble with waking up too early and not being able to fall asleep again?” 4) ”How often did you feel unrested during the day regardless of the number of hours of sleep you had?” Response options were “never”, “rarely” (1–2 nights per week), “occasionally” (3–4 nights per week), and “frequently” (5 or more nights per week). Insomnia symptoms was coded as 1 if the response was ‘occasionally’ or ‘frequently’ for any of the four symptoms (3 or more nights per week). For sensitivity analysis, a continuous scale of insomnia symptoms with a score of 0–12 was created as a summary of four items with the responses ranging 0 (never) to 3 (frequently). The JSS-4 scale of assessing insomnia symptoms has proved excellent reliability and demonstrated good construct validity.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">” The internal consistency of JSS-4 was excellent in this study (Cronbach’s alpha value: 0.88).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Main Explanatory Variables</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Chronic diseases refer to self-report of physician diagnosed chronic conditions that include hypertension, diabetes, neurological/psychiatric disorders, chronic lung disease, chronic heart disease, stroke, and any bone or joint diseases. Participants self-reported these diseases in response to the query: “Has any health professional ever diagnosed you with the following chronic conditions or diseases?” Responses were coded as “yes” to indicate the presence of specific disease, and “no” otherwise. The number of chronic diseases was categorized as no disease, one, two, and three plus diseases. The specific diseases analyzed in this study are as follows:
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><list list-type="order"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: Participants were reported about whether they had been diagnosed with hypertension or high blood pressure by a healthcare professional, and their responses were categorized as “no” or ‘yes’.</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Individuals were questioned regarding whether they had received a diagnosis of diabetes or high blood sugar from any healthcare provider, and their responses were categorized as “no” or ‘yes”.</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Neurological/ psychiatric disorder</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: This data was gathered through inquiries regarding whether individuals had ever received a diagnosis of neurological or psychiatric conditions, such as depression, Alzheimer’s/Dementia, unipolar/bipolar disorders, convulsions, Parkinson’s, etc., from any healthcare provider. Their responses were categorized as “no” or “yes”.</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Chronic lung disease</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: This data originated from a question regarding whether individuals had ever been diagnosed with chronic lung disease, such as asthma, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), chronic bronchitis, or other chronic respiratory issues by any healthcare provider. Their responses were classified as “no” or “yes”.</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Chronic heart disease</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Participants were asked about whether they had received a diagnosis of chronic heart diseases, such as coronary heart disease (heart attack or myocardial infarction), congestive heart failure, or other chronic heart conditions from any healthcare professional, and their responses were categorized as “no” or “yes”.</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Stroke</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Participants were questioned about whether they had been diagnosed with a stroke by any healthcare professional, and their responses were categorized as “no” or “yes”.</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Bone or joint related diseases</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Participants were inquired about whether they had received a diagnosis of arthritis or rheumatism, osteoporosis, or other bone/joint diseases from any healthcare professional, and their responses were classified as “no” or “yes”.</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Control Variables</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Age was categorized into three groups: 60–69 years, 70–79 years, and 80 years and above. Sex was categorized as men or women. Educational attainment was categorized as no education/primary not completed, primary, secondary, and higher education. Marital status was categorized as currently married, widowed and others which encompassed individuals who were divorced, separated, or never married. Living arrangements were categorized as living alone, living with spouse, or living with others. Work status was categorized into never worked, currently not working, currently working and retired. Physical activity was assessed according to the WHO guidelines, using the survey questions on moderate and vigorous physical activity.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> We categorized it into four groups: 1) none (physically inactive), 2) only moderate, 3) only vigorous, 4) and moderate and vigorous. Sleep medications was assessed using the survey question, “In the past month, have you taken any medications or used other treatments to help you sleep?” and the responses were coded as 0 “no” and 1 “yes”.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The quintiles of monthly per-capita consumption expenditure (MPCE) were determined using household consumption data. Sets of 11 and 29 questions regarding expenditures on food and non-food items, respectively, were administered to the sampled households. Food expenditure was recorded over a seven-day period, while non-food expenditure was recorded over reference periods of 30 days and 365 days. Both food and non-food expenditures were adjusted to a standardized 30-day reference period. The MPCE was calculated and employed as the comprehensive measure of consumption.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The variable was segmented into five quintiles, ranging from the least affluent (poorest) to the most affluent (richest). Religion was reclassified into Hindu, Muslim, and Others. Caste was reclassified into Scheduled Tribe/Scheduled Caste (SC/ST), Other Backward Class (OBC), and Others. Place of residence was categorized as urban and rural.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Descriptive statistics and bivariate analysis were employed to present the sample characteristics and to report the prevalence of insomnia symptoms. Subsequently, multivariable logistic regression analysis was conducted to assess the relationship between chronic diseases, the number of chronic diseases and insomnia symptoms. To estimate sex-specific odds ratios (ie, risks for insomnia), we used sex-stratified models. To test whether the associations between chronic diseases and insomnia symptoms differed between men and women, we included each chronic disease × sex interaction term in the multivariable model. The multivariable results were presented as unadjusted odds ratios, and adjusted odds ratios (AOR) with 95% confidence intervals (CI). Multiple multivariable logistic regression models were employed to examine the associations between chronic diseases and each insomnia symptom which adjusts for all covariates considered in the study, ie, age, education, marital status, living arrangements, work status, physical activity, sleep medications, wealth quintiles, religion, caste and place of residence.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Sensitivity analyses were conducted by employing multivariable linear regression models on a continuous scale of insomnia symptoms (score ranging 0–12) and chronic conditions. Additionally, separate logistic regression models were employed to analyse each insomnia symptom individually by chronic conditions and other background characteristics. Multivariable analyses were weighted to account for the stratified sampling and to provide the national estimates. Regression diagnostics were used to rule out any potential violation of regression assumptions. The statistical analysis was conducted using Stata 16.1.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> shows the sex-specific sample distribution of respondents by background characteristics. About 11.04% of the men and 11.52% of the women belonged to the 80+ age group. Around 28% of men and 37% of women had hypertension; 2.7% of men and 2.9% of women had neurological or psychiatric disorders; 9% of men and 8% of women had lung disease; 5.81% of men and 4.64% of women had heart disease; 3.29% of men and 2.23% women had stroke; and 16.25% of men and 22.8% of women had bone and joint related disease.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Socioeconomic and Health Profile of the Study Participants</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Background Factors</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men (N= 15,098)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women (N= 16,366)</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Chi-square p-value</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (in years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 60–69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8961 (57.82)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,013 (59.13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 70–79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4545 (31.14)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4556 (29.35)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 80+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1592 (11.04)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1797 (11.52)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Educational status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5479 (38.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,410 (72.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Primary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3361 (22.36)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2479 (13.12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Secondary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4249 (26.22)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1857 (11.04)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Higher</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009 (12.83)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">620 (3.13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marital status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Currently married</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12398 (81.09)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7522 (44.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Widowed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2293 (16.49)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8426 (53.99)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Others</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">407 (2.43)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">418 (1.95)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living arrangement</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Alone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">365 (2.52)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1257 (8.53)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> With spouse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3739 (26.03)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2476 (15.19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> With others</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10994 (71.45)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,633 (76.28)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Work status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Never worked</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">759 (3.83)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8025 (46.84)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Currently not working</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5979 (40.88)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5011 (32.45)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Currently working</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6044 (42.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2953 (18.87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Retired</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2316 (13.24)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">377 (1.84)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPCE quintile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Poorest</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3035 (20.83)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3449 (22.49)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Poorer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3068 (21.32)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3409 (22.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Middle</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3064 (21.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3352 (20.35)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Richer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2990 (19.22)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3180 (19.16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPCE quintile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Poorest</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3035 (20.83)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3449 (22.49)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Poorer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3068 (21.32)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3409 (22.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Middle</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3064 (21.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3352 (20.35)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Richer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2990 (19.22)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3180 (19.16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Richest</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2941 (17.02)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2976 (15.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Religion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.475</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hindu</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11078 (82.04)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,959 (82.39)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Muslim</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1804 (11.72)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1927 (10.88)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Others</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2216 (6.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2480 (6.73)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caste</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.156</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> SC/ST</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4884 (26.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5429 (27.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> OBC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5781 (45.86)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6105 (44.66)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Others</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4433 (27.63)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4832 (27.84)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Place of residence</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Urban</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5021 (27.95)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5718 (30.82)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Rural</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10077 (72.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,648 (69.18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical activity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8109 (52.67)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,755 (73.39)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Only vigorous activity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">915 (6.39)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">730 (4.39)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Only moderate activity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5000 (35.19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3314 (19.45)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Moderate and vigorous activity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">808 (5.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">358 (2.77)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep medications</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14632 (97.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,757 (96.95)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">396 (2.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">573 (3.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10401 (72.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9986 (62.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4640 (27.95)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6355 (37.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12594 (85.39)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,927 (86.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2444 (14.61)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2416 (13.94)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neurological or psychiatric disorders</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.944</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14636 (97.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,902 (97.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">403 (2.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">440 (2.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic lung disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13791 (90.99)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,222 (92)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1250 (9.01)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1120 (8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic heart disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14155 (94.19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,656 (95.36)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">886 (5.81)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">686 (4.64)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stroke</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14546 (96.71)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,994 (97.77)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">495 (3.29)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">347 (2.23)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bone or joint related disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12824 (83.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,975 (77.21)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2217 (16.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3368 (22.79)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of chronic diseases</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7269 (49.32)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7147 (44.58)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> One</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4272 (28.40)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4954 (30.31)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Two</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2326 (15.33)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2788 (15.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Three plus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1167 (6.94)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1448 (9.36)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: N, Unweighted counts; %, Weighted percentage to account for the stratified sampling and to provide the national estimates; MPCE, Monthly per capita consumption expenditure; SC/ST, Scheduled caste/scheduled tribe; OBC, Other backward class.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Bivariate and multivariable logistic regression estimates of insomnia symptoms with chronic diseases and other background characteristics were shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. Beginning with the associations with background characteristics, for both men and women, the prevalence of insomnia symptoms was higher among those aged 80 years and above, uneducated, those who were widowed and those who lived alone. For women only, the prevalence of insomnia symptoms was higher among those who were not working currently (AOR: 1.26; CI: 1.10–1.45), retired (AOR: 1.65; CI: 1.14–2.40), and lived in rural areas (AOR: 1.20; CI: 1.02–1.41) compared to their counterparts (who never worked and lived in urban areas).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Bivariate and Multivariable Logistic Regression Estimates for Insomnia Symptoms by Chronic Conditions and Other Background</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variables</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Men</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Women</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chi-square p-value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chi-square p-value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AOR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AOR (95% CI)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (in years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 60–69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 70–79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 (0.95–1.23)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (0.86–1.17)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 80+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22* (1.01–1.52)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.85–1.30)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Educational status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Primary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 (0.80–1.08)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 (0.71–1.01)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Secondary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77*** (0.67–0.90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55*** (0.41–0.74)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Higher</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66*** (0.53–0.82)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52*** (0.37–0.74)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marital status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Currently married</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Widowed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 (0.83–1.16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 (0.84–1.13)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Others</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76 (0.54–1.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 (0.77–1.58)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living arrangement</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Alone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> With spouse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 (0.56–1.20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72** (0.56–0.92)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> With others</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 (0.69–1.42)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79* (0.65–0.96)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Work status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.064</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Never worked</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Currently not working</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29 (0.97–1.71)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26*** (1.10–1.45)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Currently working</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 (0.74–1.31)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.78–1.09)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Retired</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (0.80–1.49)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65** (1.14–2.40)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPCE quintile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.831</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Poorest</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Poorer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (0.85–1.18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 (0.76–1.07)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Middle</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 (0.91–1.29)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 (0.81–1.14)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Richer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.88–1.26)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 (0.73–1.07)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Richest</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 (0.88–1.29)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 (0.81–1.22)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Religion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hindu</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Muslim</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 (0.74–1.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (0.83–1.19)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Others</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80* (0.65–0.98)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88 (0.74–1.06)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caste</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> SC/ST</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> OBC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 (0.82–1.09)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 (0.82–1.10)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Others</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.77–1.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 (0.93–1.31)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Place of residence</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Urban</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Rural</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 (0.99–1.33)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20* (1.02–1.41)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical activity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Only vigorous activity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26 (0.99–1.61)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30 (1.00–1.70)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Only moderate activity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 (0.88–1.16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 (0.95–1.27)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate and vigorous activity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 (0.76–1.48)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13 (0.66–1.92)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep medications</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.32*** (4.36–9.17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.11*** (2.83–5.97)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20** (1.06–1.36)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36*** (1.20–1.53)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 (0.97–1.35)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80* (0.65–0.98)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neurological or psychiatric disorders</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38* (1.01–1.91)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82*** (1.32–2.49)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic lung disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65*** (1.38–1.97)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 (0.96–1.63)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic heart disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (0.83–1.43)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.52–1.27)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stroke</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37* (1.04–1.80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78** (1.24–2.55)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bone or joint related disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.88*** (1.62–2.18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.46*** (1.26–1.70)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of chronic diseases<sup>¥</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ref.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Single</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27*** (1.22–1.46)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45*** (1.27–1.66)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Two</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.77*** (1.48–2.12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.77*** (1.51–2.07)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Three plus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.43*** (1.97–3.02)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01*** (1.48–2.74)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: %, Weighted percentage; Ref, Reference; *if p&lt;0.05, **if p&lt;0.01, ***if p&lt;0.001; AOR, Adjusted Odds Ratio; MPCE, Monthly per capita consumption expenditure; SC/ST, Scheduled caste/scheduled tribe; OBC, Other backward class; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>¥</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">, Individual chronic diseases were not included in controls.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Turning to the main associations with chronic diseases, for both men and women, the prevalence of insomnia symptoms was higher among those who had hypertension or diabetes or had neurological or psychiatric disorders, chronic lung disease, chronic heart disease, stroke or bone and joint related diseases compared to their healthy peers in the current study. More specifically, older men (AOR: 1.20; CI: 1.06–1.36) and women (AOR: 1.36; CI: 1.20–1.53) who had hypertension had higher odds of insomnia symptoms compared to their peers with no hypertension. Older women who had diabetes had lower odds of insomnia symptoms (AOR: 0.80; CI: 0.65–0.98) than those who were not, and the association was not significant among men. Odds of insomnia symptoms were higher among men (AOR: 1.38; CI: 1.01–1.91) and women (AOR: 1.82; CI: 1.32–2.49) who had neurological or psychiatric disorders; men (AOR: 1.37; CI: 1.04–1.80) and women (AOR: 1.78; CI: 1.24–2.55) who had stroke; and men (AOR: 1.88: CI: 1.62–2.18) and women (AOR: 1.46; CI: 1.26–1.70) who had bone and joint related diseases than their peers without the disease. Older men who had chronic lung disease had higher odds of insomnia symptoms (AOR: 1.65; CI: 1.38–1.97) than their peers with no lung disease and the association was not significant among women. There was no significant association between chronic heart disease and insomnia symptoms in both men and women. Furthermore, older men (AOR: 2.43; CI: 1.97–3.02) and women (AOR: 2.01; CI: 1.48–2.74) who had three and more chronic diseases had higher odds of insomnia symptoms compared to their healthy peers.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The additional analysis of interaction of sex in the associations between each chronic disease and insomnia symptoms (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>–</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">G</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) showed that these associations are mostly similar between men and women, except for diabetes (p-value: 0.018) and bone and joint related diseases (p-value: 0.027). Having each of these two conditions was associated with higher odds of insomnia symptoms particularly for men. The interaction of sex in the association between number of chronic diseases on insomnia symptoms (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) showed that older men and women who were having three and more diseases had similarly higher levels of insomnia symptoms. Notably, although the interactions were not significant, compared to those with no diseases, insomnia symptoms were higher among men with a single and two chronic diseases than women with single and two chronic diseases, whereas it was higher among women with three plus chronic diseases than men with three plus chronic diseases.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">(</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A-G</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">): Associations between each chronic disease and insomnia symptoms by sex after adjustment for socioeconomic and behavioural factor.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1339-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Association between number of chronic diseases and insomnia symptoms by sex after adjustment for socioeconomic and behavioural factor.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1339-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Sensitivity Analyses</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Results from the sensitivity analysis of linear regression models of insomnia symptoms (0–12) by chronic conditions and other covariates are presented in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=456025.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Table S1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. The results were consistent for all the chronic diseases except for diabetes, for which the association was not significant in both men and women.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=456025.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Table S2</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> presents the adjusted odds ratios of each insomnia symptom by chronic diseases among older men and women. Older men and women who had hypertension had higher odds of all the insomnia symptoms as compared to their peers with no hypertension. The odds of each insomnia symptom were higher among those who had neurological or psychiatric disorders, greater for women than men in all the symptoms. The odds of each insomnia symptom were higher among those who had lung disease and those who had bone and joint related diseases, greater for men than women in all the symptoms. In addition, older men who had a chronic heart disease had higher odds difficulty of waking up frequently during the night (AOR: 1.46; CI: 1.08–1.96) and waking up too early (AOR: 1.50; CI: 1.11–2.02).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The study sheds light on the associations between chronic diseases and insomnia symptoms among older adults in India. In line with our hypothesis, we found that women had higher prevalence of insomnia symptoms than men (44.73% vs 37.15%). While the overall associations between chronic diseases and insomnia symptoms did not differ much between men and women (based on sex interaction analyses), the magnitude of the insomnia risk associated with specific chronic conditions differed between men and women (based on sex stratified analyses). Together, these results highlight the need to promoting sex-tailored public health preventive measures that focus on individuals living with insomnia symptoms and comorbid conditions. Below, we discuss the implications of our findings.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Regarding the sex difference in the prevalence of insomnia symptoms found in this study sample, three explanations could be provided. First, women may experience a higher level of insomnia symptoms due to their overall socioeconomic disadvantages compared to men, viz., lower income and less education,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and this may be particularly true for Indian women. Second, women report sleeping difficulties due to hot flashes and stress during the postmenopausal period.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Third, women are more likely than men to experience physical problems, such as osteoporosis, hypertension, back pain, and hormonal disorder after menopause, which may lead to sleep disturbances and insomnia.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Unsurprisingly, we observed that women living in rural areas had a higher risk of insomnia symptoms than urban residents. Workforce petrification could be a possible reason for this. Most of the older adults in rural India are involved in physical work that may lead to muscle pain or bone disease, significant contributors to insomnia symptoms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This study found that having hypertension, stroke and neurological or psychiatric disorders were associated with higher risks of insomnia symptoms among older adults, with a seemingly greater risk for women than men. Proposed mechanisms behind these associations include physiological hyperarousal in persons with insomnia,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and activation of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis and the stress-diathesis model.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Moreover, insomnia symptoms and OSA commonly co-occur and studies have shown the effect of comorbid insomnia and sleep apnea (COMISA) on hypertension, cardiovascular events such as angina, heart disease and stroke, and all-cause mortality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49–52</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> As evident in previous studies, symptoms of neurological disorders, and medications for specific diseases may lead to insomnia and/or other sleep problems.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The insomnia risk associated with having a neurological or psychiatric disorder seemed particularly higher among women than men (AOR=1.82 vs 1.38). This sex difference could be explained by differences in depressive symptomatology and that women are more prone to ruminate than men.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Further, in India, majority of women depend on others in terms of economic and social support in older age.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Previous studies have also noted that older Indian women, especially widowed, are considered liabilities and are neglected or abused by others compared to men.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Consequently, older Indian women become depressed more than older Indian men, which increases the risk of insomnia symptoms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Similarly, living alone may increase feeling of loneliness and psychological distress in women than in men which could lead to a greater risk of insomnia symptoms in women compared to men.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Interestingly, having diabetes was associated with a lower risk of insomnia symptoms in older Indian women, though insomnia symptoms were shown to be associated with subsequent incidence of type 2 diabetes mellitus.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> This unexpected finding may require further investigation.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Consistent with previous studies,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62–64</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> we found that insomnia symptoms among older Indian men were associated with the prevalence of chronic lung diseases. This association might be related to sleep-disordered breathing as both insomnia and sleep-related breathing disorders were shown to increase collapsibility of the upper airway and lead to respiratory symptoms and COPD.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65–67</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> A reverse causation is also possible. For example, medical studies have shown a reduction in alveolar ventilation among lung patients, decreasing baseline oxygen saturation and ventilatory response to hypoxia.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> During rapid eye movement (REM) sleep, breathing variability and rate may increase.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> As a result, lung patient may have trouble falling asleep and experience night-time awakening, leading to insomnia.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Older people suffer from common and frequent physical health problems including bone-related diseases viz—chronic pain in joints, arthritis, rheumatism, and osteoporosis.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In support of our hypothesis and in line with the existing evidence,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71–74</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> the present study observed that bone and joint related diseases were significantly associated with insomnia symptoms among older adults and men in particular. Our findings also support previous evidence that older persons with chronic joint pain are more likely to experience sleep disturbances.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Furthermore, functional impairment due to pain also limits the degree of physical activity,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> which can exacerbate late‐life insomnia symptoms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> More studies are required to explore potential mechanisms underlying the observed associations to better understand the nature of the associations.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">When we used the number of chronic diseases, older Indian adults with three plus diseases had a higher probability of insomnia symptoms, similarly across men and women. Our findings are consistent with the previous studies that found that multimorbidity has a significant role in suffering from insomnia symptoms among older adults.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Although we found no significant interaction between multimorbidity and sex on insomnia symptoms in our sample, the influence of sex differences on this relationship warrants further investigation. This could involve examining how sex interacts with other demographic variables such as age, socioeconomic position, and cultural factors in the association between chronic diseases and insomnia symptoms. Understanding these nuances will help in developing targeted strategies to manage insomnia in older men and women with multimorbidity.</citation_analysis></p>
      <sec id="s0004-s2001">
        <title>Implications for Policy, Practice and Future Research</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The findings suggest an urgent need for developing preventive measures, including evidence-based strategies that may reduce sleep difficulties and improve overall health. Given the increased risk of NCDs in old age, the Government of India has launched NCD cells in all districts to reduce the burden of these diseases. However, despite these efforts, prevalence of NCDs in India has continued to grow steadily.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Multimorbidity in older adults is common and associated with adverse outcomes including a worsened sleep, suggesting that policymakers should intervene by targeting specific chronic diseases associated with insomnia symptoms. As such, there is a need for comprehensive management of comorbid chronic diseases, which can exacerbate insomnia symptoms. Particularly, the current study suggests that specific diseases such as hypertension, chronic lung disease and neurological or psychiatric disorders must be targeted as they were found to be significant risk factors of insomnia symptoms among older men and women alike. Clinicians should be aware of the importance of screening their patients for potential sleep disorders and insomnia symptoms. Similarly, integrated care models, which address both physical and mental health needs, may be more effective in managing insomnia symptoms in older adults with chronic diseases.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Specifically, the role of mindfulness, meditation, and relaxation techniques need to be further investigated in reducing the risk of cardiovascular diseases and insomnia symptoms in older adults.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Health practitioners should promote the use of technology, such as telemedicine and mobile health applications, to provide accessible and scalable interventions for improving sleep quality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Community-based programs that promote social engagement, physical activity, and mental well-being, that can have a positive impact on sleep should be enhanced. Finally, non-pharmacological approaches such as cognitive behavioural therapy have potential to reduce the burden of chronic conditions comorbid with insomnia symptoms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0084" ref-type="bibr">84–86</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> As such, future research is required to explore the effectiveness of these in reducing sleep problems in diverse populations of older adults. There is also a need for longitudinal studies to assess the long-term impact of various chronic diseases on sleep health in older adults.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Strength and Limitations</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Using a large sample of older adults from a nationally representative survey in India is the main strength of this study. A limited number of studies have looked into the issue of insomnia, especially in LMICs,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> and the current findings may be relevant to the broader community of older people in those countries with similar socio-demographics. The consideration of multiple different types of chronic diseases is another strength of this study. The large sample size also enabled evaluating sex differences in insomnia symptoms by chronic diseases while controlling for a large number of covariates, including sleep medications, physical activity and socio-demographics.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Although this study contributes to the literature on insomnia symptoms, it also carries some limitations. First, previous studies have reported under-diagnosis of diseases in LMICs including India, especially among lower socioeconomic groups.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0087" ref-type="bibr">87</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Therefore, we cannot ignore the possibility of under-estimation of chronic diseases. Moreover, the study was based on self-reported physician diagnosis of chronic conditions, and thus it may be prone to reporting bias due to unawareness of the existence of specific disease. Second, due to the cross-sectional nature of the dataset, we could not establish a temporal relationship between chronic diseases and insomnia symptoms among older adults, and therefore, longitudinal studies are required to draw conclusions on whether specific diseases precede insomnia symptoms or vice-versa. Third, we did not consider the chronicity and severity of insomnia symptoms and co-existence of other sleep disorders which could affect the current findings. Future studies should consider these factors while examining the associations between chronic conditions and insomnia symptoms.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This study found significant associations between hypertension, chronic lung disease, neurological or psychiatric disorders, stroke and bone and joint related diseases with insomnia symptoms among older men and women in India. We also found a positive association between number of chronic diseases and insomnia symptoms among older adults. Some of these associations (ie, with diabetes, bone and joint related diseases) were more apparent for men as compared to women. Yet, addressing insomnia is not a high priority for public health in developing countries like India. To achieve the Sustainable Development Goals for health and well-being, our findings suggest a critical need to raise awareness on the risk of insomnia associated with chronic diseases among all stakeholders, including health care workers, policymakers, and the general public. Effective preventions such as disease-specific management and routine screening for insomnia symptoms are required to support the vulnerable older adult population with sleep problems to build a healthy aging society.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgment</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors gratefully acknowledge the International Institute for Population Sciences (IIPS) for providing the LASI Wave 1 data set for conducting this study.</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Ethics declarations</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The analysis is based on secondary data available in public domain for research; thus, no approval was required from any institutional review board (IRB). Thereby, it is certified that all applicable institutional and governmental regulations concerning the ethical approval of human volunteers were followed during the survey. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.iipsindia.ac.in/sites/default/files/LASI_India_Report_2020_compressed.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.iipsindia.ac.in/sites/default/files/LASI_India_Report_2020_compressed.pdf</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s0008">
      <title>Data sharing statement</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The study uses secondary data which is available on reasonable request through </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.iipsindia.ac.in/content/lasi-wave-i" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.iipsindia.ac.in/content/lasi-wave-i</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0009">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">All authors contributed to data analysis, drafting or revising the article, have agreed on the journal to which the article will be submitted, gave final approval of the version to be published, and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0010">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Dr Soomi Lee reports she received funding support from National Institutes of Health (R01HL163226, PI: Lee), outside the submitted work. The authors declare no other conflicts of interest.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vitiello</surname>
<given-names>MV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gooneratne</surname>
<given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep in normal aging</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Clin</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>171</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsmc.2022.02.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35659071</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Miner</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kryger</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep in the aging population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Clin</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>311</fpage>–<lpage>318</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsmc.2020.02.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32386704</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Matricciani</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bin</surname>
<given-names>YS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lallukka</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Rethinking the sleep-health link</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Health</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>339</fpage>–<lpage>348</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleh.2018.05.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30031526</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gulia</surname>
<given-names>KK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>VM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disorders in the elderly: a growing challenge</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychogeriatrics</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>165</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/psyg.12319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29878472</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Koyanagi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garin</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olaya</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Chronic conditions and sleep problems among adults aged 50 years or over in nine countries: a multi-country study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114742</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jana</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chattopadhyay</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalence and potential determinants of chronic disease among elderly in India: rural-urban perspectives</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>e0264937</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0264937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35275937</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stepnowsky</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ancoli-Israel</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and Its Disorders in Seniors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Clin</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>281</fpage>–<lpage>293</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsmc.2008.01.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19122865</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Plantinga</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rao</surname>
<given-names>MN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schillinger</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalence of self-reported sleep problems among people with diabetes in the United States, 2005-2008</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Prevent Chron Dis</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>2005</fpage>–<lpage>2008</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sivertsen</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lallukka</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salo</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia as a risk factor for ill health: results from the large population-based prospective HUNT Study in Norway</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of Sleep Research</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>124</fpage>–<lpage>132</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24635564</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Spiegelhalder</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scholtes</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Riemann</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The association between insomnia and cardiovascular diseases</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nature Sci of Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S7471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23616699</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Grandner</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jackson</surname>
<given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pak</surname>
<given-names>VM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gehrman</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disturbance is associated with cardiovascular and metabolic disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of Sleep Research</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>433</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.2011.00990.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22151079</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dangol</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shrestha</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rai Koirala</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia and its associated factors among older people of selected ward of Banepa municipality, Nepal</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nurs Open</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>363</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/nop2.396</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31871720</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>RHY</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wing</surname>
<given-names>YK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ho</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fong</surname>
<given-names>SYY</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Gender differences in insomnia—a study in the Hong Kong Chinese population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychosom Res</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>601</fpage>–<lpage>609</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-3999(02)00437-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12127178</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pepin</surname>
<given-names>J-L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Borel</surname>
<given-names>A-L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tamisier</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baguet</surname>
<given-names>J-P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Levy</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dauvilliers</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Hypertension and sleep: overview of a tight relationship</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>509</fpage>–<lpage>519</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2014.03.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24846771</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Calhoun</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harding</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>138</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>434</fpage>–<lpage>443</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.09-2954</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20682533</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Moldofsky</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep influences on regional and diffuse pain syndromes associated with osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Semin Arthritis Rheum</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>18</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0049-0172(89)90011-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2658072</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vgontzas</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liao</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pejovic</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Calhoun</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Karataraki</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bixler</surname>
<given-names>EO</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia with objective short sleep duration is associated with type 2 diabetes: a population-based study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes Care</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1980</fpage>–<lpage>1985</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc09-0284</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19641160</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ohayon</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Epidemiology of insomnia: what we know and what we still need to learn</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>111</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/smrv.2002.0186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12531146</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nadorff</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drapeau</surname>
<given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pigeon</surname>
<given-names>WR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Psychiatric illness and sleep in older adults: comorbidity and opportunities for intervention</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Clin</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsmc.2017.09.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29412986</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Y-ES</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Videnovic</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vaughn</surname>
<given-names>BV</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Comorbid sleep disturbances in neurologic disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Continuum</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>1117</fpage>–<lpage>1131</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28777179</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Louie</surname>
<given-names>GH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tektonidou</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caban-Martinez</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ward</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disturbances in adults with arthritis: prevalence, mediators, and subgroups at greatest risk. Data from the 2007 national health interview survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arthr Care Res</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>247</fpage>–<lpage>260</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/acr.20362</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>C-H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chuang</surname>
<given-names>L-P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>S-W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Factors responsible for poor sleep quality in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Pulm Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>118</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12890-016-0281-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27501837</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ungvari</surname>
<given-names>GS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration and its association with demographics, lifestyle factors, poor mental health and chronic diseases in older Chinese adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>257</volume>:<fpage>212</fpage>–<lpage>218</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2017.07.036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28777953</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sofi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cesari</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Casini</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macchi</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abbate</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gensini</surname>
<given-names>GF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia and risk of cardiovascular disease: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Prev Cardiolog</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2047487312460020</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wallace</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>10-year Stability of an Insomnia Sleeper Phenotype and Its Association with Chronic Conditions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychosomatic Med</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<fpage>10</fpage>–<lpage>1097</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ramos</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wheaton</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Peer Reviewed: sleep Deprivation, Sleep Disorders, and Chronic Disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Prevent Chron Dis</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<fpage>20</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lan</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ren</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Individual insomnia symptom and increased hazard risk of cardiocerebral vascular diseases: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychiatr</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>654719</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2021.654719</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y-W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>L-Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>F-X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep-associated movement disorders and the risk of cardiovascular disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">World J Meta Anal</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>187</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.13105/wjma.v3.i3.181</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rani</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arokiasamy</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Selvamani</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sikarwar</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Gender differences in self-reported sleep problems among older adults in six middle-income countries: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Women Aging</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>605</fpage>–<lpage>620</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08952841.2021.1965425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34436971</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Assari</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sonnega</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pepin</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leggett</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Residual effects of restless sleep over depressive symptoms on chronic medical conditions: race by gender differences</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Racial Ethnic Health Dispar</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40615-015-0202-z</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Appleton</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gill</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Influence of gender on associations of obstructive sleep apnea symptoms with chronic conditions and quality of life</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>930</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph15050930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29735909</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Newman</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Enright</surname>
<given-names>PL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Manolio</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haponik</surname>
<given-names>EF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wahl</surname>
<given-names>PW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disturbance, psychosocial correlates, and cardiovascular disease in 5201 older adults: the Cardiovascular Health Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Geriatr Soc</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1532-5415.1997.tb00970.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8994480</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kay</surname>
<given-names>DB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dzierzewski</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep in the Context of Healthy Aging and Psychiatric Syndromes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Clin</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsmc.2014.11.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25750599</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tandon</surname>
<given-names>VR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sharma</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mahajan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mahajan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tandon</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Menopause and sleep disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Mid Life Health</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/jmh.jmh_18_22</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>PY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reddy</surname>
<given-names>RT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep, testosterone and cortisol balance, and ageing men</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Rev Endocr Metab Disord</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1323</fpage>–<lpage>1339</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11154-022-09755-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36152143</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="newspaper"><collab>International Institute for Population Sciences (IIPS)</collab>, <article-title>NPHCE, MoHFW HTHCS of PH (HSPH) and the U of SC (USC). Longitudinal Ageing Study in <italic toggle="yes">India</italic> (LASI) Wave 1, 2017-18, <italic toggle="yes">India</italic> Report. <italic toggle="yes">Mumbai</italic></article-title>, <year>2020</year>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://lasi-india.org/public/documentation/LASI_India_Report_2020.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://lasi-india.org/public/documentation/LASI_India_Report_2020.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ding</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Small</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bergström</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holmgren</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A cross-sectional survey of night-time symptoms and impact of sleep disturbance on symptoms and health status in patients with COPD</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>589</fpage>–<lpage>599</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/COPD.S122485</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28243077</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lallukka</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sares-Jäske</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kronholm</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sociodemographic and socioeconomic differences in sleep duration and insomnia-related symptoms in Finnish adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>565</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-12-565</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22839359</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fabbri</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beracci</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martoni</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meneo</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tonetti</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Natale</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Measuring Subjective Sleep Quality: a Review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1082</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph18031082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33530453</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>P</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Gender, Age, and the Risk of Insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">CNS Spectrum</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>S17</issue>):<fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1092852900003357</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kaushal</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vohora</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jalali</surname>
<given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jha</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalence of osteoporosis and osteopenia in an apparently healthy Indian population - a cross-sectional retrospective study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Osteoporosis Sarcopenia</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.afos.2018.04.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30775543</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Saxena</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bloom</surname>
<given-names>DE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cafiero-Fonseca</surname>
<given-names>ET</given-names></string-name>, et al. <source><italic toggle="yes">Economics of Non-Communicable Diseases in India: The Costs and Returns on Investment of Interventions to Promote Healthy Living and Prevent, Treat, and Manage NCDs</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jayamani</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gopichandran</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alexander</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Christopher</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Prasad</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Diet and Physical Activity Among Women in Urban and Rural Areas in South India: a Community Based Comparative Survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Family Med Prim Care</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>334</fpage>–<lpage>338</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/2249-4863.123782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26664837</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Moreno</surname>
<given-names>CRC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lowden</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vasconcelos</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marqueze</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Musculoskeletal pain and insomnia among workers with different occupations and working hours</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chronobiol Int</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>749</fpage>–<lpage>753</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/07420528.2016.1167730</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27088881</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lanfranchi</surname>
<given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pennestri</surname>
<given-names>M-H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fradette</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dumont</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morin</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Montplaisir</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Nighttime blood pressure in normotensive subjects with chronic insomnia: implications for cardiovascular risk</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>760</fpage>–<lpage>766</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/32.6.760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19544752</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vgontzas</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fernandez-Mendoza</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia With Physiological Hyperarousal Is Associated With Hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>644</fpage>–<lpage>650</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.114.04604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25624338</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bathgate</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fernandez-Mendoza</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia, short sleep duration, and high blood pressure: recent evidence and future directions for the prevention and management of hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Hypertens Rep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11906-018-0850-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29349522</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Thomas</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Calhoun</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep, insomnia, and hypertension: current findings and future directions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Soci Hypertens</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>122</fpage>–<lpage>129</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jash.2016.11.008</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Luyster</surname>
<given-names>FS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baniak</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Imes</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of comorbid obstructive sleep apnea and insomnia with risk of major adverse cardiovascular events in sleep medicine center patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Health</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>341</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleh.2024.03.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38704352</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Draelants</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Point</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wacquier</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lanquart</surname>
<given-names>J-P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Loas</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hein</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>10-year risk for cardiovascular disease associated with COMISA (co-morbid insomnia and sleep apnea) in Hypertensive Subjects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Life</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1379</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/life13061379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37374161</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lechat</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Appleton</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Melaku</surname>
<given-names>YA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Comorbid insomnia and sleep apnoea is associated with all-cause mortality</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Respir J</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<fpage>60</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lechat</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Appleton</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Melaku</surname>
<given-names>YA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The association of co‐morbid insomnia and sleep apnea with prevalent cardiovascular disease and incident cardiovascular events</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of Sleep Research</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e13563</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.13563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35166401</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mayer</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Happe</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Evers</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia in neurological diseases</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurol Res Pract</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>15</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s42466-021-00106-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33691803</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Öberg</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johansson</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sandberg</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johansson</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Broström</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Experiences and management of incidents that influence sleep in patients with cardiovascular disease and insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cardiovasc Nurs</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>364</fpage>–<lpage>374</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JCN.0000000000000626</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31904689</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0055">
        <label>55.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jaussent</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dauvilliers</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ancelin</surname>
<given-names>M-L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia symptoms in older adults: associated factors and gender differences</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Geriatric Psychiat</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>88</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JGP.0b013e3181e049b6</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0056">
        <label>56.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vlassoff</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Gender Differences in Determinants and Consequences of Health and Illness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Health Popul Nutr</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17615903</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0057">
        <label>57.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gambhir</surname>
<given-names>IS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chakrabarti</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sharma</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saran</surname>
<given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia in the elderly - A hospital-based study from North India</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Gerontol Geriatrics</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>121</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcgg.2014.05.005</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0058">
        <label>58.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>CN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fultz</surname>
<given-names>EK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferdousian</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Transgenic Analyses of Homer2 Function Within Nucleus Accumbens Subregions in the Regulation of Methamphetamine Reward and Reinforcement in Mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Frontiers in Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2020.00011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32116834</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0059">
        <label>59.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chu</surname>
<given-names>HS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oh</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The relationship between living arrangements and sleep quality in older adults: gender differences</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>3893</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph19073893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35409576</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0060">
        <label>60.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Widhowati</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>C-M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>L-H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>C-K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fetzer</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Living alone, loneliness, and depressive symptoms among Indonesian older women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Health Care Women Int</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>984</fpage>–<lpage>996</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07399332.2020.1797039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33079645</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0061">
        <label>61.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yao</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia symptoms are associated with an increased risk of type 2 diabetes mellitus among adults aged 50 and older</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breathing</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0062">
        <label>62.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sundbom</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malinovschi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lindberg</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Almqvist</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Janson</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia symptoms and asthma control—Interrelations and importance of comorbidities</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Experimental Allergy</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>170</fpage>–<lpage>177</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cea.13517</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0063">
        <label>63.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>SQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>XW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impact of insomnia and obstructive sleep apnea on the risk of acute exacerbation of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>101444</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2021.101444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33601330</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0064">
        <label>64.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hynninen</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pallesen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hardie</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia symptoms, objectively measured sleep, and disease severity in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease outpatients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1328</fpage>–<lpage>1333</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2013.08.785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24238965</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0065">
        <label>65.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>George</surname>
<given-names>CF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bayliff</surname>
<given-names>CD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Management of insomnia in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Drugs</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>379</fpage>–<lpage>387</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/00003495-200363040-00004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12558460</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0066">
        <label>66.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wickwire</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Collop</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia and sleep-related breathing disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>137</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1449</fpage>–<lpage>1463</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.09-1485</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20525657</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0067">
        <label>67.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Budhiraja</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Siddiqi</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quan</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep Disorders in Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease: etiology, Impact, and Management</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>03</issue>):<fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>270</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.4540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25700872</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0068">
        <label>68.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Garcia</surname>
<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Effect of Chronic Disorders on Sleep in the Elderly</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Geriatric Med</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cger.2007.08.008</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0069">
        <label>69.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Choi</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>D-H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ryu</surname>
<given-names>S-H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ha</surname>
<given-names>J-H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Severity of Sleep Disordered Breathing Induces Different Decrease in the Oxygen Saturation During Rapid Eye Movement and Non-Rapid Eye Movement Sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Invest</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>652</fpage>–<lpage>658</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4306/pi.2016.13.6.652</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0070">
        <label>70.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rains</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Penzien</surname>
<given-names>DB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and chronic pain: challenges to the alpha-EEG sleep pattern as a pain specific sleep anomaly</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychosom Res</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-3999(02)00545-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12505558</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0071">
        <label>71.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Boeselt</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koczulla</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nell</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep and rheumatic diseases</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Best Pract Res</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>101434</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.berh.2019.101434</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0072">
        <label>72.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>De Baets</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Runge</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Labie</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The interplay between symptoms of insomnia and pain in people with osteoarthritis: a narrative review of the current evidence</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>101793</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2023.101793</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37269784</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0073">
        <label>73.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pickering</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chapurlat</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kocher</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peter‐Derex</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep Disturbances and Osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pain Pract</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>244</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/papr.12271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25639339</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0074">
        <label>74.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stone</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Engeland</surname>
<given-names>CG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lane</surname>
<given-names>NE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buxton</surname>
<given-names>OM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Arthritis, Sleep Health, and Systemic Inflammation in Older Men</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arthritis Care &amp; Research</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>965</fpage>–<lpage>973</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/acr.23923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31074577</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0075">
        <label>75.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Blyth</surname>
<given-names>FM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Noguchi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Chronic musculoskeletal pain and its impact on older people</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Best Pract Res Clin Rheumatol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>160</fpage>–<lpage>168</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.berh.2017.10.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29224694</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0076">
        <label>76.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Morgan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Daytime activity and risk factors for late-life insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>238</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2869.2003.00355.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12941062</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0077">
        <label>77.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lima</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Barros</surname>
<given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malta</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Medina</surname>
<given-names>PBL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Szwarcwald</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association of self-reported sleep problems with morbidities and multimorbidities according to sex: national Health Survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epidemiol Serv Saude</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e2021386</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/ss2237-9622202200007.especial</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35730889</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0078">
        <label>78.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shin</surname>
<given-names>JI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jacob</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association between physical multimorbidity and sleep problems in 46 low- and middle-income countries</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Maturitas</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>160</volume>:<fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.maturitas.2022.01.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35550705</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0079">
        <label>79.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bloom</surname>
<given-names>DE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cafiero</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jané-Llopis</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The Global Economic Burden of Noncommunicable Diseases</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Prog Glob Demograp Aging</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0080">
        <label>80.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kusko</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blake</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A Narrative Review of the Effects of Mindfulness on Sleep and Hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Hypertens Rep</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11906-023-01279-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37921937</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0081">
        <label>81.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zolfagharzadeh</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Esfandiari</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nazari</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of Benson’s relaxation technique on sleep quality of patients with cardiovascular diseases: a narrative review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Nurs Rep Clin Pract</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0082">
        <label>82.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shamim-Uzzaman</surname>
<given-names>QA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bae</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ehsan</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The use of telemedicine for the diagnosis and treatment of sleep disorders: an American Academy of Sleep Medicine update</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1103</fpage>–<lpage>1107</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.9194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33599202</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0083">
        <label>83.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Guillodo</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lemey</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simonnet</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Clinical applications of mobile health wearable–based sleep monitoring: systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JMIR mHealth and uHealth</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e10733</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/10733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32234707</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0084">
        <label>84.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>NY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>JWY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>SX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wing</surname>
<given-names>YK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Non-pharmacological approaches for management of insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurotherapeutics</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>32</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13311-021-01029-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33821446</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0085">
        <label>85.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ferini‐Strambi</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Auer</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bjorvatn</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia disorder: clinical and research challenges for the 21st century</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>2156</fpage>–<lpage>2167</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ene.14784</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33619858</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0086">
        <label>86.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>JQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Appleman</surname>
<given-names>ER</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salazar</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ong</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cognitive behavioral therapy for insomnia comorbid with psychiatric and medical conditions: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>175</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1461</fpage>–<lpage>1472</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2015.3006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26147487</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0087">
        <label>87.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Muhammad</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sahoo</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The burden of disease-specific multimorbidity among older adults in India and its states: evidence from LASI</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Geriatr</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>53</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12877-023-03728-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36710322</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0088">
        <label>88.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vellakkal</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Subramanian</surname>
<given-names>SV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Millett</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Basu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stuckler</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ebrahim</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Socioeconomic inequalities in non-communicable diseases prevalence in India: disparities between self-reported diagnoses and standardized measures</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>e68219</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23869213</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
