<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39308666</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">11416112</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">475497</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S475497</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Validation of the Athens Insomnia Scale Among Young Chinese Male Population in a High-Altitude Situation</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Tang et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Tang et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Xugang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Qiang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Shuang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Xiuchuan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>Qian</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2278-9212</contrib-id><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Yongjian</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Cardiology, The General Hospital of Western Theater Command</institution>, <addr-line>Chengdu</addr-line>, <addr-line>Sichuan</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Cardiology, The Sixth Medical Center of Chinese PLA General Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Yongjian Yang, <institution>Department of Cardiology, The General Hospital of Western Theater Command</institution>, <addr-line>Chengdu</addr-line>, <addr-line>Sichuan</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, Tel/Fax <phone content-type="general">+86 28 8657 1255</phone>, Email yyjcdzyy@sina.com</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>1377</fpage><lpage>1386</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Tang et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Tang et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Purpose</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The Athens Insomnia Scale (AIS) is a widely used and authorized questionnaire for evaluating insomnia symptoms. However, its reliability and validity at high altitudes are uncertain. Therefore, this study aimed to confirm the validity and reliability of AIS during a 3658 m altitude exposure.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Patients and Methods</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">A total of 387 young Chinese males were enlisted in the acute high-altitude exposure group. They flew for about two hours, climbing from 400 m to 3658 m. The high-altitude-acclimated group consisted of 86 young Chinese men who had lived at least six months at 3658 m altitude. The sleep quality of the acute high-altitude exposure group was evaluated using the AIS before the ascent and after exposure to 3658 m for 24 hours, and one week. The sleep quality of the high-altitude-acclimated group was also assessed. The AIS’s internal consistency, reliability, and validity were evaluated.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The respondents’ quality of sleep significantly decreased after being exposed to 3658 m as opposed to 400 m. Two factors comprised the AIS, according to an exploratory factor analysis: “sleep problem” (items 1–5) and “daytime dysfunction” (items 6–8). The Cronbach’s α internal consistency coefficients exceeded 0.8, and the corrected item-total correlations were all greater than 0.5 when the subjects were exposed to 3658 m. The model fit index was well within the criterion. The average variance extracted and composite reliability were all higher than 0.5 and 0.7, respectively. The interclass correlation coefficient was deemed “fair to good” at 0.482, which is greater than the 0.4 threshold. The AIS has satisfactory discriminant validity, as shown by the Fornell-Larcker criterion and cross-loading results. The daytime dysfunction R-square values (&gt;0.33) show that the frameworks have considerable predictive accuracy.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The AIS exhibits strong consistency, reliability, and validity. The AIS’s features and simplicity make it an essential psychometric tool for high-altitude sleep research.</citation_analysis></p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>athens insomnia scale</kwd><kwd>high altitude</kwd><kwd>internal consistency</kwd><kwd>reliability</kwd><kwd>sleep</kwd><kwd>validity</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Major Military Logistics Research Projects</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the Major Military Logistics Research Projects (grant no. AWS21J004).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="4"/><ref-count count="40"/><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Ascending to altitudes above 2500 m can lead to acute mountain sickness (AMS), which is a common condition characterized by headaches, dizziness, gastrointestinal symptoms (eg, anorexia, nausea, or vomiting), weakness or fatigue, and sleep disturbance.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Sleep disturbance is one of the most commonly reported symptoms of acclimatization to hypobaric hypoxia, and it is evaluated using the Lake Louise AMS scoring system. For the sleep quality item, subjects report whether they slept as well as usual (0 points), did not sleep as well as usual (1 point), woke up many times/had a poor night’s sleep (2 points), or could not sleep at all (3 points).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Restful sleep is essential to perform work optimally the next day. However, sleep disturbance can worsen headaches and anxiety and cause daytime dysfunction after exposure to high altitudes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In addition to causing general discomfort, aggravating anxiety, despair, and other negative feelings, poor sleep quality can also accelerate the onset of AMS and impair cognitive function during the day.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Low oxygen and low pressure-related sleep disturbances have become prevalent for those living at high altitudes, with detrimental effects on both physical and mental well-being.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Research on sleep at high altitudes carries significant implications for enhancing the quality of life and sleep health of those who visit or live in high-altitude areas.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Polysomnography is an effective method for diagnosing sleep disorders. Still, it is expensive and time-consuming, which limits its use in high-altitude environments.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Several insomnia-related, self-rating scales are currently available for evaluating subjective sea-level sleep quality. The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8–10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Insomnia Severity Index (ISI),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and Athens Insomnia Scale (AIS)</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13–15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> are commonly used and authorized insomnia symptom questionnaires. The AIS is considered a handy tool in clinical and research settings for clarifying the state of insomnia. It is more effective than the PSQI and the ISI in evaluating changes in sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The AIS has been translated into several languages, including English,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> French,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Greek,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Arabic,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Japanese,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and Spanish,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> and it is utilized by a variety of populations across the world. Additionally, the Chinese version of the AIS has been validated among both cancer patients</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and Chinese athletes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Several studies have used AIS to evaluate changes in sleep in subjects following high-altitude exposure,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> but more research is needed to determine the reliability and validity of the AIS for evaluating changes in sleep in subjects following high-altitude exposure.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Therefore, the current study aimed to validate the reliability and validity of the AIS for the assessment of altitude-related sleep disturbances in subjects following rapid exposure to 3658 m. Here we tested the hypothesis that the AIS is accurate enough to estimate sleep disturbances in a high-altitude setting.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Study Design</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This research was conducted in May 2023, at two different altitudes in Southwest China: 400 m and 3658 m. The participants underwent baseline tests one week before starting their journey while they were at the 400 m altitude. A flight of almost two hours was needed to ascend from 400 m to 3658 m. After spending 24 hours and one week at the high-altitude location, high-altitude measurements were taken. In addition, another group of participants who had spent more than 6 months at 3658 m as a control group underwent the same test. All participants followed the same daily routine and avoided strenuous exercise during the journey. They also ate the same foods and stayed in the same barracks. The flowchart of the present study is presented in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Flowchart.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1377-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Subjects</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We selected male lowlanders from locations below 500 meters who had not been exposed to high altitudes in the past six months, had no cardiovascular or respiratory problems, and did not use any prescription or non-prescription drugs. For the high-altitude acclimated group, volunteers had to meet the above-mentioned criteria, in addition to having stayed at high altitudes for at least six months. We excluded participants who had respiratory disease, cardiovascular or cerebrovascular disease, kidney or liver disease, or malignant tumors. All participants provided written consent and could withdraw from the study at any time. The study was conducted according to the Declaration of Helsinki and approved by the Ethics Committee of the General Hospital of Western Theater Command of the People’s Liberation Army (Approval identifier: 2022EC3-ky062).</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We recruited a total of 419 young Chinese men, aged 18 to 37, at 400 m. At 3658 m, we recruited a total of 86 young Chinese men, aged 18 to 38, as part of the high-altitude-acclimated group. All participants were males, and a regular training component was in high altitudes. All participants were in good physical condition, as evidenced by chest X-ray, echocardiogram, and electrocardiogram tests.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Screening of the Study Subjects</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The study conducted clinical investigations, such as resting heart rate (HR), blood pressure (BP), pulse oximeter saturation (SpO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">), chest X-ray, echocardiography, and electrocardiogram, for one week before the trip. The purpose of these investigations was to eliminate patients with pulmonary and cardiovascular disorders from the study. Additionally, a questionnaire was used to gather demographic parameters, including age, weight, body mass index (BMI), and current drinking and smoking habits of the participating individuals.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Measurements of Physiological Parameters</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">After completing the questionnaires, we measured the participants’ resting HR (using OMRON HEM-6200; Omron Health Care, Inc., Bannockburn, IL, USA) and SpO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> (using Onyx 9500; Nonin Medical, Inc., Plymouth, MN, USA) three times consecutively, with approximately half-minute intervals between each measurement. We then calculated the mean of the three measurements and used it for our analysis.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Assessment of Sleep Quality Using the AIS</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In this study, the AIS was used to assess the subjects’ sleep quality before and after exposure to high altitudes. The AIS consists of eight items that are rated on a 4-point scale ranging from 0 (no problem) to 3 (severe problem).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The scale is designed to measure the subjective sleep quality of the participants over the past month. A higher score on the AIS indicates poorer sleep quality and a total score of 6 or more is considered insomnia. Studies have shown that using a score of 6 or more on the AIS as a threshold for insomnia diagnosis has a sensitivity of 92% and specificity of 66% at sea level.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The reliability of the AIS was found to be very satisfactory at sea level, with Cronbach’s alpha of 0.89.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> To measure test-retest reliability, the subjects were assessed using the AIS three times a week apart, before and after being exposed to high altitudes.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2006">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The data are presented as mean ± SD or n (%), as appropriate, and were analyzed using IBM SPSS22.0. The study used a significance level of p&lt;0.05 for two-sided tests. The distribution of quantitative variables was tested for normality using the Kolmogorov–Smirnov test. Mean values were compared using a </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-test, while the Pearson chi-squared test was used for comparing categorical variables.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The data analysis included exploratory factor analysis (EFA), confirmatory factor analysis (CFA), reliability analysis, and structural equation modeling (SEM). The AIS’s reliability and EFA were assessed using SPSS22.0, while CFA and SEM were performed using Mplus 8.3 and SmartPLS 4.1. The indirect impact test in SEM was conducted 5000 times using bootstrapping.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In the EFA study, the factors were extracted using principal component analysis and the maximum variance rotation approach, with components having eigenvalues greater than 1.0. If the explained variance of the first factor before rotation is &lt;50%, it indicates no significant common method bias.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We followed the guidelines provided by Hair et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> for CFA and SEM analysis. To evaluate the model fit, we employed indices such as χ</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">/df &lt;5, Root Mean Square Error of Approximation (RMSEA) &lt;0.10, Standardized Root Mean Square Residual (SRMR) &lt;0.05, Comparative Fit Index (CFI) &gt;0.90, and the Tucker-Lewis Index (TLI) &gt;0.90. To ensure the AIS’s convergent validity, Average Variance Extracted (AVE) (&gt;0.5) and Construct Reliability (CR) (&gt;0.7) were calculated using factor loadings. To determine the AIS’s discriminant validity, the Fornell-Larcker criterion and cross-loadings were used.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We used Cronbach’s α and corrected item-total correlations (CITC) in the AIS’s reliability analysis to determine the internal consistency coefficients, which had to be greater than 0.7</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and 0.4,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> respectively. For the evaluation of the test-retest reliability of the AIS, we computed the interclass correlation coefficient (ICC) by comparing the item scores of the data from the AIS, which had to be greater than 0.4.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">At 400 m, we signed up 419 young Chinese males as the acute high-altitude exposure group. However, incomplete data prevented 32 patients from participating in the data analysis. At 3658 m, we recruited a total of 86 young Chinese men as part of the high-altitude-acclimated group. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> displays the clinical features of the sample. The BMI, drinking, and smoking patterns of the acute high-altitude exposure group and the high-altitude-acclimated group did not differ significantly, except in age.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Characteristics of the Sample</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">The Acute High-Altitude Exposure Group (n = 387)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">The High-Altitude-Acclimated Group (n = 86)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, yrs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.6 ± 3.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0 ± 5.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, kg/m2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.7 ± 2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.2 ± 2.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.073</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking, yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">175 (45%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (38%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.247</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drinking, yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (8.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (11.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.322</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Mean ± SD or n (%).</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>HR and SpO<sub>2</sub></title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In this study, we used participants’ heart rate and oxygen saturation to observe the trend of altitude adaptation, as these indicators were used to measure altitude acclimation.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> shows that HR in the acute high-altitude exposure group increased considerably after exposure to 3658 m (p&lt;0.01). The opposite pattern was observed for SpO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. The HR of the high-altitude-acclimated group was 79.8 ± 12.1 beats/min, substantially lower than that of the acute high-altitude exposure group (p&lt;0.001). The high-altitude-acclimated group had a considerably higher SpO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> (91.2 ± 2.3%) than the acute high-altitude exposure group (p&lt;0.05).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Changes in HR, SpO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, and AIS Scores of the Acute High-Altitude Exposure Group After High-Altitude Exposure</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">400 m</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">3658 m 24 h</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">3658 m 7 d</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR, beats/min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.8 ± 9.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.3 ± 9.6*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.2 ± 8.1*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SpO<sub>2</sub>, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.0 ± 0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.3 ± 3.1*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.3 ± 2.7*<sup>‡</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AIS scores</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9 ± 2.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1 ± 3.9*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1 ± 3.9*<sup>‡</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: Data are shown as the mean ± SD. Compared to the values obtained at 400 m using repeated measures ANOVA with Bonferroni post hoc testing: *p&lt;0.01. Compared to the values obtained at 3658 m 24 h using repeated measures ANOVA with Bonferroni post hoc testing: </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>‡</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">p&lt;0.01.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0003"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: AIS, Athens Insomnia Scale; HR, heart rate; SpO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, pulse oximeter saturation.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>AIS Score</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The acute high-altitude exposure group’s AIS scores significantly increased after exposure to 3658 m (p&lt;0.01) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). After staying for 7 days at 3658 m, the AIS scores in the acute high-altitude exposure group decreased significantly as compared to the values obtained at 3658 m 24 h (p&lt;0.01). The high-altitude-acclimated group had significantly higher AIS scores (5.9 ± 4.6) than the acute high-altitude exposure group remaining for 7 days at 3658 m (p&lt;0.01) and insomnia prevalence (38/86 vs 121/387, p&lt;0.05). Changes in each item of the AIS of the acute high-altitude exposure group after high-altitude exposure are presented in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=475497.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Table S1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Measurement Model</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The results of the EFA study indicate that the AIS is a valid instrument. The Kaiser-Meyer-Olkin measure value was 0.845 (p&lt;0.001) for 400 m, 0.900 (p&lt;0.001) for 3658 m 24 h, and 0.892 (p&lt;0.001) for 3658 m 7 days, respectively. All values were greater than 0.7, which indicates that the instrument was suitable for factor analysis. Based on the eigenvalue criteria, the study identified two primary factors: Factor 1 (f1) = 3.339, which related to sleep issues (items 1–5), and Factor 2 (f2) = 1.022, which dealt with dysfunction throughout the day (items 6–8). The first factor explained 41.737% of the variance before rotation, suggesting no significant common method bias. The two factors combined explained 54.513% of the variance.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">A study was conducted to evaluate the structural validity of the AIS using CFA. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> shows the model fit index. The results indicated that the fit for the AIS items was acceptable. All standardized factor loadings were within a good range of 0.576–0.880 when the subjects were exposed to 3658 m (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">), confirming the indicators’ reliability.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The AIS’s Reliability and Validity Indices</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variables</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">The Acute High-Altitude Exposure Group</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">The High-Altitude-Acclimated Group</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">400 m</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">3658 m 24 h</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">3658 m 7 d</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">χ<sup>2</sup>/<italic toggle="yes">df</italic> (&lt;5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.546/19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.405/19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.282/19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.559/13</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RMSEA (&lt;0.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.069</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.072</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.082</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CFI (&gt;0.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.952</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.990</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.971</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.976</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TLI (&gt;0.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.929</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.985</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.957</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.948</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SRMR (&lt;0.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AVE (&gt;0.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> <italic toggle="yes">f1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.494</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.605</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.637</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.623</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> <italic toggle="yes">f2</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.595</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.628</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.648</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.673</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CR (&gt;0.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> <italic toggle="yes">f1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.765</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.850</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.870</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.856</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> <italic toggle="yes">f2</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.658</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.711</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.729</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.768</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cronbach’s α (&gt;0.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.796</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.860</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.874</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.882</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: AIS, Athens Insomnia Scale; AVE, Average Variance Extracted; CFI, Comparative Fit Index; CR, Construct Reliability; RMSEA, Root Mean Square Error of Approximation; SRMR, Standardized Root Mean Square Residual. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">f1</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, factor 1, sleep problem, including the AIS’s items 1–5; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">f2</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, factor 2, daytime dysfunction, including the AIS’s items 6–8; χ</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">/</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">df</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, the ratio of the chi-square statistic to the respective degrees of freedom.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Construct reliability and validity of the AIS. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) 400 m altitude. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) 3658 m 24 hours. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>C</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) 3658 m 7-day. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>D</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) 3658 m 6-month.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1377-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The values of AVE of f1 and f2 were both higher than 0.5 when the subjects were exposed to 3658 m, confirming the convergent validity of the constructs. The CRs were all higher than 0.7 when the subjects were exposed to 3658 m, which approves the reliability of the constructs (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The EFA study’s internal consistency coefficient test revealed the reliability of the AIS. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> shows that all Cronbach’s α values for the AIS exceeded 0.7. The CITC were all greater than 0.5 when the subjects were exposed to 3658 m, demonstrating good internal consistency.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">For the AIS total scores, the ICC value was 0.261 (subjects remaining at 400 m vs 3658 m for 24h, p&lt;0.001) and 0.482 (subjects staying at 3658 m for 24 h vs 3658 m for 7 days, p&lt;0.001), respectively. When the subjects were exposed to 3658 m, the ICC value (0.482, &gt;0.4) was deemed “fair to good”,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> indicating acceptable test-retest reliability. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=475497.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Table S2</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> displays the ICCs for each item.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2005">
        <title>Convergent and Discriminant Validity</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We used two methods, namely the Fornell-Larcker criterion, and cross-loadings, to evaluate the discriminant validity of the AIS. The Fornell-Larcker criterion states that the square root of AVE should be greater than the correlation to every other latent variable for each latent variable.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> On the other hand, cross-loadings require that each indicator’s loading should be greater than all its cross-loadings. The results of our analysis are presented in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=475497.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Table S3</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">–</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=475497.docx" ext-link-type="uri">10</ext-link>.</underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Based on our findings, we conclude that the AIS has satisfactory convergent and discriminant validity and reliability.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The present study aimed to measure the variance inflation factor (VIF) values to identify any collinearity issues in the Framework. As per previous research,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> if the VIF value is &lt;5, then the results are considered to be free of collinearity issues. The inner VIF values for all constructs ranged from 1.161 to 2.966. The results indicate that there are no collinearity issues with the data and that the survey findings are reliable and stable.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2006">
        <title>Predictive Accuracy</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In this study, a bootstrapping technique was utilized to evaluate a hypothesis using 5000 samples.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The structural model was assessed using the R-square, which is a measure of how well the model fits the data.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> According to Hair et al’s proposal, an R-square value above 0.33 is considered moderate. As shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=475497.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Table S11</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, the R-square values for daytime dysfunction (3658 m 24-hour), daytime dysfunction (3658 m 7-day), and daytime dysfunction (3658 m 6-month) were 41.3%, 42.2%, and 49.5%, respectively. These results indicate that the frameworks have moderate predictive accuracy.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The study found that sleep has a positive influence on daytime function when individuals are exposed to high altitudes, as hypothesized. The positive impact of sleep on daytime function was observed in subjects exposed to 3658 m (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). These findings support the hypothesis.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Hypothesis Testing</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothesis</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Path Coefficient</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">T</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Findings</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep problem→ Daytime dysfunction 400 m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.559</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.950</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Supported</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep problem→ Daytime dysfunction 3658 m 24 h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.643</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.929</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Supported</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep problem→ Daytime dysfunction 3658 m 7-day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.650</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.307</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Supported</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep problem→ Daytime dysfunction 3658 m 6-month</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.703</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.755</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Supported</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">T</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, T-statistic produced by the SmartPLS software.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study to examine the consistency, reliability, and validity of the AIS in a high-altitude situation. In this study, we validate the AIS using a large sample of young Chinese males. Our study found that participants exposed to 3658 m had Cronbach’s α values greater than 0.8 for AIS and 0.5 for CITC, respectively. The ICC results for AIS total scores indicated that the AIS had acceptable test-retest reliability. The Kaiser-Meyer-Olkin measure values were all greater than 0.8. The structural validity of the AIS was satisfactory (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=475497.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Table S3</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">–</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=475497.docx" ext-link-type="uri">10</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). The administration and evaluation of AIS in a high-altitude situation revealed that this scale is very dependable, practical, and simple to use. Furthermore, the AIS’s consistency, reliability, and validity were proven to be excellent in high-altitude conditions.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In the present study, we observed an increase in HR and a decrease in SpO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> when the subjects were rapidly exposed to 3658 m, consistent with the previous studies</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and the progress of acclimatization at high altitudes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">High altitude conditions have a significant impact on sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Inadequate sleep can lead to high-altitude daytime dysfunction, emotional instability, and disrupted cognitive functioning.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Despite the inherent limitations of subjective measures, questionnaires offer the benefit of being time and financially efficient. They also make it possible to gather large, longitudinal datasets within subjects, which can be used to investigate cause-and-effect relationships and the predictive power of various variables (eg, sleep quality and consequences linked to health). AIS was one of the questionnaires that was used to assess the change in high altitude-related sleep quality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> In this study, we showed that a high-altitude environment affects participants’ subjective sleep quality over the short and long term (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). Moreover, we examined the consistency, validity, and reliability of the AIS in a high-altitude environment.</citation_analysis></p>
      <sec id="s0004-s2001">
        <title>Consistency of the AIS</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our study found that the AIS had very satisfactory internal consistency when subjects were exposed to 3658 m. Cronbach’s α values were good (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). This indicates a high level of homogeneity of the AIS, which is further supported by the finding that Cronbach’s α remained very high among high-altitude-acclimated subjects (Cronbach’s α: 0.882). However, Cronbach’s α was slightly lower when subjects stayed at 400 m (Cronbach’s α: 0.796). One possible reason for this may be that smaller subjects staying at 400 m suffered from sleep disturbance. In previous research, non-patient controls had a lower Cronbach’s α of 0.75, while patients with primary insomnia and psychiatric patients had a higher Cronbach’s α of equal to or greater than 0.85.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> This may be because fewer subjects from the non-patient controls suffered from sleep disturbance compared to subjects from the primary patients with primary insomnia and psychiatric patients. Therefore, our results are supported by the research.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Moreover, when the subjects were exposed to 3658 m, all of the CITCs were larger than 0.5, further demonstrating the AIS’s good internal consistency.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2002">
        <title>Reliability of the AIS</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">For the AIS total scores, the ICC value was relatively low. However, the ICC value for the AIS total scores was significantly increased when the subjects were exposed to 3658 m for 7 d, which was greater than 0.4, as proposed by Fleiss et al.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> This may indicate that the effect of the high-altitude environment on sleep quality persists with prolonged altitude exposure, which is supported by that the insomnia prevalence in the high-altitude-acclimated group was higher than that in the acute high-altitude exposure group. The estimated test-retest reliability score for the AIS in clinical samples, according to a meta-analysis by Jahrami et al, is 0.84 at sea level,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and 0.64 for another clinical study by Enomoto et al.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Differences in the research contexts and samples may account for the discrepancy between Jahrami et al’s and Enomoto et al’s and our results. Therefore, we believe that the total score test-retest coefficient for the AIS may continue to rise as the duration of exposure to the plateau continues to increase and then maintain a stable level, which needs further study to verify.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2003">
        <title>Validity of the AIS</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our EFA investigation revealed two main components in the AIS: sleep problem (items 1–5) and daytime dysfunction (items 6–8), which is consistent with the other research.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Furthermore, the current study’s eigenvalue values and factor loadings matched those reported by Sattler et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and Enomoto et al.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The structures in the AIS were considered good as all the factor loadings of the items were above 0.5, the AVEs were greater than 0.5, and the CRs were above 0.7 when the subjects were at an altitude of 3658 m (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). The square root of the AVEs in the current study were all greater than the correlation to every other latent variable for each latent variable. Each item’s loading was greater than all of its cross-loadings, as determined by the Fornell-Larcker criterion and cross-loadings, which are used to assess the discriminant validity of the AIS (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=475497.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Table S3–10</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). In addition, our results (all the VIF &lt;3) indicate that there are no collinearity issues with the data and that the survey findings are reliable and stable.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Lastly, the R-square values for daytime dysfunction at high altitudes were all greater than 0.33,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> which indicates that the frameworks have moderate predictive accuracy (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=475497.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Table S11</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). The hypothesis that sleep quality has a positive influence on daytime function when individuals are exposed to high altitudes was verified (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In total, the findings of the present study suggested that the model of two factors with 8 items of the AIS showed a good fit and achieved construct validity in a high-altitude environment.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This study has several limitations that need to be considered. Firstly, the results are based on self-reported measures, which are prone to response and information bias, and therefore may not be entirely accurate. Secondly, due to limited existing research in the highlands, there is no gold standard for evaluating the AIS’s criterion validity. Finally, the sample used in this study only included young Chinese males, which means that females and older individuals were not represented, thus limiting the generalizability of the findings. These limitations should be taken into account when interpreting the results, and future studies should aim to address these issues.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In conclusion, the AIS is a scale that may be used in a wide range of clinical and research settings to quantify sleep difficulties. The AIS exhibits strong consistency, reliability, and validity. The AIS’s features and simplicity make it an essential psychometric tool in sleep research in high-altitude situations.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors would like to express their gratitude to all the subjects and investigators who participated in the research.</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s0006">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/supplementary material, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding authors.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation, or in all these areas; took part in drafting, revising or critically reviewing the article; gave final approval of the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0008">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The study obtained written informed consent from all participants and was approved by the Ethics Committee of the General Hospital of Western Theater Command of People’s Liberation Army (Approval identifier: 2022EC3-ky062). The author(s) report no conflicts of interest in this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Roach</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bärtsch</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hackett</surname>
<given-names>PH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <part-title>Hypoxia and molecular medicine</part-title>. In: <string-name><surname>Sutton</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Houston</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coates</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, editors. <source><italic toggle="yes">The Lake Louise Acute Mountain Sickness Scoring System</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Burlington, VT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Queen City Printers</publisher-name>; <year>1993</year>:<fpage>272</fpage>–<lpage>274</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>XG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>XC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xin</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>YJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Anxiety as a risk factor for acute mountain sickness among young Chinese men after exposure at 3800 m: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>2573</fpage>–<lpage>2583</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NDT.S436438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38046832</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>de Aquino Lemos</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Antunes</surname>
<given-names>HK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dos Santos</surname>
<given-names>RV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lira</surname>
<given-names>FS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tufik</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Mello</surname>
<given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>High altitude exposure impairs sleep patterns, mood, and cognitive functions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychophysiology</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1298</fpage>–<lpage>1306</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8986.2012.01411.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22803634</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Guan</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ga</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep disturbances in long-term immigrants with chronic mountain sickness: a comparison with healthy immigrants at high altitude</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Respir Physiol Neurobiol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>206</volume>:<fpage>4</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resp.2014.11.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25462013</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bao</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effects of altitude-related hypoxia exposure on the multiscale dynamics of blood pressure fluctuation during sleep: the observation from a pilot study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Sci Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1147</fpage>–<lpage>1155</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S319031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34290536</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tan</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lanzi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep at high altitude: a bibliometric study and visualization analysis from 1992 to 2022</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Heliyon</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e23041</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e23041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38163230</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nussbaumer-Ochsner</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schuepfer</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Siebenmann</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maggiorini</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bloch</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>High altitude sleep disturbances monitored by actigraphy and polysomnography</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">High Alt Med Biol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>236</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/ham.2010.1073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21962066</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Physical activity attenuates the association of long-term exposure to nitrogen dioxide with sleep quality and its dimensions in Chinese rural older adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Affect Disord</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>349</volume>:<fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2024.01.036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38199389</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Benavides-Gelvez</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosa</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hipolide</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cespedes</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ribeiro da Silva Vallim</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Assessing subjective sleep quality using the Pittsburgh sleep quality index among homeless individuals in São Paulo, Brazil</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">SLEEP MED</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>115</volume>:<fpage>85</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2023.11.263</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Leng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knutson</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carnethon</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yaffe</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between sleep quantity and quality in early adulthood with cognitive function in midlife</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>102</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e208056</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000208056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38170947</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jülich</surname>
<given-names>ST</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lei</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Latent profile of the insomnia severity index: a longitudinal study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">SLEEP MED</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>115</volume>:<fpage>202</fpage>–<lpage>209</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2024.02.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38368737</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tański</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tomasiewicz</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jankowska-Polańska</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disturbances as a consequence of long COVID-19: insights from actigraphy and clinimetric examinations-an uncontrolled prospective observational pilot study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Med</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>839</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm13030839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38337533</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Anxiety and depression among patients with insomnia during the first wave and the release of the COVID-19 in Northeast China: a cross-sectional survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Affect Disord</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>349</volume>:<fpage>62</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2023.12.088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38176447</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nagasaki</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kobayashi</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nishizaki</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of sleep quality with duty hours, mental health, and medical errors among Japanese postgraduate residents: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1481</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-51353-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38233476</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Vaccination against SARS-CoV-2 contributed to reducing the prevalence of depression in Chinese adults - A cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Affect Disord</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>349</volume>:<fpage>407</fpage>–<lpage>413</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2024.01.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38190859</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Okajima</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nakajima</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kobayashi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Inoue</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Development and validation of the Japanese version of the Athens insomnia scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>420</fpage>–<lpage>425</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pcn.12073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23910517</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Soldatos</surname>
<given-names>CR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dikeos</surname>
<given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paparrigopoulos</surname>
<given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Athens insomnia scale: validation of an instrument based on ICD-10 criteria</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychosom Res</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>555</fpage>–<lpage>560</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-3999(00)00095-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11033374</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baize</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meriaux-Scoffier</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chrétien</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hayotte</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Piponnier</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>d’Arripe-Longueville</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep assessment in competitive athletes: development and validation of French versions of the Athens insomnia scale and the athlete sleep behavior questionnaire</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Sci</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>183</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0043-1770803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37425979</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Soldatos</surname>
<given-names>CR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dikeos</surname>
<given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paparrigopoulos</surname>
<given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The diagnostic validity of the Athens insomnia scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychosom Res</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>267</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-3999(02)00604-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12932801</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hallit</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haddad</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hallit</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Validation of selected sleeping disorders related scales in Arabic among the Lebanese population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Biol Rhythms</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>183</fpage>–<lpage>189</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s41105-018-0196-0</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Iwasa</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Takebayashi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suzuki</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Psychometric evaluation of the simplified Japanese version of the Athens insomnia scale: the Fukushima health management survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e12771</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30311710</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gómez-Benito</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruiz</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guilera</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A Spanish version of the Athens insomnia scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Qual Life Res</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>931</fpage>–<lpage>937</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11136-010-9827-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21210225</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chiou</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Validation of the Taiwanese version of the Athens insomnia scale and assessment of insomnia in Taiwanese cancer patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Pain Symptom Manage</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>904</fpage>–<lpage>914</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2010.07.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21420272</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tan</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cao</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Reliability and validity of the Chinese version of the Athens insomnia scale for non-clinical application in Chinese athletes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1183919</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2023.1183919</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37780167</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Szymczak</surname>
<given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sitek</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sławek</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Basiński</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Siemiński</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wieczorek</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Subjective sleep quality alterations at high altitude</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Wilderness Environ Med</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>305</fpage>–<lpage>310</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1580/1080-6032-020.004.0305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20030436</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>WY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bian</surname>
<given-names>SZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Physiological and psychological factors associated with onset of high-altitude headache in Chinese men upon acute high-altitude exposure at 3700 m</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cephalalgia</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>336</fpage>–<lpage>347</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0333102416646761</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27152016</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>CY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>ASK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nejati</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A thorough psychometric comparison between Athens insomnia scale and insomnia severity index among patients with advanced cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e12891</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12891</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31328319</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Hair</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Black</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Babin</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Anderson</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Multivariate Data Analysis</italic></source>. <edition>7th</edition> ed. <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pearson</publisher-name>; <year>2014</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fornell</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Larcker</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Evaluating structural equation models with unobservable variables and measurement error</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Marketing Res</italic></source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/002224378101800104</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>SW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gregory</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nylander</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The SIBDQ: further validation in ulceratives colitis patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Gastroenterol</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>95</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>151</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1572-0241.2000.01676.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10638574</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Fleiss</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">The Design and Analysis of Clinical Experiments</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name>; <year>1986</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Insalaco</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Romano</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salvaggio</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pomidori</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mandolesi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cogo</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Periodic breathing, arterial oxyhemoglobin saturation, and heart rate during sleep at high altitude</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">High Alt Med Biol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>258</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/ham.2012.1035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23270442</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sarstedt</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ringle</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Henseler</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hair</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>On the emancipation of PLS-SEM: a commentary on Rigdon (2012)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Long Range Planning</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>154</fpage>–<lpage>160</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lrp.2014.02.007</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tenenhaus</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vinzi</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chatelin</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lauro</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>PLS path modeling</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Comput Stat Data Anal</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>205</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.csda.2004.03.005</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hair</surname>
<given-names>JFJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sarstedt</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matthews</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ringle</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Identifying and treating unobserved heterogeneity with FIMIX-PLS: part I–method</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Bus Rev</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/EBR-09-2015-0094</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>XG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>XS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between decreased osteopontin and acute mountain sickness upon rapid ascent to 3500 m among young Chinese men</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Travel Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>1</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jtm/tay1075</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>West</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schoene</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Milledge</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>. <part-title>Sleep</part-title>. In: <string-name><surname>West</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schoene</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Milledge</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, editors. <source><italic toggle="yes">High Altitude Medicine and Physiology</italic></source>. <edition>4th</edition> ed. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hodder Arnold</publisher-name>; <year>2007</year>:<fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>188</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>West</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Commuting to high altitude: value of oxygen enrichment of room air</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">High Alt Med Biol</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>235</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/15270290260131948</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12162865</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Enomoto</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adachi</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yamada</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Reliability and validity of the Athens insomnia scale in chronic pain patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Pain Res</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>793</fpage>–<lpage>801</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/JPR.S154852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29713192</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sattler</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seddig</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zerbini</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Assessing sleep problems and daytime functioning: a translation, adaption, and validation of the Athens insomnia scale for non-clinical application (AIS-NCA)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Health</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1006</fpage>–<lpage>1031</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08870446.2021.1998498</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34766856</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
