<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39464512</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">11512775</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">461993</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S461993</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Sleep Habits and Disturbances in Healthcare Workers: A Cross-Sectional Survey in French Public Hospitals</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Bouchou et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Bouchou et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0009-0005-8678-8250</contrib-id><name><surname>Bouchou</surname><given-names>Yanis</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0009-0006-4760-6597</contrib-id><name><surname>Giffard-Quillon</surname><given-names>Lorine</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1870-3671</contrib-id><name><surname>Fontana</surname><given-names>Luc</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6115-7958</contrib-id><name><surname>Roche</surname><given-names>Frédéric</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Pélissier</surname><given-names>Carole</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6415-7694</contrib-id><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>Mathieu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Sainbiose, Inserm U1059, Service of Clinical Physiology, University Hospital and University Jean Monnet of Saint-Etienne</institution>, <addr-line>Saint-Etienne</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Occupational Medicine, University Hospital of Saint-Etienne</institution>, <addr-line>Saint-Étienne</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Université de St Etienne, Université Lyon 1, Université Gustave Eiffel, UMRESTTE, UMR T9405</institution>, <addr-line>Saint-Etienne</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Laboratoire Interuniversitaire de Biologie de la Motricité (LIBM), EA 7424, Université Jean Monnet</institution>, <addr-line>Saint-Etienne</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Mathieu Berger, <institution>Sainbiose, DVH Team, Inserm U1059, University Hospital of Saint-Etienne and University of Saint-Etienne</institution>, <addr-line>Mines Saint-Etienne</addr-line>, <addr-line>Saint-Etienne</addr-line>, <country>France</country>, <phone content-type="general">Tel +33 477829014</phone>, Email mathieuberger@outlook.com</corresp><fn id="ft0001"><label>*</label><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">These authors contributed equally to this work</citation_analysis></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>1687</fpage><lpage>1698</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Bouchou et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Bouchou et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Purpose</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">To describe the sleep habits (bedtime hours, waking hours, sleep duration) and to assess the prevalence of sleep disturbances (acute and chronic insomnia, insufficient sleep, perceived sleep debt) among French healthcare workers.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Participants and Methods</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Nurses and assistant nurses working in public hospitals from the Loire department at different work schedules (2x12h, 2x8h, fixed daytime, fixed nighttime) were asked about their socioprofessional and demographic information, their sleep habits and disturbances during night shifts, and the acceptability of a 20-min nap opportunity.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">A total of 297 healthcare workers completed the survey with 76% reporting a sleep debt with a lower prevalence for fixed nighttime workers (62%) and a higher prevalence for 2x12 h (84%) workers. The prevalence of acute insomnia was 76% with a significant difference between fixed nighttime (60%) and 2x12 h (82%); whereas the prevalence of chronic insomnia was 35% without any significant difference between working schedules. Moreover, 18% of healthcare workers reported excessive daytime sleepiness, while 13% admitted to using sleep medication at least once a week.</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">French healthcare workers reported poor sleep quality with a high prevalence of sleep debt, acute and chronic insomnia symptoms without an obvious impact of working schedules.</citation_analysis></p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Sleep habits</kwd><kwd>healthcare workers</kwd><kwd>shift work</kwd><kwd>epidemiology</kwd><kwd>nurses</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="2"/><ref-count count="46"/><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">About 15–20% of the adult population in Europe works atypical hours, outside the 6 a.m. to 8 p.m. range.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In some countries like France, night shift work has increased in popularity over the past 20 years with 2 times more night shift workers.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Little is known about the sleep habits and disorders of French healthcare workers, and the acceptability of potential countermeasures such as napping also remains in question.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Previous studies have shown that shift work and night shift work are associated with deleterious outcomes, such as cancers, cardiovascular events or diabetes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3–5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> One common point to most of these outcomes is probably sleep debt.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Indeed, it has been shown that most of the time, night shift workers have less than 6 h of sleep per 24 hours.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Insomnia prevalence was also shown to be 5 times higher in a sample of clinical workers with atypical work schedules.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Shift work is also known to disrupt circadian rhythms, with previous findings on nurses showing that melatonin secretion is reduced by exposure to light during night work.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Despite these short- and long-term outcomes, shift work remains essential to ensure continuity in many emergency sectors such as healthcare.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In this article, we describe the sleep habits and sleep-related disorders of French healthcare workers. In France, there are four primary working schedules in healthcare settings: 1) Fixed daytime schedule, in which caregivers work consistently for 7 hours and 40 minutes per day, starting usually between 8:00 and 11:00 a.m. and ending between 4:10 and 7:00 p.m.; 2) Fixed nighttime schedule, in which caregivers work a 10-hour night shift from 8:30 p.m. to 6:30 a.m.; 3) 8-hour alternating schedule, in which caregivers alternate between a morning shift from 6:30 a.m. to 1:30 p.m. and an afternoon shift from 1:30 p.m. to 8:30 p.m.; and 4) 12-hour alternating schedule, in which caregivers alternate between a 12-hour day shift from 7:30 a.m. to 7:30 p.m. and a 12-hour night shift from 7:30 p.m. to 7:30 a.m..</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In the last 4 years, the needs in term of workforce in the healthcare sector has drastically increased with the COVID-19 pandemic</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> and to cope with the lack of healthcare workers in France, many Hospital departments have favored the 2x12 h work schedule instead of the 2x8 h one. Still, the impact of these different work schedules on sleep remains largely unknown. In a cohort of Chinese health workers, rotating shift workers showed higher risks of sleep disturbance than the fixed day shift workers.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In the same time, several studies reported an increase in sleep disturbances prevalence among nurses. For example, a meta-analysis reported a 57% prevalence in sleep disturbances between March and May 2020 versus 22.8% between January and February 2020.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> An umbrella review showed that frontline Hospital staff have a higher prevalence of insomnia or sleep disturbances than second-line hospital staff.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> It is important to emphasize that the two studies previously mentioned were carried out within the context of the COVID-19 pandemic. This explains the shift towards 12-hour working days and a rise in absenteeism among the nursing staff. Therefore, it is important to have a better view of sleep habits, especially among healthcare workers for prevention of deleterious outcomes. A recent narrative review including 13 studies showed that 57–83.2% of nurses in shift work reported sleep disturbances, sleep deprivation or poor sleep quality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> These data are associated with an increased prevalence of physical, emotional and social stress.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> More incident medical errors and driving accidents were also reported among nurses with sleep loss.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In France, a study from Ohayon &amp; Colleagues</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> reported 20 min less sleep duration among daytime rotating nurses for a morning shift compared to fixed daytime schedule. Moreover, nurses working on night shift or fixed nighttime schedule slept 1 h less than rotating daytime or fixed daytime nurses. To our knowledge, no other survey has investigated sleep habits in French healthcare workers since this study performed 20 years ago. Still, both societal habits and the organization of care have changed since early 2000 and updated data on sleep in healthcare workers are needed.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The primary objective of this study was to describe the sleep habits (bedtime hours, waking hours, sleep duration) of French healthcare workers according to their work schedule (fixed daytime, fixed nighttime, 2x8 h or 2x12 h). The secondary objectives were to assess the prevalence of sleep disturbances (acute and chronic insomnia, insufficient sleep, perceived sleep debt and excessive daytime sleepiness (EDS) in this population of healthcare workers according to their work schedules and to assess the feasibility of an on-duty nap during night-shift work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Research Design</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">A multicentric, open, cross-sectional, observational survey was conducted in 4 out of 20 hospitals from the Loire territory Hospital group (THG) electronically using a secure web application (LimeSurvey GmbH, Hamburg, Germany). The study was approved by the local ethics committee (Commission recherche de Terre d’Éthique Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Saint-Etienne, IRBN352022/CHUSTE, France) and complies with the principles outlined in the Declaration of Helsinki. All participants gave their written informed consent electronically using a secure web application (LimeSurvey GmbH, Hamburg, Germany). We adhered to relevant EQUATOR guidelines using the STROBE cross-sectional checklist.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Data Collection and Participants</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The THG Loire gathers more than 15300 healthcare professionals and 7700 hospital beds. All these hospitals work together to ensure coordination, consultation and care offering. Thus, THG Loire appeared as a representative population to investigate sleep habits and sleep disturbances in France. This study was restricted to nurses and care assistants. Physicians and technicians were not included. No other eligibility criteria were defined. This study was coordinated by the Occupational Health Service from the University Hospital of Saint-Etienne. The principal investigator (CP) contacted occupational health physicians from four peripheral hospitals randomly selected to participate in this survey. Then each occupational health physician randomly selected departments from their Hospital to participate in this study. Data were collected from May 2022 to September 2022. A total of 13 departments were selected from the University Hospital of Saint-Etienne, 11 services from this center and 18 from three peripheral hospitals (Roanne, Montbrison/Feurs, Annonay) accepted to participate in this study. An Email was sent to the head physician and healthcare manager of each department selected to present the study objectives. If a positive answer was provided, then an appointment was organized with the healthcare workers (nurses and care assistants) to present the purpose and procedures of this study. Flyers and posters presenting the study were left in the selected departments with a QR code allowing participation in the survey using LimeSurvey.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Working Schedule</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Four different working schedules were investigated: 1) fixed daytime schedule for those always working 7 h 40/d (between 8:00 to 11:00 a.m. to 4:10–7:00 p.m); 2) fixed nighttime schedule for those always working 10 h during night shift (from 8:30 p.m. to 6:30 a.m); 3) 2x8 h for those working alternating morning shift (6:30 a.m. to 1:30 p.m) and afternoon shift (1:30 p.m. to 8:30 p.m); 4) 2x12 h for those working alternating day shift (from 7:30 a.m. to 7:30 p.m) and night shift (from 7:30 p.m. to 7:30 a.m).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Measurements</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The survey was electronically and anonymously completed by volunteer nurses and nursing care assistants in LimeSurvey .This survey included 4 parts.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">1) A socioprofessional and demographic section to collect age, sex, seniority, occupational status, work schedule, function, Hospital center.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">2) A section about sleep habits and sleep disturbances. Self-reported sleep habits were assessed by asking about bedtime hours, waking hours, sleep duration on rest day, and nap habits on work days (depending of the working schedule) and during rest days. 24 h sleep opportunity was estimated by adding time in bed and nap time for each work schedule on work day and on rest day. Perceived sleep debt was subjectively assessed by asking participants if they felt sleep deprived. Severe sleep debt was defined as a difference greater than 90 min between self-reported sleep time and ideal sleep time.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Chronotype was assessed by one question asking whether participants felt alert in the morning and sleepy in the evening (morning type), not alert/sleepy in the morning or in the evening (intermediate type), or sleepy in the morning and alert in the evening (vesperal type).</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Insomnia was assessed according to the third International Classification of Sleep Disturbances (ICSD-3) based on insomnia symptoms (difficulties with sleep initiation, sleep maintenance, or early awakening) for at least 3 times per week and the duration of exposure &gt;3 months (chronic) or &lt;3 months (acute). The Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS) was used to assess subjective EDS.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The ESS score ranged from 0–24 and a score ≥11 indicated EDS.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">3) A section investigated lifestyle habits by asking about physical activity at different levels (sedentary, moderate, vigorous), alcohol consumption (number of alcohol drinks per week), coffee consumption (number of cups per day) and smoking status (nonsmoker, previous or current smoker).</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">4) The last section concerned the identification of barriers and levers inherent to the implementation of a 20-min nap on the night shift. The first question was designed to determine whether healthcare workers working night shifts (2x12h and fixed night shifts) would support the introduction of a 20-min nap at their workstation. In order to identify the barriers and levers inherent to napping, a multiple-choice question was asked to the study participants, with the following response choices: a) continuity of care provided by a colleague; b) a quiet room with room to lie down; c) a dedicated nap room inside the department; d) a dedicated room for napping outside the department.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Statistical Analyses</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Data are presented as mean and standard deviation (SD) for continuous variables or as number of subjects and percentages for categorical variables. Normality was assessed with the Shapiro Wilks test. A one-way ANOVA was used to compare continuous parametric variables according to work schedule, following by a Bonferroni post hoc in case of significance. Otherwise, the Kruskal–Wallis test was used as a nonparametric equivalent. For categorical variables, chi-square test or Fischer exact test was used, as appropriate. All statistical analyses were performed using IBM SPPS Statistics version 26.0 for Macintosh (IMB Corp, Armonk, N.Y. USA). Significant results were considered for a two-sided test with p &lt; 0.05.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Participants Characteristics</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Among 740 eligible participants, 297 (40%) healthcare workers completed this survey, including 210 nurses (70.7%) and 87 (29.3%) care assistants. Among them, 49.6% (n=147) worked in a 2×12 h shift schedule, 18% (n=53) worked in a fixed nighttime schedule,15.5% (n=46) worked in a 2x8h schedule, and 13.8% (n=41) worked in a fixed daytime schedule. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> shows their demographic characteristics. Most participants of the sample were female (87.2%), middle aged (mean age: 38.2 ± 10.7 years old) with a mean seniority of 13.2 ± 9.8 y, and a mean seniority inside their department of 8.0 ± 7.4 y.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sociodemographic Characteristics</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall (n=297)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fixed Daytime (n=41)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fixed Nighttime (n=53)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 h Shift Work (n=56)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12-h Shift Work (n=147)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Age (y)</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.2 ± 10.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.1 ± 10.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.2 ± 11.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.6 ± 11.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.3 ± 9.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.192</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Gender</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">259 (87.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (92.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (90.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (94.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120 (81.6%)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>0.037</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Man (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (12.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (7.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (9.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (5.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (18.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Job</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nurses (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">210 (70.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (56.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (62.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (60.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120 (81.6%)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Assistants Nurses (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (29.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (43.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (37.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (39.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (18.4%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Current smoker (%)</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 (22.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (21.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (22.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (23.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (23.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.997</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Coffee consumption</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (33.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (19.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (47.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (31.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (31.8%)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.135</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–3 cups</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110 (42.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (58.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (32.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (44.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (40.2%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 cups</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (24.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (22.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (19.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (23.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (28.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Chronotype</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Morning type (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">131 (50.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (20.6%)*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (10.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (19%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (49.6%)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1"><bold>0.007</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intermediate type (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (23.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (6.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (24.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (22.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (46.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vesperal type (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (23.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (27.8%)*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (13.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (55.1%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Number of children</italic> (n)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 ± 1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 ± 1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 ± 1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 ± 1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 ± 1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.782</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Distribution of working time in full-time equivalent (%)</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.1 ± 9.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.4 ± 8.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.7 ± 11.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.3 ± 9.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.0 ± 8.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.149</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Seniority in the job (y)</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.2 ± 9.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.9 ± 10.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.1 ± 11.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0 ± 9.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4 ± 8.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.010</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Seniority in the service (y)</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0 ± 7.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9 ± 4.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1 ± 8.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5 ± 8.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1± 7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.208</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: Data are presented as mean ± SD or n (%); significant p-values are in bold; * indicate adjusted residuals &gt; │2│.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Sleep Habits Characteristics</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Sleep habits characteristics according to working schedule are shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. Bedtime varies according to the working schedule (fixed day/night schedule, 2x8 h, 2x12 h) and the work or rest period. On average, during working days, fixed day workers reported spending 7.5 h in bed, while fixed night worker spent 6 h in bed. For rotating workers (2x8 h and 2 x12 h), the time spent in bed is less during work days before the morning/night shift schedule for 2x12 h. However, it differs following the afternoon/day shift in favor of afternoon shift with 9.5 h bedtime for 2x8h and only 7.5 h bedtime for 2x 12 h (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep Habits of Healthcare Workers by Work Schedule</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Work Schedule</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fixed Daytime (n=41)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fixed Nighttime (n=53)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">8-h Shift Work (n=46)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">12-h Shift Work (n=147)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bedtime (hh:mm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day/morning</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:30 (10:00–11:00) p.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:30 (9:10–11:00) p.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:30 (10:00–11:00) p.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.076</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Night/afternoon</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8:30 (8:00–9:00) a.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11:00 (10:30–11:30) p.m. <sup>###</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9:00 (8:30–9:00) a.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Free day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11:00 (10:30–11:30) p.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11:00 (10:30–0:00) p.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11:00 (10:30–11:30) p.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11:00 (20:30–11:30) p.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.300</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wake up time (hh:mm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day/morning</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6:00 (5:40–6:30) a.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5:25 (5:00–5:34) a.m. <sup>###</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6:00 (5:45–6:20) a.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Night/afternoon</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2:30 (1:30–3:00) p.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8:20 (7:00–9:30) a.m. <sup>###</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2:00 (1:00–3:00) p.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Free day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8:00 (7:20–9:00) a.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7:30 (7:00–9:45) a.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8:00 (7:00–9:30) a.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8:00 (7:00–9:00) a.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.548</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time in Bed (hh:mm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day/morning</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7:30 (7:00–8:08) a.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7:00 (6:30–8:00) a.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7:30(7:00–8:00) a.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.141</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Night/afternoon</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6:00 (5:00–7:00) a.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9:30 (8:00–10:30) a.m. <sup>###</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5:00 (4:00–6:00) a.m.<sup>†</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Free day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9:00 (8:00–10:00) a.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8:00 (7:00–9:00) a.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9:30 (8:00–10:30) a.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9:00 (8:00–10:00) a.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.986</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimated sleep duration (hh:mm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Free day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8:00 (7:00–9:00) a.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8:00 (7:00–9:00) a.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8:00 (7:00–9:20) a.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8:00 (8:00–9:00) a.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.293</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Off duty nap (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day/morning</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (37%)*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Night/afternoon</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (42%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (37%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (47%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.428</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Free day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (19%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (89%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (28%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (27%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.585</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of off duty nap (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day/morning</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (45–120)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (45–120)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75(30–140)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.592</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Night/afternoon</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (52–90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (45–120)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (45–120)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.202</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Free day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (30–60)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (20–80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (37–120)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (30–60)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.120</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24-h sleep opportunity (h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day/morning</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7:30 (7:00–8:10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7:30 (6:30–8:30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7:30 (7:00–8:00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold>.714</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Night/afternoon</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6:30 (5:15–7:00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10:00 (8:30–10:30)<sup>###</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5:30 (4:30–6:30)<sup>†</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Free day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9:00 (8:30–10:10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9:00 (8:15–10:40)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9:30 (8:15–10:30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9:25 (8:30–10:30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.315</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe sleep debt (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (14.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (27.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (6.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (16.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.057</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnosed obstructive sleep apnea (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.854</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Data are presented as median (interquartile range), mean ± SD or n (%). Significant p-values are in bold. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>###</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: p&lt;0.001 vs fixed nighttime and 12-h shift work; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>†</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: p&lt;0.05 vs fixed nighttime; * indicate adjusted residuals &gt; │2│.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Off-duty naps during rest days were mainly taken by fixed night shift workers, who are 3–4 times more likely to take a nap on days off compared to other shift schedules (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). Off-duty naps were mainly reported by 2x12 h workers (19%) during night shift and more scarcely reported by fixed nighttime workers (4%).</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Violin plots showing 24-h sleep opportunity distribution according to shift work are shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Violin plots showing 24-h sleep opportunity distribution according to shift work schedule.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1687-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Sleep Disturbances</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Acute insomnia was highly prevalent in our healthcare workers population with 76% of the sample reporting at least one symptom of insomnia defined as difficulty falling asleep at night, waking up during the night, waking up too early more than 3 times per week. When comparing shift schedules, we found that healthcare workers working on the 2x12 h shift schedule were more likely to report acute insomnia (82%) compared to other groups; while those working on a fixed night schedule were less likely to report acute insomnia symptoms (60%, p=0.020) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). Chronic insomnia was two times lower in the overall sample compared to acute insomnia (35% vs 76%, respectively) and no significant differences were found according to work schedules (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Acute and chronic insomnia symptoms among healthcare workers (%).</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1687-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: * indicate adjusted residuals &gt; │2│.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In our sample, 88% reported sleep disturbances. Healthcare workers in the fixed nighttime schedule reported lower sleep disturbances (77%), while those in the 2x12 h shift schedule reported more sleep disturbances (93%) (p=0.019; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">(</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) Prevalence of sleep disturbances; (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) Prevalence of sleep debt; (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>C</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) Sleep debt duration (min); (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>D</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) Prevalence of excessive daytime sleepiness; (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>E</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) Use of medication at least once a week.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1687-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">More than 76% of healthcare workers felt sleep deprived with a significant difference between working schedules (p=0.017; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). Moreover, healthcare workers working on 2x12 h exhibited sleep debt almost twice higher than fixed nighttime with 99.6 min vs 55.2 min, respectively and three time higher than fixed daytime and 2x8h workers (p&lt;0.01; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3C</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). Overall, 18% of the healthcare workers reported EDS and no significant difference was found between work schedules (p = 0.423) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3D</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). Finally, 13% of healthcare workers reported using medication at least once a week to sleep. Again, no significant difference was found between workers with different sleep schedules (p = 0.583) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3E</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Nap</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Concerning the identification of barriers and levers inherent to the implementation of a 20-min nap during night shifts, 197 healthcare workers (160 women, 81%) working either in fixed night shifts (27%) or in 2x12 h shifts (73%) responded. The vast majority of healthcare workers working at night (90%) were in favor of the implementation of a nap within their post. Regarding the barriers and levers, two main levers emerge from the survey: the need to ensure the continuity of care and the provision of a quiet room to lie down.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This study aimed to explore the sleep habits of French healthcare workers working different work schedules (fixed day, fixed night, 2x8 h, 2x12 h). The results revealed that 18% of the healthcare workers were excessively sleepy and 13% used sleeping pills more than once a week. Regarding insomnia, three quarters of the healthcare workers reported symptoms of acute insomnia, while one third reported chronic insomnia. Finally, three quarters reported sleep debt and only 12% reported no sleep disturbance.</citation_analysis></p>
      <sec id="s0004-s2001">
        <title>Sleep Habits and Sleep Debt Among Healthcare Workers</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our data are similar to those of Ohayon &amp; colleagues who found a median sleep duration of 6 h for those working night shifts and fixed night schedules. In our study, we only reported time in bed, so total sleep duration is likely even shorter. Other studies have reported similar short sleep duration associated with night shift work and are consistent with ours.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Reasons for such a short sleep may be explained by daytime light environment that prevents melatonin secretion from inducing sleep since melatonin secretion is a major factor in the development of sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Surprisingly, when considering perceived sleep deprivation, it is interesting to note that fixed night shift workers exhibited less sleep deprivation than 2x8 h workers (62 vs 73%) and significantly less than 2x12h workers (62 vs 84%). One might have expected a lower prevalence of perceived sleep deprivation among 2x8h workers since they get more sleep than workers on fixed night schedules. Despite a similar 24-h sleep opportunity between fixed nighttime and 2x12 h shift schedules, fixed nighttime workers reported less perceived sleep debt. Reasons for such discrepancies may be explained by the specific profile of night shift workers who may have a shorter sleep profile. Indeed, a fixed atypical work rhythm such as fixed night work allows the biological clock to adapt, whereas a work rhythm with rotations forces a continuous adaptation of the circadian rhythm of the workers, especially if these are fast as happens for healthcare workers.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The 2x8h workers in our sample woke up at a median time of 5:25 a.m., a time of day that corresponds to the circadian nadir of body temperature.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Ohayon &amp; colleagues reported that rotating day workers suffer from more fragmented sleep than fixed scheduled or night shift workers. Although sleep fragmentation was not investigated in the present study, our results on insomnia symptoms suggest that this population not concerned by night shift work is still at high risk of sleep disturbance.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Healthcare workers working a 2x12 h schedule reported a greater perceived sleep debt than all other work schedules in our study. A previous study performed in employees of a power plant in Australia showed no difference in sleep debt between 2x12 h and 2x8 h shift work, but employees on 12-h shifts are at greater risk of occupational injury.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Another study showed that 2x12 h nurses were described as having a greater need for recovery,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> which could be associated with a greater need for sleep among 2x12 h healthcare workers. One reason for such a sleep debt in our 2x12 h healthcare workers is the time spent in bed which is at least 1 h lower than all other shift schedules with a median time in bed of 5 h. These findings are consistent with a previous study showing that among 80 US nurses working 2x12 h for three consecutive days, their time in bed is only 5.4 h after the night shift,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> which is very similar to our population sample.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This study found greater sleepiness during night work, which may subsequently increase the risk of injury or accident. In our study, we found an 18% prevalence of EDS with no significant difference according to shift schedules. These results are consistent with previous finding</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> that showed a 29% EDS prevalence in rotating daytime workers compared to 25% in our study, although questionnaires to assess EDS differed.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2002">
        <title>Sleep Disturbances</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Only 4 participants (1.3%) reported being treated for obstructive sleep apnea, without significant difference between work schedules. However, in our sample, about three quarters of healthcare workers had symptoms of acute insomnia. Among them, healthcare workers in fixed night shift work we likely to report acute insomnia while those in 2x12 h shift were more likely to report these symptoms. For acute insomnia, healthcare workers working on a 2x12 h shift schedule were more likely to report sleep debt (84%) compared to other groups; while those working on a fixed night schedule were less likely to report sleep debt (62%). These findings suggest that a similar pattern seems to emerge regarding the prevalence of chronic insomnia and reported sleep debt among our participants. Of note, chronic insomnia was twice lower than acute insomnia with about one third of our sample reporting symptoms of insomnia for more than 3 months without significant difference between work schedules. However, the prevalence of healthcare workers reporting chronic insomnia in our sample remains twice higher compared to results of</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> (31–41% vs 12–18%, respectively). Reasons for such discrepancies may be explained by changes in sleep habits over time.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Moreover, one significant difference lies in use of new technologies such as smartphones that may explain shortening sleep probably due to the overuse of screens at bedtime.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">A survey using a sample of 1586 Norwegian nurses assessed chronic insomnia with the Bergen Shift Work Sleep Questionnaire</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> working either in three-shift rotation, two-shift rotation and permanent night. The results found that insomnia was more prevalent in the two-shift rotation schedule than the three-shift rotation schedule (29.8% and 19.8%, respectively). Insomnia during the night shift showed higher frequencies among three-shift rotation workers compared with permanent night workers (67.7% and 41.7%, respectively).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In our study, we did not have a three-shift rotation sample, but on the evening shift the prevalence is comparable to ours; whereas for fixed nighttime the Norwegian survey showed a higher prevalence compare to our fixed nighttime sample. A Canadian survey had indicated that insomnia was more common among night and shift workers than among day workers.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In that study, it appeared that being a shift worker or working at night was associated with insomnia, but the association was stronger between total sleep time and insomnia than with shift work.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Interestingly, subjective sleep debt followed the same pattern as the findings for acute insomnia in our study. Therefore, our results for acute insomnia may be related to shorter sleep time associated with severe sleep debt rather than to the work schedule itself.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">No significant differences were found concerning the use of sleeping pills in our study, with overall 13% of the healthcare workers taking sleeping pills. To our knowledge, no other study on a French population of healthcare workers reported such information. By comparison, a Norwegian study</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> found that 7.5% of nurses used prescribed sleeping pills, while 4.7% and 2.0% reported using over-the-counter sleeping pills and melatonin, respectively. Results regarding the use of sleeping pills are, however, heterogeneous. Indeed, a Japanese study</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> found that 10% of shift workers used hypnotics, whereas 56% of Canadian emergency physicians used them regularly.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In our sample, most healthcare workers (17%) who use sleeping pills worked at night or in daytime rotating shift (2x8 h), but no significant difference was found with other work schedules.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2003">
        <title>Countermeasure</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">One countermeasure adopted by healthcare workers to counter the effects of workplace sleepiness and fatigue has been identified: napping. Regarding napping, Ohayon et al reported a similar proportion (approximately 35%) of healthcare workers working night shifts, fixed night shifts, and rotating day shifts who napped 3 times per week</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our results do not follow this pattern, with fixed night workers napping less off duty compared to 2x12h night workers and morning workers. The proportion of napping in the morning shift could be explained by short sleep duration and early awakening, due to the forbidden zone,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> a phenomenon that prevents sleep induction before 9 p.m., so afternoon naps provide recovery to compensate. Most night workers in our study took a nap on their day off (89%). This strategic placement of napping is consistent with prophylactic napping defined as a nap to reduce sleep pressure and alleviate alertness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> With respect to the duration of naps, the aforementioned authors did not report this, but a Japanese observational study found that on a 16-h shift, 30.1% of 196 night workers slept for &gt;90 min and 69.9% for &lt;90 min, whereas none of our subjects napped for &gt;75 min on average.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Napping at work seems to be more popular in some countries, such as Japan and less so in France or South Korea, where at best 43% of healthcare workers working a 2x12 h shift take a nap on the shift in our study and nearly 80% of the 2165 night workers did not have the opportunity to nap.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> This can be explained by cultural and representational differences between countries, as well as the healthcare system, which must allow for continuity of care.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> On the other hand, napping at work has been shown to decrease sleepiness and improve performance</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> and may be an excellent strategy to implement to improve health and healthcare performance for those working nights. Results concerning the identification of specific levers for the implementation of an “official” nap within the service highlighted some interesting elements for its practical implementation. The first being the need to ensure the continuity of care, while the second point that stands out is the setting up of a room with the possibility of lying down. These findings highlighted the need to modify working/rest schedule and workplace to facilitate these implementations; but further qualitative studies are needed to better identify the organizational, structural and societal barriers and levers to an “official” nap implementation during night work.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2004">
        <title>Study Strengths and Limitations</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This survey has allowed to update our knowledge on sleep habits and sleep disturbances prevalence in French healthcare workers since workstation and workload have consistently evolved in the last two decades. The main strength of this study relies on the investigation of four different shift schedules, while previous studies usually grouped different rotating shifts without distinction.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Some limitations should, however, be mentioned. Although services participating in this study were randomized, this remains a convenience sample since only voluntary and interested healthcare workers completed the survey, which may have induced a selection bias limiting the generalizability of the results. Sleep data were self-reported and may have been underestimated or overestimated.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Further studies with objective measurements are needed to confirm these self-reported findings.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Regarding sleep habits, we only collected time in bed on workdays, but subjective sleep quality was not reported and information regarding sleep onset latency or wake after sleep onset is lacking. We have chosen not to include this questionnaire so as not to make the survey too time-consuming to complete and to encourage adhesion.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Lastly, some clinical diagnosis such as chronic insomnia must be confirmed by clinical interview with a physician.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our results highlighted a high variability in sleep habits in healthcare workers depending of their work schedule. This high variability in sleep habits from one day to the other, together with sleep debt, may explain the high prevalence of acute and chronic insomnia symptoms reported in our French healthcare workers population. Knowing the impact of sleep disturbances and sleep deprivation on health outcomes, it is urgently needed to set up prevention actions on sleep in healthcare workers. Future studies should focus on the development of effective countermeasures such as physical activity, diet or naps to combat the negative effects of shift work on sleep among healthcare workers.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We would like to express our sincere gratitude to physicians in outlying centers, healthcare managers, department heads, hospital management and volunteers for their contribution to data collection.</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">EDS, excessive daytime sleepiness; THG, territory Hospital group; ICSD-3, third International Classification of Sleep Disturbances; ESS, Epworth Sleepiness Scale.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s0007">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Data supporting the results reported in this manuscript will be made available by the authors upon reasonable request.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0008">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation, or in all these areas; took part in drafting, revising or critically reviewing the article; gave final approval of the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0009">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest in this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Sixth European Working Conditions Survey – overview report. Eurofound</article-title>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>July</month>
<day>10</day>, 2023</date-in-citation>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.eurofound.europa.eu/publications/report/2016/working-conditions/sixth-european-working-conditions-survey-overview-report" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.eurofound.europa.eu/publications/report/2016/working-conditions/sixth-european-working-conditions-survey-overview-report</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Night shift work in 2012</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">DARES Analysis</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Manohar</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thongprayoon</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheungpasitporn</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mao</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Herrmann</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Associations of rotational shift work and night shift status with hypertension: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Hypertens</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1929</fpage>–<lpage>1937</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/HJH.0000000000001442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28650914</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wegrzyn</surname>
<given-names>LR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tamimi</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosner</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Rotating Night-Shift Work and the Risk of Breast Cancer in the Nurses Health Studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>186</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>532</fpage>–<lpage>540</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwx140</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28541391</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Torquati</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mielke</surname>
<given-names>GI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kolbe-Alexander</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Shift work and the risk of cardiovascular disease. A systematic review and meta-analysis including dose-response relationship</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Scand J Work Environ Health</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>238</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5271/sjweh.3700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29247501</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Di Milia</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rogers</surname>
<given-names>NL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Åkerstedt</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleepiness, long distance commuting and night work as predictors of driving performance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e45856</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0045856</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23029278</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bushnell</surname>
<given-names>PT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Colombi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caruso</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tak</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Work schedules and health behavior outcomes at a large manufacturer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ind Health</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>395</fpage>–<lpage>405</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2486/indhealth.mssw-03</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20720331</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ohayon</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lemoine</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arnaud-Briant</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dreyfus</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalence and consequences of sleep disorders in a shift worker population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychosom Res</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>577</fpage>–<lpage>583</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0022-3999(02)00438-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12127174</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Books</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coody</surname>
<given-names>LC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kauffman</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abraham</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Night Shift Work and Its Health Effects on Nurses</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Health Care Manag</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>347</fpage>–<lpage>353</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/HCM.0000000000000177</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Walia</surname>
<given-names>HK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hayes</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Przepyszny</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Karumanchi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Clinical presentation of shift workers to a sleep clinic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath Schlaf Atm</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>543</fpage>–<lpage>547</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-011-0540-y</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Razavi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Devore</surname>
<given-names>EE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bajaj</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Shift Work, Chronotype, and Melatonin Rhythm in Nurses</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cancer Epidemiol Biomark Prev Publ Am Assoc Cancer Res Cosponsored Am Soc Prev Oncol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1177</fpage>–<lpage>1186</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-18-1018</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nie</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Su</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guan</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Psychological impact of COVID‐19 outbreak on frontline nurses: a cross‐sectional survey study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Nurs</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>21–22</issue>):<fpage>4217</fpage>–<lpage>4226</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jocn.15454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32786150</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nie</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Relationship between shift work schedule and self-reported sleep quality in Chinese employees</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chronobiol Int</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>261</fpage>–<lpage>269</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07420528.2017.1399902</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29172737</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Marvaldi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mallet</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dubertret</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moro</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guessoum</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Anxiety, depression, trauma-related, and sleep disorders among healthcare workers during the COVID-19 pandemic: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurosci Biobehav Rev</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>126</volume>:<fpage>252</fpage>–<lpage>264</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2021.03.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33774085</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dragioti</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsartsalis</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mentis</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mantzoukas</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gouva</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on the mental health of Hospital staff: an umbrella review of 44 meta-analyses</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Nurs Stud</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>131</volume>:<fpage>104272</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2022.104272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35576637</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ji</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep problems in shift nurses: a brief review and recommendations at both individual and institutional levels</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Nurs Manag</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>10</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jonm.12656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30171641</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shao</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chou</surname>
<given-names>YC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yeh</surname>
<given-names>MY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tzeng</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep quality and quality of life in female shift-working nurses</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Adv Nurs</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1565</fpage>–<lpage>1572</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2648.2010.05300.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20492021</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Suzuki</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ohida</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaneita</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yokoyama</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Uchiyama</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Daytime sleepiness, sleep habits and occupational accidents among Hospital nurses</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Adv Nurs</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>445</fpage>–<lpage>453</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2648.2005.03610.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16268848</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Scott</surname>
<given-names>LD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hwang</surname>
<given-names>WT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rogers</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nysse</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dean</surname>
<given-names>GE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dinges</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The relationship between nurse work schedules, sleep duration, and drowsy driving</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1801</fpage>–<lpage>1807</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/30.12.1801</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18246989</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Léger</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>du</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bayon</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guignard</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pâquereau</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beck</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Short sleep in young adults: insomnia or sleep debt? Prevalence and clinical description of short sleep in a representative sample of 1004 young adults from France</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>454</fpage>–<lpage>462</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2010.12.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21474376</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Johns</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A new method for measuring daytime sleepiness: the Epworth sleepiness scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>540</fpage>–<lpage>545</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/14.6.540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1798888</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pélissier</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cavelier</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vercherin</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roche</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patural</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fontana</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Vigilance and sleepiness in nurses working 12-hr shifts and their coping strategies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Nurs Manag</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>962</fpage>–<lpage>970</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jonm.13233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33305408</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ryu</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>KS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Factors associated with sleep duration in Korean adults: results of a 2008 community health survey in Gwangju metropolitan city, Korea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Korean Med Sci</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1124</fpage>–<lpage>1131</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3346/jkms.2011.26.9.1124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21935265</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Faraut</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cordina-Duverger</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aristizabal</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Immune disruptions and night shift work in Hospital healthcare professionals: the intricate effects of social jet-lag and sleep debt</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Immunol</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>939829</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2022.939829</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36164341</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Daugaard</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garde</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bonde</surname>
<given-names>JPE</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Night work, light exposure and melatonin on work days and days off</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chronobiol Int</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>942</fpage>–<lpage>955</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07420528.2017.1327867</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28613972</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Harris</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Waage</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ursin</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hansen</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bjorvatn</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eriksen</surname>
<given-names>HR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cortisol, reaction time test and health among offshore shift workers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychoneuroendocrinology</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1339</fpage>–<lpage>1347</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psyneuen.2010.03.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20399022</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Choosong</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arporn</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chaikittiporn</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A study of melatonin levels and stress in female shift workers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Southeast Asian J Trop Med Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1048</fpage>–<lpage>1053</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17333753</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mitchell</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williamson</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Evaluation of an 8 hour versus a 12 hour shift roster on employees at a power station</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Appl Ergon</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0003-6870(99)00025-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10709754</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kundi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koller</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stefan</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lehner</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaindlsdorfer</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rottenbücher</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Attitudes of nurses towards 8-h and 12-h shift systems</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Work Stress</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>2017</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02678379508256547</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Geiger-Brown</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rogers</surname>
<given-names>VE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trinkoff</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kane</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bausell</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scharf</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep, sleepiness, fatigue, and performance of 12-hour-shift nurses</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chronobiol Int</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>219</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/07420528.2011.645752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22324559</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Léger</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep Time in France</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Bull Épidémiologique Hebd</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>2019</volume>(<issue>8–9</issue>):<fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>160</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Leger</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Richard</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Collin</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sauvet</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Faraut</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Napping and weekend catchup sleep do not fully compensate for high rates of sleep debt and short sleep at a population level (in a representative nationwide sample of 12,637 adults)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>278</fpage>–<lpage>288</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.05.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32866843</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Flo</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bjorvatn</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Folkard</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A reliability and validity study of the Bergen Shift Work Sleep Questionnaire in nurses working three-shift rotations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chronobiol Int</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>937</fpage>–<lpage>946</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/07420528.2012.699120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22823877</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Flo</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pallesen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Åkerstedt</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Shift-related sleep problems vary according to work schedule</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Occup Environ Med</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>70</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>238</fpage>–<lpage>245</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/oemed-2012-101091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23343860</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vallières</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Azaiez</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moreau</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>LeBlanc</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morin</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia in shift work</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1440</fpage>–<lpage>1448</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2014.06.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25277664</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Forthun</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Waage</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pallesen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moen</surname>
<given-names>BE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bjorvatn</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep medication and melatonin use among Norwegian nurses - A cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nurs Open</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>244</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/nop2.1057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34534412</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Futenma</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Asaoka</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Takaesu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impact of hypnotics use on daytime function and factors associated with usage by female shift work nurses</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>604</fpage>–<lpage>611</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2014.11.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25890782</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Francis</surname>
<given-names>MN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wishart</surname>
<given-names>IM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williamson</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Iverach</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Use of Pharmacologic Sleep Aids and Stimulants Among Emergency Medicine Staff Physicians in a Canadian Tertiary Care Setting: a Web-Based Survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Emerg Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>73</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>325</fpage>–<lpage>329</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.annemergmed.2018.07.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30146443</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lavie</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Ultrashort sleep-waking schedule. “Gates” and “forbidden zones” for sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Electroencephalogr Clin Neurophysiol</italic></source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>414</fpage>–<lpage>425</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0013-4694(86)90123-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2420557</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bonnet</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arand</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Consolidated and distributed nap schedules and performance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.1995.tb00154.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Watanabe</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sugimura</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shishido</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Konya</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yano</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of 90 min Napping on Fatigue and Associated Environmental Factors among Nurses Working Long Night Shifts: a Longitudinal Observational Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>9429</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph19159429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35954787</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ham</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jeong</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of work organization on the occurrence and resolution of sleep disturbances among night shift workers: a longitudinal observational study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>5499</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-85017-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33750873</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dinges</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Orne</surname>
<given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whitehouse</surname>
<given-names>WG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Orne</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Temporal placement of a nap for alertness: contributions of circadian phase and prior wakefulness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>329</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3659730</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Smith-Coggins</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Howard</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mac</surname>
<given-names>DT</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Improving alertness and performance in emergency department physicians and nurses: the use of planned naps</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Emerg Med</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>596–604,604.e1</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.annemergmed.2006.02.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17052562</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kilby</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jorgensen</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Douglas</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Napping and night shift work: effects of a short nap on psychomotor vigilance and subjective sleepiness in health workers: naps and night shift</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Biol Rhythms</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1479-8425.2007.00261.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cespedes</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>FB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Redline</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Comparison of Self-Reported Sleep Duration With Actigraphy: results From the Hispanic Community Health Study/Study of Latinos Sueño Ancillary Study</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>183</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>561</fpage>–<lpage>573</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26940117</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
