<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39502379</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">11537196</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">489668</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S489668</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Clinical and PSG Characteristics Comparison of Central Sleep Apnea in the Elderly and Non-Elderly Patients</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Zhang et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Zhang et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Guoxin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Liqin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Fang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0873-7229</contrib-id><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Xiaoyun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine Department, Tianjin Chest Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Tianjin</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Institute of Mental Health, Tianjin Anding Hospital, Mental Health Center of Tianjin Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Tianjin</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Xiaoyun Zhao, <institution>Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine Department, Tianjin Chest Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Tianjin</addr-line>, <addr-line>300222</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, <phone content-type="general">Tel +86 8818 2075</phone>, Email zxydoctor@163.com</corresp><fn id="ft0001"><label>*</label><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">These authors contributed equally to this work</citation_analysis></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>01</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>1749</fpage><lpage>1756</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>01</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Zhang et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Zhang et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Objective</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">To explore the characteristics of elderly patients with central sleep apnea (CSA).</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">This retrospective study divided 123 patients with CSA into elderly and non-elderly groups, and compared them in terms of demographic characteristics (age, BMI, etc), underlying diseases (hypertension, coronary heart disease, and cardiac arrhythmias, etc). and polysomnography parameters. Multiple linear regression analysis was conducted to investigate the potential risk factors of central apnea index (CAI).</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Compared with the non-elderly group, patients in the elderly group had lower body mass index, a higher proportion of comorbidities of coronary heart disease, arrhythmias, and diabetes, lower apnea-hypopnea index (AHI), obstructive apnea index (OAI) and oxygen desaturation index (ODI). CAI of the elderly group showed a trend higher than that of the non-elderly group with no statistical difference. However, the ratio of CAI to AHI in the elderly group was significantly higher (0.264 vs 0.154, P=0.003). True CSA was less prevalent than companion CSA in both groups. The results of multiple regression analysis indicated CAI was independently associated with age (β=0.256, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=0.005), OAI (β=−0.543, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;0.001), MAI (β=−0.267, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=0.005), ODI (β=0.538, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;0.001), heart failure (β=0.300, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;0.001).</citation_analysis></p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">CSA typically coexists with other types of sleep apnea. Elderly CSA patients have characteristics such as a lower BMI, and a milder decrease in blood oxygen saturation, along with higher prevalence of arrhythmia and coronary heart disease. Age may be a potential risk factor for CSA.</citation_analysis></p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>elderly people</kwd><kwd>sleep apnea</kwd><kwd>heart failure</kwd><kwd>oxygen desaturation index</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Tianjin Health Science and Technology Clinical Key Specialty Project (Grant No. TJWJ2024ZK003)</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by 1. National Clinical Key Specialty Construction Project, Tianjin Key Medical Discipline (Specialty) Project (Grant No. TJYXZDXK-049A), and 2. Tianjin Health Science and Technology Clinical Key Specialty Project (Grant No. TJWJ2024ZK003).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="3"/><ref-count count="35"/><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep apnea syndrome (SAS), characterized by recurrent episodes of apnea during sleep, is the second largest group of sleep disorders. Cessation of oral and nasal airflow but presence of chest and abdominal movements are the hallmarks of obstructive sleep apnea (OSA), the most common and well-studied type of sleep apnea. However, central sleep apnea (CSA), which results in the cessation of both oronasal airflow and thoracoabdominal movements, is much less common and not well understood.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1–4</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">CSA is not frequently diagnosed in the general population. Some specific types of CSA are secondary to CPAP treatment, high altitude residence, or intake of opioids, but otherwise, CSA is usually not easy to identify. Snoring, a prominent symptom in OSA, is absent in CSA sometimes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Daytime sleepiness and morning headaches caused by sleep fragmentation and intermittent hypoxia are common in both OSA and CSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Moreover, the related symptoms caused by CSA are often confused with the patients’ underlying conditions and are difficult to distinguish.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> CSA usually has a higher incidence in the population with heart failure, stroke, and neuromuscular disorders.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Evidence showed that incidence of CSA increases with age.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> The risk factors for the increased incidence of CSA in the elderly include weakened sleep stability, unstable respiratory regulation function, an increased proportion of cardiovascular disease, neurological disorders, and intakes of sedative hypnotic drugs.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Unlike OSA, which is treated mainly with surgery and non-invasive positive pressure ventilation, CSA treatment includes drug intervention, oxygen therapy, adaptive servo-ventilation (ASV), and diaphragmatic pacing.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13–15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Therefore, it is crucial to identify the characteristics of CSA in the elderly to ensure correct diagnosis and appropriate treatment. However, there have been few studies on CSA in the elderly. Therefore, this study aimed to compare the characteristics of elderly and non-elderly patients with CSA and investigate the potential risk factors of CSA.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Subjects and Study Design</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This retrospective study enrolled patients who were admitted to the Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine Department of Tianjin Chest Hospital, China, from January 2017 to March 2021 and had polysomnography (PSG) confirmed CSA. Patients’ medical records were collected through an electronic case system and medical insurance system. We divided patients into elderly (aged ≥ 65 years) and non-elderly (aged &lt; 65 years) groups. We excluded patients with a total PSG monitoring time &lt; 6 hours, prolonged sedative and sleeping pill use, or previous diagnosis of sleep apnea or non-invasive positive pressure ventilation.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We recorded sex, age, height, weight, neck circumference, waist circumference, and comorbidities. The body mass index (BMI) is the weight in kilograms divided by the square of the height in meters. Atrial arrhythmia was defined as persistent atrial fibrillation (AF) or atrial flutter. Heart failure was defined by a previous diagnosis via echocardiography, assay of the brain natriuretic peptide (BNP) level, or obvious symptoms.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>PSG Monitoring</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Overnight PSG, which yielded electroencephalography data (F4/M1, C4/M1, O2/M1, F3/M2, C3/M2, and O1/M2), included electrooculography, submental electromyography, bilateral anterior tibialis electromyography, and electrocardiography. Respiratory inductance plethysmography was used to monitor respiratory effort during thoracoabdominal movement. Airflow was assessed using oronasal thermal and pressure sensors. A finger pulse oximeter was used to record oxygen saturation.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep stages were identified based on the 2017 American Academy of Sleep Medicine criteria.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Apnea was defined as an airflow reduction &gt; 90% for ≥ 10s relative to the pre-event baseline, and hypopnea was defined as a reduction in airflow ≥ 30% for ≥ 10s relative to the pre-event baseline with ≥ 3% oxygen desaturation. OSA and CSA events were defined as apnea in the presence and absence of respiratory effort, respectively. Indexes of respiratory events were determined, including the central apnea index (CAI), obstructive apnea index (OAI), and mixed apnea index (MAI). A CAI/apnea-hypopnea index (AHI) ratio &gt; 50% is taken to indicate “true CSA”, while a CAI/AHI ratio ≤ 50% is defined as “companion CSA”. The oxygen desaturation index (ODI) was defined as the number of occasions on which the oxygen saturation decreased by 3%/h.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Quantitative data that conformed to a normal distribution were presented as mean ± standard deviation (SD), while non-normally distributed parameters were described as median (P25, P75). Qualitative data were described as </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> (%). Between-group comparisons were conducted using the Independent Samples </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-test, Mann–Whitney </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">U</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-test, or chi-square test depending on the data type and normality of the data distribution. Multiple linear regression analysis was performed to assess the underlying factors of CAI. CAI was set as the dependent variable, and non-collinearity factors of polysomnography parameters, demographic characteristics, and comorbidities were set as independent variables in the multiple regression model. For all analyses, a two-tailed </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> &lt; 0.05 was considered significant. All analyses were performed using SPSS software (ver. 25; IBM Corp, Armonk, NY, USA).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Demographic Characteristics and Comorbidities</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">123 out of 1249 patients were selected according to the inclusion and exclusion criteria and were divided into elderly (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 58) and non-elderly (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> = 65) groups (As shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). Both groups mainly comprised males, and there was no difference in gender distribution between the two groups. BMI and waist circumference were significantly lower in the elderly group (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.05), while the elderly group had significantly higher rates of coronary heart disease, arrhythmias, and diabetes than the non-elderly group (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Demographic Characteristics and Comorbidities of the Elderly and Non-Elderly Groups</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elderly<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 58</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-elderly<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 65</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T/χ<sup>2</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Demographic characteristics</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Age, mean±SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.26±7.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.25±7.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.220</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001***</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Males, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (79.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (87.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.582</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.209</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Anatomical characteristics (mean</bold>±<bold>SD)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.79±3.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.79±4.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.703</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Neck circumference (cm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.17±3.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.72±3.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.902</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.369</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Waist circumference (cm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.19±10.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108.23±12.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.428</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Comorbidities</bold>, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hypertension</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (56.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (44.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.849</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.174</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Coronary heart disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (51.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (20.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.566</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001***</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Arrhythmias</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (32.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (10.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.891</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Heart failure</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (5.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (6.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.550</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.815</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Diabetes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (21.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.609</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Cerebrovascular disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.278</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.131</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: *</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.05, **</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.01, ***</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.001 vs the non-elderly group.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: SD, standard deviation; BMI, body mass index (weight in kilograms divided by the square of the height in meters).</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Cohort selection protocol.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1749-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>PSG Parameters and CSA Phenotype</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">According to the definition of CSA in the Method-PSG monitoring section, companion CSA was more common than true CSA in both groups. The proportion of true CSA was higher in our elderly group, but there was no significant difference in the distribution of the different types of CSA between the two groups (χ</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 1.436, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.231) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">CSA often coexisted with other types of apnea (companion CSA). True CSA (CAI ≥ 5 and CAI/AHI ratio &gt; 50%) was less common than companion CSA in both groups. Although true CSA tended to be more common in the elderly group, the difference was not significant.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1749-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The AHI (44.55 [33.23, 58.15] vs 55.10 [42.60, 71.40], </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.002) and OAI (14.30 [7.70, 26.47] vs 24.40 [13.00,43.00], </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.004) of the elderly group were significantly lower than those of the non-elderly group. There was a trend toward a higher CAI in the elderly group (9.20 [6.90, 20.58] vs 8.70 [6.20, 17.00], </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &gt; 0.05). To further measure the weight of central apnea in all apnea events, we calculated the ratio of CAI, MAI, and OAI to AHI, respectively. The ratio of CAI to AHI in the elderly group was significantly higher than that in the non-elderly group (0.264 [0.159, 0.474] vs 0.154 [0.109, 0.326], </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.003). When discussing the desaturation during the period of sleep apnea, the ODI of the elderly group was lower than that of the non-elderly group (32.70 [19.30, 46.40] vs 45.30 [34.20, 60.20], </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.001), and the lowest pulse oxygen saturation (LowSpO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) was higher in the elderly group (78.00 [71.00, 83.00] vs 73.00 [64.00, 80.00], </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.027) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">PSG Parameters of the Elderly and Non-Elderly Groups</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters<sup>a</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elderly<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 58</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-elderly<break/><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 65</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI (times/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.55 [33.23, 58.15]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.10 [42.60, 71.40]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.086</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OAI (times/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.30 [7.70, 26.47]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.40 [13.00, 43.00]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.893</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAI (times/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.20 [6.90, 20.58]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.70 [6.20, 17.00]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.722</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.470</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAI (times/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.55 [0.90, 11.85]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.80 [1.60, 14.20]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.087</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.277</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OAI/AHI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0. 390 [0.169, 0.580]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.661 [0.461, 0.753]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.895</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.058</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAI/AHI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.264 [0.159, 0.474]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.154 [0.109, 0.326]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.954</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAI/AHI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.078 [0.025, 0.219]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.077 [0.032, 0.245]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.372</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.710</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MeanSpO<sub>2</sub> (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.00 [90.80, 94.00]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.00 [91.10, 94.20]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.077</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.939</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LowSpO<sub>2</sub> (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.00 [71.00, 83.00]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.00 [64.00, 80.00]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.205</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ODI (times/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.70 [19.30, 46.40]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.30 [34.20, 60.20]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.479</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001**</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>a</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Parameters were presented as median (P25, P75); *</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.05, **</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.01 vs the non-elderly group.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative">: AHI, apnea hypopnea index; OAI, obstructive apnea index; CAI, central apnea index; MAI, mixed apnea index; SpO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, pulse oxygen saturation; ODI, oxygen desaturation index.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Underlying Risk Factors for CSA</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">To evaluate the underlying factors related to CAI, we performed a multiple linear regression analysis. CAI was the dependent variable, and factors that may be related to CAI were included in the regression model as independent variables. AHI was excluded because CAI was a component of AHI. Neck and waist circumference were excluded because of their collinearity with BMI. The results indicated that age (β=0.256, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=0.005), OAI (β=−0.543, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;0.001), MAI (β=−0.267, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=0.005), ODI (β=0.538, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;0.001), heart failure (β=0.300, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;0.001) might be the underlying factors contribute to CAI (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Multiple Linear Regression Analysis for Central Apnea Index</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">β</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<sup>2</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value of the Mode</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.391</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Males</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.792</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.079</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.399</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OAI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.543</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.267</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ODI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.538</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.064</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.480</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coronary heart disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.133</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.131</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arrhythmias</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.989</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart failure</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.300</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.052</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.533</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cerebrovascular disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.876</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: **</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.01, ***</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.001.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0006"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative">: BMI, body mass index (weight in kilograms divided by the square of the height in meters); OAI, obstructive apnea index; MAI, mixed apnea index; ODI, oxygen desaturation index.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We conducted a retrospective study to investigate the characteristics of elderly CSA patients. The results indicated that CSA patients in the elderly group were more likely to comorbid with coronary heart disease, arrhythmia, and diabetes. Whether in the elderly or non-elderly group, CSA rarely existed independently but often coexisted with other types, ultimately leading to sleep apnea events. BMI, AHI, OAI, and ODI were lower, while the CAI to AHI ratio was higher in the elderly group than in the non-elderly group. The result of multiple regression analysis indicated age might be a potential risk factor for CAI.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In CSA, the cessation of oral and nasal airflow, as well as chest and abdominal breathing during sleep apnea, leads to hypoxemia, hypercapnia, and fragmented sleep, resulting in a series of pathological and physiological changes. CSA is subdivided into primary CSA, CSA with Cheyne Stokes breathing, CSA caused by disease without Cheyne Stokes breathing, and CSA caused by high-altitude periodic breathing, etc.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The pathogenesis varies among the different types of CSA, but they share a common pathological and physiological basis: periodic low or excessive ventilation leads to hypocapnia below the apnea threshold and a weaker central respiratory impulse, and high loop gain causes patients to experience periodic apnea.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Elderly people have impaired pharyngeal muscle tone, decreased local reflex activity in the pharyngeal cavity, more frequent brief awakenings, less stable sleep, and unstable respiratory regulation function. The proportion of elderly people taking oral psychotropic drugs,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> concomitant cardiovascular and cerebrovascular diseases has increased, in turn greatly increasing the incidence of CSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Night-time apnea in elderly individuals may not be apparent, and memory loss and cognitive function changes are also easily misdiagnosed as age-related degenerative changes. Clinical features often overlap with underlying disorders.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Therefore, understanding the characteristics of CSA in elderly patients is of great importance for early identification and management of the disease.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In this study, there were significantly more male CSA patients than females in both the elderly and non-elderly groups and the BMI was lower in the elderly group. Lucas et al reported that the overall prevalence of CSA in a community population was 0.9%, with incidence rates of CSA in men and men aged &gt; 65 years of 1.8% and 2.7%, respectively.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Similarly, Bixler et al reported that CSA was significantly more prevalent among males than females.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> A recent investigation showed obesity prevalence was 39.8% among US adults aged 20–39 years, 44.3% among adults aged 40–59 years, and 41.5% among adults aged 60 years and older.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> These data are consistent with our results, that is BMI is lower in the elderly group. Evidence shows that the prevalence of OSA increases in individuals with obesity,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> on the other hand, weight loss is associated with a significant improvement in the severity of OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The lower BMI may be part of the reasons for the lower OAI in the elderly group in our study.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Inflammation, oxidative stress, and hypoxia are reported as key mediators that link OSA with various comorbidities, such as obesity, cardiovascular disease, and diabetes. Chronic intermittent hypoxia, the hallmark of OSA, leads to endothelial dysfunction and the progression of atherosclerosis, then increases the risk of hypertension, stroke, and myocardial infarction.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27–29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> However, the association between these comorbidities and CSA is rarely reported in the literature. In our study, the proportions of elderly participants with coronary heart disease, and diabetes were significantly higher than those of the non-elderly participants. This result seems to contrast with the established associations between OSA and coronary heart disease, and diabetes. This inconsistency may reflect the important role of age in diabetes and coronary heart disease morbidity.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">It is widely believed that CSA is closely related to arrhythmia and heart failure.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30–34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> We speculate that the small sample size for heart failure cases may have limited our ability to detect statistically significant differences between the two groups. However, heart failure was independently associated with CAI when a multiple regression was conducted. Although the proportion of patients with arrhythmia was higher in the elderly group, unfortunately, our multiple analyses did not confirm the correlation between arrhythmia and CSA. Studies involving multiple centers and a large sample size are required to obtain higher-level evidence.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">CAI in the elderly group showed a trend higher than that in the non-elderly group with no statistical difference, however, the ratio of CAI to AHI was significantly higher in the elderly group. Besides, the result of multiple regression analysis supported that CAI was positively correlated with age. The above results indicated that elderly patients had a potentially higher risk of developing CSA. Whether in the elderly or non-elderly group, CSA rarely existed independently but coexisted with other types, ultimately leading to sleep apnea events, which was consistent with our previous results.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> True CSA seemed more common in our elderly group.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Compared to the non-elderly group, the elderly group had lower ODI and higher lowest SpO2, indicating a milder decrease in blood oxygen saturation in elderly patients during sleep apnea events. This may be related to the lower rate of OSA events in elderly patients. In clinical practice, we found that the severity of intermittent hypoxia was greater in OSA than in CSA. No relevant literature was found on the comparison of blood oxygen saturation between OSA and CSA. We speculate that, during CSA, the airway is not completely blocked, and air may enter the lungs through the still-open airway for gas exchange. When OSA occurs, the airway is blocked and no air enters the lungs.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">There were limitations in this study. This was a single-center retrospective study with a relatively small sample size, thus we could only investigate the differences between the elderly and non-elderly patients with CSA, but not draw a causal relationship. When determining the patients’ comorbidities, we could only rely on the medical records. Some information was not available. Due to strict selection criteria, the sample size was relatively small. This might limit the ability to detect statistically significant associations with certain indicators, such as heart failure. Nevertheless, as far as we knew, this was one of the only studies to explore the clinical characteristics of elderly CSA patients, and the results might improve the understanding and attention of CSA.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">In summary, CSA typically coexists with other types of sleep apnea. Elderly CSA patients has characteristics such as a milder decrease in blood oxygen saturation, combined with arrhythmia and coronary heart disease. Age may be a potential risk factor for CSA.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We are grateful for all the subjects who were included in the study and all the staff in the Sleep Center of Tianjin Chest Hospital.</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s0006">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The datasets generated during and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Ethical Statements</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This study was approved by the Ethics Committee of the Tianjin Chest Hospital (2024LW-030). All the scientific research processes and data were supervised by the hospital ethics committee.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0008">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis, and interpretation, or in all these areas; took part in drafting, revising or critically reviewing the article; gave final approval of the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0009">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors declare that no conflicting financial interests exist.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Eckert</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jordan</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Central sleep apnea: pathophysiology and treatment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>131</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>595</fpage>–<lpage>607</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.06.2287</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17296668</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Randerath</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baillieul</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tamisier</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Central sleep apnoea: not just one phenotype</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">European respira revi</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>171</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/16000617.0141-2023</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aini</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Banda</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence of sleep-related breathing disorders and associated risk factors among people with dementia: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>:<fpage>10351</fpage>–<lpage>10361</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2023.01.020</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Rana</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sankari</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <source>Central Sleep Apnea. StatPearls</source>. <publisher-loc>Treasure Island</publisher-loc>; <year>2022</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Randerath</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Central sleep apnea: the problem of diagnosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<fpage>34224</fpage>–<lpage>34225</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2016.12.015</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Atalla</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carlisle</surname>
<given-names>TW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simonds</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleepiness and activity in heart failure patients with reduced ejection fraction and central sleep-disordered breathing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>:<fpage>34217</fpage>–<lpage>34223</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2016.11.022</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baillieul</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dekkers</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep apnoea and ischaemic stroke: current knowledge and future directions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>78</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s1474-4422(21)00321-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34942140</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ratz</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wiitala</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Correlates and consequences of central sleep apnea in a national sample of US veterans</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>9</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsy058</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yujie</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fan</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Expert Consensus on Diagnosis and Evaluation of Elderly Sleep Apnea Syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chinese General Practice</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1283</fpage>–<lpage>1293</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bixler</surname>
<given-names>EO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vgontzas</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of age on sleep apnea in men: i</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Preval Severity Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <volume>157</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>144</fpage>–<lpage>148</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/ajrccm.157.1.9706079</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baillieul</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Revol</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Diagnosis and management of central sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Expert Rev Respir Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>545</fpage>–<lpage>557</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17476348.2019.1604226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31014146</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Orr</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malhotra</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pathogenesis of sleep disordered breathing in the setting of opioid use: a multiple mediation analysis using physiology</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsae090</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aurora</surname>
<given-names>RN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bista</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Updated Adaptive Servo-Ventilation Recommendations for the 2012 AASM Guideline: ”The Treatment of Central Sleep Apnea Syndromes in Adults: practice Parameters with an Evidence-Based Literature Review and Meta-Analyses”</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>757</fpage>–<lpage>761</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.5812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27092695</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aurora</surname>
<given-names>RN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chowdhuri</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The treatment of central sleep apnea syndromes in adults: practice parameters with an evidence-based literature review and meta-analyses</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.1580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22215916</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jacobowitz</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Afifi</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Penzel</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Endorsement of: ”treatment of adult obstructive sleep apnea with positive airway pressure: an American academy of Sleep Medicine Clinical Practice Guideline” by World Sleep Society</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>:<fpage>8919</fpage>–<lpage>8922</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2021.10.007</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Berry</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brooks</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gamaldo</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>AASM Scoring Manual Updates for 2017 (Version 2.4)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>665</fpage>–<lpage>666</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.6576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28416048</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>AAoS</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <source>American Academy of Sleep Medicine. International Classificationof Sleep Disorders.</source>
<publisher-loc>Darien, Illinois</publisher-loc>; <year>2023</year>:<fpage>ICSD–3</fpage>–<lpage>TR</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sankri-Tarbichi</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rowley</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Badr MS.Inhibition of ventilatory motor output increases expiratory retro palatal compliance during sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Respir Physiol Neurobiol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>176</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>136</fpage>–<lpage>143</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resp.2011.02.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21334465</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sankri-Tarbichi</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Richardson</surname>
<given-names>NN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chowdhuri</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name> et al. <article-title>Hypocapnia is associated with increased upper airway expiratory resistance during sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Respir Physiol Neurobiol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>177</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>108</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resp.2011.04.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21513820</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Javaheri</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Badr MS.Central Sleep Apnea: pathophysiologic Classification</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsac113</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fudim</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shahid</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Emani</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al.<article-title>Evaluation and Treatment of Central Sleep Apnea in Patients with Heart Failure</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Prob Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>101364</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cpcardiol.2022.101364</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Donovan</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Kapur VK.Prevalence and Characteristics of Central Compared to Obstructive Sleep Apnea: analyses from the Sleep Heart Health Study Cohort</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1353</fpage>–<lpage>1359</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.5962</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27166235</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bixler</surname>
<given-names>EO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vgontzas</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence of sleep-disordered breathing in women: effects of gender</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>163</volume>(<issue>3 Pt 1</issue>):<fpage>608</fpage>–<lpage>613</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/ajrccm.163.3.9911064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11254512</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>AJ</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carroll</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey 2017–March 2020 prepandemic data files development of files and prevalence estimates for selected health outcomes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Natl Health Stat Re</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Benjafield</surname>
<given-names>AV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ayas</surname>
<given-names>NT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eastwood</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name> et al. <article-title>Estimation of the global prevalence and burden of obstructive sleep apnoea: a literature-based analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Respir Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>687</fpage>–<lpage>698</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s2213-2600(19)30198-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31300334</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barnes</surname>
<given-names>HN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Joosten</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, et al.. <article-title>The effect of surgical weight loss on obstructive sleep apnoea: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Medicine Reviews</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<fpage>4285</fpage>–<lpage>4299</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2018.06.001</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kanclerska</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wieckiewicz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep architecture and vitamin D in hypertensives with obstructive sleep apnea: a polysomnographic study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Dental Med Prob</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>61</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17219/dmp/172243</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Karuga</surname>
<given-names>FF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jaromirska</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between glucose metabolism, the circadian cycle and hypoxia: evaluation of the NPAS2 and Rev-Erb-α protein serum levels in obstructive sleep apnea patients - a pilot study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Dental Med Prob</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>61</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>465</fpage>–<lpage>469</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17219/dmp/185718</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yi Li</surname>
<given-names>YL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Zhi Lyu.Association of Short Sleep Duration and Obstructive Sleep Apnea with Central Obesity: a Retrospective Study Utilizing Anthropometric Measures</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nature and Science of Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2024</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S483984</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Arzt</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oldenburg</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalence and predictors of sleep-disordered breathing in chronic heart failure: the SchlaHF-XT registry</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">ESC Heart Failure</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>4100</fpage>–<lpage>4111</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ehf2.14027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36052740</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Terziyski</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Draganova</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Central Sleep Apnea with Cheyne-Stokes Breathing in Heart Failure - From Research to Clinical Practice and Beyond</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Adv Exp Med Biol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<fpage>1067327</fpage>–<lpage>1067351</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/5584_2018_146</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Orr</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ayappa</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eckert</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Research Priorities for Patients with Heart Failure and Central Sleep Apnea. An Official American Thoracic Society Research Statement</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>203</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e11</fpage>–<lpage>e24</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.202101-0190ST</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33719931</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Grimm</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sass</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sibai</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> et al. <article-title>Severe central sleep apnea is associated with atrial fibrillation in patients with left ventricular systolic dysfunction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pacing Clin Electrophysiol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>706</fpage>–<lpage>712</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pace.12495</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25196395</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Harmon</surname>
<given-names>EK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stafford</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Atrial fibrillation is associated with central sleep apnea in clinic patients undergoing diagnostic polysomnography</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Arrhythm</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>991</fpage>–<lpage>996</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/joa3.12427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33335615</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Contribution of central sleep apnea to severe sleep apnea hypopnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-023-02776-6</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
