<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">NSS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31807104</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6842311</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">220436</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S220436</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>The Relationship Between Global Sleep Score And Inflammatory Markers In Obese Adults From The United States</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Huang et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Huang et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <given-names>Ying</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FT0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Jiang</surname>
            <given-names>Ying</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0002">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FT0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>Meilan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="AN0001"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0002">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="AFF0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Cardiovascular Medicine, The Second Affiliated Hospital of Nanchang University</institution>, <addr-line>Nanchang</addr-line>, <addr-line>Jiangxi</addr-line>
<addr-line>330006</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="AFF0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Rehabilitation, The Second Affiliated Hospital of Nanchang University</institution>, <addr-line>Nanchang</addr-line>, <addr-line>Jiangxi</addr-line>
<addr-line>330006</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="AN0001">Correspondence: Meilan Zhu <institution>Department of Rehabilitation, The Second Affiliated Hospital of Nanchang University</institution>, <addr-line>No. 1 Minde Road, Donghu District</addr-line>, <addr-line>Nanchang</addr-line>, <addr-line>Jiangxi</addr-line><addr-line>330006</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country> Email 15070896289@139.com</corresp>
        <fn id="FT0001">
          <label>*</label>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">These authors contributed equally to this work</citation_analysis></p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>05</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2019</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2019</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>11</volume>
      <fpage>317</fpage>
      <lpage>324</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2019</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>08</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2019</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2019 Huang et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Huang et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="S2001">
          <title>Background</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Poor sleep is a risk factor for cardiovascular diseases (CVDs). The underlying pathogenesis is not clear. Levels of inflammatory markers, such as C-reactive protein (CRP), interleukin-6 (IL-6) and tumor necrosis factor-ɑ (TNF-ɑ), have been found to be elevated in patients with CVDs.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="S2002">
          <title>Aim</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The study aimed to investigate the associations between sleep quality and serum inflammatory markers in a cohort of obese adults.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="S2003">
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This was a second analysis of the data from the Midlife in the United States (MIDUS) study, a longitudinal study of a national (US) sample of adults. A total of 1255 participants completed comprehensive biological assessments. The associations between global sleep score and serum levels of inflammatory markers were analyzed.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="S2004">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Univariate analysis showed that a higher global sleep score was correlated with lower age (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = −0.079, P= 0.009), higher BMI (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.100, P= 0.001) and heavier perceived stress (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.335, P&lt;0.001). Multivariate linear regression analysis showed that the global sleep score was positively related to levels of IL-6 (Sβ=0.074, P=0.009), IL-8 (Sβ=0.089, P=0.002), TNF-ɑ (Sβ=0.0.082, P=0.005), E-selectin (Sβ=0.071, P=0.016) and intercellular adhesion molecule-1 (ICAM-1, Sβ=0.117, P&lt;0.001) after adjustments were made for age, gender, race, marital status, education, current smoking status, physician-diagnosed CVDs and respiratory diseases, BMI and perceived stress. However, the global sleep score was not associated with serum IL-10 (Sβ=−0.021, P=0.463) and CRP (Sβ=0.035, P=0.059) levels after adjustments were made for these confounding factors.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="S2005">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Poor sleep is positively associated with serum inflammatory marker levels among obese adults. Sufficient sleep may be particularly important for obese adults to prevent CVDs.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>global sleep score</kwd>
        <kwd>inflammation</kwd>
        <kwd>body mass index</kwd>
        <kwd>perceived stress</kwd>
        <kwd>obese adults</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="3"/>
        <table-count count="3"/>
        <ref-count count="49"/>
        <page-count count="8"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="S0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Concern for sleep problems as risk factors for adverse health has grown since an association between poor sleep and mortality was ﬁrst described over four decades ago.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Studies have generally shown a significantly positive relationship between poor sleep and mortality. In other words, people with poor sleep have a greater mortality risk than those with higher sleep quality. Many publications have begun reporting that poor sleep can predict a growing number of diseases.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In recent years, however, due to increasingly social and economic factors, shorter sleep time, poor sleep quality and other sleep problems have become increasingly serious.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">–</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Poor sleep is related to poor decision making, risk taking and mood disruptions.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">–</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The direct effect of poor sleep is tiredness during low-stimulation activities, including attentiveness while studying, driving, performing repetitive activities and engaging in other activities.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Many investigations have shown that sleep in the classroom has become a very common phenomenon in many high schools.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> A previous study showed that poor-quality sleep and insufficient sleep are pervasive in the general population and are linked with impairments in cognitive control and greater risk taking.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Moreover, some other studies suggested that another important effect of sleep deprivation is related to mood. Relationships have been found between poor sleep and depression or mood lability.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Although the negative effects of sleep problems on psychosocial and behavioral problems are well understood, less is known about the relationship between sleep and biomarkers of physical health in the general population. It is well known that inflammation has attracted increasing attention and is considered a biomarker of risk for several chronic adult health conditions, such as cardiovascular diseases (CVDs), that may be associated with sleep problems.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">–</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Research has suggested that chronic sleep problems lead to increased inflammation levels, such as C-reactive protein (CRP), among adults.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">–</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Some studies have also shown that disrupted sleep has negative effects on the production and activation of cells involved in immune regulation, causing an alteration of inflammatory factors.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Therefore, the aim of this study was to assess the relationships between global sleep score and systemic inflammatory factors in a comprehensive and multi-level manner.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S0002">
      <title>Materials And Methods</title>
      <sec id="S0002-S2001">
        <title>Study Population</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This was a reanalysis of the data from the Midlife in the United States (MIDUS) study, a longitudinal study of a national (US) sample of adults aged 34–84 years at baseline. The MIDUS study investigates the association between psychological, behavioral, and social factors and age-related physical and mental health problems. As a sub-component of the MIDUS study, 1255 participants completed the Biomarkers Project, in which participants provided comprehensive biological assessments as a way to integrate behavioral and psychosocial factors with biology.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The measures described below were included to best capture our contents of interest.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Full details of the MIDUS study biomarker protocol are available elsewhere.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Complete data and specific codebooks are also available at </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.midus.wisc.edu/">http://www.midus.wisc.edu/</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. In summary, participants in the MIDUS study were originally recruited in 1995–1996 by means of a national sample collected by random-digit dialing procedures. To be as inclusive as possible, all living participants in the first MIDUS survey who could safely go to the clinic were considered eligible for participation in the Biomarkers Project. They were recruited to participate using e-mail and follow-up phone calls. Data were collected between 2004 and 2009 at one of three affiliated General Clinical Research Centers of the MIDUS study (University of Wisconsin-Madison; Georgetown University; University of California-Los Angeles). By using a standardized protocol that was consistent across the three sites, participants completed detailed self-administered questionnaires, medical history interviews, and the collection of blood specimens during a 2-day visit. Each participant was remunerated $200 for participating, and traveling expenses were covered. The Biomarkers Project protocol was approved by the institutional review boards of each General Clinical Research Center, and all participants gave written informed consent.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Serum samples from all participants were collected and tested during a 2-day visit between 2004 and 2009. The following serum inflammatory markers were measured: CRP, interleukin-6 (IL-6), IL-8, IL-10, E-selectin, intracellular adhesion molecule-1 (ICAM-1), and tumor necrosis factor-ɑ (TNF-ɑ). These serum biomarkers were collected during a medical exam at one of three General Clinical Research Centers. Biomarkers were obtained from a fasting blood draw. Full measurement methods have been described in detail elsewhere.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In this study, body mass index (BMI) ≥ 25 was defined as overweight or obesity. For our purposes, all included participants were overweight or obese adults.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0002-S2002">
        <title>Global Sleep Score</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The global sleep score was measured with the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The PSQI is widely used and a reliable measure of global sleep quality and sleep disturbances over the past month. The 19 items are divided into seven component scores that reflect the frequency of sleep problems in the following areas: subjective sleep quality, sleep latency, sleep duration, habitual sleep efficiency, sleep disturbance, use of sleep medication, and daytime dysfunction. A global sleep score ranging from 0 to 21 can be obtained by summing the seven components after weighting them on a scale ranging from 0 to 3 [ɑ=0.74]. For each component as well as the global score, higher scores show worse sleep quality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0002-S2003">
        <title>Perceived Psychological Stress</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The Perceived Stress Scale (PSS) is a 10-item measure that can assess the degree of pressure on participants in their lives.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Each item (e.g., “In the past month, how often have you been upset because of something that happened unexpectedly?”) used a 5-point scale ranging from 1 (never) to 5 (very often), and items were reverse-coded as needed so that higher scores show greater perceived stress [ɑ=0.84].</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0002-S2004">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The normality of the data was analyzed by the Kolmogorov–Smirnov test combined with Q-Q plots. The data that were not normally distributed were expressed as the median (interquartile range [IQR]), and data with normal distributions were expressed as the mean ± standard deviation (M±SD). First, the correlations between global sleep score and age, BMI and perceived stress were computed with Spearman correlation analysis in this study. Then, all variables with non-normal distributions were standardized with z-scores and analyzed with Pearson’s correlation coefficient. The associations between global sleep score and serum inflammatory markers were further assessed by multivariate linear regression analysis. All of the analyses were performed using R3.4.4 and SPSS. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> ≤ 0.05 was considered to be statistically significant.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="S0003-S2001">
        <title>The Characteristics Of The Study Subjects</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Due to the lack of complete serum test data for 148 participants during the follow-up period, data for the remaining 1107 participants were included in the study and further analyzed.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="T0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> presents the N (%), M±SD and median (IQR) for the variables. The sociodemographic characteristics were as follows: 474 participants (42.8%) were males, 1018 participants (92.0%) were white, 702 participants (63.4%) were married, 443 participants (40.0%) had bachelor’s degrees or higher, and 163 participants (14.6%) were current smokers. The median age of the entire population in this study was 54 years. A higher global sleep score was correlated with younger age (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = −0.079, P= 0.009, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">), higher BMI (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.100, P= 0.001, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) and heavier perceived stress (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.335, P&lt;0.001, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap id="T0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Participant Characteristics</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (%) or M(IQR) or M ±SD</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sociodemographic characteristics</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (45–63)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender (% male)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">474 (42.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race (% white)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1018 (92.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marital status (married), n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">702 (63.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education (with bachelor’s degree or higher), n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">443 (40.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current smoker, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">163(14.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.59 (26.13–33.05)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perceived stress scale</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (18–26)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Global Sleep Score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.21±3.67</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subjective Sleep Quality</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00±0.69</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Latency</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95±0.94</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Duration</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84±0.80</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitual Sleep Efficiency</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69±1.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Disturbances Range</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32±0.58</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleeping Medication</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58±1.08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daytime Dysfunction</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83±0.67</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physician diagnosed cardiovascular diseases</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Heart diseasen, (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">`126 (11.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> TIA or stroke, (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (3.9%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Diabetes, (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">132 (11.9%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> High blood pressure, (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">402 (36.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physician diagnosed respiratory diseases</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Asthma, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">127 (11.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Emphysema/COPD, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (2.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum inflammatory biomarkers</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> IL-6 (pg/mL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80 (0.56–1.22)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> IL-8 (pg/mL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.40 (9.13–15.79)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> IL-10 (pg/mL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22 (0.17–0.32)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> CRP (ug/mL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43 (0.69–3.66)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> TNF-ɑ (pg/mL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.05 (1.69–2.51)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> E-Selectin (ng/mL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.11 (28.09–51.85)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ICAM-1 (ng/mL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">273.92 (221.03–336.05)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> M (IQR) for nonnormally distributed data, M ±SD for normally distributed data and n (%) for categoric variables.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> BMI, body mass index; COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; IL, Interleukin; CRP, C-reactive protein, TNF-ɑ, tumor necrosis factor-ɑ; ICAM-1, intercellular adhesion molecule-1; M (IQR), median interquartile range; M ±SD, mean±standard deviation.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig id="F0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The relationship between global sleep score and age in all subjects.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-11-317-g0001"/></fig></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig id="F0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The relationship between global sleep score and BMI in all subjects.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-11-317-g0002"/></fig></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig id="F0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The relationship between global sleep score and perceived stress in all subjects.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-11-317-g0003"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0003-S2002">
        <title>Relationships Between Sleep And Inflammation Markers By Univariate Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">As shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="T0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">, higher global sleep scores were associated with higher serum levels of all inflammation markers in this study except IL-10 (all P&lt;0.05). Worse subjective sleep quality was related to higher levels of TNF-ɑ, E-selectin and ICAM-1 (all P&lt;0.05). Longer sleep latency showed a positive association with IL-6, CRP and ICAM-1 levels (all P&lt;0.05), and shorter sleep duration was associated with higher levels of CRP, E-selectin and ICAM-1 (all P&lt;0.05). Worse habitual sleep efficiency was positively related to levels of IL-6, IL-8, CRP, E-selectin and ICAM-1 (all P&lt;0.05). Those with a greater range of sleep disturbances had higher IL-8, TNF-ɑ, CRP and ICAM-1 levels (all P&lt;0.05). The frequency of sleeping medication use was positively associated with IL-6, IL8 and ICAM-1 (all P&lt;0.05), and the frequency of daytime dysfunction did not show a positive relationship with inflammation markers (all P&gt;0.05). These results showed that worse sleep quality was associated with higher serum inflammation levels by Pearson correlation analysis. However, the 7 factors were not associated with serum IL-10 levels.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap id="T0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Bivariate Correlations Using Standardized Variables</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1. Global Sleep Score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2. Subjective Sleep Quality</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70 <sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3. Sleep Latency</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70 <sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4. Sleep Duration</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64 <sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5. Habitual Sleep Efficiency</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 <sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6. Sleep Disturbances Range</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 <sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7. Sleeping Medication</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56 <sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8. Daytime Dysfunction</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 <sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9. IL-6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10<sup>&amp;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08<sup>&amp;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09<sup>&amp;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08<sup>&amp;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10. IL-8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09<sup>&amp;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11. IL-10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12. TNF-ɑ</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08<sup>&amp;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13. CRP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12 <sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09<sup>&amp;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08<sup>&amp;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08<sup>&amp;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14. E-Selectin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11 <sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08<sup>&amp;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09<sup>&amp;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08<sup>&amp;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15<sup>&amp;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15. ICAM-1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09<sup>&amp;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07<sup>&amp;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08<sup>&amp;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08<sup>&amp;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29<sup>&amp;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15<sup>&amp;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07*</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>*P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;0.05, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>&amp;</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;0.01, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>#</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;0.001. Pearson correlation analysis was used.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> IL, Interleukin; CRP, C-reactive protein, TNF-ɑ, tumor necrosis factor-ɑ; ICAM-1, intercellular adhesion molecule-1.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0003-S2003">
        <title>Associations Between Global Sleep Score and Inflammatory Markers After Adjusting For Confounding Factors</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">To further prove the correlation between sleep quality and serum inflammatory biomarkers, multiple linear regression analysis was performed. As shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="T0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">, the global sleep score was positively related to IL-6 (Sβ=0.095, P=0.001), IL-8 (Sβ=0.097, P=0.001), CRP (Sβ=0.106, P&lt;0.001), TNF-ɑ (Sβ=0.102, P=0.001), E-selectin (Sβ=0.114, P&lt;0.001) and ICAM-1 (Sβ=0.140, P&lt;0.001) after adjusting for age, gender, race, marital status, education, current smoking status and physician-diagnosed CVDs and respiratory diseases (Model 1). After other confounding factors were added, including BMI and perceived stress in addition to CRP, the global sleep score still had a strong relationship with these inflammatory biomarkers (all P&lt;0.05, Model 3). However, consistent with univariate analysis, the global sleep score was not associated with serum levels of IL-10 after adjustments were made for these confounding factors in multivariate analysis (all P&gt;0.05, Model 3).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap id="T0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Multivariate Linear Regression Analysis Of Association Between Global Sleep Scores And Inflammatory Markers</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<sup>2</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sβ</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Model 1</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> IL-6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.095</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037–0.153</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> IL-8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.097</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039–0.156</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> IL-10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.078–0.039</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.517</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> CRP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.106</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.048–0.165</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> TNF-ɑ</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.102</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042–0.162</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> E-Selectin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.114</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.056–0.173</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ICAM-1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.036</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.140</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.082–0.199</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Model 2</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> IL-6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.036</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.088</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030–0.146</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> IL-8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.103</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.044–0.161</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> IL-10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.572–0.042</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.573</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> CRP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.083</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021–0.145</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> TNF-ɑ</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.090</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030–0.150</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> E-Selectin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.098</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038–0.158</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ICAM-1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.086</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028–0.144</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Model 3</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> IL-6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.074</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019–0.129</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> IL-8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.127</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.089</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033–0.144</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> IL-10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.120</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.076–0.035</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.463</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> CRP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.121</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.025–0.094</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.059</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> TNF-ɑ</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.126</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.082</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025–0.139</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> E-Selectin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.071</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014–0.128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ICAM-1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.133</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.117</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061–0.172</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Model 1: adjusted for age, gender, race, marital status, education, current smoker and physician diagnosed CVD and respiratory diseases. Model 2: adjusted for age, gender, race, marital status, education, current smoker, physician diagnosed CVD and respiratory diseases and BMI. Model 3: adjusted for age, gender, race, marital status, education, current smoker, physician diagnosed cardiovascular diseases and respiratory diseases, BMI and perceived stress. Multivariate linear regression analysis was used.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> IL, Interleukin; CRP, C-reactive protein, TNF-ɑ, tumor necrosis factor-ɑ; ICAM-1, intercellular adhesion molecule-1; CVD, cardiovascular diseases; BMI, body mass index.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This study with obese adults aimed to investigate the associations between sleep quality and key biomarkers of inflammation that predict chronic health problems, such as CVDs, in adulthood. In addition to daytime dysfunction, the other 6 indicators from the PSQI were strongly associated with inflammatory factors by univariate analysis. Higher global sleep scores were significantly linked to higher levels of inflammatory factors after adjustments were made for other confounding factors in multivariate analysis.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Sleep-related research has been ongoing for more than 40 years. Poor sleep is a risk factor for CVDs.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">–</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> A large number of studies have shown that poor sleep and sleep-related diseases play an important role in the morbidity and mortality of adults, but these studies cannot prove this association.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">–</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Few studies have tried to establish a model of long-term partial sleep deprivation that can best reflect the daily decline in sleep quality. These studies did not include a comprehensive sleep score, had insufficient inflammatory indicators, had insufficient correction for confounding factors, had flawed research designs and had unrepresentative research populations.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">–</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Thus, to achieve this goal, well-designed prospective studies with assessments of all aspects of sleep, inflammation, many confounding factors of sleep and associated risks are necessary. Our research has met these conditions. The results of our study contribute to the literature in three different ways. On the one hand, the data of this study were from the MIDUS study, a longitudinal investigation of a national (US) sample of adults. Multiple aspects of sleep quality were assessed, thus expanding upon existing research on the association between adult sleep and inflammation.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">–</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> On the other hand, our results via multivariate analysis first proved that sleep quality, as evaluated with the global sleep score, was significantly and independently associated with levels of inflammatory factors, including IL-6, IL-8, TNF-ɑ, E-selectin and ICAM-1. These serum inflammatory markers have been proven to play an important role in the occurrence and development of CVDs among middle-aged and elderly adults.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">–</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Additionally, this study was the first to explore the relationships between sleep quality and inflammatory factors in an obese population with a high risk of many diseases, such as type 2 diabetes mellitus and CVDs.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Interestingly, none of the PSQI sleep variables were associated with IL-10 in the univariate and multivariate analyses in this study. A possible explanation is that IL-10 is an anti-inflammatory factor, and the decline in sleep quality is more likely to be related to a pro-inflammatory effect instead of anti-inflammation.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Our results are consistent with previous experimental evidence that poor sleep leads immune cells to produce higher levels of pro-inflammatory factors when stimulated in vitro. For instance, a study showed that sleep restriction with one night of 3.5 h of sleep was related to a significant increase in monocyte-derived production of TNF-ɑ and IL-1β.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Similarly, poor sleep has been linked with the upregulation of TNF-a and IL-6 mRNA expression</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and promoted the activation of nuclear factor (NF)-kB, which is a transcription factor that plays an important role in promoting the expression of pro-inflammatory genes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Our findings generalize prior laboratory findings to show that the decline in sleep quality is associated with inflammatory competence, suggesting a possible mechanism relating poor sleep to susceptibility to inflammatory diseases, such as CVDs.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> CVDs remain the main cause of death in many developed and developing countries. Research from the past decades has shown that inflammation plays a key role in the progression of CVDs.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The atherosclerotic plaque in the vasculature is known as a complex inflammatory reaction of the vascular wall with inflammatory stimulation from the circulating blood. Therefore, pro-inflammatory cytokines may provide a pathway linking poor sleep to an increased risk of inflammatory diseases, such as CVDs. In summar, previous studies and our findings may explain this association with the consistent results of the activation of immune cells and the elevation of serum inflammatory levels in populations with poor sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In addition, some of our findings diverge from those of previous studies, which showed that elevated CRP levels tended to be more consistently associated with worse sleep quality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">–</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> These inconsistent findings can be at least partly explained by the different study designs used and study populations selected, the hypotheses being investigated, the inherent challenges of obtaining epidemiologic measurements of intricate and the different methods of analyzing data. In our findings, the global sleep score was associated with CRP levels after adjustments were made for age, gender, race, marital status, education, current smoking status, BMI, and physician-diagnosed CVDs and respiratory diseases, but after perceived stress was then added into Model 2, the global sleep score was no longer related to CRP levels. The difference is that in previous studies, adjustments were not made for perceived stress.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">–</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Perceived stress may reduce the correlation between poor sleep and CRP levels.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Continued research would need to elucidate the reason. In summary, our results showed a significant negative correlation between sleep quality and serum levels of proinflammatory factors in the obese population.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S0005">
      <title>Limitations</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Finally, there are some limitations in our findings. To participate in this study, all participants needed to be healthy enough to go to a MIDUS study research center, thus leading to the potential for bias. Additionally, the PSQI is used for assessing participants’ self-reported subjective sleep quality. A more objective tool is necessary to assess the association between sleep quality and inflammatory biomarkers.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S0006">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Poor sleep is positively associated with serum pro-inflammatory marker levels among obese adults. Pro-inflammatory cytokines may provide a pathway linking poor sleep to an increased risk of inflammatory diseases. Sufficient sleep may be particularly important for obese adults to prevent chronic health problems, such as CVDs.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgment</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Thank you for Ying Jiang’s help with the data processing and analysis.</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="S0007" sec-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CIT0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hammond</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>SOME PRELIMINARY FINDINGS ON PHYSICAL COMPLAINTS FROM A PROSPECTIVE STUDY OF 1,064,004 MEN AND WOMEN</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Public Health Nations Health</italic></source>. <year>1964</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.54.1.11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14117648</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gangwisch</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heymsfield</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bodenalbala</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Short sleep duration as a risk factor for hypertension analyses of the first National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>833</fpage>–<lpage>839</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.HYP.0000217362.34748.e0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16585410</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malhotra</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>White</surname>
<given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association between reduced sleep and weight gain in women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>164</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>947</fpage>–<lpage>954</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwj280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16914506</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Social and demographic factors related to sleep duration</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1077</fpage>–<lpage>1078</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/30.9.1077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17910376</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ling</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Associations of weekday-to-weekend sleep differences with academic performance and health-related outcomes in school-age children and youths</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2019.04.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31060028</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Drapeau</surname>
<given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nadorff</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCall</surname>
<given-names>WV</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Screening for suicide risk in adult sleep patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2019.03.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31060027</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wolfson</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carskadon</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Early school times affect sleep and daytime functioning in adolescents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>117</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Telzer</surname>
<given-names>EH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fuligni</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lieberman</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The effects of poor quality sleep on brain function and risk taking in adolescence</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">NeuroImage</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>Complete</issue>):<fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>283</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2013.01.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23376698</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Riemann</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berger</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Voderholzer</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and depression - results from psychobiological studies: an overview</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biol Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>1–3</issue>):<fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0301-0511(01)00090-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11454435</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bonnet</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effect of sleep disruption on sleep, performance, and mood</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1985</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>11</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/8.1.11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3992104</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ross</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Atherosclerosis–an inflammatory disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>340</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM199901143400207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9887164</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Libby</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Inflammation in atherosclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nature</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>420</volume>(<issue>6917</issue>):<fpage>868</fpage>–<lpage>874</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature01323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12490960</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cappuccio</surname>
<given-names>FP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cooper</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>D’Elia</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration predicts cardiovascular outcomes: a systematic review and meta-analysis of prospective studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Heart J</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1484</fpage>–<lpage>1492</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehr007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21300732</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ayas</surname>
<given-names>NT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>White</surname>
<given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Manson</surname>
<given-names>JAE</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A prospective study of sleep duration and coronary heart disease in women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>163</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>209</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.163.2.205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12546611</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hall</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Muldoon</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jennings</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Self-reported sleep duration is associated with the metabolic syndrome in midlife adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>635</fpage>–<lpage>643</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/31.5.635</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18517034</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lagrand</surname>
<given-names>WK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Visser</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hermens</surname>
<given-names>WT</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>C-reactive protein as a cardiovascular risk factor: more than an epiphenomenon?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Circulation</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>100</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>96</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.CIR.100.1.96</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10393687</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ridker</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Comparison of C-reactive protein and low-density lipoprotein cholesterol levels in the prediction of first cardiovascular events</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>347</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>1557</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa021993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12432042</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Danesh</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Low grade inflammation and coronary heart disease: prospective study and updated meta-analyses</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>321</volume>(<issue>7255</issue>):<fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>204</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.321.7255.199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10903648</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Irwin</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Why sleep is important for health: a psychoneuroimmunology perspective</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Annu Rev Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>172</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-psych-010213-115205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25061767</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Irwin</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ribeiro</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep loss activates cellular inflammatory signaling</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biol Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>538</fpage>–<lpage>540</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2008.05.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18561896</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dienberg Love</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seeman</surname>
<given-names>TE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weinstein</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Bioindicators in the MIDUS National Study: protocol, measures, sample, and comparative context</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Aging Health</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1059</fpage>–<lpage>1080</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0898264310374355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20876364</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gruenewald</surname>
<given-names>TL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Karlamangla</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>History of socioeconomic disadvantage and allostatic load in later life</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Soc Sci Med</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>74</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2011.09.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22115943</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Iii</surname>
<given-names>CFR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monk</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The Pittsburgh sleep quality index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0165-1781(89)90047-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2748771</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A global measure of perceived stress</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Health Soc Behav</italic></source>. <year>1983</year>;<volume>24</volume>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2136404</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gangwisch</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malaspina</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Posner</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia and sleep duration as mediators of the relationship between depression and hypertension incidence</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Hypertens</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>62</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ajh.2009.202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19893498</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Newman</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spiekerman</surname>
<given-names>CF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Enright</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Daytime sleepiness predicts mortality and cardiovascular disease in older adults. The Cardiovascular Health Study Research Group</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Geriatr Soc</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1532-5415.2000.tb03901.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10682939</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Overtime work, insufficient sleep, and risk of non-fatal acute myocardial infarction in Japanese men</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Occup Environ Med</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>447</fpage>–<lpage>451</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/oem.59.7.447</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12107292</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Davey Smith</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hart</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heslop</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration and mortality: the effect of short or long sleep duration on cardiovascular and all-cause mortality in working men and women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>305</fpage>–<lpage>314</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1389-9457(02)00016-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14592192</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Meisinger</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heier</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>L?Wel</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration and sleep complaints and risk of myocardial infarction in middle-aged men and women from the general population: the MONICA/KORA Augsburg cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1121</fpage>–<lpage>1127</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/30.9.1121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17910384</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shankar</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koh</surname>
<given-names>WP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yuan</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration and coronary heart disease mortality among Chinese adults in Singapore: a population-based cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>168</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1367</fpage>–<lpage>1373</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwn281</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18952563</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Grandner</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hale</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moore</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Mortality associated with short sleep duration: the evidence, the possible mechanisms, and the future</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>0</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2009.07.006</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gallicchio</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kalesan</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep duration and mortality: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>148</fpage>–<lpage>158</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.2009.18.issue-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19645960</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cappuccio</surname>
<given-names>FP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>D’Elia</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Strazzullo</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration and all-cause mortality: a systematic review and meta-analysis of prospective studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>585</fpage>–<lpage>592</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/33.5.585</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20469800</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rd</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Serody</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Okun</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Protecting sleep, promoting health in later life: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychosom Med</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>178</fpage>–<lpage>186</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM199704033361401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19995884</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cizza</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marincola</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mattingly</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Treatment of obesity with extension of sleep duration: a randomized, prospective, controlled trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Trials</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>274</fpage>–<lpage>285</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1740774510368298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20423926</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fang</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hui</surname>
<given-names>RT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Is hypertension an inflammatory disease?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Med Hypotheses</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>236</fpage>–<lpage>240</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mehy.2004.06.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15607546</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Coles</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fielding</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rose-John</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Classic interleukin-6 receptor signaling and interleukin-6 trans-signaling differentially control angiotensin ii-dependent hypertension, cardiac signal transducer and activator of transcription-3 activation, and vascular hypertrophy in vivo</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Pathol</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>171</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>0</fpage>–<lpage>325</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2353/ajpath.2007.061078</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>FB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meigs</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>TY</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Inflammatory markers and risk of developing type 2 diabetes in women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>693</fpage>–<lpage>700</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/diabetes.53.3.693</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14988254</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ridker</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cushman</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stampfer</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Inflammation, aspirin, and the risk of cardiovascular disease in apparently healthy men</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>336</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>973</fpage>–<lpage>979</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM199704033361401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9077376</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jonk</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Houben</surname>
<given-names>AJHM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jongh</surname>
<given-names>RTD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Microvascular dysfunction in obesity: a potential mechanism in the pathogenesis of obesity-associated insulin resistance and hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiology</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>252</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physiol.00012.2007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17699878</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Prather</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marsland</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hall</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Normative variation in self-reported sleep quality and sleep debt is associated with stimulated pro-inflammatory cytokine production</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biol Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>82</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>0</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsycho.2009.04.008</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Uthgenannt</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schoolmann</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pietrowsky</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of sleep on the production of cytokines in humans</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychosom Med</italic></source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00006842-199503000-00001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7792381</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Irwin</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep deprivation and activation of morning levels of cellular and genomic markers of inflammation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>166</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>1756</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.166.16.1756</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16983055</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Esquifino</surname>
<given-names>AI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cardinali</surname>
<given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and the immune system</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Immunol Rev</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Larkin</surname>
<given-names>EK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Variation of C-reactive protein levels in adolescents: association with sleep-disordered breathing and sleep duration</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circulation</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>111</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>1978</fpage>–<lpage>1984</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.CIR.0000161819.76138.5E</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15837952</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Meier-Ewert</surname>
<given-names>HK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ridker</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rifai</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Absence of diurnal variation of C-reactive protein concentrations in healthy human subjects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Chem</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>426</fpage>–<lpage>430</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11238292</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Glynn</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macfadyen</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ridker</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Tracking of high-sensitivity C-reactive protein after an initially elevated concentration: the JUPITER Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Chem</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>305</fpage>–<lpage>312</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1373/clinchem.2008.120642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19095726</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liao</surname>
<given-names>JK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Genetically elevated C-reactive protein and ischemic vascular disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>245</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lavretsky</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Newhouse</surname>
<given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Stress, inflammation, and aging</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Geriatr Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>729</fpage>–<lpage>733</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JGP.0b013e31826573cf</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22874577</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
