<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33324127</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7733439</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">275698</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S275698</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Atypical Sleep and Postoperative Delirium in the Cardiothoracic Surgical Intensive Care Unit: A Pilot Prospective Study</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Chen et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Chen et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Qiong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Peng</surname>
            <given-names>Yanchun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>Yanjuan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0003">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Sailan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <given-names>Xizhen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Liang-Wan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0002"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label>Department of Nursing, <institution>Fujian Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Fuzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Fujian</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label>Department of Cardiac Surgery, <institution>Union Hospital, Fujian Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Fuzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Fujian</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label>Department of Nursing, <institution>Union Hospital, Fujian Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Fuzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Fujian</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Yanjuan Lin<institution>Department of Nursing, Union Hospital, Fujian Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>No. 29 Xinquan Road</addr-line>, <addr-line>Fuzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>350001</addr-line><addr-line>Fujian Province</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country><phone>Tel +86 59186218581</phone><fax>Fax +86 83344034</fax> Email fjxhyjl@163.com</corresp>
        <corresp id="an0002">Liang-Wan Chen<institution>Department of Cardiac Surgery, Union Hospital, Fujian Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Fuzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Fujian</addr-line><addr-line>350001</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country><phone>Tel +86 59186218581</phone><fax>Fax +86 59183301393</fax> Email chenliangwan@tom.com</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>08</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2020</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2020</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>12</volume>
      <fpage>1137</fpage>
      <lpage>1144</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>05</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2020</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2020</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2020 Chen et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2020</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Chen et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Postoperative delirium (POD) is a very common and serious neurological complication in patients admitted to the cardiothoracic surgical intensive care unit (CSICU). We aimed to identify a novel potential sleep-based marker for POD and investigate the relevance between atypical sleep and POD.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Patients and Methods</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This was a prospective, observational study of patients admitted to the CSICU between December 2019 and February 2020 at our center. Sleep characteristics from 21:00 on postoperative day 1 to 07:00 on postoperative day 2 were assessed using polysomnography (PSG). POD from the end of PSG monitoring until postoperative day 5 was evaluated using the Confusion Assessment Method for the Intensive Care Unit.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This analysis included 20 patients admitted to the CSICU. The incidence of atypical sleep was 45.0%. Compared to patients without delirium, those with delirium had less delta power, less percentage REM sleep, and a higher proportion of atypical sleep and REM sleep loss (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.05).</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The presence of atypical sleep and the absence of REM sleep were associated with POD in patients admitted to the CSICU.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>postoperative delirium</kwd>
        <kwd>intensive care unit</kwd>
        <kwd>atypical sleep</kwd>
        <kwd>cardiac surgery</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
            <institution-wrap>
              <institution>Innovation of Science and Technology, Fujian province</institution>
            </institution-wrap>
          </funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
            <institution-wrap>
              <institution>Guiding Project of Fujian Science and Technology</institution>
            </institution-wrap>
          </funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported by the Joint Finds for the Innovation of Science and Technology, Fujian province (Grant number: 2017Y9052) and the Guiding Project of Fujian Science and Technology (2017Y0038).</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="3"/>
        <table-count count="8"/>
        <ref-count count="39"/>
        <page-count count="8"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Postoperative delirium (POD), is a common acute disturbance of consciousness occurring postoperatively among 11.5–39.0% of the patients admitted to the cardiothoracic surgical intensive care unit (CSICU), it is associated with prolonged hospital stay, poor outcomes, and increased health costs and mortality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1–5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Hence, identifying risk factors for POD is important. Current research shows that POD after cardiac surgery results from a combination of several factors, including advanced age, pre-existing cognitive impairment, previous psychiatric conditions, cerebrovascular disease, mechanical ventilation time, atrial fibrillation, and so forth.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> However, sleep disturbances, common among CSICU patients, could be a potential risk factor for POD.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Most recent studies have only considered the association between delirium and normal sleep characteristics but not abnormal sleep characteristics. Normal sleep consists of 3 stages: WAKE, non-rapid eye movement (NREM) sleep (further divided into stages N1, N2, and N3), and rapid eye movement (REM) sleep. These can be identified using polysomnography (PSG).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, these typical sleep characteristics are often absent in patients admitted to the intensive care unit. Atypical sleep is an abnormal sleep subtype, characterized by loss of N2 stage markers (K-complexes and sleep spindles).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The incidence of atypical sleep has been reported to be 28–50%</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11–14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> among awake or lightly sedated patients and 60–85%</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> among deeply sedated patients.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Only limited data exist regarding the association between atypical sleep and delirium, and the causality remains unclear. Previous studies indicate that delirium occurs in 44% of patients with atypical sleep as compared to 18% of patients without atypical sleep; however, whether atypical sleep occurs before delirium onset remains unclear.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> According to a study assessing sleep among 14 patients with mechanical ventilation, typical sleep features were only recognized in 1 patient without delirium.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Another study reported no significant difference in the incidence of delirium during the PSG period between atypical and typical sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Although the cited studies were important, they did not definitively establish the association between atypical sleep and delirium primarily because these could not establish the sequence of delirium and atypical sleep. Hence, studies assessing the association between atypical sleep and delirium through a rigorous experimental design are lacking.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In this pilot study, we conducted PSG monitoring on the first postoperative night after cardiac surgery using cardiopulmonary bypass (CPB) and assessed delirium daily after PSG monitoring until postoperative day 5 to test the hypothesis that atypical sleep occurs before the onset of and is associated with delirium.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Design and Setting</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We conducted a pilot prospective study between December 2019 and February 2020 at the CSICU of our hospital. The study was approved by the Ethics Committee of our hospital and is registered at </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.chictr.org.cn">http://www.chictr.org.cn</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> (ChiCTR1900023094).</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We enrolled 23 patients aged ≥18 years and undergoing cardiac surgery using CPB. Patients with the following conditions were excluded: (1) history or current diagnosis of mental illness or neurological disorders; (2) alcoholism (defined using the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test Consumption score ≥4 in men and ≥3 in women);</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> (3) sleep disturbance (defined as a STOP-Bang score of ≥3);</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> (4) self-reported use of anticonvulsants, antidepressants, and neuroleptics 48 hours before the study; (5) contraindications for PSG, including infection, recent trauma, and head or neck surgery; (6) PSG monitoring time ≤7 h for various reasons (eg, wire loss or equipment failure); (7) delirium onset after the surgery till the end of monitoring; (8) inability to use the Confusion Assessment Method for the Intensive Care Unit (CAM-ICU) to confirm delirium or non-delirium (the Richmond Agitation-Sedation Scale [RASS ≤ −4]).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Sleep Assessment</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">A portable 52-channel sleep monitor (BMC Polypro, Beijing) was used for sleep monitoring. Electrode placement conformed to the “International 10–20” System.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Electrodes were placed by a trained technician and included the following: 6 electroencephalogram (EEG) channels (2 frontal channels: F3-M2, F4-M1; 2 central channels: C3-M2, C4-M1; and 2 occipital channels: O1-M2, O2-M1), 2 electrooculogram (E1, E2), and 2 electromyograms (EMG</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>＋</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-EMG</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>−</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). PSG was started at 21:00 on postoperative day 1 and was continuously performed until 07:00 on the next day (07:00, morning nursing; 21:00, end of visiting). All records, every 30-second epoch, were scored by a trained sleep technologist and reviewed by 2 sleep medicine physicians. The sleep technologist and sleep medicine physicians were blinded to patient group assignment during the study. If PSG observations conformed with the standard sleep stages, it was scored according to the 2007 American Academy of Sleep Medicine Manual for the Scoring of Sleep and Associated Events. If some epochs of PSG could not be scored using the standard criteria but were consistent with the description of atypical sleep,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> it was scored as atypical sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">For each EEG data set, we selected 100 minutes from a period with minimal care intervention (02:00–03:40); the spectral analysis of the delta (0.5–3.9 Hz), theta (4.0–7.9 Hz), alpha (8.0–13.0 Hz), and beta (13.1–30.0 Hz) bands was performed using fast Fourier transformation of each 4-s epoch. The spectral power estimates were averaged across 6 EEG channels (F3-M2, F4-M1, C3-M2, C4-M1, O1-M2, and O2-M1).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Delirium Assessment</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">POD was defined as delirium lasting from the end of PSG monitoring till postoperative day 5, ensuring that delirium occurred after sleep monitoring. Patients were screened for delirium from the end of PSG monitoring until postoperative day 5 by trained nurses using RASS and CAM-ICU.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> To ensure that the sleep data were recorded before delirium and to minimize the effect of the assessment process on patients’ sleep at night, patients were screened for delirium at 08:00, 14:00, and 20:00 every day. If patients presented any clinical evidence of delirium (such as agitation or illusion, as observed by the nurses) at other times (including entire sleep monitoring period), they were additionally screened by nurses using RASS and CAM-ICU.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Clinical Data Collection</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Patients’ sociodemographic characteristics, preoperative status, intraoperative variables, and relevant postoperative data were collected (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). As analgesia and sedation may promote delirium,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> we also collected analgesia and sedation use information pre- and post-operatively till the end of PSG. Analgesics used were morphine, fentanyl, and dezocine, and sedatives used were dexmedetomidine, midazolam, and chlorpromazine.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap id="t0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep Characteristics of CSICU Patients</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">All Patients (n=20)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total recording time (min), mean (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">506.42±55.11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total sleep time (min), mean (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">235.62±83.24</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep efficiency (%), mean (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.7±18.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage N1 sleep (%), mean (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0±7.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage N2 sleep (%), mean (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.3±20.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage N3 sleep (%), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0, 3.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM sleep (%), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0, 2.9)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> REM, rapid eye movement; SD, standard deviation; IQR, interquartile range.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Patients were divided into the delirium and non-delirium groups based on whether they developed POD. Continuous variables were presented as mean ± standard deviation (SD; normally distributed data) or medians and interquartile ranges (non-normally distributed data; 25–75% quartiles), and categorical variables were presented as numbers and percentages. The chi-square or Fisher exact test was used to compare qualitative data, as applicable, and the Student </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> or Mann–Whitney </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>U</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-test was used to compare quantitative data, as applicable. SPSS software (version 17.0) was used for data statistical analysis. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Of the 23 patients, 1 was excluded because of delirium onset before the end of PSG monitoring, 2 were excluded because of PSG monitoring lasting ≤7 h (caused by wire disconnection). Of the 20 CSICU patients, 9(45.0%) had atypical sleep (atypical stages 1–3) per the Watson classification.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The total atypical sleep duration was 4396 min. A representative EEG of a patient with atypical sleep is shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figures 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> shows the percentage distribution of the sleep stages. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> summarizes the sleep characteristics of all patients.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Electroencephalography tracing from an atypical sleep patient. F3, F4, C3, C4, O1, O2 indicate EEG lead locations.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-12-1137-g0001"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> EMG, electromyogram; LOC and ROC, left and right electrooculogram, respectively.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep stage distribution in CSICU patients.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-12-1137-g0002"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> NREM, non-rapid eye movement; REM, rapid eye movement.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> shows the distribution of POD. No significant differences existed between the groups in baseline characteristics including sociodemographic, preoperative, intraoperative, and postoperative variables (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). Patients with delirium had decreased delta power (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.010) and percentage REM sleep (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.011) and a higher incidence of atypical sleep (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.005) and REM sleep absence (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.028) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap id="t0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Baseline Characteristics in Non-Delirium Group vs. Delirium Group</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Delirium (n=12)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delirium (n=8)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t/z/x<sup>2</sup></italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Sociodemographic characteristics</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Age (y), mean (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.25±15.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.38±12.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.598</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.557<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (50.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (62.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.670<sup>ξ</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>), mean (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.90±4.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.52±7.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.855</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.408<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Married, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (91.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (100.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; 0.999<sup>ξ</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Education level, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.235</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.539<sup>‡</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Primary school and below</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (41.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (25.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Junior and senior high school</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (41.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (37.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  College and above</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (16.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (37.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Smoker, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (50.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (25.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.373<sup>ξ</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Drinker, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.400<sup>ξ</sup></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Preoperative</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hypertension, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (41.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (87.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070<sup>ξ</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Diabetes, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (8.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; 0.999<sup>ξ</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Cerebrovascular disease, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.400<sup>ξ</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sedation use, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.400<sup>ξ</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Analgesia use, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (66.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (75.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; 0.999<sup>ξ</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> LVEF (%), mean (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.3±6.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.5±6.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.086</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.932<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Intraoperative</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Operating time (min), mean (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">282.58±58.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">312.38±129.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.609</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.558<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> CPB time (min), mean (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">145.91±43.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">144.43±49.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.068</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.946<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Aortic cross-clamp time (min), mean (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.83±28.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.88±29.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.984</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.338<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Postoperative to the end of PSG</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sedation use, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (25.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.242<sup>ξ</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Analgesia use, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (33.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (37.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; 0.999<sup>ξ</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> APACHE-Ⅱ score, mean (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.27±6.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.75±2.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.216</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.832<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Length of MV (h), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0 (19.0, 148.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.5 (20.3, 98.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.133</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.894*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Length of ICU stays (d), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5 (3.3, 14.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5 (3.0, 9.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.428</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.668*</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>†</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Student’s </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-test; *Mann–Whitney </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>U</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-test; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>‡</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Chi-square test; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>ξ</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Fisher’s Exact Test.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0003"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> BMI, body mass index; LEVF, left ventricular ejection fraction; CPB, cardiopulmonary bypass; APACHE, acute physiology and chronic health evaluation; MV, mechanical ventilation; ICU, intensive care unit; SD, standard deviation; IQR, interquartile range.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap id="t0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep Characteristics in Non-Delirium Group vs. Delirium Group</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Delirium (n=12)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delirium (n=8)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t/z</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total recording time (min), mean (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">492.93±59.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">526.65±44.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.371</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.187<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total sleep time (min), mean (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">260.80±83.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">197.85±71.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.744</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.098<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep efficiency (%), mean (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.1±18.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.0±14.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.048</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.055<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage N1 sleep (%), mean (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.4±6.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.1±9.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.508</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.618<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage N2 sleep (%), mean (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.1±23.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.2±13.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.306</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.208<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage N3 sleep (%), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (0, 3.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0, 2.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.435</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.151*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM sleep (%), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 (0, 3.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0, 0.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.535</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delta (μV<sup>2</sup>), median (IQR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,866.60 (10,191.84, 36,892.07)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6431.76 (4861.79, 10,907.65)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.582</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Theta (μV<sup>2</sup>), mean (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4585.63±2626.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2894.31±1873.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.377</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.206<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alpha (μV<sup>2</sup>), mean (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1198.91±726.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1121.87±687.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.201</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.844<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beta (μV<sup>2</sup>), mean (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">165.50±115.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">196.48±107.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.511</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.619<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absence of stage N3 sleep, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (25.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (62.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.167<sup>ξ</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absence of REM sleep, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (33.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (87.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028<sup>ξ</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atypical sleep, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (16.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (87.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005<sup>ξ</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>†</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Student’s </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-test; *Mann–Whitney </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>U</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-test; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>ξ</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Fisher’s Exact Test.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0005"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> REM, rapid eye movement; SD, standard deviation; IQR, interquartile range.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig id="f0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Composition ratio of postoperative delirium in different periods of CSICU patients.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-12-1137-g0003"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">To our knowledge, this is the first study assessing the association between atypical sleep and delirium using PSG through prospectively collected sleep data before delirium onset. Overall, (1) sleep quality was generally poor among all CSICU patients; (2) 45.0% patients (9/20) developed atypical sleep on the first night after cardiac surgery; (3) and patients with delirium had decreased delta power and percentage REM sleep and a higher proportion of atypical sleep and REM sleep absence.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">According to the Principles and Practice of Sleep Medicine (Version 6, 2017),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> stage N1, N2, N3, and REM sleep generally constitute about 2%-5%, 45%-55%, 13%-23%, and 20–25% of sleep. However, sleep in CSICU patients is often altered because of the influence of various factors, such as pain, dyspnea, sleep-affecting drugs, ICU environment, and so forth.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> A study by Orr analyzed sleep in 6 patients undergoing open-heart surgery and found that only 1 patient showed electrophysiologic evidence of stage N2 sleep until the 2nd postoperative night, and 5 patients showed a total absence of REM sleep until the 4th postoperative night.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In another study of 38 patients undergoing coronary artery bypass grafting, the total sleep time reduced to 253.6 ± 94.1 min, with suppressed stage N3 sleep and REM sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Trends among our data are generally consistent with results of the aforementioned studies, including decreased total sleep time, lower sleep efficiency, and suppressed stage N3 and REM sleep (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Severe REM sleep reduction (&lt;6% of total sleep time) is associated with delirium.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> A study by Evans</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> including patients undergoing artificial hip replacement showed that reduced total sleep time and reduced non-REM delta power on the 2nd night postoperatively are related to greater POD severity. Similarly, in this study, we found that reduced delta power and absence of REM sleep are associated with POD. Animal studies have shown that REM sleep deprivation cause neurotransmitters imbalance, including increased acetylcholinesterase activity (responsible for acetylcholine degradation) and dopamine levels.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Neurotransmitter imbalance (particularly decreased acetylcholine level and increased dopamine level) plays a key role in the development of delirium.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In contrast, we did not find any statistically significant association between total sleep time and POD. Our inclusion of critically ill patients undergoing cardiac surgery with CPB in this study could explain this difference. Several studies have reported on cardiac surgery affecting sleep characteristics.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Moreover, sleep in the CSICU is disturbed more often because of the lights, noise, and a high frequency of medical and nursing activities than in the general ward.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The concept of atypical sleep was introduced by Cooper in 2012, and it is prevalent among ICU patients.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> A study verifying the feasibility of unattended PSG indicated that 44% of the patients with atypical sleep had delirium compared to 18% of patients with normal sleep; however, this study could not conclusively establish whether atypical sleep occurs before delirium onset, and the association was not statistically significant.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The results of our study showed that atypical sleep that occurred before POD is associated with POD. K-complexes and sleep spindle loss are key characteristics of atypical sleep. Higher spindle density has been shown to predict better performance with regard to verbal ability and attention; this indicates the potential utility of sleep spindles as markers of cognitive functioning.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Regarding K-complexes, studies have associated these not only with sleep maintenance but also with executive function.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Clinical studies have confirmed that worse cognitive performance is an important trigger for delirium.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36–38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Therefore, we speculate that the association between atypical sleep and POD may be linked to acute impairment in cognitive function caused by K-complex and sleep spindles loss.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Study Limitations</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">The main limitation of this study is its small sample size that, precluded establishing atypical sleep as an independent risk factor of POD. Some patients underwent emergency surgery such as aortic dissection surgery. Thus, we could not obtain preoperative PSG data of all patients. Preoperative sleep disturbance is a potential risk factor for POD.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In our study, although we excluded patients with high-risk sleep disturbance (STOP-Bang score ≥3) and gathered detailed history of sleep-related disease, all patients with preoperative sleep disturbance could not be excluded. Furthermore, we did not assess daytime sleep characteristics. However, a long-term (24 h) PSG study among ICU patients found that sleep architecture and quality were generally similar between the day and night.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Thus, we believe that nighttime studies were sufficient for characterizing the sleep patterns of our patients.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">According to our results, atypical sleep and no REM sleep on the first postoperative night are associated with POD. Further large-scale studies are needed to validate these results.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors thank the Department of Neurology and Sleep Medicine of Fujian Medical University Union Hospital for providing PSG technical support and the Heart Medicine Research Center of Fujian Medical University Union Hospital for providing study site. Yanjuan Lin and Liang-Wan Chen are co-corresponding authors.</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Ethics Approval and Informed Consent</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All procedures performed in this study were in accordance with the ethical standards of the Union Hospital, Fujian Medical University and with the 1964 Helsinki declaration and its later amendments or comparable ethical standards. Informed consent was obtained from all individual participants included in the study.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0008" sec-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Järvelä</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Porkkala</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Karlsson</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martikainen</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Selander</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bendel</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Postoperative delirium in cardiac surgery patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1597</fpage>–<lpage>1602</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.jvca.2017.12.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29361457</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cereghetti</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Siegemund</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schaedelin</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Independent predictors of the duration and overall burden of postoperative delirium after cardiac surgery in adults: an Observational Cohort Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1966</fpage>–<lpage>1973</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.jvca.2017.03.042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28711314</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Thomason</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shintani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peterson</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pun</surname>
<given-names>BT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jackson</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ely</surname>
<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Intensive care unit delirium is an independent predictor of longer hospital stay: a prospective analysis of 261 non-ventilated patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Crit Care</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>R375</fpage>–<lpage>R381</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/cc3729</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16137350</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vasilevskis</surname>
<given-names>EE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chandrasekhar</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holtze</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The cost of ICU delirium and coma in the intensive care unit patient</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Med Care</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>890</fpage>–<lpage>897</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MLR.0000000000000975</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30179988</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ely</surname>
<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shintani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Truman</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Delirium as a predictor of mortality in mechanically ventilated patients in the intensive care unit</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>291</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>1753</fpage>–<lpage>1762</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.291.14.1753</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15082703</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Thorsteinsdóttir</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sveinsdóttir</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Snædal</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Delirium after open cardiac surgery: systematic review of prevalence, risk factors and consequences</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Laeknabladid</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>101</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>305</fpage>–<lpage>311</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26158535</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gosselt</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Slooter</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boere</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zaal</surname>
<given-names>IJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Risk factors for delirium after on-pump cardiac surgery: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Crit Care</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>346</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13054-015-1060-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26395253</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Weinhouse</surname>
<given-names>GL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schwab</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Watson</surname>
<given-names>PL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Bench-to-bedside review: delirium in ICU patients - importance of sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Crit Care</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>234</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/cc8131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20053301</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Iber</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ancoli-Israel</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chesson</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">The AASM Manual for the Scoring of Sleep and Associated Events: Rules, Terminology and Technical Specifications</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Westchester, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</publisher-name>; <year>2007</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cooper</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thornley</surname>
<given-names>KS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Young</surname>
<given-names>GB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Slutsky</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stewart</surname>
<given-names>TE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hanly</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep in critically ill patients requiring mechanical ventilation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>117</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>809</fpage>–<lpage>818</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.117.3.809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10713011</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Knauert</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yaggi</surname>
<given-names>HK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Redeker</surname>
<given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Murphy</surname>
<given-names>TE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Araujo</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pisani</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Feasibility study of unattended polysomnography in medical intensive care unit patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Heart Lung</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>445</fpage>–<lpage>452</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25023504</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Thille</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reynaud</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marie</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impact of sleep alterations on weaning duration in mechanically ventilated patients: a prospective study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Respir J</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>4</issue>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Drouot</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roche-Campo</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thille</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A new classification for sleep analysis in critically ill patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2011.07.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22153778</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Roche Campo</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drouot</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thille</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Poor sleep quality is associated with late noninvasive ventilation failure in patients with acute hypercapnic respiratory failure</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>477</fpage>–<lpage>485</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19789439</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Watson</surname>
<given-names>PL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pandharipande</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gehlbach</surname>
<given-names>BK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Atypical sleep in ventilated patients: empirical electroencephalography findings and the path toward revised ICU sleep scoring criteria</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1958</fpage>–<lpage>1967</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23863228</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Boesen</surname>
<given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Andersen</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bendtsen</surname>
<given-names>AO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jennum</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and delirium in unsedated patients in the intensive care unit</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Anaesthesiol Scand</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/aas.12582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26190149</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bradley</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>DeBenedetti</surname>
<given-names>AF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Volk</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frank</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kivlahan</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>AUDIT-C as a brief screen for alcohol misuse in primary care</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Alcohol Clin Exp Res</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1208</fpage>–<lpage>1217</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17451397</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yegneswaran</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liao</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>STOP questionnaire: a tool to screen patients for obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Anesthesiology</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>108</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>812</fpage>–<lpage>821</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18431116</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ely</surname>
<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Margolin</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Francis</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Evaluation of delirium in critically ill patients: validation of the Confusion Assessment Method for the Intensive Care Unit (CAM-ICU)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1370</fpage>–<lpage>1379</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00003246-200107000-00012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11445689</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sessler</surname>
<given-names>CN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gosnell</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grap</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The richmond agitation-sedation scale: validity and reliability in adult intensive care unit patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>166</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1338</fpage>–<lpage>1344</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12421743</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shadvar</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baastani</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mahmoodpoor</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bilehjani</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Evaluation of the prevalence and risk factors of delirium in cardiac surgery ICU</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Nurs Res</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>161</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Swart</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van der Zanden</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spies</surname>
<given-names>PE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Rooij</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van Munster</surname>
<given-names>BC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The comparative risk of delirium with different opioids: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Drugs Aging</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>437</fpage>–<lpage>443</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40266-017-0455-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28405945</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Skrobik</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duprey</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hill</surname>
<given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Devlin</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Low-dose nocturnal dexmedetomidine prevents ICU delirium. a randomized, placebo-controlled trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>197</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1147</fpage>–<lpage>1156</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201710-1995OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29498534</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Kryger</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roth</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dement</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Principles and Practice of Sleep Medicine</italic></source>. <edition>6th</edition> ed. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>; <year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liao</surname>
<given-names>W-C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>C-Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>T-Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hwang</surname>
<given-names>S-L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A systematic review of sleep patterns and factors that disturb sleep after heart surgery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Nurs Res</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>288</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22089653</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Orr</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stahl</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disturbances after open heart surgery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>1977</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>196</fpage>–<lpage>201</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0002-9149(77)80191-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">299975</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Edéll-Gustafsson</surname>
<given-names>UM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hetta</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arén</surname>
<given-names>CB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and quality of life assessment in patients undergoing coronary artery bypass grafting</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Adv Nurs</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1213</fpage>–<lpage>1220</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2648.1999.01006.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10320506</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Trompeo</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vidi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Locane</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep disturbances in the critically ill patients: role of delirium and sedative agents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Minerva Anestesiol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>77</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>604</fpage>–<lpage>612</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21617624</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Evans</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nadler</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Preud’homme</surname>
<given-names>XA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Pilot prospective study of post-surgery sleep and EEG predictors of post-operative delirium</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Neurophysiol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>128</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1421</fpage>–<lpage>1425</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinph.2017.05.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28618293</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Siddique</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tamilselvan</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vishnupriya</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Balamurugan</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Evaluation of neurotransmitter alterations in four distinct brain regions after Rapid Eye Movement Sleep Deprivation (REMSD) induced mania-like behaviour in Swiss Albino Mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurochem Res</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1171</fpage>–<lpage>1181</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11064-018-2533-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29671235</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Benedito</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Camarini</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Rapid eye movement sleep deprivation induces an increase in acetylcholinesterase activity in discrete rat brain regions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Braz J Med Biol Res</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11151034</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shen</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Postoperative delirium in the elderly: the potential neuropathogenesis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Aging Clin Exp Res</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1287</fpage>–<lpage>1295</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40520-018-1008-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30051417</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lafortune</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gagnon</surname>
<given-names>J-F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep spindles and rapid eye movement sleep as predictors of next morning cognitive performance in healthy middle-aged and older participants</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24245769</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schilling</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schlipf</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spietzack</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Fast sleep spindle reduction in schizophrenia and healthy first-degree relatives: association with impaired cognitive function and potential intermediate phenotype</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Arch Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>267</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00406-016-0725-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27565806</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ramakrishnan</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sartory</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van Beekum</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lohrmann</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pietrowsky</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep-related cognitive function and the K-complex in schizophrenia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Brain Res</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>234</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbr.2012.06.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22743003</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Koskderelioglu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Onder</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gucuyener</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Altay</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kayali</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gedizlioglu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Screening for postoperative delirium in patients with acute hip fracture: assessment of predictive factors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Geriatr Gerontol Int</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>919</fpage>–<lpage>924</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27283273</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Miao</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shen</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Neopterin and mini-mental state examination scores, two independent risk factors for postoperative delirium in elderly patients with open abdominal surgery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cancer Res Ther</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1234</fpage>–<lpage>1238</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30488836</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shin</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kyeong</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A personality trait contributes to the occurrence of postoperative delirium: a prospective study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>371</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12888-016-1079-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27809817</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fadayomi</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ibala</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bilotta</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Westover</surname>
<given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Akeju</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A systematic review and meta-analysis examining the impact of sleep disturbance on postoperative delirium</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>e1204</fpage>–<lpage>e1212</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/CCM.0000000000003400</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30222634</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
