<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33623458</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7894796</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">290586</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S290586</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Persistent Short Sleep from Childhood to Adolescence: Child, Parent and Peer Predictors</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Ranum et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Ranum et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ranum</surname>
            <given-names>Bror M</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wichstrøm</surname>
            <given-names>Lars</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pallesen</surname>
            <given-names>Ståle</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0003">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0004">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Falch-Madsen</surname>
            <given-names>Jonas</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Steinsbekk</surname>
            <given-names>Silje</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label>Department of Psychology, <institution>Norwegian University of Science and Technology</institution>, <addr-line>Trondheim</addr-line>, <country>Norway</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label>Department of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, <institution>St. Olavs Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Trondheim</addr-line>, <country>Norway</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label>Department of Psychosocial Science, <institution>University of Bergen</institution>, <addr-line>Bergen</addr-line>, <country>Norway</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label>Norwegian Competence Center for Sleep Disorders, <institution>Haukeland University Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Bergen</addr-line>, <country>Norway</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Bror M Ranum <institution>Department of Psychology, Norwegian University of Science and Technology</institution>, <addr-line>Trondheim</addr-line><addr-line>7049</addr-line>, <country>Norway</country><phone>Tel +4795156994</phone> Email bror.ranum@ntnu.no</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>13</volume>
      <fpage>163</fpage>
      <lpage>175</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>05</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2020</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2021 Ranum et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Ranum et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Many children have periods when they sleep too little, with widely recognized detrimental effects. Less is known about persistent short sleep during childhood. Therefore, the present study aimed to investigate the prevalence of persistent short sleep in school-aged children and identify a set of child, parent, and peer predictors thereof.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Participants and Methods</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Objectively measured sleep duration (hip-held accelerometer) was biennially assessed in a community sample followed from 6 to 14 years (n=801). A latent profile analysis was applied to assess whether a subgroup of children slept consistently short across time and predictors of persistent short sleep were determined through regression analysis.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">A subgroup of children (n=160; 20.2%) was identified as having persistent short sleep across time. Temperamental negative affectivity (β=0.08; 95% CI=0.01, 0.15; p=0.03) and low observer-assessed parental emotional availability (β=−.09; 95% CI=−.18, −.01; p=0.04) predicted membership to that group. Teacher ratings of victimization from bullying were not associated with persistent short sleep (β=0.01; 95% CI: −.10, 11; p=0.88).</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">High child temperamental negative affectivity and low parental emotional availability may be involved in the development of persistent short sleep through childhood.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>actigraphy</kwd>
        <kwd>childhood</kwd>
        <kwd>early adolescence</kwd>
        <kwd>parental emotional availability</kwd>
        <kwd>prospective cohort study</kwd>
        <kwd>negative affectivity</kwd>
        <kwd>sleep duration</kwd>
        <kwd>insufficient sleep</kwd>
        <kwd>victimization from bullying</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="3"/>
        <table-count count="8"/>
        <ref-count count="81"/>
        <page-count count="13"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Short sleep is associated with negative health outcomes in children, such as cardiometabolic risk,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> symptoms of psychiatric disorders,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and cognitive and behavioral problems.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Sleep duration among children and adolescents has declined significantly during the past century,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and many parents (6</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> –50%</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) report that their children sleep insufficiently on a regular basis, underscoring the potential gravity of this historic trend for children’s health and development. For adults, sleep curtailment has been shown to produce adverse long-term effects.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Whether this is also true of children is unknown because of the paucity of prospective studies. Notably, a systematic review of emerging evidence suggests that shortened sleep is associated with reduced brain function in children and adolescents in the short term.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Experimental evidence moreover indicates that children take longer to recover from sleep curtailment than adults,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> adding to this concern. It is plausible that the negative outcomes seen after such relatively brief periods of sleep deprivation would be even more pronounced if shortened sleep continues for longer periods. Interventions and treatment efforts toward persistent short sleep in children would benefit from knowledge of its predictors. At present, such predictors are not sufficiently explored.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Even though the stability of sleep duration from one assessment point to the next is only modest to moderate in childhood,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10–12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> indicating that most children will outgrow short sleep, a sub-group of children characterized by curtailed sleep over longer time-periods during development may still exist. However, which children this encompass, how many are affected, and predictors thereof are currently unknown.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Identifying a valid cut-off point for insufficient sleep duration at any one point in development is associated with many complexities and remains difficult to pinpoint.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Defining persistent insufficient sleep carries additional challenges because some children may fluctuate slightly above or below a predefined cut-point during development, thereby not being defined as persistent short sleepers through childhood according to such criteria (eg, less than 7 hours), even though they sleep consistently less than others. Therefore, it is timely to ask whether a class of children consistently sleeping little—and less than others—throughout childhood can be identified.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">If such a class of children can be identified, its predictors should be determined. Theoretical models of insomnia</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and results from experimental</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and cross-sectional research</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> converge in underscoring that downregulation of arousal is needed for sleep initiation and maintenance and thus sleeping adequately. According to ecological</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and transactional</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> models of development, impaired downregulation abilities may stem from endogenous child (eg, temperament), parent (eg, parenting style) or environmental factors (eg, school environment and peer relations), including their interactions. In the present inquiry, and as outlined in detail below, we focus on temperamental negative affectivity, parents’ emotional availability and bullying from peers as potential predictors.</citation_analysis></p>
      <sec id="s0001-s2001">
        <title>Negative Affectivity and Sleep</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Temperamental negative affectivity refers to the tendency to experience negative emotions (eg, sadness, fear, anger, and discomfort) more often, more intensely, and for a longer duration than others.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Physiological-emotional reactivity—corresponding to temperamental negative affectivity—is theorized to be one of the most important endogenous child factors influencing sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Empirical evidence from early childhood studies supports this claim. Infants and preschool children with high negative affectivity are perceived by their mothers to have more difficulties falling asleep,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> which is associated with shorter sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, less is known about the role of negative affectivity in school-aged children and adolescents’ sleep. A cross-sectional study revealed that 6–13-year-olds who expressed their emotions more frequently and intensely than their peers also slept shorter</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> but prospective studies and evidence for the direction of influence are scarce. Only two studies seem to exist,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> both showing that short sleep (parent report by questionnaire</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and time diaries</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) at age 6 was predicted by difficult temperament (closely related to high negative affectivity). The conclusions that can be drawn from these studies are limited for two methodological reasons: sleep duration and temperament were both parent-reported; thus, their association may be confounded by common method bias.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Moreover, the correspondence between parent- or self-reported sleep and objectively measured sleep is modest</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and varies according to the sleep parameters assessed, the recall period, whether schooldays are distinguished from days off from school, as well as respondent- and data collection method.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Furthermore, findings from infants and young children do not necessarily apply to older children and adolescents. Consequently, it is not known whether negative affectivity is involved in the etiology of objectively measured short sleep in school-aged children and adolescents.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0001-s2002">
        <title>Parental Emotional Availability</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Parental emotional availability refers to the ability of parents to demonstrate warmth, consistency, understanding, support, and positive communication. According to Biringen,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> parental emotional availability comprises the following factors: 1) Sensitivity: Parent’s ability to develop and maintain a positive and healthy emotional connection with the child—promoting engaging, joyous, and creative play; 2) structuring: Parent’s contribution in structuring activities and how effectively the parent limit unwanted behavior in the child that may reduce the emotional connection; 3) nonintrusiveness: Parents ability to facilitate child autonomy by not taking too much control, helping too much, or overprotecting the child; and 4) nonhostility: not displaying behavior that can be frightening or threatening to the child—such as showing dissatisfaction, impatience, boredom, anger or raising one’s voice. Typically, parents are children’s most salient and important regulatory scaffold and thus constitute the environmental factor which impacts children’s sleep the most. Emotionally available parents may help protect against sleeping too little along two pathways. First – external regulation; effective and consistent parent practices may help to soothe and downregulate the child at bedtime or at night if the child awakens. Indeed, parental emotional availability works as a buffer against the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenocortical (HPA) axis response.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Given the reciprocal relationship between sleep and the secretory activity of the HPA-axis,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> it seems conceivable that helping the child downregulate arousal both directly and through skill acquisition can improve sleep. Consequently, parents who are emotionally available to the child may protect against curtailed sleep. Supporting this notion, high-quality parent–child interactions at 12–18 months have been prospectively associated with better sleep 2–3 years later.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Second – internal regulation; developmental theory</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> suggests that emotionally available parents are better at promoting the acquisition of self-regulation capacities in the child. The child may then take responsibility for the needed downregulation and consistent bed-time routines itself as she or he ages. Such theorizing is supported by findings</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> suggesting that parents’ emotional availability indeed fosters self-regulation, which predicts fewer sleep problems.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Of note, most theoretical and empirical work on parental emotional availability focus on infants, toddlers and preschoolers. Even though parents continue to be an important source of external (down)-regulation and facilitate the learning of self-regulation throughout childhood, the proposition that parental emotional availability continues to be of importance—also for school-aged children and adolescents’ sleep duration—has never previously been investigated. Furthermore, most studies examining the relationship between the parent–child interaction and sleep have relied on subjective reports,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> risking inflating associations due to common method effects. To reduce this impact, using observer ratings of the parent–child interaction and measuring sleep by objective methods, would advance this field.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0001-s2003">
        <title>Victimization from Bullying</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Peers become increasingly important and impactful throughout childhood, to the better or worse. Bullying and victimization is a widespread phenomenon in childhood.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Victimization from bullying by peers is strongly associated with psychosocial stress (low psychological well-being and poor social adjustment) in children.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Psychosocial stress is related to episodes of impaired sleep,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and this also seems to be the case for victimization from bullying—specifically—in children</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and adolescents.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Fortunately, bullying can be reduced by a range of interventions.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Thus, victimization from bullying may be one of the most important malleable exogenous factors that affect children’s sleep. However, it remains unknown whether victimization from bullying is predictive of prospective persistent short sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0001-s2004">
        <title>Interactive Effects</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Environmental factors may impact some children, for genetic or other organismic reasons, more than other—more impervious—children. Indeed, temperamental traits, including negative affectivity, have repeatedly been found to interact with environmental factors in shaping children’s development.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42–45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Such interactive effects may be operative with respect to short sleep as well: One may speculate that highly reactive children struggle the most with downregulating (and thus sleep less) from the aftermath of victimization from bullying or insensitive, harsh or intrusive parents (ie, low emotional availability), whereas children less dominated by negative affectivity would be less afflicted.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0001-s2005">
        <title>The Present Study</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Based on the aforementioned theoretical notions and existing research, the following hypotheses will be tested: Can a subgroup of children with shortened sleep throughout childhood and adolescence be identified (H1)?; Can such persistent short sleep be predicted from higher negative affectivity (H2), low parental emotional availability (H3), victimization from bullying (H4)? Moreover, we hypothesize that the negative environmental effects of parents’ emotional unavailability and victimization from bullying are stronger for children with high negative affectivity (H5). Because socioeconomic status,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> male gender,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and emotional and behavioral problems</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> have been associated with shorter sleep duration and may be associated with the predictors, we included socioeconomic status, gender and emotional and behavioral problems as covariates.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants and Procedure</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The data were derived from the Trondheim Early Secure Study (TESS).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Together with the appointment for an age-4 routine health check-up (N=3456), an invitation letter was sent to the parents of all children in the 2003 and 2004 birth cohorts in Trondheim, Norway, together with a screening questionnaire for emotional and behavioral problems, the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ) 4–16 version.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The health nurse informed parents about TESS and collected written consent. All the procedures used in TESS have been reviewed and approved by the Regional Committee for Medical and Health Research Ethics, Mid-Norway. A flow-chart of recruitment and attrition is depicted in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Flow chart of recruitment and follow-up.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-163-g0001"/><attrib><bold>Notes:</bold> Number of participants at the various assessment points is based on the number of participants invited to participate (n=1250) minus those who did not participate at the respective measurement points (i.e., T1, T2).</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Because one of the main aims of TESS is to study mental health, children with emotional or behavioral problems were oversampled to increase statistical power. To accomplish this, the participants were allocated to four strata according to their SDQ scores (cut-offs: 0–4, 5–8, 9–11, 12–40). The probability of selection increased with increasing SDQ-scores—0.37, 0.48, 0.70, and 0.89 in the four strata, respectively. Population weights were applied in the analyses to provide corrected population estimates. The dropout rate after consenting to participate did not vary by SDQ score (t=0.17, df=1, p=0.86) or gender (Cramer’s v2=1.02, df=1, p=0.31) at the age-4 assessment. The accelerometer assessment of sleep was implemented from 6 years of age (49% boys) onwards; therefore, the data from the first assessment (4 years) were not included in the present analyses. Accelerometer measurement and interview were conducted biennially at the ages of 6 (n=685, Mage=6.6 years, SD=0.52), 8 (n=618; Mage=8.8 years, SD=0.23), 10 (n=617, Mage=10.5 years, SD=0.15), 12 (n=557, Mage=12.5, SD=0.14), and 14 years (n=557, Mage=14.3, SD=0.63). Participants with valid accelerometer data on at least one occasion comprised the analytical sample (n=801). At age 6 years 52% completed all 7 days of accelerometer measurement. The corresponding numbers for the subsequent measurement points were as follows: 45% at age 8 years; 48% at age 10 years; 37% at age 12 years; and 36% at age 14 years. None of the sample characteristics in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> predicted selection to the analytic sample from the main TESS sample. Within the analytical sample, short-sleep duration at 8 years of age predicted attrition at 10 years (standardized beta β= −.13; 95% confidence interval [CI]: −.25, −.01; p=0.02) but explained a negligible part of the variance in drop-out (proxy R2=0.02). Similarly, sleep duration at 12 years of age-predicted attrition at 14 years (β= −.12; 95% CI: −.23, −.01; p=0.04) but explained virtually none of the variance in drop-out (proxy R2=0.01). Boys (β=0.17; 95% CI: 0.05–0.28; p=0.005), and children with higher negative affectivity (β=0.16; 95% CI: 0.05–0.27; p=0.003) were more likely to drop out at 10 years (proxy R2=0.03 for each predictor). </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> displays the sample characteristics of the analytic sample at 6 years of age.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap id="t0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sample Characteristics of Analytic Sample at T2 (Age 6)</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender of child</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender of parent informant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Ethnic origin of biological mother</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Norwegian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Western Countries</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other Countries</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Ethnic origin of biological father</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Norwegian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Western Countries</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other Countries</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Biological parents’ marital status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Married</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohabitating</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Divorced/Separated</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">Informant parents’ socioeconomic status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaders</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Higher professionals</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower professionals</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skilled workers</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Farmers/fishermen</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unskilled workers</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Household gross annual income</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0–225ʹ NOK (0–26,500 USD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">225ʹ – 525ʹ NOK (26,500–62ʹ USD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">525ʹ – 900ʹ NOK (62ʹ – 106ʹ USD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; 900ʹ NOK (&gt; 106ʹ USD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.8</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Measures</title>
        <sec id="s0002-s2002-s3001">
          <title>Sleep Duration</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Was assessed using a triaxial ActiGraph GT3X accelerometer (Manufacturing Technology Incorporated, Fort Walton Beach, Florida, USA). The accelerometer is a small hip-strapped device measuring acceleration in three dimensions. Children were instructed to wear the accelerometer for seven consecutive days, 24 hours a day, only taking it off when bathing or showering. Sleep diaries were not administered. Bedtime and rise time were manually scored by a bachelor level student of psychology (instructed by an expert in accelerometry) inspecting each individual actogram. The inter-scorer reliability (ICC = intraclass correlation coefficient) between the student and the expert was ICC=0.90 at age 6, ICC=0.86 at age 8, ICC=0.84 at age 10, ICC=0.88 at age 12. Age 14 accelerometer data were not coded by both raters. Human visual scoring has been shown to have superior correlation with polysomnography compared to autodetection by computer</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> and is closely aligned with sleep diary entries, with the resulting difference in sleep duration being minuscule (0.7 minutes).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Sleep duration (minutes scored as asleep between bedtime and rise time, excluding minutes awake) was derived using Sadeh’s sleep algorithm</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and was based on 60-second epochs (time-blocks).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Sadeh’s algorithm scores an epoch as asleep or awake depending on activity during the current epoch considering activity in the previous and subsequent five minutes. For the best possible measure of individual differences in sleep duration and to reduce the influence of measurement error, we created a latent variable for each measurement occasion loading on sleep duration at each night of the week (illustrated in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). Only nocturnal sleep was considered.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Factor analysis of sleep duration with standardized beta coefficients (β), standard errors (SE) and correlations (r).</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-163-g0002"/><attrib><bold>Notes:</bold> All coefficients and correlations are significant at p&lt;0.001 level. Correlations between sleep duration age 6 and sleep duration age 10, etc., are left out for parsimonious reasons.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2002-s3002">
          <title>Child Negative Affectivity</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Was assessed using the Children’s Behavior Questionnaire,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> a caregiver report measure designed to provide a detailed assessment of temperament in children 3 to 7 years of age. We calculated a composite score reflecting negative affectivity from five domains (anger, discomfort, fear, sadness, and reversed soothability) with a total of 31 items, which had a good internal consistency (Cronbach’ alpha [α]=.82).</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2002-s3003">
          <title>Parent Emotional Availability Scales (EAS)</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Is a measure of the quality of parent–child interactions and was assessed through the coding of parent–child interaction. Parents and children were observed through video recording of four consecutive 5-min sequences of play (free play, child lead play, parent-led play, and a clean-up task). Videotapes of the interactions were scored according to the EAS 3rd ed.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The Emotional Availability Scale was administered to rate four parental dimensions (sensitivity, structuring, nonintrusiveness, and nonhostility) of emotional availability. We used a composite score of the four dimensions as a measure of the quality of the parent–child interaction. The four parent ratings yielded an acceptable internally consistent score (α=0.74). All the raters were trained and certified as reliable by Zeynep Biringen, who developed the EAS. The interrater reliability between multiple blinded coders on a random 10% of the sample of the videotapes for the total parent scale, assessed using the interclass correlation coefficient (ICC),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> was ICC=0.71.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2002-s3004">
          <title>Victimization from Bullying</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Was assessed by teacher report using five questions from the Olweus Bully/Victim Questionnaire,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> which had an acceptable internal consistency (α=0.77). The questions covered victimization from direct bullying such as physical assault, verbal assault and breaking/hiding toys and indirect bullying in the form of social exclusion.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2002-s3005">
          <title>Socioeconomic Status (SES)</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Was measured in terms of parental occupation coded according to the International Standard Classifications of Occupations.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> If parents were living together, the parent with the highest socioeconomic status was chosen. Socioeconomic status was ranked from high to low as follows: leaders, higher level professionals, lower level professionals, formally skilled workers, farmers/fishermen, and unskilled workers.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2002-s3006">
          <title>Emotional and Behavioral Problems</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Was assessed by teacher report using the Teacher Report Form (TRF) from the Achenbach System of Empirically Based Assessment (ASEBA) scales.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The Teacher Report Form consists of 120 items and is used to rate children between ages 4 and 18 years. The TRF has scales for anxious/depressed, withdrawn/depressed, somatic complaints, social problems, thought problems, attention problems, rule-breaking behavior, and aggressive behavior. The two aggregate categories of internalizing and externalizing problems were used to measure emotional and behavioral problems, respectively.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All statistical analyses were performed using Mplus, version 7.4.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Missing data were handled by applying the full information maximum likelihood (FIML).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Because we oversampled children with high SDQ scores, the data were weighted proportional to the number of children in a specific stratum in the population divided by the number of participating children in that specific stratum. A robust maximum likelihood estimator was used that does not presuppose multivariate normality.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">A much-used approach to identify clusters of developmental trajectories is latent growth-mixture modeling.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, such an approach examines individual growth or decline over time (ie, change). Because our hypotheses concerned the level of sleep over time, and not linear (or curvilinear) changes over time, we applied latent profile analysis (LPA).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> By this approach, classes with specific characteristics are identified and each child is given a probability of belonging to the emerging classes. All available datapoints on sleep duration were included in the Latent Profile Analysis (age 6, 8, 10, 12, 14 years). To determine the number of classes, we applied the Voung–Lo–Mendell–Rubin test,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> along with entropy and class size as indicators.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">To test our hypotheses concerning predictors, the probability of belonging to a subgroup of children sleeping persistently shorter than others was regressed on age 6 measures of child negative affectivity, emotional availability of the parent, and victimization from bullying. Parental socioeconomic status, gender, and emotional and behavioral problems were included as covariates. The assumption that children high in negative affectivity would be more affected was tested by adding multiplicative terms between negative affectivity and emotional availability and victimization, respectively, to the regression analysis.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Bivariate correlations between the study variables are displayed in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. Factor loadings, correlations and standard errors for the latent variable sleep duration are presented in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap id="t0002" orientation="landscape" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Mean, Standard Deviation (SD) and Correlations of Study Variables</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration age 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.14**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration age 8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.12**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.12**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration age 10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.10*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.15***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration age 12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.17***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration age 14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.11*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative affectivity of child age 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emotional availability of parent age 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.08*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Victimization from bullying age 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.10*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73***</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Socioeconomic status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emotional problems age 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93***</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Behavioral problems age 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The results of the latent profile analysis revealed that the length of sleep throughout childhood was not evenly distributed between participants, but rather tended to cluster in a group-wise fashion. A solution with three classes of sleep duration showed a better fit to the data (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) compared to two, four and five classes, and this solution also had acceptable entropy. The largest class comprised children with moderately long sleep throughout childhood and early adolescence, and the second-largest class slept comparatively longer than the others, about half an hour longer each night than the “moderate” class. Importantly, a smaller—albeit sizable (n=160; 20.2%)—class slept less than the others at all time-points; about half an hour shorter than the moderate class and an hour shorter each day than the long-sleeping class. This subgroup of children characterized by persistent short sleep was the focus of the remaining hypothesis testing. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> provides data on the percentage of children in each class and the mean sleep duration with standard deviation for the three classes at all ages. This is graphically illustrated in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap id="t0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Fit Statistics of Latent Profile Analysis (LPA)</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Classes</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AIC</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">BIC</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">LMRT</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Entropy (0–1)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37,779.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37,826.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36,349.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36,424.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.836</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>35,731.88</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>35,834.97</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>p=0.012</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.852</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35,446.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35,577.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.691</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.846</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35,250.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35,410.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p=0.234</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.862</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Data in bold formatting indicates the best fitting model relative to the other models tested.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0003"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviation:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> LMRT, Lo–Mendell–Rubin Test.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap id="t0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Mean Sleep Duration (Hours) with Standard Deviation for Three Classes by Age</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Persistent Short Sleep (n= 160; 20.2%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medium Sleep Duration (n=422; 52.4%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long Sleep (n=219; 27.4%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.14 (0.59)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.64 (0.46)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.08 (0.47)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.69 (0.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.23 (0.44)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.72 (0.44)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.41 (0.42)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.99 (0.40)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.54 (0.41)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.08 (0.46)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.67 (0.47)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.18 (0.48)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.78 (0.73)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.42 (0.66)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.00 (0.73)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig id="f0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Profile analysis of sleep duration (with 95% CI).</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-163-g0003"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Displaying higher levels of negative affectivity and having a less emotionally available parent predicted an increased probability of belonging to the class characterized by persistent short sleep (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). No interactions emerged between the predictors. Note that socioeconomic status, gender, and emotional and behavioral problems were included as covariates. Boys were more likely than girls to belong to the short-sleep class.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap id="t0005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Predictors of Probability of Belonging to a Class of Short Sleepers. Linear Regression Model Testing Association Between Covariates and Probability of Being a Short Sleeper</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standardized Regression Coefficient β</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative affectivity of child</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01, 0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emotional availability of parent</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.18, −0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Victimization from bullying</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.10, 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Socioeconomic status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.09, 0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02, 0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emotional problems</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.27, 0.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Behavioral problems</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.18, 0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Given the lack of knowledge about the persistence of short sleep in childhood, we investigated whether a class of children with enduring short sleep could be identified and, if so, investigated the proposition that temperamental negative affectivity, low emotional availability from parents and victimization from bullying by peers predicted persistent short sleep. Using latent profile analysis, we identified three classes differentiated by the duration of sleep: 1) short-sleep duration; 2) intermediate sleep duration 3) long sleep duration. The class characterized by short-sleep duration manifested comparatively short sleep—ie, 0.5 and 1 hour shorter than the two other classes—at all ages from 6 to 14 years. Higher negative affectivity and reduced emotional availability from parents at 6 years of age-predicted likelihood of belonging to the persistent short-sleep group. Contrary to our hypothesis, victimization from bullying was unrelated to persistent short sleep and negative affectivity did not moderate the effect of parental emotional availability or victimization from bullying. Gender and socioeconomic status were included as covariates, and the results showed that boys were more likely to have persistent short sleep, whereas socioeconomic status was unrelated to the risk of persistent short sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
      <sec id="s0004-s2001">
        <title>A Class of Children with Persistent Short Sleep</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our results are in line with, and extend, previous prospective studies finding that 6% of children had persistent short sleep as reported by parents (both from age 2 to 6</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and from age 2 to 10</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">); and that 15% of preadolescents (age 10–13) had persistent short sleep (parent reported).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The present study adds to previous knowledge by showing that persistent short sleep in children is also evident when objective measures of sleep are applied, and not merely reflected by persistence in parent report. Please note that we identified a somewhat larger portion of children (20.2%) had persistent short sleep compared to former research. The different proportion of children having short sleep across studies might reflect differences in measurement methods, age spans captured, cultural differences in sleep practices, or other factors not identified. Recall that the correlation between reported sleep duration and objectively measured sleep duration varies considerably, ranging from 0.29</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> to 0.64</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> in 6–10 year olds.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The mean sleep duration at age 6 years in the persistent short-sleep class was 9.1 hours, which is in the lower end of recommended sleep duration (9–11 hours) for this age group (6–14 years) by the National Sleep Foundation.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, due to the yearly decline in sleep duration by approximately 10 minutes, from the age of 8 years onward, the short-sleep group fell below recommendations, indicating that we accurately identified a group sleeping too little throughout most of childhood and into adolescence. Hip-held actigraphy (used in this study) is prone to overestimate sleep duration compared with polysomnography.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Thus, it is likely that a share of the short-sleeping group also slept too little at the age of 6 years, adding confidence to the construct validity of this group.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Roughly half an hour separated the three classes identified in the present inquiry. The clinical significance of this is hard to determine. Still, experimental research indicates that restricting sleep by one hour compared to the habitual amount impair neuro-cognitive performance.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Further, sleep curtailment has demonstrated negative effects in natural contexts, such as poor school functioning.3 Because individual sleep need is unknown, such comparisons are difficult though.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2002">
        <title>Negative Affectivity Predicts Persistent Short Sleep</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Previous findings in infants</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and children</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> concerning the potential impact of temperament on parent proxy-reports of short sleep were supported by the present findings. We also extended this by showing that childhood negative affectivity is associated with persistent short sleep across childhood. In terms of potential mechanisms, children high in negative affectivity are more easily emotionally activated (eg, anger and frustration) and have poorer emotional regulation abilities.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> They display more bedtime resistance,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> which is linked to later sleep onset. Thus, these children may fall asleep later at night than less reactive children, typically resulting in curtailed sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Additionally, negative affectivity is associated with a more easily exited nervous system that might prolong sleep onset latency and increase the number and duration of nocturnal awakenings,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> explaining the results of this study.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2003">
        <title>Parental Emotional Availability May Protect Against Persistent Short Sleep</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Although a sparse number of former studies on infants and toddlers have hinted at the quality of the parent–child relationship being important for sleep,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> we here show that high emotional availability of parents reduces the risk of persistent short sleep in also older offspring. This finding concurs with the conclusion from a meta-analytic evidence that, broadly speaking, a negative family environment is associated with short-sleep duration among adolescents.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Our results extend this research by pointing to parental emotional availability as a specific factor. Future research should determine whether different aspects of parental emotional availability—such as sensitivity, structuring, nonintrusiveness, and nonhostility—are of particular importance. One common explanation for why parental emotional availability may affect sleep duration is that it buffers against hyperarousal (eg, prevents children from becoming very upset) and/or facilitates children’s own emotion regulation (ie, promotes the development of downregulating skills) thus reducing the risk for problems with initiating and maintaining sleep when exposed to stressors. Emotional availability also comprises successful limit setting by the parent, which may contribute to longer sleep duration through parent-set bedtimes</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> and consistent bedtime routines</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> as well as less bedtime resistance,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> all promoting longer sleep duration. Moreover, parental overinvolvement (an aspect of low emotional availability) may interfere with the sleep initiation process by impeding the development of self-soothing and by reinforcing behavior counteracting sleep initiation (eg, overresponding to signaling behavior).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Future research may clarify to what degree and under which circumstances each of these mechanisms are involved.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2004">
        <title>Clinical Implications</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The present findings indicate that interventions aimed at reducing negative affectivity may reduce the risk of persistent short sleep. Cognitive-behavioral therapy for youth (aged 9–13 years) with anxiety disorders have been shown to counteract self-reported negative affectivity.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Likewise, a few studies examining interventions targeting emotional availability or the attachment between the child and parent have shown beneficial effects on parental emotional availability.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In sum, the factors identified to predict persistent short sleep in the current study do seem to be modifiable and thus could be addressed in preventive efforts.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2005">
        <title>Limitations</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Although the present study had several strengths, including involving a representative community sample followed repeatedly from childhood to adolescence, objectively recorded sleep and independent measures of predictors, thereby minimizing common method bias (ie, observations, parent, and teacher reports), we acknowledge some limitations. First, the study captures sleep duration only, thus other important aspects of sleep such as quality, timing, night-to-night variability in sleep duration, sleep architecture, and sleep problems were not accounted for. Although negative affectivity, parental emotional availability and victimization from bullying were not associated with persistent short sleep, these variables may still be associated with other aspects (eg, timing, architecture, problems) of sleep. As such, the specific focus on sleep duration limit generalizations to other sleep variables. Second, the short persistent sleep class may include children with less need for sleep than others (then being inconsequential), and it may contain children that get inadequate sleep on a regular basis.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Third, predictors were measured at one time point only and may thus not fully capture the developmental sequelae of continued parent, child, and peer interactions over time. Hence, predictors might differ over developmental periods. Fourth, although gender and socioeconomic status were controlled for, other confounding variables could potentially explain the results, such as behavioral sleep problems, insomnia or genes common to both parental emotional availability and offspring sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Fifth, as there are cultural differences in sleep duration among children,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> generalization of the present findings to cultures with other sleep practices should be made with caution.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">A subgroup of 20% of children display persistent short sleep across the ages of 6 to 14 years. The probability of having persistent short sleep is higher for children high in temperamental negative affectivity and for those whose parents are less emotionally available. Interventions to promote healthy sleep should consider mitigating the impact of temperamental negative affectivity and targeting parent–child interactions.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec id="s0006" sec-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Matricciani</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paquet</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Galland</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Short</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olds</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Children’s sleep and health: a meta-review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>136</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2019.04.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31121414</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ranum</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wichstrøm</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pallesen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Falch-Madsen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Halse</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Steinsbekk</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between objectively measured sleep duration and symptoms of psychiatric disorders in middle childhood</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Netw Open</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>e1918281</fpage>–<lpage>e1918281</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.18281</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31880797</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Beebe</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cognitive, behavioral, and functional consequences of inadequate sleep in children and adolescents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatr Clin N Am</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>649</fpage>–<lpage>665</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pcl.2011.03.002</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Matricciani</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olds</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petkov</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>In search of lost sleep: secular trends in the sleep time of school-aged children and adolescents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2011.03.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21612957</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Touchette</surname>
<given-names>É</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petit</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Séguin</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boivin</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tremblay</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Montplaisir</surname>
<given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Associations between sleep duration patterns and behavioral/cognitive functioning at school entry</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1213</fpage>–<lpage>1219</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/30.9.1213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17910393</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Magee</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gordon</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caputi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Distinct developmental trends in sleep duration during early childhood</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatrics</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>133</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e1561</fpage>–<lpage>e1567</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2013-3806</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24843067</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wyatt</surname>
<given-names>JK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Uncovering residual effects of chronic sleep loss on human performance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Transl Med</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>14ra13</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.3000458</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dutil</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Walsh</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Featherstone</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Influence of sleep on developing brain functions and structures in children and adolescents: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>184</fpage>–<lpage>201</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2018.08.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30241996</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Carskadon</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harvey</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dement</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Acute restriction of nocturnal sleep in children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Percept Mot Skills</italic></source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>112</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2466/pms.1981.53.1.103</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ranum</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wichstrøm</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pallesen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Steinsbekk</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalence and stability of insufficient sleep measured by actigraphy: a prospective community study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatr Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>88</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>110</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41390-020-0768-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32005964</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pesonen</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martikainen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heinonen</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Continuity and change in poor sleep from childhood to early adolescence</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>297</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.3400</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24497657</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kelly</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>El-Sheikh</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Reciprocal relations between children’s sleep and their adjustment over time</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Dev Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1137</fpage>–<lpage>1147</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0034501</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24188035</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Blunden</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Galland</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The complexities of defining optimal sleep: empirical and theoretical considerations with a special emphasis on children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>18</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2014.01.002</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Riemann</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spiegelhalder</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feige</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The hyperarousal model of insomnia: a review of the concept and its evidence</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2009.04.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19481481</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>NKY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harvey</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of cognitive arousal and physiological arousal on sleep perception</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/27.1.69</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14998240</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Alfano</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pina</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zerr</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Villalta</surname>
<given-names>IK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pre-sleep arousal and sleep problems of anxiety-disordered youth</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Child Psychiatry Hum Dev</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>156</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10578-009-0158-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19680805</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bronfenbrenner</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Toward an experimental ecology of human development</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am Psychol</italic></source>. <year>1977</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>513</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0003-066X.32.7.513</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sameroff</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Transactional models in early social relations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hum Dev</italic></source>. <year>1975</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1–2</issue>):<fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000271476</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rothbart</surname>
<given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ahadi</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hershey</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fisher</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Investigations of temperament at three to seven years: the children’s behavior questionnaire</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Child Dev</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1394</fpage>–<lpage>1408</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1467-8624.00355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11699677</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kahn</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sheppes</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sadeh</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and emotions: bidirectional links and underlying mechanisms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Psychophysiol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>89</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>218</fpage>–<lpage>228</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpsycho.2013.05.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23711996</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aviezer</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scher</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Children’s sleep regulation is linked to mothers’ sleep-related childhood experiences</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Early Child Res Q</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>281</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecresq.2012.07.004</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Weissbluth</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep duration and infant temperament</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Pediatr</italic></source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>817</fpage>–<lpage>819</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-3476(81)80422-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7299565</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>El‐Sheikh</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buckhalt</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Vagal regulation and emotional intensity predict children’s sleep problems</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Dev Psychobiol</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>317</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dev.20066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15832322</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Belmon</surname>
<given-names>LS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van Stralen</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Busch</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harmsen</surname>
<given-names>IA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chinapaw</surname>
<given-names>MJM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>What are the determinants of children’s sleep behavior? A systematic review of longitudinal studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>60</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2018.09.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30529431</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Simard</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nielsen</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tremblay</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boivin</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Montplaisir</surname>
<given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Longitudinal study of preschool sleep disturbance: the predictive role of maladaptive parental behaviors, early sleep problems, and child/mother psychological factors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>162</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>360</fpage>–<lpage>367</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archpedi.162.4.360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18391145</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Podsakoff</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>MacKenzie</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>J-Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Podsakoff</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Common method biases in behavioral research: a critical review of the literature and recommended remedies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Appl Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>88</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>879</fpage>–<lpage>903</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0021-9010.88.5.879</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14516251</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bauer</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blunden</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>How accurate is subjective reporting of childhood sleep patterns? A review of the literature and implications for practice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Pediatr Rev</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>132</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/157339608784462025</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Matricciani</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Subjective reports of children’s sleep duration: does the question matter? A literature review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>303</fpage>–<lpage>311</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2013.01.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23481486</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Biringen</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">The Emotional Availability (EA) Scales Manual</italic></source>. <edition>4rd</edition> ed. <publisher-loc>Boulder, CO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International Center for Excellence in Emotional Availability</publisher-name>; <year>2008</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Vygotsky</surname>
<given-names>LS</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mind in Society: The Development of Higher Psychological Processes</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, Mass</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>; <year>1978</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Volling</surname>
<given-names>BL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McElwain</surname>
<given-names>NL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Notaro</surname>
<given-names>PC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Herrera</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Parents’ emotional availability and infant emotional competence: predictors of parent-infant attachment and emerging self-regulation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Fam Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>447</fpage>–<lpage>465</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0893-3200.16.4.447</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12561291</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berthelsen</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Walker</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nicholson</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Developmental Cascade</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Model of behavioral sleep problems and emotional and attentional self-regulation across early childhood</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15402002.2015.1065410</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26619760</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kertes</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Donzella</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Talge</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garvin</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Ryzin</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gunnar</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Inhibited temperament and parent emotional availability differentially predict young children’s cortisol responses to novel social and nonsocial events</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Dev Psychobiol</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>521</fpage>–<lpage>532</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dev.20390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19676107</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>van Dalfsen</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Markus</surname>
<given-names>CR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The influence of sleep on human hypothalamic–pituitary–adrenal (HPA) axis reactivity: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>194</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2017.10.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29126903</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bordeleau</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bernier</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carrier</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Longitudinal associations between the quality of parent−child interactions and children’s sleep at preschool age</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Fam Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>254</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0027366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22369463</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Adams</surname>
<given-names>GC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stoops</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Skomro</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep tight: exploring the relationship between sleep and attachment style across the life span</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>495</fpage>–<lpage>507</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2014.03.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24721278</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Olweus</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Bullying at School: What We Know and What We Can Do</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Malden, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>; <year>1993</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rigby</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Consequences of bullying in schools</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Can J Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>583</fpage>–<lpage>590</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/070674370304800904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14631878</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sadeh</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Stress, trauma, and sleep in children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Child Adolesc Psychiatr Clin N Am</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>685</fpage>–<lpage>700</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1056-4993(18)30356-0</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chambers</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Logan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Robinson</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association of common health symptoms with bullying in primary school children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>313</volume>(<issue>7048</issue>):<fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.313.7048.17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8664762</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Simon</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kevin</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>James</surname>
<given-names>MEB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Josephine</surname>
<given-names>NB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Susan</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Adolescent bullying and sleep difficulties</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Northerner</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trentacosta</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McLear</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Negative affectivity moderates associations between cumulative risk and at-risk toddlers’ behavior problems</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Child Fam Stud</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>691</fpage>–<lpage>699</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10826-015-0248-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26924917</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Steinsbekk</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barker</surname>
<given-names>ED</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Llewellyn</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fildes</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wichstrøm</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Emotional feeding and emotional eating: reciprocal processes and the influence of negative affectivity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Child Dev</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>89</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1234</fpage>–<lpage>1246</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cdev.12756</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28439888</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lonigan</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vasey</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Negative affectivity, effortful control, and attention to threat-relevant stimuli</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Abnorm Child Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>387</fpage>–<lpage>399</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10802-008-9284-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19043783</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kochanska</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Toward a synthesis of parental socialization and child temperament in early development of conscience</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Child Dev</italic></source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>325</fpage>–<lpage>347</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1131254</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Biggs</surname>
<given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lushington</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van den Heuvel</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kennedy</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Gender, socioeconomic, and ethnic differences in sleep patterns in school-aged children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1304</fpage>–<lpage>1309</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2013.06.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24074692</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Astill</surname>
<given-names>RG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van der Heijden</surname>
<given-names>KB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Ijzendoorn</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Someren</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep, cognition, and behavioral problems in school-age children: a century of research meta-analyzed</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Bull</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>138</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1109</fpage>–<lpage>1138</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0028204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22545685</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Steinsbekk</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wichstrøm</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cohort profile: the trondheim early secure study (TESS)—a study of mental health, psychosocial development and health behaviour from preschool to adolescence</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1401</fpage>–<lpage>1401i</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyy190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30215720</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Goodman</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ford</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simmons</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gatward</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meltzer</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Using the strengths and difficulties questionnaire (SDQ) to screen for child psychiatric disorders in a community sample</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Br J Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>177</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>534</fpage>–<lpage>539</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/bjp.177.6.534</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11102329</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Boyne</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sherry</surname>
<given-names>DD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gallagher</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olsen</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brooks</surname>
<given-names>LJJS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Breathing. Accuracy of computer algorithms and the human eye in scoring actigraphy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>411</fpage>–<lpage>417</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-012-0709-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22581483</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kinder</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thompson</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hicks</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Topp</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Madsen</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Validation of a hip-worn accelerometer in measuring sleep time in children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Pediatr Nurs</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>133</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pedn.2010.11.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22341191</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sadeh</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sharkey</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carskadon</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Activity-based sleep—wake Identiﬁcation: an empirical test of methodological issues</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>207</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/17.3.201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7939118</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><article-title>Actilife version 6.13.3 [computer program]</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Pensacola, Florida, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Actigraph</publisher-name>; <year>2009</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Biringen</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Robinson</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Emde</surname>
<given-names>RN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Appendix B: the emotional availability scales (; an abridged infancy/early childhood version)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Attach Hum Dev</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>256</fpage>–<lpage>270</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14616730050085626</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0055">
        <label>55.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shrout</surname>
<given-names>PE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fleiss</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Intraclass correlations: uses in assessing rater reliability</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Bull</italic></source>. <year>1979</year>;<volume>86</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>420</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0033-2909.86.2.420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18839484</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0056">
        <label>56.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Solberg</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olweus</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalence estimation of school bullying with the olweus bully/victim questionnaire</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Aggress Behav</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>268</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ab.10047</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0057">
        <label>57.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>International Labour Office</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">ISCO-88 International Standard Classification of Occupation</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International Labour Office</publisher-name>; <year>1990</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0058">
        <label>58.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Achenbach</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rescorla</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Manual for the ASEBA Preschool Forms and Profiles</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Burlington, VT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Vermont</publisher-name>; <year>2000</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0059">
        <label>59.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><article-title>Mplus version 7.4 [computer program]</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Muthén &amp; Muthén</publisher-name>; <year>1998</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0060">
        <label>60.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sterne</surname>
<given-names>JAC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>White</surname>
<given-names>IR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carlin</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Multiple imputation for missing data in epidemiological and clinical research: potential and pitfalls</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>338</volume>(<issue>jun29 1</issue>):<fpage>b2393</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.b2393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19564179</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0061">
        <label>61.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jung</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wickrama</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>An introduction to latent class growth analysis and growth mixture modeling</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Soc Personal Psychol Compass</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>302</fpage>–<lpage>317</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1751-9004.2007.00054.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0062">
        <label>62.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Oberski</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <chapter-title>Mixture models: latent profile and latent class analysis</chapter-title> In: <source><italic toggle="yes">Modern Statistical Methods for HCI</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>; <year>2016</year>:<fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>287</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0063">
        <label>63.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nylund</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Asparouhov</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Muthén</surname>
<given-names>BO</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Deciding on the number of classes in latent class analysis and growth mixture modeling: a Monte Carlo simulation study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Struct Equ Modeling</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>535</fpage>–<lpage>569</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10705510701575396</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0064">
        <label>64.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>M-C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deng</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bi</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ye</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Performance of the entropy as an index of classification accuracy in latent profile analysis: a Monte Carlo simulation study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Psychol Sin</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1473</fpage>–<lpage>1482</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0065">
        <label>65.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Seegers</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Touchette</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dionne</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Short persistent sleep duration is associated with poor receptive vocabulary performance in middle childhood</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>325</fpage>–<lpage>332</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26781184</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0066">
        <label>66.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Seegers</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petit</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Falissard</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Short sleep duration and body mass index: a prospective longitudinal study in preadolescence</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>173</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>621</fpage>–<lpage>629</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwq389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21303806</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0067">
        <label>67.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Goodwin</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Silva</surname>
<given-names>GE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaemingk</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sherrill</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morgan</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quan</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Comparison between reported and recorded total sleep time and sleep latency in 6-to 11-year-old children: the Tucson children’s assessment of sleep apnea study (TuCASA)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-006-0086-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17165092</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0068">
        <label>68.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Allik</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Larsson</surname>
<given-names>J-O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smedje</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep patterns of school-age children with asperger syndrome or high-functioning autism</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Autism Dev Disord</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>585</fpage>–<lpage>595</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10803-006-0099-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16617404</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0069">
        <label>69.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hirshkowitz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whiton</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Albert</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>National sleep foundation’s updated sleep duration recommendations: final report</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Health</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>243</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleh.2015.10.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29073398</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0070">
        <label>70.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zinkhan</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berger</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hense</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Agreement of different methods for assessing sleep characteristics: a comparison of two actigraphs, wrist and hip placement, and self-report with polysomnography</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1107</fpage>–<lpage>1114</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2014.04.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25018025</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0071">
        <label>71.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sadeh</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gruber</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raviv</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effects of sleep restriction and extension on school-age children: what a difference an hour makes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Child Dev</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>74</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>444</fpage>–<lpage>455</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1467-8624.7402008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12705565</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0072">
        <label>72.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Santucci</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Silk</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shaw</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gentzler</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fox</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kovacs</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Vagal tone and temperament as predictors of emotion regulation strategies in young children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Dev Psychobiol</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>216</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dev.20283</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18335488</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0073">
        <label>73.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wilson</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lumeng</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaciroti</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep hygiene practices and bedtime resistance in low-income preschoolers: does temperament matter?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>412</fpage>–<lpage>423</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15402002.2014.940104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25221914</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0074">
        <label>74.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gradisar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gardner</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dohnt</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Recent worldwide sleep patterns and problems during adolescence: a review and meta-analysis of age, region, and sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>110</fpage>–<lpage>118</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2010.11.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21257344</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0075">
        <label>75.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kalmbach</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cuamatzi-Castelan</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tonnu</surname>
<given-names>CV</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Hyperarousal and sleep reactivity in insomnia: current insights</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Sci Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>201</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S138823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30046255</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0076">
        <label>76.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bélanger</surname>
<given-names>M-È</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bernier</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simard</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bordeleau</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carrier</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
<suffix>VIII</suffix></string-name>. <article-title>Attachment and sleep among toddlers: disentangling attachment security and dependency</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Monogr Soc Res Child Dev</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>80</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>140</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mono.12148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25704739</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0077">
        <label>77.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bartel</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gradisar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williamson</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Protective and risk factors for adolescent sleep: a meta-analytic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>72</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2014.08.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25444442</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0078">
        <label>78.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mindell</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meltzer</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carskadon</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chervin</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Developmental aspects of sleep hygiene: findings from the 2004 national sleep foundation sleep in America poll</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>771</fpage>–<lpage>779</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2008.07.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19285450</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0079">
        <label>79.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sadeh</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cognitive–behavioral treatment for childhood sleep disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Psychol Rev</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>612</fpage>–<lpage>628</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cpr.2005.04.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15979219</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0080">
        <label>80.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kendall</surname>
<given-names>PC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Flannery-Schroeder</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Panichelli-Mindel</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Southam-Gerow</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Henin</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Warman</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Therapy for youths with anxiety disorders: a second randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Consult Clin Psychol</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>366</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0022-006X.65.3.366</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0081">
        <label>81.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jenni</surname>
<given-names>OG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Connor</surname>
<given-names>BB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Children’s sleep: an interplay between culture and biology</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatrics</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>115</volume>(<issue>1 Suppl</issue>):<fpage>204</fpage>–<lpage>216</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2004-0815B</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15866854</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
