<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33737848</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7961129</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">297707</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S297707</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Moderating Effect of BMI on the Relationship Between Sympathetic Activation and Blood Pressure in Males with Obstructive Sleep Apnea</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Chen et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Chen et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1884-4960</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Baixin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Somers</surname>
            <given-names>Virend K</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0003">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tang</surname>
            <given-names>Xiangdong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0004">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6276-9104</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Yun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label>Department of Sleep Medicine, <institution>Shantou University Mental Health Center, Shantou University Medical College</institution>, <addr-line>Shantou</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label>Sleep Medicine Center, <institution>Shantou University Medical College</institution>, <addr-line>Shantou</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label>Department of Cardiovascular Medicine, <institution>Mayo Clinic</institution>, <addr-line>Rochester</addr-line>, <addr-line>MN</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label>Sleep Medicine Center, Translational Neuroscience Center, West China Hospital, <institution>Sichuan University</institution>, <addr-line>Chengdu</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Yun Li <institution>Department of Sleep Medicine, Shantou University Mental Health Center, Shantou University Medical College</institution>, <addr-line>Shantou</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country> Email s_liyun@stu.edu.cn</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>11</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>13</volume>
      <fpage>339</fpage>
      <lpage>348</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2020</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2021 Chen et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Chen et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Background</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Sympathetic activation is a primary mechanism mediating increased blood pressure (BP) in obstructive sleep apnea (OSA). However, the relationships between overweight/obesity, sympathetic activation and BP in OSA are not well understood. We hypothesized that increased sympathetic drive is associated with increased BP in normal weight, but not in overweight/obese males with OSA. We therefore examined the effects of body mass index (BMI) on the association between sympathetic activation and BP in males with OSA.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We studied 115 males with OSA recruited consecutively from clinic. Twenty-four-hour urinary norepinephrine was used to assess sympathetic activation. Blood pressure was measured both in the evening and in the morning. Hypertension was defined based on either BP measurements or an existing diagnosis. Linear and logistic regressions were conducted to examine the associations between sympathetic activation and both BP and risk of hypertension.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We found 24-hour urinary norepinephrine levels were associated with systolic and diastolic BP (SBP, β=0.157, p=0.082; DBP, β=0.212, p=0.023) and mean arterial pressure (MAP, β=0.198, p=0.032) after adjusting for confounders. Interestingly, these associations were modified by overweight/obesity. After adjusting for confounders, increased 24-hour urinary norepinephrine levels were significantly associated with elevated SBP (β=0.454, p=0.012), DBP (β=0.399, p=0.041), and MAP (β=0.432, p=0.023) in normal weight, but not in overweight/obese patients (all p&gt;0.2). Similar findings were observed in the associations between 24-hour urinary norepinephrine levels and hypertension.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sympathetic activation is associated with elevated BP in normal weight but not in overweight/obese males with OSA, suggesting that BMI may moderate the association between sympathetic activation and BP in males with OSA.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>obesity</kwd>
        <kwd>overweight</kwd>
        <kwd>sympathetic activation</kwd>
        <kwd>blood pressure</kwd>
        <kwd>hypertension</kwd>
        <kwd>obstructive sleep apnea</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
            <institution-wrap>
              <institution>the National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution>
            </institution-wrap>
          </funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
            <institution-wrap>
              <institution>the Guangdong High-level University Development Program and Department of Educational of Guangdong Province</institution>
            </institution-wrap>
          </funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
            <institution-wrap>
              <institution>2020 Li Ka Shing Foundation Cross-Disciplinary Research Grant</institution>
            </institution-wrap>
          </funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>This study was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No.81970087), Grant for Key Disciplinary Project of Clinical Medicine under the Guangdong High-level University Development Program and Department of Educational of Guangdong Province (2017KTSCX065) and 2020 Li Ka Shing Foundation Cross-Disciplinary Research Grant (2020LKSFG05B).</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="2"/>
        <table-count count="6"/>
        <ref-count count="49"/>
        <page-count count="10"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) is highly prevalent in the general population, affecting approximately 20–30% of males and 10–15% of females.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The association of OSA with cardiovascular comorbidities, such as hypertension, is well established. Approximately 50% of patients with OSA are hypertensive</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and a dose–response relationship between OSA severity and the prevalence of hypertension has been observed.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sympathetic activation, independent of obesity,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> has been reported as the primary mechanisms for acute increases in blood pressure in patients with OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Increased sympathetic outflow, measured as muscle sympathetic nerve activity (MSNA) and urinary and plasma catecholamines, may also contribute importantly to longer term increases in blood pressure. Increases in both nocturnal (apneic)</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and diurnal (non-apneic) sympathetic activity</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> are evident in patients with OSA. Acute sympathetic activation during apneic sleep leads to blood pressure surges at the end of apneic events</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and chronic persistent sympathetic activation during normoxic wakefulness is accompanied by sustained increases in blood pressure and in likelihood of hypertension.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Conversely, heightened nocturnal and diurnal sympathetic activation, as well as increased blood pressure, were attenuated by treatment of OSA using nasal continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Obesity and sympathetic activation are closely linked and both conditions are associated with increased risk for hypertension.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> However, previous findings have suggested that sympathetic activity differs in normal weight and obese essential hypertension patients.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In normal weight essential hypertension, the total spillover of norepinephrine to plasma is increased and higher than in obesity hypertension.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Furthermore, it has been reported that body mass index (BMI) moderated the association between urinary norepinephrine and blood pressure in women without OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Weber et al reported that the cardiovascular characteristics of lean hypertensive patients were more dependent on catecholamines compared to obese patients.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Taken together, it appears that obese hypertensive patients might be spared the toxic effects of sympathetic activation. OSA and obesity are highly associated</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and sympathetic activation has been proposed as an underlying mechanism for hypertension in OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, whether heightened sympathetic activity has more striking pressor consequences in normal weight versus overweight/obese patients with OSA remains unknown.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We therefore sought to examine the effects of BMI on the association between sympathetic activation and blood pressure in males with OSA. Specifically, we hypothesized that increased sympathetic drive is associated with increased blood pressure in normal weight, but not in overweight/obese males with OSA.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Subjects</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We studied 115 male adults (age≥18 years) who had a diagnosis of OSA. The subjects were consecutively recruited from the Sleep Disorders Clinic. All subjects were interviewed following a comprehensive questionnaire, which provided a history of sleep complaints, general health, and medication use. Obstructive sleep apnea was defined as an apnea-hypopnea index (AHI) ≥5 events/hour based on an overnight polysomnography (PSG) recording.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Exclusion criteria included a history of type 2 diabetes mellitus, coronary artery disease, other sleep disorders (ie, insomnia, narcolepsy, periodic limb movement disorder, and circadian disorder), and/or psychiatric disorders (ie, major depression, panic disorder, generalized anxiety disorder or substance abuse), and use of medications or supplements that may affect sympathetic activity (ie, steroids, serotonin-norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors and amphetamines, etc.). Patients were also excluded if they had previously received treatment of OSA such as CPAP and oral appliances. Because this study did not involve any potential harmful examination or intervention, a verbal informed consent was conducted instead of in a written form. Prior to the enrollment, a verbal informed consent was obtained from each participant and the information was documented in each patient’s medical record by researchers. The study and verbal informed consent were approved by the Institutional Review Board of Shantou University Mental Health Center (SUMHC 20190604). This study complied with the Declaration of Helsinki.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Power calculation revealed that with a sample size of 29 normal weight and 86 overweight/obese patients, there was 72% statistical power to reject the null hypothesis and detect a significant difference of regression coefficients of 24-hour urinary norepinephrine on blood pressure between normal weight and overweight/obese patients with alpha set at 0.05 (PASS 15.0.5, NCSS, Kaysville, Utah).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Sleep Laboratory</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All potential participants were evaluated for an overnight PSG in the sleep laboratory in sound-attenuated, light- and temperature-controlled rooms. During this evaluation, subjects were allowed to sleep ad libitum based on their habitual sleep time, with the recording time ranging from 22:00–23:00 to 6:00–7:00. Subjects were continuously monitored with 16-channel polygraphs, including the electroencephalogram, electrooculogram, electromyogram, and electrocardiogram. All polysomnography measures were analyzed and scored according to the international criteria of the American Academy of Sleep Medicine.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Mild, moderate and severe OSAs were defined based on AHI=5–14.9/hour, 15–29.9/hour and ≥30/hour, respectively.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Body mass index was calculated as weight (kg) divided by the square of height (m), which were measured by a nurse as part of the physical examination. Overweight/obesity was defined as BMI≥25 kg/m</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and normal weight was defined as BMI=18.5–24.9 kg/m</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS) was used to assess daytime sleepiness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Twenty-Four-Hour Urinary Norepinephrine</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Twenty-four-hour urinary norepinephrine was used to assess sympathetic activity. From 3 days prior to urine collection till its completion, participants were instructed to avoid vigorous exercise, smoking and certain foods (ie, coffee, tea, chocolate, bananas) which could affect norepinephrine levels. On the day of PSG recording, participants were asked to collect complete 24-hour urine specimens. Urine samples were collected in polyethylene bottles containing 25 mL of 0.6 mol/L hydrochloric acid. After the total volume of 24-hour urine collection was measured, 20-mL aliquots were frozen at −80</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>°</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">C until being assayed. Urine volume and creatinine were measured to confirm the completeness of each collection. To exclude demonstrable inaccuracy of norepinephrine measures, samples were excluded if their 24-hour urine volume was &lt;400 mL. Urinary norepinephrine was measured by radioimmunoassay.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Higher levels of 24-hour urinary norepinephrine indicate higher levels of sympathetic activity during a 24-hour period. The sensitivity for 24-hour urinary norepinephrine was ±1.1 ug.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Blood Pressure Measurement</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Blood pressure was measured at 2 time points: in the evening prior to the PSG recording (20:00 to 21:00) and in the morning right after the end of PSG recording (6:00 to 7:00). After at least 10 minutes of rest in the supine position, blood pressure was recorded as the average of 3 consecutive readings during a 5-minute period. An electronic sphygmomanometer (Omron, HEM-7136) with the accuracy of ±3 mm Hg, which was checked against a mercury sphygmomanometer at least once a month, was used for blood pressure measurements. Mean arterial pressure (MAP) was calculated as (systolic blood pressure [SBP] + 2* diastolic blood pressure [DBP])/3.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The mean values of SBP, DBP, and MAP were calculated as (evening BP values + morning BP values)/2 and were used for statistical analyses. Hypertension was defined as: 1) the mean value of evening and morning DBP ≥90 mm Hg or the mean value of evening and morning SBP ≥140 mm Hg,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> or 2) a self-report of history of a hypertension diagnosis by a physician or using antihypertensive medication.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Data are presented as the mean±standard deviation for continuous variables and percentage for categorical variables. Bivariate comparisons between groups were performed using independent </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-test or Mann–Whitney </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>U</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">-test for normally and non-normally distributed continuous variables, respectively, or using χ</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> test for categorical variables.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In order to examine the association between 24-hour urinary norepinephrine and blood pressure, we conducted 3 linear regression models with 24-hour urinary norepinephrine values as predictors and mean values of SBP, DBP and MAP at evening and morning as outcomes, respectively. Given that there are clear associations between blood pressures and age, overweight/obesity, and use of antihypertensive medications, age, overweight/obesity, and use of antihypertensive medications were always entered in the models as covariates using a forced entry method, while other relevant demographic, nighttime sleep and daytime sleepiness covariates (p-value of the comparison between subjects with and without hypertension ≤0.1, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) were entered using a backward conditional method. As the severity of OSA may affect the association between 24-hour urinary norepinephrine levels and blood pressure, we further adjusted for AHI as sensitivity analyses. Due to the strong correlation between AHI and minimum oxygen saturation (min SaO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, r=−0.604, p&lt;0.001), we did not include AHI and min SaO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> in regression models simultaneously. Thus, we first adjusted min SaO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> and then conducted sensitivity analyses with AHI as a covariate in regression models to control for the severity of OSA. To assess the potential BMI effects on the association between 24-hour norepinephrine levels and blood pressure in OSA, we further conducted linear regression models to examine these associations in normal weight (BMI&lt;25 kg/m</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) and overweight/obese patients with OSA (BMI≥25 kg/m</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) after adjusting for potential confounders, respectively. Logistic regression models with 24-hour urinary norepinephrine levels as predictors and hypertension as outcome were provided as secondary analyses to examine BMI effects on the association between 24-hour urinary norepinephrine levels and hypertension in normal weight and overweight/obese patients with OSA, respectively. Similar to linear regression models, age was always entered in these models as a covariate using a forced entry method, while other relevant demographic, nighttime sleep and daytime sleepiness covariates (p-value of the comparison between subjects with and without hypertension ≤0.1, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) were entered in the models using a backward conditional method. Furthermore, binary correlation analyses were conducted to examine the correlations between 24-hour urinary norepinephrine levels and sleep parameters, including sleep onset latency, total sleep time, sleep efficiency, wake time after sleep onset, percentages of non-rapid eye movement (NREM) sleep stage 1, stage 2, stage 3, and rapid eye movement (REM) sleep, AHI, and min SaO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. The level of p&lt;0.05 was used to determine statistical significance. All analyses were conducted using SPSS 23.0 (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap id="t0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Demographic, Clinical and Sleep Characteristics of Study Sample</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall N=115</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal-Weight N=29</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overweight/Obesity N=86</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No Hypertension N=49</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension N=66</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (year)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.72±8.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.38±8.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.84±8.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.810</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.79±7.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.33±9.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.32±3.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.46±1.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.62±2.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.27±3.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.38±2.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.845</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBP (mm Hg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">126.39±15.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">124.23±17.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">127.11±14.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.560</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">117.88±9.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">138.10±14.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DBP (mm Hg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.10±11.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.17±13.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.10±11.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.130</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.83±7.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.72±11.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAP (mm Hg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.20±12.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.55±14.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.10±11.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.221</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.18±7.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107.85±11.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM-SBP (mm Hg) *</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">124.47±13.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">122.29±16.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125.22±12.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.618</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">117.88±9.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">140.02±10.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM-DBP (mm Hg) *</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.28±11.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.96±11.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.42±10.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.163</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.83±7.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.13±8.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM-MAP (mm Hg) *</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.01±11.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.07±13.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.02±10.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.261</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.18±7.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110.76±7.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (57.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (55.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (58.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.780</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (100)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoke (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (55.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (62.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (53.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.421</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (57.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (54.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.782</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep onset latency (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.56±14.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.95±10.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.43±15.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.146</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.81±15.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.22±12.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.830</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total sleep time (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">436.48±61.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">425.10±51.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">440.32±64.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.252</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">439.17±57.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">432.86±67.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.589</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep efficiency (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.26±9.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.81±8.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.09±10.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.67±8.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.72±10.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.611</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NREM sleep stage 1 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.14±21.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.87±19.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.57±21.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.807</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.94±20.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.11±21.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.209</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NREM sleep stage 2 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.18±17.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.37±16.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.78±17.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.668</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.69±17.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.79±16.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.054</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NREM sleep stage 3 (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.33±5.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.69±5.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.21±5.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.624</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.50±5.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.11±5.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.582</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM sleep (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.34±6.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.05±5.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.44±6.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.770</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.86±6.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.98±6.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.568</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wake time after sleep onset (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.29±48.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.53±40.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.16±50.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.32±46.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.94±52.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.619</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI (event/hour)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.82±23.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.71±23.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.56±23.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.29±24.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.88±23.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.428</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum SaO<sub>2</sub> (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.00±18.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.10±19.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.28±18.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.47±15.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.33±21.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.077</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESS scores</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.72±5.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.31±4.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.53±5.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.76±5.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.02±5.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24-hour urinary norepinephrine (ug/day)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.02±26.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.77±28.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.13±25.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.46±22.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.81±30.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.127</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Data are presented as mean ±standard deviation for continuous variables, and sample size (percentage) for categorical variables. *There are 94 subjects not on antihypertensive medication, including 70 normal-weight and 24 overweight/obese patients, and 66 non-hypertensive and 28 hypertensive patients. Overweight/obesity was defined as a body mass index≥25 kg/m</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> AHI, apnea hypopnea index; BMI, body mass index; DBP, diastolic blood pressure; ESS, Epworth Sleepiness Scale; MAP, mean arterial pressure; NM-DBP, diastolic blood pressure in subjects not on antihypertensive medication; NM-SBP, systolic blood pressure in subjects not on antihypertensive medication; NM-MAP, mean arterial pressure in subjects not on antihypertensive medication; NREM, non-rapid eye movement; REM, rapid eye movement; SaO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, oxygen saturation; SBP, systolic blood pressure.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">A total of 115 male patients with OSA with a mean age of 43.72 ± 8.80 years (range: 21 to 64) and mean BMI of 27.32 ± 3.06 kg/m</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> (range: 18.52 to 36.23) were included. Twenty-nine patients were normal-weight and 86 patients were overweight/obese. Of these, 7 patients had mild, 16 patients had moderate, and 94 patients had severe OSA, respectively. Demographic, clinical, sleep, and 24-hour urinary norepinephrine measures of the whole study sample, as well as the overweight/obese and hypertension subgroups, are presented in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In linear regression models, increased levels of 24-hour urinary norepinephrine were significantly associated with higher DBP (β=0.212, p=0.023) and MAP (β=0.198, p=0.032) after adjusting for age, antihypertensive medication use, overweight/obesity, min SaO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, percentage of NREM sleep stage 2 and total scores of ESS (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). The association between 24-hour urinary norepinephrine and SBP was marginally significant (β=0.157, p=0.082, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). Sensitivity analyses showed that findings were similar and in the same direction after adjusting AHI instead of min SaO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap id="t0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Association Between 24-Hour Norepinephrine Levels and Blood Pressure in Males with Obstructive Sleep Apnea</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Overall*</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Normal-Weight<sup>†</sup></th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Overweight/Obesity<sup>†</sup></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">β</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interaction p<sup>‡</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">β</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">β</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="11" rowspan="1"><bold>SBP (mm Hg)</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24-hour urinary norepinephrine (ug)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.093</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.157</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.082</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.277</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.454</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.909</td></tr><tr><td colspan="11" rowspan="1"><bold>DBP (mm Hg)</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24-hour urinary norepinephrine (ug)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.212</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.140</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.182</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.399</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.060</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.133</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.223</td></tr><tr><td colspan="11" rowspan="1"><bold>MAP (mm Hg)</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24-hour urinary norepinephrine (ug)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.095</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.198</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.213</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.432</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.089</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.407</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> *The linear regression models in overall samples were adjusted for age, overweight/obesity, antihypertensive medications use, minimum oxygen saturation, Epworth Sleepiness Scale scores, and percentage of non-rapid eye movement sleep stage 2. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>†</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The linear regression models in normal weight and overweight patients with OSA were adjusted for age, antihypertensive medications use, minimum oxygen saturation, Epworth Sleepiness Scale scores, and percentage of non-rapid eye movement sleep stage 2. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>‡</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The p values of interaction between 24-hour urinary norepinephrine and overweight/obesity. Overweight/obesity was defined as a body mass index≥25 kg/m</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> B, unstandardized coefficients; β, standardized coefficients; DBP, diastolic blood pressure; MAP, mean arterial pressure; SBP, systolic blood pressure.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We further examined the effects of BMI on the association between 24-hour urinary norepinephrine and blood pressure. Interestingly, we found that the association between 24-hour urinary norepinephrine and blood pressure was modified by overweight/obesity. Interactions between 24-hour urinary norepinephrine and overweight/obesity on SBP (interaction-p=0.009) and MAP (interaction-p=0.046), as well as DBP (interaction-p=0.140) were significant and marginally significant, respectively. As showed in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, after adjusting for age, antihypertensive medication use, min SaO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">, percentage of NREM sleep stage 2, and total scores of ESS, increased 24-hour urinary norepinephrine was significantly associated with higher SBP (β=0.454, p=0.012), DBP (β=0.399, p=0.041), and MAP (β=0.432, p=0.023) in normal-weight male patients with OSA, but not in overweight/obese patients (all p&gt;0.2). As shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1A</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">, each 10 ug rise in 24-hour urinary norepinephrine was associated with 2.77 and 0.07 mm Hg rise in SBP (p=0.009), 1.82 and 0.60 mm Hg rise in DBP (p=0.140), and 2.13 and 0.42 mm Hg rise in MAP (p=0.046) in normal-weight and overweight/obese male patients with OSA, respectively. Sensitivity analyses showed that findings were similar and in the same direction after adjusting AHI instead of min SaO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">(</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) Blood pressure increase for each 10 ug rise in 24-hour urinary norepinephrine levels in normal-weight and overweight/obese male patients with obstructive sleep apnea. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) Odds ratios of hypertension for each 10 ug rise in 24-hour urinary norepinephrine levels in normal-weight and overweight/obese male patients with obstructive sleep apnea.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-339-g0001"/><attrib><bold>Notes:</bold> *P&lt;0.05. Error bars indicate standard error. Overweight/obesity was defined as a body mass index≥25 kg/m<sup>2</sup>. All data were adjusted for age, antihypertensive medication use, minimum oxygen saturation, percentage of non-rapid eye movement sleep stage 2, and total scores of Epworth Sleepiness Scale.</attrib><attrib><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> DBP, diastolic blood pressure; MAP, mean arterial pressure; SBP, systolic blood pressure.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In secondary analyses, we used logistic regression models to examine BMI effects on the association between 24-hour urinary norepinephrine and hypertension in normal-weight and overweight/obese male patients with OSA, respectively. As shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1B</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, after adjusting for age, min SaO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">, percentage of NREM sleep stage 2, and total scores of ESS, each 10 ug rise in 24-hour urinary norepinephrine was significantly associated with 2.32-fold increased odds for hypertension in normal-weight male patients with OSA (adjusted OR=2.33, 95% CI=1.06 to 5.09, p=0.034), but not in overweight/obese patients (adjusted OR=0.98, 95% CI=0.81 to 1.18, p=0.849). Interaction between 24-hour urinary norepinephrine and overweight/obesity on hypertension was significant (interaction-p=0.022). Sensitivity analyses showed that these findings were similar and in the same direction after adjusting for AHI instead of min SaO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">As shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2A</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, 24-hour urinary norepinephrine levels were significantly higher in normal-weight male patients with OSA and hypertension compared to those without hypertension (p=0.035) after adjusting for age, min SaO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">, percentage of NREM sleep stage 2 and total scores of ESS. However, among those overweight/obese patients with OSA, no significant difference in 24-hour urinary norepinephrine levels was observed between patients with and without hypertension (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2B</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, p=0.664).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">(</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) Twenty-four-hour urinary norepinephrine levels in normal-weight male OSA patients with and without hypertension. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) Twenty-four-hour urinary norepinephrine levels in overweight/obese male OSA patients with and without hypertension.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-339-g0002"/><attrib><bold>Notes:</bold> Error bars indicate standard error. Overweight/obesity was defined as a body mass index ≥25 kg/m<sup>2</sup>. HT=hypertension; OSA=obstructive sleep apnea. All data were adjusted for age, minimum oxygen saturation, percentage of non-rapid eye movement sleep stage 2, and total scores of Epworth Sleepiness Scale.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">As shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=297707.docx">Supplemental Table 1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, among overweight/obese OSA patients, correlations between levels of 24-hour urinary norepinephrine and percentage of REM sleep (r=0.242, p=0.025) and min SaO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> (r=−0.211, p=0.051) were significant, while no significant correlation was observed between levels of 24-hour urinary norepinephrine and other sleep parameters (all p-values&gt;0.1). No significant correlation was observed between levels of 24-hour urinary norepinephrine and any sleep parameters in normal-weight OSA patients (all p-values&gt;0.07).</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">To our knowledge, this is the first study examining moderating effects of BMI on the association between sympathetic activation and blood pressure in males with OSA. Our data suggest that sympathetic activation is differentially associated with elevated blood pressure in OSA, with this association only evident in normal-weight, but not in overweight/obese males with OSA.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sympathetic activation has been proposed as one of the primary pathways of OSA related hypertension.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In contrast to normal sleep, sympathetic activity as well as blood pressure does not fall during sleep in patients with OSA due to repetitive episodes of hypoxia and arousal induced by respiratory events during sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> These high levels of sympathetic activity are sustained into wakefulness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In the current study, we found increased 24-hour urinary norepinephrine was independently and significantly associated with elevated blood pressure in patients with OSA, which was consistent with previous findings.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, this relationship was evident only in normal-weight, but not in overweight/obese patients with OSA.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Although obesity is a major risk factor for OSA and hypertension, up to 36–74% patients with OSA may not be obese.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23–26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Evidence from previous studies showed a dose–response relationship between the severity of untreated OSA and risk of hypertension, and this association was independent of obesity.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Similarly, heightened sympathetic drive is present in patients with OSA independent of obesity.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Our data show that increased sympathetic activity was associated with elevated blood pressure and increased risk of hypertension in normal-weight, but not overweight/obese patients with OSA. These findings suggest that sympathetic activation is likely to be a key mechanism mediating OSA-related hypertension in normal-weight patients with OSA.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The mechanisms mediating the more potent pressor effect of sympathetic activation on blood pressure in normal-weight patients with OSA are unclear. It has been demonstrated that the patterns of sympathetic activation differ in normal-weight and obesity-related hypertension.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The firing rate of single vasoconstrictor nerve fibers is increased in normal-weight essential hypertension subjects, whereas it is normal in obese subjects regardless of their prevailing blood pressure despite the total multiunit MSNA being elevated.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> It appears that previously silent nerve fibers are recruited in obesity, but they do not subserve vasoconstriction. Furthermore, sustained elevation of MSNA in obesity might lead to downregulation of α-adrenergic receptors and reduction of sympathetic vascular tone.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In support of this, it has been reported that the reflex sympathetic responses during baroreceptor stimulation and deactivation induced by intravenous infusions of phenylephrine and nitroprusside were preserved in normal-weight hypertensive subjects but reduced in obese hypertensive subjects.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> As for obesity-related hypertension, it may be related to several collective mechanisms other than sympathetic drive, such as systemic inflammation,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> insulin resistance,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> increased levels of leptin,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and activation of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In addition, there may be a “ceiling effect”, where the rise in blood pressure is finite, and addition of further pressor mechanisms above and beyond a certain level, does not result in further substantial blood pressure increase. Thus, given the multifactorial contribution to elevated blood pressure in obese patients with OSA, the redundancy in mechanisms driving higher blood pressure may blur any individual contribution of sympathetic activation. Indeed, compared to normal-weight patients with OSA, overweight/obese patients are reported to have greater likelihood of objective daytime sleepiness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> We recently found that OSA with objective daytime sleepiness was associated with systemic inflammation</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> and increased risk for hypertension.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, we did not assess measures of systemic inflammation in the current study to further examine this hypothesis.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In a recent meta-analysis, sympathetic activity was evaluated in 1438 obese or overweight subjects without hypertension and metabolic syndrome, and MSNA was noted to be significantly greater in overweight and obese individuals compared to normal weight subjects.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Consistent with the findings of this meta-analysis, we found that overweight/obese patients had higher 24-hour urinary norepinephrine compared to normal weight patients, independent of blood pressure status. The increased sympathetic activation in obese subjects might conceivably be mediated by hyperinsulinemia,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> hyperleptinemia</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and/or baroreflex impairment</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> in obesity. In another study in 10 obese normotensive OSA patients, Marrone et al reported that one night CPAP therapy had significant effects on normalizing blood pressure oscillations whereas it did not have any effect on decreasing nocturnal urinary norepinephrine levels.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Taken together, it appears that the association of sympathetic overactivation and elevated blood pressure may be only present in normotensive, normal weight OSA patients. Future studies should be conducted to examine this hypothesis.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our findings have several important clinical implications, suggesting that the underlying mechanisms driving OSA-related hypertension in normal-weight and overweight/obese subjects might be different. Thus, in order to prevent and improve OSA-related hypertension, treatments for normal-weight patients with OSA should target reductions in sympathetic activity levels (ie, CPAP or renal sympathetic denervation),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> while weight loss interventions should be emphasized in addition to CPAP treatment for overweight/obese patients with OSA. Indeed, regarding the former, prior studies strongly suggest that the blood pressure lowering effects of renal sympathetic denervation are especially evident in resistant hypertensive patients with co-morbid OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Our results also provide support for individualized antihypertensive medication in patients with OSA-related hypertension. For example, central sympathetic inhibitors and/or β-adrenergic blockade combined with CPAP treatment might provide selective cardiovascular benefit in normal-weight patients with OSA-related hypertension. As for overweight/obese hypertensive OSA patients, diuretics and RAAS blockers combined with CPAP treatment might possibly produce greater antihypertensive effects.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Strengths of our study include the measurement of sympathetic drive using 24-hour urinary norepinephrine. Because the norepinephrine levels are easily influenced by stress, and their moment-to-moment variation is great due to the very short half-life in plasma (only 2 to 3 minutes),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> we used 24-hour urinary norepinephrine to assess overall systemic sympathetic drive, rather than use a single measurement of plasma norepinephrine or the direct measurement of sympathetic nerve traffic via microneurography. Furthermore, compared to the direct measurement of sympathetic nerve traffic via microneurography, 24-hour urinary norepinephrine is a noninvasive, convenient and easy operative measure in clinical practice. However, several limitations should be acknowledged. First, we only included male patients with OSA in this study and our findings cannot be generalized to females with OSA. However, gender differences in sympathetic activation</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and OSA-related cardiometabolic outcomes</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> have been well established. Further studies should be conducted to examine the BMI effects on the association between sympathetic activation and blood pressure in females with OSA. Second, we did not examine daytime and nighttime urinary norepinephrine separately. However, 24-hour urinary norepinephrine is a valid surrogate marker of 24-hour sympathetic activity. Third, the lack of data regarding adherence and types of antihypertensive medications prevented further analyses of their impact on blood pressure. In mitigation, this may have negligible effects on the results because our statistical models have been adjusted for “presence or absence of antihypertensive medications” and the findings remained similar after excluding 21 patients on antihypertensive medications. Finally, we did not perform ambulatory blood pressure monitoring or examine CPAP treatment effects on sympathetic activity and blood pressure in normal-weight and overweight/obese males with OSA. Future randomized controlled trials using ambulatory blood pressure monitoring should be conducted.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In conclusion, sympathetic activation was associated with increased blood pressure as well as higher odds for hypertension in normal-weight, but not in overweight/obese male patients with OSA. These findings suggest that BMI may moderate the association between sympathetic activation and blood pressure in males with OSA.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors thank the sleep technicians and staff of the Sleep Medicine Center at the Shantou University Medical College for their support with this project.</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">AHI, apnea-hypopnea index; BMI, body mass index; CPAP, continuous positive airway pressure; DBP, diastolic blood pressure; ESS, Epworth Sleepiness Scale; HT, hypertension; MAP, mean arterial pressure; Min SaO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, minimum oxygen saturation; MSNA, muscle sympathetic nerve activity; NM-DBP, diastolic blood pressure in patients not on antihypertensive medication; NM-SBP, systolic blood pressure in patients not on antihypertensive medication; NM-MAP, mean arterial pressure in patients not on antihypertensive medication; NREM, non-rapid eye movement; OR, odds ratio; OSA, obstructive sleep apnea.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007" sec-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All authors have seen and approved the manuscript. Dr. Somers has served as a consultant for Respicardia, Sleep Number, Baker Tilly and Jazz Pharmaceuticals. Dr Somers also reports grants from NIH, outside of the submitted work. Drs. Li, Chen and Tang have reported that no potential conflicts of interest exist with any companies/organizations whose products or services may be discussed in the article. The authors report no other conflicts of interest in this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Peppard</surname>
<given-names>PE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Young</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barnet</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Palta</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hagen</surname>
<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hla</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Increased prevalence of sleep-disordered breathing in adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>177</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1006</fpage>–<lpage>1014</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kws342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23589584</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Somers</surname>
<given-names>VK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>White</surname>
<given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amin</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep apnea and cardiovascular disease: an American heart association/American college of cardiology foundation scientific statement from the American heart association council for high blood pressure research professional education committee, council on clinical cardiology, stroke council, and council on cardiovascular nursing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>686</fpage>–<lpage>717</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2008.05.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18702977</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Peppard</surname>
<given-names>PE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Young</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Palta</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Skatrud</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prospective study of the association between sleep-disordered breathing and hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>342</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>1378</fpage>–<lpage>1384</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM200005113421901</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10805822</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Grassi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Facchini</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trevano</surname>
<given-names>FQ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea-dependent and -independent adrenergic activation in obesity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>321</fpage>–<lpage>325</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.HYP.0000174243.39897.6c</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15983234</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Venkataraman</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vungarala</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Covassin</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Somers</surname>
<given-names>VK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep apnea, hypertension and the sympathetic nervous system in the adult population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>591</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm9020591</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Narkiewicz</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van de Borne</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Montano</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dyken</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Phillips</surname>
<given-names>BG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Somers</surname>
<given-names>VK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Contribution of tonic chemoreflex activation to sympathetic activity and blood pressure in patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circulation</italic></source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>97</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>943</fpage>–<lpage>945</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.CIR.97.10.943</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9529260</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rumantir</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vaz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jennings</surname>
<given-names>GL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Neural mechanisms in human obesity-related hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Hypertens</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1125</fpage>–<lpage>1133</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004872-199917080-00012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10466468</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Landsberg</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Troisi</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parker</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Young</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weiss</surname>
<given-names>ST</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obesity, blood pressure, and the sympathetic nervous system</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>295</fpage>–<lpage>303</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/1047-2797(91)90040-J</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1669511</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Esler</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lambert</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schlaich</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dixon</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sari</surname>
<given-names>CI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lambert</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obesity paradox in hypertension: is this because sympathetic activation in obesity-hypertension takes a benign form?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.117.09790</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29158358</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Weber</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Neutel</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Contrasting clinical properties and exercise responses in obese and lean hypertensive patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0735-1097(00)01103-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11153733</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>van Berge-landry</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bovbjerg</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>James</surname>
<given-names>GD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Relationship between waking-sleep blood pressure and catecholamine changes in African-American and European-American women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Blood Press Monit</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>257</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MBP.0b013e3283078f45</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18799950</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">International Classification of Sleep Disorders</italic></source>. <edition>3rd</edition> ed. <publisher-loc>Darien, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</publisher-name>; <year>2014</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Berry</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Albertario</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harding</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <collab>for the American Academy of Sleep Medicine</collab>, et al. <source><italic toggle="yes">The AASM Manual for the Scoring of Sleep and Associated Events: Rules, Terminology and Technical Specifications. Version 2.5</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Darien, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</publisher-name>;<year>2018</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="web"><collab>World Health Organization</collab>. <article-title>Definition of obesity</article-title>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/topics/obesity/en/">https://www.who.int/topics/obesity/en/</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>3</month><day>1</day>, 2020</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Johns</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A new method for measuring daytime sleepiness: the Epworth sleepiness scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>540</fpage>–<lpage>545</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/14.6.540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1798888</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Raum</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Methods of plasma catecholamine measurement including radioimmunoassay</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Physiol</italic></source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>247</volume>(<issue>1 Pt 1</issue>):<fpage>E4</fpage>–<lpage>E12</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpendo.1984.247.1.E4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6742189</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hallisey</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Greenwood</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Beyond mean arterial pressure and lactate: perfusion end points for managing the shocked patient</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Emerg Med Clin North Am</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>395</fpage>–<lpage>408</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.emc.2019.03.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31262411</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>LS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>2010 Chinese guidelines for the management of hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Zhonghua Xin Xue Guan Bing Za Zhi</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>579</fpage>–<lpage>615</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22088239</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Somers</surname>
<given-names>VK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dyken</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clary</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abboud</surname>
<given-names>FM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sympathetic neural mechanisms in obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Invest</italic></source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>96</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1897</fpage>–<lpage>1904</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI118235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7560081</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Marrone</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Riccobono</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salvaggio</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mirabella</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bonanno</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bonsignore</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Catecholamines and blood pressure in obstructive sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>103</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>722</fpage>–<lpage>727</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.103.3.722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8449058</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Narkiewicz</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Somers</surname>
<given-names>VK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The sympathetic nervous system and obstructive sleep apnea: implications for hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Hypertens</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>12 Pt 2</issue>):<fpage>1613</fpage>–<lpage>1619</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004872-199715120-00062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9488212</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vardhan</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shanmuganandan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Hypertension and catecholamine levels in sleep apnoea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Med J Armed Forces India</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0377-1237(11)60128-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24669036</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vgontzas</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Mild-to-moderate sleep apnea is associated with incident hypertension: age effect</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>4</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsy265</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Quan</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Connor</surname>
<given-names>GT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quan</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of physical activity with sleep-disordered breathing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>157</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-006-0095-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17221274</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Young</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peppard</surname>
<given-names>PE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gottlieb</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Epidemiology of obstructive sleep apnea: a population health perspective</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>165</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1217</fpage>–<lpage>1239</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.2109080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11991871</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Duran</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Esnaola</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rubio</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Iztueta</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea-hypopnea and related clinical features in a population-based sample of subjects aged 30 to 70 yr</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>163</volume>(<issue>3 Pt 1</issue>):<fpage>685</fpage>–<lpage>689</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/ajrccm.163.3.2005065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11254524</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bixler</surname>
<given-names>EO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vgontzas</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of hypertension and sleep-disordered breathing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>160</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>2289</fpage>–<lpage>2295</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.160.15.2289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10927725</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Young</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peppard</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Palta</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Population-based study of sleep-disordered breathing as a risk factor for hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>157</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>1746</fpage>–<lpage>1752</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.1997.00440360178019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9250236</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Henderson</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macefield</surname>
<given-names>VG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnoea and hypertension: the role of the central nervous system</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Hypertens Rep</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>59</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11906-016-0665-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27278369</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lambert</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Straznicky</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schlaich</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Differing pattern of sympathoexcitation in normal-weight and obesity-related hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>862</fpage>–<lpage>868</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.107.094649</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17909120</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Agapitov</surname>
<given-names>AV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Correia</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sinkey</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haynes</surname>
<given-names>WG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dissociation between sympathetic nerve traffic and sympathetically mediated vascular tone in normotensive human obesity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>687</fpage>–<lpage>695</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.107.109603</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18695151</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Grassi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seravalle</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dell’Oro</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Turri</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bolla</surname>
<given-names>GB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mancia</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Adrenergic and reflex abnormalities in obesity-related hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>538</fpage>–<lpage>542</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.HYP.36.4.538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11040232</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Javaheri</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barbe</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Campos-Rodriguez</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep apnea: types, mechanisms, and clinical cardiovascular consequences</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>841</fpage>–<lpage>858</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2016.11.069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28209226</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Drager</surname>
<given-names>LF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Polotsky</surname>
<given-names>VY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Donnell</surname>
<given-names>CP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cravo</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lorenzi-Filho</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Machado</surname>
<given-names>BH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Translational approaches to understanding metabolic dysfunction and cardiovascular consequences of obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>309</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>H1101</fpage>–<lpage>H1111</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpheart.00094.2015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26232233</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Haynes</surname>
<given-names>WG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sivitz</surname>
<given-names>WI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morgan</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Walsh</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mark</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sympathetic and cardiorenal actions of leptin</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>3 Pt 2</issue>):<fpage>619</fpage>–<lpage>623</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.HYP.30.3.619</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9322991</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jin</surname>
<given-names>ZN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>YX</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Meta-analysis of effects of obstructive sleep apnea on the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Geriatr Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>333</fpage>–<lpage>343</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11909/j.issn.1671-5411.2016.03.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27403143</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vgontzas</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bixler</surname>
<given-names>EO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chrousos</surname>
<given-names>GP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obesity-related sleepiness and fatigue: the role of the stress system and cytokines</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann N Y Acad Sci</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>1083</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>329</fpage>–<lpage>344</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1196/annals.1367.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17148748</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vgontzas</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fernandez-Mendoza</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Objective, but not subjective, sleepiness is associated with inflammation in sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>2</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsw033</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ren</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Covassin</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Objective but not subjective short sleep duration is associated with hypertension in obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>610</fpage>–<lpage>617</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.118.11027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29987105</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Grassi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Biffi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seravalle</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sympathetic neural overdrive in the obese and overweight state</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>74</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>349</fpage>–<lpage>358</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.119.12885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31203727</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Da</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Do</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mouton</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hall</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Role of hyperinsulinemia and insulin resistance in hypertension: metabolic syndrome revisited</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Can J Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>671</fpage>–<lpage>682</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cjca.2020.02.066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32389340</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Phillips</surname>
<given-names>BG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kato</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Narkiewicz</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Choe</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Somers</surname>
<given-names>VK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Increases in leptin levels, sympathetic drive, and weight gain in obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>279</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>H234</fpage>–<lpage>H237</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpheart.2000.279.1.H234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10899061</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Narkiewicz</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pesek</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kato</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Phillips</surname>
<given-names>BG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davison</surname>
<given-names>DE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Somers</surname>
<given-names>VK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Baroreflex control of sympathetic nerve activity and heart rate in obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1039</fpage>–<lpage>1043</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.HYP.32.6.1039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9856970</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Warchol-Celinska</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Prejbisz</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kadziela</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Renal denervation in resistant hypertension and obstructive sleep apnea: randomized proof-of-concept phase II trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>390</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.118.11180</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29941516</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Witkowski</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Prejbisz</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Florczak</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of renal sympathetic denervation on blood pressure, sleep apnea course, and glycemic control in patients with resistant hypertension and sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>559</fpage>–<lpage>565</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.111.173799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21844482</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kalil</surname>
<given-names>GZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haynes</surname>
<given-names>WG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sympathetic nervous system in obesity-related hypertension: mechanisms and clinical implications</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertens Res</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>4</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/hr.2011.173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22048570</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Eisenberg</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zimlichman</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lavie</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Plasma norepinephrine levels in patients with sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>322</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>932</fpage>–<lpage>933</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2314430</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hinojosa-Laborde</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chapa</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lange</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haywood</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Gender differences in sympathetic nervous system regulation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Exp Pharmacol Physiol</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>122</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1440-1681.1999.02995.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10065332</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cano-Pumarega</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barbe</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Esteban</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martinez-Alonso</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Egea</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duran-Cantolla</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep apnea and hypertension: are there sex differences? The Vitoria sleep cohort</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>152</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>742</fpage>–<lpage>750</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chest.2017.03.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28300571</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
