<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34234597</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">8254410</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">312808</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S312808</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Dissociation of Subjective and Objective Alertness During Prolonged Wakefulness</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Hao et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Hao et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hao</surname>
            <given-names>Chao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Mingzhu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Luo</surname>
            <given-names>Wei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8225-2847</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Ma</surname>
            <given-names>Ning</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Key Laboratory of Brain, Cognition and Education Sciences (South China Normal University), Ministry of Education; Center for Sleep Research, Center for Studies of Psychological Application, Guangdong Key Laboratory of Mental Health and Cognitive Science, School of Psychology, South China Normal University</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>510631</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>School of Architecture and Urban Planning, Shenzhen University</institution>, <addr-line>Shenzhen</addr-line>, <addr-line>518060</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Ning Ma <institution>School of Psychology, South China Normal University</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>510631</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country> Email maning@m.scnu.edu.cn</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>13</volume>
      <fpage>923</fpage>
      <lpage>932</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2021 Hao et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Hao et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Background</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Although the deterioration of subjective and objective alertness during prolonged wakefulness has been investigated rigorously, whether perceived sleepiness and fatigue are consistent with actual decrements in behavioral performance in the time course is still disputed. The present study examined the dissociation between decrements of subjective alertness and performance deficits during prolonged wakefulness of one night and explored the relationship between body temperature and the impairments of subjective and objective alertness.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Participants and Methods</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Thirty-eight participants (27 females; age: 21.76 ± 2.37 years old) underwent prolonged wakefulness for one night at habitual bedtime (0:00–6:00 am). Participants completed a 10-min PVT to assess objective alertness, fatigue, and sleepiness ratings to assess subjective alertness every 2 hours, and body temperature was measured every hour during scheduled wakefulness.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Subjective alertness reflected a linear decline with time, but the magnitudes of objective performance deterioration increased significantly between 4:00 and 6:00 am. The increasing magnitudes of performance deficits were associated with the change of body temperature between 4:00 and 6:00 am.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">These results indicate that the perceived degree of decline in alertness is temporally dissociated with the actual decline in objective vigilance with increased duration of wakefulness. The dissociation of magnitudes of subjective and objective alertness decrements mainly occurs between 4:00 and 6:00 am, and the changes of performance deficits have a relationship with body temperature.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>prolonged wakefulness</kwd>
        <kwd>subjective ratings</kwd>
        <kwd>objective performance</kwd>
        <kwd>dissociation</kwd>
        <kwd>body temperature</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
            <institution-wrap>
              <institution>Guangdong Basic and Applied Basic Research Foundation, China</institution>
            </institution-wrap>
          </funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
            <institution-wrap>
              <institution>Natural Science Foundation of SZU</institution>
            </institution-wrap>
          </funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported by Guangdong Basic and Applied Basic Research Foundation, China (No. 2019A1515012182) and Natural Science Foundation of SZU (No. 827-000259).</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="4"/>
        <table-count count="6"/>
        <ref-count count="54"/>
        <page-count count="10"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">It is increasingly common that prolonged wakefulness for study, working, and even entertainment happens in modern society. These working and lifestyle demands frequently require individuals to sacrifice their regular sleep schedules, resulting in sleep loss and circadian misalignment. Prolonged wakefulness across the night is associated with increases in subjective fatigue and sleepiness and a broad range of decrements in objective performance, including longer response time and more lapses in cognitive performance, particularly for alertness and sustained attention.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Measures of sleepiness and fatigue can be assessed using subjective ratings like the Stanford Sleepiness Scale (SSS) and Karolinska sleepiness scale (KSS).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3–5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Various behavioral tests have been developed to objectively assess the degree of cognitive performance deterioration related to prolonged wakefulness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Multiple studies have analyzed the temporal variations of decrements of subjective evaluations and objective performance during prolonged wakefulness periods.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8–11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Subjective ratings and objective performance deteriorate significantly when wakefulness is extended into the usual bedtime, and the most severe deterioration emerges in the early morning hours.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Despite continued wakefulness, both subjective ratings and objective performance were improved after the early morning. Because the circadian process represents a nearly 24 h oscillation, promoting wakefulness across the habitual daytime.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> However, other studies have revealed that decrements of subjective ratings and objective performance are not quantitatively correlated.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13–15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The actual decline in objective vigilance maybe not consistent with individuals’ perceived degrees of fatigue and sleepiness during sleep loss.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Subjective and objective alertness involve different brain oscillations. Decrements in subjective ratings are related to a decreased EEG activity in the high alpha range. However, the impairments of objective performance are related to an increase in EEG delta activity and reaction time is also highly correlated to EEG gamma.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Although the relationship between subjective and objective alertness has been examined, it is not clear whether prolonged wakefulness affected subjective alertness and objective performance to different extents.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Prolonged wakefulness across the night also influences the physiological statuses controlled by the peripheral nervous system, including body temperature, heart rate, and blood pressure.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Sleep restriction potentially affects the circadian rhythms of body temperature, resulting in dysfunctional control of body temperature.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Mean body temperature significantly decreases during the sleep restriction condition compared to the natural sleep condition.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20–22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> When sleep deprivation lasts for more than one night, heart rate decreases due to increased vagal activity, whereas shorter periods of sleep deprivation do not seem to affect heart rate.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22–24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Previous studies have reported that blood pressure is elevated following acute total sleep deprivation and partial sleep restriction.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The peripheral nervous system is controlled by a neural system named the central autonomic network (CAN). Within the CAN, the integrated activity of respiratory, cardiovascular, and thermoregulatory regulation, together with behavioral responses, operates to maintain homeostasis of the human body.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The hypothalamus modulates the timing of sleep and wakefulness, as well as waking behavior, such as sleepiness and cognitive performance.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The physiological activity changes with wake and sleep states; in turn, the physiological activity also modulates the wake-sleep state.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The alternations of physiological functions are associated with the changes in neurobehavioral performance. An increased body temperature is correlated with improved performance and alertness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Objective performance deterioration may be partly attributed to disruption of body temperature rhythms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Heart rate variability can be used to estimate sleepiness-related decrements in psychomotor vigilance during total sleep deprivation.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The changes in physiological functions due to circadian misalignment may correlate with the deterioration in subjective ratings and objective performance during prolonged wakefulness periods.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The present study aimed to examine the effects of prolonged wakefulness overnight on the objective performance on PVT and subjective ratings of fatigue and sleepiness and whether the magnitudes of increase in subjective ratings temporally correspond with the decrease in objective performance. This research also analyzed the potential relationship of body temperature variations with the changes in subjective alertness decrements and performance deficits during prolonged wakefulness. We have hypothesized that both subjective and objective alertness deteriorated continuously with time on task during prolonged wakefulness periods. However, the rate of change in subjective alertness was temporally inconsistent with the rate of variation in performance impairments. Previous research has established a positive relationship between daily rhythms of body temperature and cognitive performance in humans.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29–31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> According to previous studies, we hypothesized that the changes in performance deficits were associated with the variation in body temperature during periods of prolonged wakefulness.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Participants and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Forty-two healthy volunteers completed this study, which was conducted in the Center for Sleep Research at the South China Normal University. Four participants were excluded as outliers with an absolute value of standardized residuals greater than 3.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Therefore, the final sample consisted of thirty-eight participants (M</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>age</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 21.76 ± 2.37 years old, 27 females) with normal body mass index (20.86 ± 1.75 kg/m</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) and normal or corrected-to-normal vision. All study procedures were approved by the Ethical Committee of the South China Normal University and were conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. All participants provided written informed consent and were financially compensated for their time.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Their demographic information, sleep and health history were assessed by a structural screening questionnaire. They were all nonsmokers and had no past or present major physical, psychiatric, and sleep-related disorders. Participants were ineligible if they had a history of shift work or traveling across time zones within two months before starting the study. Three days before the study, participants were asked to avoid alcohol, caffeine, or medications. Participants were also required to maintain a stable daily sleep-wake schedule (habitual 6.5–8 hours’ sleep duration and awake times between 6:00 am and 9:00 am) within two weeks before the study, verified by sleep diaries and actigraphy (Actiwatch Spectrum, Philips).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Experimental Procedures</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Participants attended the sleep laboratory at 19:00 and were kept awake at habitual bedtime (0:00–6:00 am) in the lab. This period was monitored by researchers to ensure participants’ wakefulness. All the tests began at 0:00 am. Participants completed a 10-min psychomotor vigilance task (PVT)</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> to assess objective alertness and a series of subjective tests including fatigue and sleepiness ratings during scheduled wakefulness every 2 hours. Physiological tests, including body temperature, systolic pressure, diastolic pressure, and heart rate were measured every hour. All the subjective ratings and physiological measurements were conducted before the PVT, avoiding the interference from fatigue effects induced by PVT (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Protocol for PVT performance, physiological and subjective tests. During habitual bedtime, participants kept awake for 6 hours (shown in shadow). Participants completed a 10-min PVT (indicated by circles,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS_A_312808_O_ILF0001.jpg" id="ilf0001"/></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative">) and subjective ratings (indicated by triangles,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS_A_312808_O_ILF0002.jpg" id="ilf0002"/></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) every two hours. The physiological tests were conducted within each hour (indicated by asterisks,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS_A_312808_O_ILF0003.jpg" id="ilf0003"/></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-923-g0001"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Psychomotor Vigilance Test</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Psychomotor vigilance test (PVT) is sensitive to sleep loss, which is a simple reaction time task and requires individuals to respond to stimuli that occur at random intervals as quickly as possible.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> PVT is highly reliable and be virtually unaffected by learning.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> We applied the standard 10-min PVT protocol (adapted version of Dinges and Powell, 1985) with random visual stimuli varied randomly from 2–10 s.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The number of trials varied from 70 to 90, depending on the participants’ reaction speed. Participants were instructed to monitor a red rectangular box on the computer screen and press a response button as soon as a yellow stimulus appeared on the screen, after which they would be able to view their reaction time. Button presses when the red rectangular box is not displayed on the screen are counted as false starts or errors of commission, which participants are instructed to avoid (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Psychomotor vigilance test (PVT) task.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-923-g0002"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The mean 1/RT and the number of lapses were chosen as the primary PVT indices, which maximize sleep loss sensitivity.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Responses were assessed as valid if RT was ≥100 ms. Lapses were counted when RT was ≥500 ms. If there was a 30 s period without response, stopped timing and counted as a lapse with 30 s response time. For calculating mean 1/RT, each RT (ms) was divided by 1000 and then reciprocally transformed. 1/RT emphasizes slowing in the optimum and intermediate response domain, and it substantially decreases the contribution of long lapses.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Subjective and Physiological Test</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Fatigue was assessed by a 9-point Likert scale ranging from “1” = not at all fatigue to “9” = extremely fatigue. Participants rated their sleepiness by completing the Karolinska Sleepiness Scale (KSS).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The KSS is a 1-item visual analogue scale, scored using a 9-point response range, from 1 (extreme alertness), to 5 (neither alertness nor sleepiness), to 9 (extreme sleepiness). Body temperature was measured by an electronic oral thermometer (Omron Healthcare Co, Ltd., Kyoto, Japan). Systolic pressure, diastolic pressure, and heart rate were measured by an automatic sphygmomanometer (Omron Healthcare Co, Ltd., Kyoto, Japan), and the experimenter measured the blood pressure after the training.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The normality of data was tested using the Shapiro–Wilk test. Comparisons of differences of subjective (fatigue and sleepiness), objective (number of lapses and mean 1/RT), and physiological (temperature, systolic pressure, diastolic pressure, and heart rate) outcome metrics among prolonged wakefulness time (0:00, 2:00, 4:00, and 6:00 am) were carried out using Repeated Measurement ANOVA for normal-distributed data and Friedman tests for non-normal-distributed data. Then, to explore the variation trends of subjective ratings, objective performance, and physiological indexes, the present study calculated the relative changes in the adjacent time (2:00 minus 0:00, 4:00 minus 2:00, and 6:00 minus 0:00 am) in these variables. The magnitudes of the relative changes in the adjacent time marked as ∆subjective (∆fatigue and ∆sleepiness), ∆objective (∆number of lapses and ∆mean 1/RT), and ∆physiological (∆temperature, ∆systolic pressure, ∆diastolic pressure, and ∆heart rate) outcome metrics, which were also contrasted by Repeated Measures ANOVA for normal-distributed data and Friedman tests for non-normal-distributed data. Finally, we conducted Pearson correlation analysis for normal-distributed data and Spearman correlation analysis for non-normal-distributed data among the ∆subjective, ∆objective, and ∆physiological outcome metrics to explore the relationship among the relative changes of subjective, objective, and physiological status across the period of prolonged wakefulness. We computed respectively the correlation for each point of time (0:00, 2:00, 4:00, and 6:00 am). Analyses were performed using SPSS23.0. The statistical significance level was set at </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.05 (two-tailed) for all tests. For post-hoc analysis, the Bonferroni test was applied for </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">-value adjustments of multiple comparisons, and corrected </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-values are reported.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0004-s2001">
        <title>Assessment of the Absolute Changes</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The time courses of the subjective, objective, and physiological outcome metrics from 0:00 to 6:00 am are shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. Differences of objective, subjective indexes and body temperature among 0:00, 2:00, 4:00, and 6:00 were significant (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). The Friedman tests revealed a significantly increasing number of lapses (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3A</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>χ<sup>2</sup></italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>(3)</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 49.822, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.001) and a significantly decreasing response speed (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3B</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>χ<sup>2</sup></italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>(3)</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 72.474, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.001) over time. Post hoc tests showed that the number of lapses was more at 6:00 than 4:00 (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.006, Bonferroni corrected), as well as the mean response speed was slower at 6:00 than 4:00 (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> &lt; 0.001, Bonferroni corrected). There was a significant increase in sleepiness (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3C</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>χ<sup>2</sup></italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>(3)</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 79.917, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.001) and fatigue (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3D</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>χ<sup>2</sup></italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>(3)</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 74.146, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.001) from midnight to early morning. Post hoc tests showed that participants were sleepier and more fatigue at 2:00 than 0:00 (sleepiness, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.023, Bonferroni corrected; fatigue, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.040, Bonferroni corrected), as well as at 6:00 than 4:00 (sleepiness, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.013, Bonferroni corrected; fatigue, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> = 0.010, Bonferroni corrected). A similar reduction of result was observed for body temperature (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3E</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>F</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>(3,111)</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 12.559, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.001). Post hoc tests showed that body temperature was lower at 2:00 than 0:00 (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> &lt; 0.001, Bonferroni corrected). There was no significant difference in systolic pressure, diastolic pressure, and heart rate among 0:00, 2:00, 4:00 and 6:00 am (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=312808.docx">Table S1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, systolic pressure, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.217; diastolic pressure, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.053; heart rate, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.605).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap id="t0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Results of Absolute Values of Objective, Subjective, and Physiological Outcome Metrics Over the Course of Time (0:00, 2:00, 4:00, and 6:00 Am)</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Outcome Metrics</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">0:00</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">2:00</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">4:00</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">6:00</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">χ<sup>2</sup>/F</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">PVT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of lapses</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.18±7.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.08±7.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.76±12.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.16±13.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.822***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean 1/RT (ms−<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.90±0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.74±0.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.56±0.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.84±0.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.474***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Subjective</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleepiness</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.71±1.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.53±1.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.03±1.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.08±1.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.917***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fatigue</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.71±1.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.55±1.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.16±1.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.24±1.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.146***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physiological</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature (°C)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.48±0.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.32±0.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.29±0.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.23±0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.559***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> ***</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> &lt; 0.001. Values are shown as mean±SD. The test statistic of number of lapses, mean 1/RT, sleepiness, and fatigue is </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>χ<sup>2</sup></italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, and the test statistic of temperature is </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>F</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig id="f0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The time courses of the subjective, objective, and physiological outcome metrics from 0:00 to 6:00 am. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) Number of lapses, (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) Mean 1/RT, (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>C</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) Sleepiness, (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>D</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) Fatigue, (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>E</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) Body temperature. Asterisks indicate significant differences, *</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.05. In each plot, the mean ± SEM is shown.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-923-g0003"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2002">
        <title>Assessment of the Relative Changes in Adjacent Time</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">To assess all outcome metrics’ variation trends, we conducted the Friedman tests on ∆PVT, ∆subjective, and ∆physiological indices (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). There were significant differences in the magnitudes of objective performance deterioration in the adjacent time (∆number of lapses, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>χ<sup>2</sup></italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>(2)</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 11.651, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.003; and ∆mean 1/RT, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>χ<sup>2</sup></italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>(2)</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 23.211, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> &lt; 0.001). Post hoc tests found a significant difference of ∆mean 1/RT between 4:00 minus 2:00 and 6:00 minus 4:00 (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.001, Bonferroni corrected). However, the extents of increases in sleepiness and fatigue were steady all the time (∆sleepiness, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>χ<sup>2</sup></italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>(2)</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 4.049, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.132; ∆fatigue, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>χ<sup>2</sup></italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>(2)</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 3.907, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> = 0.142). There was no significant difference in ∆body temperature, ∆systolic pressure, ∆diastolic pressure, and ∆heart rate among 0:00, 2:00, 4:00 and 6:00 am (∆body temperature, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.353; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=312808.docx">Table S2</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, ∆systolic pressure, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.241; ∆diastolic pressure, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.529; ∆heart rate, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.418).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap id="t0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Results of Relative Values of ∆objective, ∆subjective, and ∆physiological Outcome Metrics Over Time</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Outcome Metric</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">2:00–0:00</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">4:00–2:00</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">6:00–4:00</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">χ<sup>2</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">PVT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∆Number of lapses</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.89±6.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.68±9.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.39±11.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.651**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∆Mean 1/RT (ms−<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.16±0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.18±0.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.71±0.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.211***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Subjective</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∆Sleepiness</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82±0.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50±0.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05±1.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.049</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.132</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∆Fatigue</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84±0.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61±1.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08±1.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.907</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.142</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physiological</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">∆Temperature (°C)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.16±0.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.04±0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.06±0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.080</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.353</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> **</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.01, and ***</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> &lt; 0.001. The magnitudes of the relative changes in the adjacent time marked as ∆subjective (∆fatigue and ∆sleepiness), ∆objective (∆number of lapses and ∆mean 1/RT), and ∆physiological (∆temperature) outcome metrics. Values are shown as mean±SD.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2003">
        <title>Correlation Analysis Among the Relative Changes in the Adjacent Time</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">To explore the relationship between the changes in physiological indices and the changes in objective and subjective alertness, we conducted Pearson or Spearman correlation analysis among ∆subjective, ∆objective indexes and ∆physiological indices (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). Between 0:00 and 2:00 and between 2:00 and 4:00, no ∆objective or ∆subjective outcome metrics were correlated to ∆body temperature. From 4:00 to 6:00, ∆temperature was significantly associated with ∆number of lapses (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4A</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = −0.374, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.021) and ∆mean 1/RT (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4B</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.372, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> = 0.021). The magnitudes of objective alertness deterioration were correlated to the changes in body temperature between 4:00 and 6:00. At all the time points, ∆ systolic pressure, ∆diastolic pressure, and ∆heart rate were not correlated to the ∆objective and ∆subjective outcome metrics (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=312808.docx">Table S3</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap id="t0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Correlation Analysis Results: Association of ∆temperature with ∆PVT and ∆subjective Outcome Metrics</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="2"/><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">PVT</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Subjective</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">∆Number of Lapses</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">∆Mean 1/RT</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">∆Sleepiness</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">∆Fatigue</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">∆Temperature</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0:00–2:00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.236</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.154</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.062</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.713</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.159</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.340</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.061</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.714</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2:00–4:00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.048</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.773</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.924</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.044</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.792</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.168</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.313</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4:00–6:00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.374*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.372*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.174</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.297</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.289</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.078</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> *</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic>p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> &lt; 0.05. The magnitudes of the relative changes in the adjacent time marked as ∆subjective (∆fatigue and ∆sleepiness), ∆objective (∆number of lapses and ∆mean 1/RT), and ∆physiological (∆temperature) outcome metrics.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig id="f0004" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">The correlations of the changes of subjective ratings/objective performance with the changes of body temperature during the period of prolonged wakefulness. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) ∆Number of lapses between 4:00 and 6:00, (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) ∆Mean 1/RT between 4:00 and 6:00.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-923-g0004"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The present study explored the absolute and relative changes of subjective ratings and objective performance respectively and analyzed the relationship between the variations of body temperature and the impairments of subjective and objective alertness during the period of prolonged wakefulness. This study found the expected dissociation between the magnitudes of the impairments of subjective and objective alertness temporally. The rate of PVT performance decrements was significantly increased between 4:00 and 6:00. However, the changes of sleepiness and fatigue were stable all the time. The increasing rate of objective alertness decrements was associated with the change of body temperature between 4:00 and 6:00.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Both subjective ratings and objective performance kept decline during the period of prolonged wakefulness, and the most severe deterioration occurred between 4:00 and 6:00 am. The temporal variations of both subjective and objective alertness during prolonged wakefulness are under the dual control of a homeostatic process and a circadian rhythm. The homeostatic drive for sleep competes to remain awake, resulting in a rise in sleep pressure with increasing awake time. The circadian process represents a nearly 24 h oscillation, promoting sleepiness across the habitual bedtime (0:00 – 6:00 am).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> During extended wakefulness across the night, the interaction of the dual processes leads to time-on-task decrements in subjective ratings and objective performance.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Although subjective alertness has a similar temporal pattern of alterations to objective alertness, perceived sleepiness and fatigue are inconsistent with actual decrements in behavior performance when wakefulness is extended into the biological night. Reaction speed in a vigilance task suffered significant decrements between 4:00 and 6:00, but participants had not perceived the increasing magnitudes of the objective alertness deterioration. It indicates that significant decrements of objective performance on vigilance tasks do not temporally correspond with high levels of sleepiness and fatigue between 4:00 and 6:00. Individuals tend to underestimate the level of cognitive impairment during the period of extended wakefulness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> The previous study also found the impact of sleep restriction was greater on neurobehavioral performance than that on subjective alertness, especially during the biological night.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> There was no relationship between the magnitudes of the subjective and objective alertness impairments during 27 hours of continuous wakefulness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Similarly, a recent forced desynchrony study revealed the disassociation between subjective alertness and objective performance, and this dissociation may be detrimental to safety during work or daily activities.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Here, we further found that the dissociation of the magnitudes of subjective and objective alertness deteriorations mainly occurs around the minimum of the body temperature rhythm.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Body temperature has been reported to be an underlying mechanism regulating objective performance. Well-documented studies have indicated that a decreased body temperature is correlated with deteriorated performance and alertness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Consistent with previous research, we found that the changes in body temperature were associated with the rate of decrements in objective alertness between 4:00 and 6:00. The more body temperature decreased, the more deficits of cognitive performance suffered between 4:00 and 6:00. The previous forced desynchrony studies indicated that neurobehavioral function decreased with the increasing hours awake and was worst during the biological night near the minimum of the body temperature rhythm.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41–43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Under natural conditions with awake time at 7:00 am and bedtime at 11:00 pm, body temperature falls to reach the trough of 36.5°C at 4:00 am.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In the present study, objective performance suffered significant decrements when body temperature reaches a minimum between 4:00 and 6:00. The circadian rhythm of body temperature paralleled the circadian rhythm of performance.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The daily cycle in body temperature and behavior performance, such as vigilance, cognition, and sleep-wakefulness cycle, is driven by the circadian pacemaker located in the suprachiasmatic nucleus (SCN) of the hypothalamus.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46–48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The SCN is essential for maintaining circadian rhythm and synchronizing brain oscillators and physiological status.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The circadian rhythm of body temperature has been recognized as a reliable phase marker of the circadian system.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The correlation between objective performance and body temperature can be partly attributable to the regulation of the SCN. Body temperature as a key external indicator of the endogenous circadian rhythm in humans may predict cognitive performance.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Extended wakefulness is a common phenomenon in modern society. Numerous people are used to staying up late at night or working on the night shift. Lack of sleep is a major contributor to work-related and traffic incidents. As observed in this study, subjective and objective alertness showed high vulnerability with an increased duration of wakefulness. It had better not stay up late at night to reduce the chance of accidents. Moreover, individuals may suffer a major deterioration of objective performance but perceive only modest alertness decrements during the period of extended wakefulness. It is dangerous to underestimate the magnitude of cognitive impairment. Finally, it may be a trend to predict the change in cognitive performance by indicators that are easy to measure, such as body temperature.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Limitation and Future Direction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Several limitations have to be taken into account in the present study. First, participants are age-limited, ranging from 19 to 24 years old. Age is a major factor that may contribute to attentional failures during the period of prolonged wakefulness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Therefore, the present results may not apply to adolescents or old adults. Second, our results are based on the acute effect of prolonged wakefulness. It is unclear whether the results are valid for the chronic effect of prolonged wakefulness with successive nights. Third, the present study mainly used behavioral and physiological methods. In the future, researchers may consider combining with fMRI, EEG, and the electrodermal activity</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> to explore further the dissociation between objective performance and subjective ratings during prolonged wakefulness time. Fourth, other physiological factors except body temperature may contribute to the changes in objective vigilance, such as cortisol and melatonin during the extended wakeful time. Endogenous melatonin is used alone or combined with core body temperature as a phase marker of the endogenous circadian pacemaker located in the SCN.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Therefore, endogenous melatonin might also be a valuable physiological index that regulates the objective performance during prolonged wakefulness. It is necessary to explore more physiological indexes contributing to the changes in objective vigilance between 4:00 and 6:00 in future research. Fifth, the present study chose the habitual bedtime (0:00 to 6:00 am) as the time window of observation to explore the variation tendency of objective and subjective alertness and the dissociation between them. Future researches could consider adding an absolute baseline (eg, 22:00) before habitual sleeping time. Finally, body temperature and sleep-wakefulness cycle are both driven by the circadian pacemaker located in the suprachiasmatic nucleus (SCN) of the hypothalamus. As a result, body temperature might also correlate with vigilance during the daytime. The present study focused on exploring the correlation of body temperature and the objective alertness during the habitual bedtime. Future researches could consider to correlate body temperature with vigilance during the daytime to further uncover the relation between body temperature and behavioral performance.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The current study found that both subjective and objective alertness deteriorated after prolonged wakefulness of one night, but the magnitudes of decrements in subjective alertness were temporally inconsistent with the performance deficits with the increase of waking time. The significant decrements of objective performance between 4:00 and 6:00 are associated with body temperature rhythm. The current findings revealed a broad range of negative consequences of extended wakefulness, and individuals tend to underestimate their cognitive impairment level during extended wakefulness time. Furthermore, body temperature may be a valuable indicator to predict the change in cognitive performance.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec id="s0008" sec-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors report no conflicts of financial or academic interest. All authors have read and approved the manuscript.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Killgore</surname>
<given-names>WD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of sleep deprivation on cognition</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Prog Brain Res</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>185</volume>:<fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>129</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21075236</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferguson</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matthews</surname>
<given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep, wake and phase dependent changes in neurobehavioral function under forced desynchrony</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>931</fpage>–<lpage>941</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/SLEEP.1130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21731143</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kaida</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Takahashi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Akerstedt</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Validation of the Karolinska sleepiness scale against performance and EEG variables</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Neurophysiol</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>117</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1574</fpage>–<lpage>1581</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinph.2006.03.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16679057</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>MacLean</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fekken</surname>
<given-names>GC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saskin</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knowles</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Psychometric evaluation of the Stanford sleepiness scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.1992.tb00006.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10607023</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Miley</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kecklund</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Akerstedt</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Comparing two versions of the Karolinska Sleepiness Scale (KSS)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Biol Rhythms</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>257</fpage>–<lpage>260</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s41105-016-0048-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28781579</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Basner</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dinges</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Maximizing sensitivity of the psychomotor vigilance test (PVT) to sleep loss</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>581</fpage>–<lpage>591</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/34.5.581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21532951</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vgontzas</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kritikou</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Psychomotor vigilance test and its association with daytime sleepiness and inflammation in sleep apnea: clinical implications</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1049</fpage>–<lpage>1056</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.6720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28728622</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cajochen</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chellappa</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schmidt</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>What ketif us awake?—the role of clocks and hourglasses, light, and melatonin</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int Rev Neurobiol</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>93</volume>(<issue>93</issue>):<fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20970001</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Carrier</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monk</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Circadian rhythms of performance: new trends</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chronobiol Int</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>719</fpage>–<lpage>732</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1081/CBI-100102108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11128289</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Satterfield</surname>
<given-names>BC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wisor</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schmidt</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Dongen</surname>
<given-names>HPA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Time-on-task effect during sleep deprivation in healthy young adults is modulated by dopamine transporter genotype</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>12</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsx167</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Veksler</surname>
<given-names>BZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gunzelmann</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Functional equivalence of sleep loss and time on task effects in sustained attention</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cogn Sci</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>600</fpage>–<lpage>632</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cogs.12489</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28328113</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cajochen</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blatter</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wallach</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Circadian and sleep-wake dependent impact on neurobehavioral function</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Belg</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>1–2</issue>):<fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5334/pb.1017</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chua</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tan</surname>
<given-names>WQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yeo</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Heart rate variability can be used to estimate sleepiness-related decrements in psychomotor vigilance during total sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>325</fpage>–<lpage>334</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.1688</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22379238</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Leproult</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Colecchia</surname>
<given-names>EF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berardi</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stickgold</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kosslyn</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Cauter</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Individual differences in subjective and objective alertness during sleep deprivation are stable and unrelated</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>284</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>R280</fpage>–<lpage>R290</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpregu.00197.2002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12529281</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Paech</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Banks</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pajcin</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Caffeine administration at night during extended wakefulness effectively mitigates performance impairment but not subjective assessments of fatigue and sleepiness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pharmacol Biochem Behav</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>145</volume>:<fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbb.2016.03.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27061779</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kanayama</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sato</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ohira</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Crossmodal effect with rubber hand illusion and gamma-band activity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychophysiology</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>392</fpage>–<lpage>402</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8986.2007.00511.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17371495</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Posada-Quintero</surname>
<given-names>HF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reljin</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bolkhovsky</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Orjuela-Canon</surname>
<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chon</surname>
<given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Brain activity correlates with cognitive performance deterioration during sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1001</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnins.2019.01001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31607847</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>BK</given-names></string-name>. <chapter-title>Physiology of the autonomic nervous system</chapter-title>. In: Farag E, Argalious M, Tetzlaff J, Sharma D, editors. <italic>Basic Sciences in Anesthesia</italic>. Cham: Springer; <year>2018</year>:<fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>364</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hibi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kubota</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mizuno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of shortened sleep on energy expenditure, core body temperature, and appetite: a human randomised crossover trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>39640</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep39640</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28071649</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Szymusiak</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Body temperature and sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Handb Clin Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>156</volume>:<fpage>341</fpage>–<lpage>351</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30454599</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Te Lindert</surname>
<given-names>BHW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Someren</surname>
<given-names>EJW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Skin temperature, sleep, and vigilance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Handb Clin Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>156</volume>:<fpage>353</fpage>–<lpage>365</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30454600</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vaara</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kyrolainen</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koivu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tulppo</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Finni</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effect of 60-h sleep deprivation on cardiovascular regulation and body temperature</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Appl Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>105</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>439</fpage>–<lpage>444</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00421-008-0921-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19002705</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schwartz</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Klerman</surname>
<given-names>EB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Circadian neurobiology and the physiologic regulation of sleep and wakefulness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurol Clin</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>475</fpage>–<lpage>486</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ncl.2019.03.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31256784</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhong</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hilton</surname>
<given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gates</surname>
<given-names>GJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Increased sympathetic and decreased parasympathetic cardiovascular modulation in normal humans with acute sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Appl Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>98</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2024</fpage>–<lpage>2032</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/japplphysiol.00620.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15718408</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Meier-Ewert</surname>
<given-names>HK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ridker</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rifai</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of sleep loss on C-reactive protein, an inflammatory marker of cardiovascular risk</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>678</fpage>–<lpage>683</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2003.07.050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14975482</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haack</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gautam</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meier-Ewert</surname>
<given-names>HK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mullington</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Repetitive exposure to shortened sleep leads to blunted sleep-associated blood pressure dipping</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Hypertens</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1187</fpage>–<lpage>1194</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/HJH.0000000000001284</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28169885</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zoccoli</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amici</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and autonomic nervous system</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Opion Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>128</fpage>–<lpage>133</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cophys.2020.01.002</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Goel</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Neurobehavioral effects and biomarkers of sleep loss in healthy adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Neurol Neurosci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>89</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11910-017-0799-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28944399</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wright</surname>
<given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hull</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Czeisler</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Relationship between alertness, performance, and body temperature in humans</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>283</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>R1370</fpage>–<lpage>1377</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpregu.00205.2002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12388468</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Molzof</surname>
<given-names>HE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Prapanjaroensin</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>VH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mokashi</surname>
<given-names>MV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gamble</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patrician</surname>
<given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Misaligned core body temperature rhythms impact cognitive performance of hospital shift work nurses</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurobiol Learn Mem</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>160</volume>:<fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>159</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nlm.2019.01.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30611883</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Valdez</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramírez</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>García</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Circadian rhythms in cognitive performance: implications for neuropsychological assessment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chrono Physiol Ther</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/CPT.S32586</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stevens</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Outliers and influential data points in regression analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Bull</italic></source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>95</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>334</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0033-2909.95.2.334</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Doran</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Dongen</surname>
<given-names>HP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dinges</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sustained attention performance during sleep deprivation: evidence of state instability</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Ital Biol</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>139</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>267</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11330205</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shenfield</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beanland</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Filtness</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Apthorp</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The impact of sleep loss on sustained and transient attention: an EEG study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PeerJ</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e8960</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.8960</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32411513</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dinges</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Powell</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Microcomputer analyses of performance on a portable, simple visual RT task during sustained operations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Res Methods Instrum Comput</italic></source>. <year>1985</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>652</fpage>–<lpage>655</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3758/BF03200977</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Basner</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mollicone</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dinges</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Validity and sensitivity of a brief psychomotor vigilance test (PVT-B) to total and partial sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Astronaut</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>11–12</issue>):<fpage>949</fpage>–<lpage>959</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actaastro.2011.07.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22025811</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dijk</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>von Schantz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Timing and consolidation of human sleep, wakefulness, and performance by a symphony of oscillators</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Biol Rhythms</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>279</fpage>–<lpage>290</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0748730405278292</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16077148</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dinges</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pack</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cumulative sleepiness, mood disturbance, and psychomotor vigilance performance decrements during a week of sleep restricted to 4–5 hours per night</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>277</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9231952</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferguson</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matthews</surname>
<given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Mismatch between subjective alertness and objective performance under sleep restriction is greatest during the biological night</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.2011.00924.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21564364</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McHill</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hull</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Czeisler</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Klerman</surname>
<given-names>EB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Chronic sleep curtailment, even without extended (&gt;16-h) wakefulness, degrades human vigilance performance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>115</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):<fpage>6070</fpage>–<lpage>6075</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1706694115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29784810</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="newspaper"><string-name><surname>Czeisler</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dijk</surname>
<given-names>D-J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duffy</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Entrained phase of the circadian pacemaker serves to stabilize alertness and performance throughout the habitual waking day</article-title>; <year>1994</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dijk</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duffy</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Czeisler</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Circadian and sleep/wake dependent aspects of subjective alertness and cognitive performance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>112</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.1992.tb00021.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10607036</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wyatt</surname>
<given-names>JK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ritz-de Cecco</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Czeisler</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dijk</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Circadian temperature and melatonin rhythms, sleep, and neurobehavioral function in humans living on a 20-h day</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Physiol</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>277</volume>(<issue>4 Pt 2</issue>):<fpage>R1152</fpage>–<lpage>1163</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpregu.1999.277.4.r1152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10516257</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Refinetti</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The circadian rhythm of body temperature</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Biosci</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>564</fpage>–<lpage>594</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2741/3634</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Refinetti</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Circadian rhythmicity of body temperature and metabolism</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Temperature (Austin)</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>321</fpage>–<lpage>362</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/23328940.2020.1743605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33251281</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Deboer</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Detari</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meijer</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Long term effects of sleep deprivation on the mammalian circadian pacemaker</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>257</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/30.3.257</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17425221</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gent</surname>
<given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bassetti</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adamantidis</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep-wake control and the thalamus</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Opin Neurobiol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>188</fpage>–<lpage>197</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.conb.2018.08.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30144746</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Saper</surname>
<given-names>CB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scammell</surname>
<given-names>TE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Hypothalamic regulation of sleep and circadian rhythms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nature</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>437</volume>(<issue>7063</issue>):<fpage>1257</fpage>–<lpage>1263</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature04284</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16251950</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Moore-Ede</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sulzman</surname>
<given-names>FM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sulzman</surname>
<given-names>FM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fuller</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">The Clocks That Time Us: Physiology of the Circadian Timing System</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>; <year>1982</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>ZD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>WZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A hypothalamic circuit that controls body temperature</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>114</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>2042</fpage>–<lpage>2047</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1616255114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28053227</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gradisar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lack</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Relationships between the circadian rhythms of finger temperature, core temperature, sleep latency, and subjective sleepiness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Biol Rhythms</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>163</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0748730403261560</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15038855</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Blatter</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Graw</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Munch</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knoblauch</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wirz-Justice</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cajochen</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Gender and age differences in psychomotor vigilance performance under differential sleep pressure conditions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Brain Res</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>168</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>312</fpage>–<lpage>317</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbr.2005.11.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16386807</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Posada-Quintero</surname>
<given-names>HF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bolkhovsky</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reljin</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chon</surname>
<given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep deprivation in young and healthy subjects is more sensitively identified by higher frequencies of electrodermal activity than by skin conductance level evaluated in the time domain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>409</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphys.2017.00409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28676763</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Romine</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Banerjee</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goodman</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Toward sensor-based sleep monitoring with electrodermal activity measures</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sensors (Basel)</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1417</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/s19061417</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
