<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34785965</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">8579944</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">330022</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S330022</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Gut Microbiota in Patients with Type 1 Narcolepsy</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Zhang et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Zhang et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Ruirui</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gao</surname>
            <given-names>Shanjun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Shenghui</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6784-6658</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Jiewen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bai</surname>
            <given-names>Yingying</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>He</surname>
            <given-names>Shuang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
            <given-names>Pan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Hongju</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Neurology, Henan Provincial People’s Hospital Affiliated to Henan University</institution>, <addr-line>Zhengzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Henan</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Microbiome Laboratory, Henan Provincial People’s Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Zhengzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Henan</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Neurology, Henan Provincial People’s Hospital Affiliated to Zhengzhou University</institution>, <addr-line>Zhengzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Henan</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Hongju Zhang <institution>Department of Neurology, Henan Provincial People’s Hospital Affiliated to Henan University</institution>, <addr-line>Zhengzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Henan</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country> Email hongjuz@sina.com</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>06</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>13</volume>
      <fpage>2007</fpage>
      <lpage>2018</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2021 Zhang et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Zhang et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">To explore the characteristics of gut microbiota and its relationship between clinical manifestations in patients with type 1 narcolepsy (NT1).</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Patients and Methods</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Scale and polysomnography were performed in 20 NT1 patients and 16 healthy controls (HC group) to evaluate the clinical characteristics of NT1. Illumina sequencing was performed on bacterial 16S ribosomal RNA gene using V3-V4 regions to compare the fecal microbiota in all subjects. Associations between clinical characteristics and gut microbiota were analyzed using partial correlation analysis.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Compared with the HC group, the NT1 group had a significantly higher ESS score, longer total sleep time, increased wakefulness, decreased sleep efficiency, disturbance of sleep structure, shorter mean sleep latency, and increased sleep-onset REM periods (all P &lt; 0.05). No differences in alpha and beta diversity were observed between the two groups. In contrast, there were significant differences at the level of class, order, family, and genus (all P &lt; 0.05). LEfSe analysis showed that the relative abundance of </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> in the NT1 group was higher than that in the HC group (P &lt; 0.05), while the relative abundance of </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Blautia, Barnesiellaceae, Barnesiella, Phocea, Lactococcus, Coriobacteriia, Coriobacteriales, Ruminiclostridium_5</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Bilophila</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> were lower (all P &lt; 0.05). Partial correlation analysis revealed that partial differential bacteria in the NT1 group were correlated with total sleep time, sleep efficiency, stage 1 sleep, arousal index, and sleep latency (all P &lt; 0.05).</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Our data revealed differences in intestinal flora structure between NT1 patients and the normal population, thus providing a theoretical basis for future microecological therapy for narcolepsy. However, future larger sample size studies and different study designs are needed to further clarify the possible pathogenesis and potential causality of intestinal flora in NT1 patients and explore the new treatment strategies.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>type 1 narcolepsy</kwd>
        <kwd>gut microbiota</kwd>
        <kwd>16SrRNA</kwd>
        <kwd>high throughput sequencing</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>any funding agency in the public, commercial or profit-making sector</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>This research has not received a specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial or profit-making sector.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="4"/>
        <table-count count="7"/>
        <ref-count count="57"/>
        <page-count count="12"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Narcolepsy is a rare sleep disorder characterized by excessive daytime sleepiness, cataplexy, sleep paralysis, and sleep hallucinations. Some patients may develop nocturnal sleep disturbance, obesity, mental and emotional disorders, and other problems.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1–3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> According to the content of hypocretin (Hcrt), narcolepsy can be divided into type 1 narcolepsy (NT1) (Hcrt concentration ≦ 110 pg/mL) and type 2 narcolepsy.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> NT1, which is believed to be an autoimmune disease mediated by T cells, irreversibly damages hypocretin neurons and reduces hypocretin content.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Symptomatic drugs that stimulate the central nervous system are currently considered the only treatment that can help people with narcolepsy stay awake during the day.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Narcolepsy is the result of the interaction between genetic and environmental factors. Previous studies have found that carrying the HLA-DBQ1-0602 gene can increase the risk of narcolepsy by 200 times,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> and up to 98% of NT1 patients are positive for this gene.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Over recent years, studies have found that influenza A virus infection, vaccination, and streptococcal infection all increase the risk of narcolepsy.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10–12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Streptococcus infection increases the narcolepsy risk by 5.4 times.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In 65% of patients who recently experienced narcolepsy attack, serum anti-streptolysin O titers were increased,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> thus emphasizing the relevance of the infection factors in the role of narcolepsy onset.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">High-throughput sequencing technology that uses 16S rRNA gene sequencing is a powerful method for detecting unculturable microorganisms in the gastrointestinal tract.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The human gut contains 1000 to 1150 species of about 100 trillion bacteria, which are 10 times higher than the number of human cells and 150 times larger than the human gene complement in the body.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Gut microbiota has a variety of physiological functions and is closely related to human health, affecting cell metabolism, digestion, nutrient absorption, and the development and maturation of the host’s immune system.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Gut microbiota has also been closely associated with diseases of central nervous system, immune-related diseases, psychiatric diseases, metabolic diseases, and sleep disorders.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17–24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> More recently, it has been suggested that patients with narcolepsy are at high risk of gut microbiota dysregulation.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> LeComte et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> reported reduced beta diversity in NT1 patients compared to HC patients. In this study, we explored the characteristics of intestinal microflora of Chinese NT1 patients by 16SrRNA gene sequencing technology so as to understand the effect of gut microbiota on NT1.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Patients and Methods</title>
      <sec id="S0002-S2001">
        <title>Study Population</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">From January 2017 to December 2019, 20 patients with narcolepsy (NT1 group) from the Department of Neurology, Henan Provincial People’s Hospital, and 16 healthy volunteers (HC group) were recruited. General information including age, sex, course of the disease, body mass index (BMI), Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS), and Hamilton Depression Scale (HAMD) were collected in both groups, and polysomnography (PSG), multiple sleep latency test (MSLT), Hcrt and HLA-DBQ1 * 0602 gene tests were performed. The NT1 was diagnosed according to the diagnostic criteria of the International Classification of Sleep Disorders (3rd edition).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> NT1 patients had no history of taking neuro stimulant drugs. Two patients were taking anticataplexy drug (venlafaxine) six months ago.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">All subjects were from the same province and were eating similar diets. Subjects in the two groups did not take any drugs that could affect sleep, did not have gastrointestinal diseases, organic brain diseases, mental diseases, autoimmune diseases, or other major diseases, and did not take any antibiotics, probiotics, or prebiotics for at least one month before the examination. All subjects were able to provide stool samples.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0002-S2002">
        <title>PSG and MSLT</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All subjects underwent sleep monitoring (PSG and MSLT) in our sleep center, in a quiet, comfortable, and temperature-controlled place. The monitoring contents included electroencephalogram, electroophthalmogram, electrocardiogram, chin and bilateral tibial anterior electromyogram, oral-nasal airflow, snoring, chest and abdominal movement, pulse oxygen, and body movement. Overnight nocturnal polysomnography was followed by multiple sleep latency tests the next day. A total of 5 naps were arranged with an interval of 2 hours each time, and patients were asked to get up and stay awake after each nap of 30 minutes. The monitoring results were automatically analyzed by the system and corrected by the sleep technician according to the Sleep and Related Events interpretation manual version 2.3.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0002-S2003">
        <title>Measurements of CSF Hcrt and HLA-DQB1*0602 Gene</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) samples were collected by lumbar puncture. CSF samples were snap-frozen and subsequently stored at −80°C until further analysis. CSF Hcrt was measured using a 125I radioimmunoassay kit (Phoenix Pharmaceuticals, Belmont, CA, USA).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> All samples were measured in duplicate, averaged, and compared to standard CSF samples with known CSF hcrt levels. The HLA-DQB1*0602-specific codon 9 amino acid was determined using PCR sequence-specific primer method.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The presence of DQB1*0602 is reported as positive and absence as negative.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0002-S2004">
        <title>Collection and Sequencing of Fecal Samples</title>
        <sec id="S0002-S2004-S3001">
          <title>Collection of Fecal Samples</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The stool samples of the NT1 and HC groups were collected by sterile fecal collection tubes in the hospital. The general procedure was as follows: first, urine was drained, and then 3–4 spoonfuls of feces were collected by sterile collection tubes. Then, the fecal samples were transported to GENEWIZ through dry ice for high-throughput sequencing of 16SrRNA.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="S0002-S2004-S3002">
          <title>DNA Extraction, Library Construction, and Illumina Sequencing</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">DNA was extracted from the samples using a DNA extraction kit according to manufacturer’s Protocols. DNA concentration was measured using the Equalbit dsDNA HS Assay Kit. Using 20–30ng DNA as a template, a series of PCR primers designed by GENEWIZ were used to amplify two hypervariable regions, including V3 and V4 on the 16S rDNA of prokaryotes. Then, a linker with Index was added to the end of the PCR product of 16S rDNA by PCR for Illumina sequencing. The library was purified by magnetic beads; the concentration was detected by a microplate reader, and the fragment size was detected by agarose gel electrophoresis. To quantify the library to 10nM, and PE250 double-ended sequencing was performed according to the instructions of Illumina Miseq (Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA) instrument. The sequence information was read by MiSeq Control Software (MCS).</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="S0002-S2004-S3003">
          <title>Bioinformatics Analysis</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">After quality filtration, the chimeric sequence was removed, and the final sequence was used for OTU clustering. Sequence clustering was performed using the VSearch (1.9.6) (sequence similarity was set as 97%), and the 16S rRNA reference database used for comparison was SILVA 132. Then, the RDP classifier (Ribosomal Database Program) Bayesian algorithm was used to carry out taxonomic analysis on the representative sequences of OTU, and the community composition of each sample was counted at different species classification levels.</citation_analysis></p>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Based on the results of OTU analysis, the Alpha diversity index (ACE index, Chao index, Shannon index, Simpson index) of each sample was analyzed to obtain the species abundance and diversity information of each sample. Beta diversity analysis was visualized with Non-Metric Multidimensional Scaling (NMDS) to visually display the differences in community structure among different samples and groups. LEfSe analysis was used to identify statistically significant biomarkers between the two groups.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0002-S2005">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">General data, sleep parameters, and alpha diversity analysis were performed using SPSS 22 statistical software. Shapiro–Wilk normality test and homogeneity of variance test were performed on measurement data. Measurement data conforming to normal distribution and homogeneity of variance were expressed as mean±standard deviation (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><inline-formula id="ilm0001"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-2007-e0001.jpg"/><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$$\overline X\pm S$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">); two independent samples </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-test were used. Measurement data conforming to normal distribution but not conforming to the homogeneity of variance were expressed as mean±standard deviation (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><inline-formula id="ilm0002"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-2007-e0002.jpg"/><tex-math id="M2">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$$\overline X\pm S$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">); two independent samples t' -test were used. Measurement data that did not conform to normal distribution were represented by median (quaternary)[M(Q25, Q75)], and the Mann–Whitney </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">U</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">-test was adopted. Counting data were expressed as cases and compared using Fisher’s exact probability method. Beta diversity was visualized with NMDS and compared statistically with Anosim. LEfSe online analysis tool was used to analyze the differences in community structure between groups and search for biomarkers with statistical differences. Partial correlation analysis was used to analyze the correlation between the clinical indicators and the differential flora in NTI patients. P &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. All data visualization was performed with the R statistical programming language.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="S0003-S2001">
        <title>General Data</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">There were no statistically significant differences in age, gender, and BMI (all P &gt; 0.05) between the NT1 group and HC group. The disease duration in the NT1 group was 3.0 (2.0, 7.0) years. The median BMI of the NT1 group was 25.7kg/m</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> (overweight); 8 patients (40%) had normal BMI, 5 patients (25%) were overweight, and 7 patients (35%) were obese. The average ESS score of NT1 group was 18.0±3.9, which was statistically different compared with the HC group (P = 0.000). There was no statistically significant difference in HAMD scores between the two groups (P &gt; 0.05) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Comparison of General Data and Sleep Parameters Between NT1 Group and HC Group</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Items</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NT1 Group (n = 20)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HC Group (n = 16)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.0 (14.3, 26.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.0 (18.5, 27.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.516<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.130</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male (cases)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disease duration (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0 (2.0, 7.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.337<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.7 (20.9, 28.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.7 (22.1, 25.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.672<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.094</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESS (score)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.0±3.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9±3.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.300<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HAMD (score)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.7±4.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8±4.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.871<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hcrt (pg/mL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0 (10.0, 18.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">317.4 (284.8,334.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.217<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total sleep time (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">566.1±103.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">504.0±52.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.334<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Latency (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3 (1.0, 9.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0 (10.4, 20.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.427<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep efficiency (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.1 (73.1, 90.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.6 (88.9, 93.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.089<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N1 proportion (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.3±10.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9±2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.586<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N2 proportion (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.7 (34.2, 48.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.9 (52.6, 58.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.869<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N3 proportion (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.7±9.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.8±3.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.045<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.965</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM proportion (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.3±7.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.7±.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.354<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.187</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM sleep latency (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.5 (3.8, 202.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.0 (78.0, 110.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.191<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.848</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of awakening (times)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.7±12.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3±4.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.101<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arousal index</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7±5.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2±4.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.376<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (0.3, 3.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 (0.0, 2.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.658<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.097</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean sleep latency (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4 (1.9, 5.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4 (14.4, 16.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.063<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep onset REM periods (times)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0 (3.3, 4.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.405<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>a</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Is the t value (obtained by two independent samples t-test), </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>b</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Is the t' value (obtained by two independent samples t'-test), and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>c</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Is the Z value (obtained by Mann–Whitney U-test). -: Gender calculation using Fisher’s exact probability method, no test value.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: ESS, Epworth sleepiness Scale; HAMD, Hamilton Depression Scale; REM, rapid eye movement; AHI, apnea hypopnea index.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0003-S2002">
        <title>PSG and MSLT</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Patients with NT1 slept longer during the night, had a shorter nocturnal sleep latency, decreased sleep efficiency, increased proportion of stage 1 sleep, decreased proportion of stage 2 sleep, increased number of awakening and arousal index, shorter mean sleep latency, and increased SOREMPs compared to the HC group (all P &lt; 0.05). There were no significant differences in the proportion of stage 3 sleep, REM sleep, REM sleep latency, and sleep apnea-hypopnea index (AHI) between the two groups (all P &gt; 0.05). The detailed results are shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0003-S2003">
        <title>Detection of CSF Hcrt and HLA-DQB1*0602 Gene</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The level of Hcrt in CSF in all NT1 patients was &lt;110pg/mL, with an average of 10.0 (10.0, 18.4) pg/mL. All NT1 patients were positive for the HLA-DQB1*0602 gene. While the CSF Hcrt of all control groups was &gt;110pg/mL, with an average of 317.4 (284.8,334.5) pg/mL, and all were negative for the HLA-DQB1 *0602 gene (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0003-S2004">
        <title>Analysis of Gut Microbiota</title>
        <sec id="S0003-S2004-S3001">
          <title>Alpha Diversity Analysis</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Alpha diversity analysis was used to analyze the abundance and diversity of microorganisms in the sample. The abundance index, including the ACE index and Chao index, was positively correlated with microbial abundance. The diversity index included the Simpson index and Shannon index. Simpson index was negatively correlated with microbial diversity, while Shannon index was positively correlated with microbial diversity. As shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">, there was no statistically significant difference in alpha diversity between the two groups (P &gt; 0.05).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Alpha Diversity Analysis</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alpha Diversity Index</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NT1 Group</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HC Group</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">151.2±25.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">150.8±35.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.973</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chao</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">157.2±30.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">153.1±33.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.383<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.704</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Simpson</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9 (0.9, 0.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9 (0.9, 0.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.557<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.577</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shannon</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7 (4.5, 5.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9 (4.6, 5.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.605<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.545</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>a</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Is the t value (obtained by two independent samples t-test), and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>b</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Is the Z value (obtained by Mann–Whitney U-test).</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="S0003-S2004-S3002">
          <title>Beta Diversity Analysis</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Beta diversity reflects the difference in diversity between different samples and is an indicator that measures the similarity of microbial composition between individuals. Beta diversity, based on Bray-Curtis dissimilarity, was visualized with NMDS and compared statistically with Anosim. In Anosim analysis, the range of R-value was [−1, 1]; values closer to 0 indicated no significant difference between and within groups, while values closer to 1 indicated that the difference between groups was greater than the difference within groups. As shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">, there was no statistically significant difference in beta diversity between the two groups (P = 0.634, R = −0.018).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">NMDS ordination plot. Each point in the figure represents a sample, the yellow point represents the NT1 group, and the green point represents the HC group. The closer the two points are, the more similar the microbial composition is. Stress &lt; 0.2 indicates that NMDS can accurately reflect the degree of difference between samples.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-2007-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="S0003-S2004-S3003">
          <title>Differential Microbial Abundance Analyses</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We used LEfSe</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> analysis to identify differential microbiota between NT1 patients and the HC group. LEfSe analysis combines nonparametric Kruskal–Wallis, Wilcoxon rank-sum test, and Linear discriminant analysis (LDA) Effect Size. LEfSe analysis can directly carry out a statistical test and difference analysis on the classification level of phylum/class/order/family/genus/species simultaneously, and more emphasis is placed on finding robust differences between groups, namely biomarkers. In LEfSe analysis, there are two thresholds for screening marker species, ie, P &lt; 0.05 and LDA ≥ 2 (default, the higher the LDA is, the more strict the LDA is). Only when these two conditions are met simultaneously, the taxon can be considered a marker species.</citation_analysis></p>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This analysis revealed significant differences in bacterial clades from class to species level (except phylum level) between NT1 patients and the HC group (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002 f0003 f0004" ref-type="fig">Figures 2–4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). In the NT1 group, the relative abundance of </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> was higher than that in the HC group (LDA = 3.19, P = 0.047), while the relative abundance of </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Blautia, Barnesiellaceae, Barnesiella, Phocea, Lactococcus, Coriobacteriia, Coriobacteriales, Ruminiclostridium_5</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Bilophila</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> were lower than that of HC group (all LDA &gt; 2, P &lt; 0.05) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Differential Microbial Abundance Analyses at Different Taxonomic Levels</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Domain</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDA Score</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>More abundant in NT1 individuals</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus Klebsiella</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>More abundant in HC individuals</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Class Coriobacteriia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Order Coriobacteriales</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family Barnesiellaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus Lactococcus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus Phocea</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus Ruminiclostridium_5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus Barnesiella</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus Blautia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.048</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus Bilophila</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: NT1, Type 1 narcolepsy; HC, healthy controls; LDA, linear discriminative analysis.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Histogram of LDA score distribution. This figure shows the significantly different species with LDA scores greater than the default (default 2.0). In the bar chart, the red represents the HC group, the green represents the NT1 group, and the length represents the LDA score, namely the contribution degree of the significantly different species to the different groups.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-2007-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Histogram of species distribution at the phylum level.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-2007-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0004" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Histogram of species distribution at the genus level.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-2007-g0004" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0003-S2005">
        <title>Partial Correlation Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Considering that gender, age, and course of the disease can affect the flora, the confounding factors were controlled, after which we conducted a partial correlation analysis between the differential flora and the clinical data (Sleep parameters and scale assessment) in NTI patients. The results showed that the Hcrt level was negatively correlated with the number of SOREMPs (r = −0.763; P &lt; 0.05). The relative abundance of </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Coriobacteriales, Coriobacteriia</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Blautia</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> were negatively correlated with total sleep time (r = −0.510, −0.510, −0.489; P &lt; 0.05). The relative abundance of </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Coriobacteriales</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Coriobacteriia</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> were negatively correlated with sleep efficiency (r = −0.592, −0.592; P &lt; 0.05). The relative abundance of </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Lactococcus</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> was positively correlated with stage 1 sleep and negatively correlated with arousal index (r = 0.617, −0.522; P &lt; 0.05). The abundance of </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> was positively correlated with sleep latency (r = 0.547; P &lt; 0.05).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This study found significantly higher ESS score, longer total sleep time, increased wakefulness, decreased sleep efficiency, disturbance of sleep structure, shorter mean sleep latency, and increased sleep-onset REM periods in patients with NT1 compared to healthy controls. Moreover, there were no significant differences in alpha and beta diversity between the NT1 and HC groups; yet, a significant difference was found at the level of class, order, family, and genus between the two groups (except at the phylum level). The relative abundance of </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> in the NT1 group was higher than that in the HC group, while the relative abundance of </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Blautia, Barnesiellaceae, Barnesiella, Phocea, Lactococcus, Coriobacteriia, Coriobacteriales, Ruminiclostridium_5</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, and Bilophila were lower than in the HC group. In addition, a partial correlation analysis showed that Hcrt was negatively correlated with sleep-onset REM periods; total sleep time was negatively correlated with the abundance of </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Coriobacteriales, Coriobacteriia</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Blautia</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">; sleep efficiency was negatively correlated with </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Coriobacteriales</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Coriobacteriia; Lactococcus</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> was positively correlated with stage 1 sleep and negatively correlated with arousal index, and sleep latency was positively correlated with the abundance of </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.</citation_analysis></p>
      <sec id="S0004-S2001">
        <title>Clinical and Electrophysiological Characteristics of NT1</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The results of this study revealed no significant differences in age, gender, BMI, and HAMD scores between the NT1 group and HC group. Nevertheless, the ESS score of the NT1 group was significantly increased compared with that of the HC group. Previous studies have shown that patients with narcolepsy are more likely to be obese (their BMI was 10–20% higher than the general population).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28–30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Our study revealed no significant difference in BMI between the two groups: the median BMI of the NT1 group was 25.7kg/m</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> (representing overweight); 8 cases (40%) had normal BMI, 5 cases (25%) were overweight, and 7 cases (35%) were obese, which might be related to sample size. Previous studies have found that 30% of NT1 patients are accompanied by depression and other emotional problems,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> which is believed to be related to the effect the disease was having on patients.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Yet, this was not found in this study; the inconsistencies may be related to the disease course (the average disease course is 3 years). Besides, the significant increase in ESS in this study indicated that NT1 patients suffer from daytime sleepiness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This study revealed that compared with the HC group, the NT1 group had longer total sleep time, shorter nocturnal sleep latency, decreased sleep efficiency, increased proportion of stage 1 sleep, decreased proportion of stage 2 sleep, increased number of awakening and arousal index, shorter mean sleep latency, and increased SOREMPs. There were no significant differences in the proportion of stage 3 sleep, REM sleep, REM sleep latency, and AHI between the NT1 group and the HC group. Previous studies have reported that NT1 patients have fragmented sleep, increased wakefulness, and disturbed sleep structure at night,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> which is consistent with the results of this study. In this study, the mean sleep latency of NT1 patients was 3.4 (1.9, 5.8) min, and the number of SOREMPs was 4.0 (3.3, 4.8) times, which met the international diagnostic standard of NT1.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Previous studies reported that approximately 30% of NT1 patients were associated with Obstructive sleep apnea.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> This study did not find differences in AHI between NT1 and HC groups, which may be related to the fact that obesity was not obvious in NT1 patients in this study.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0004-S2002">
        <title>Gut Microbiota of NT1</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In the present study, we found no changes in Alpha diversity and Beta diversity, which symbolize the homeostasis of gut microbes, between the NT1 patients and the HC group. The intestinal flora of the two groups were mainly composed of </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes, Bacteroidetes, Proteobacteria</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Actinobacteria</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. Yet, the comparison between NT1 and HC groups at the level of class, order, family, and genus showed statistical differences; however, these differences accounted for a relatively low proportion in the whole, suggesting that overall intestinal microecology did not significantly change during NT1. The difference in some bacteria may be related to the disease duration. As a T cell-mediated immune disease, NT1 may go through great environmental changes at the beginning of the disease, which may lead to intestinal microbiota disturbance. Furthermore, with the extension of the disease duration, just like the infection indicators can only be detected in the recent onset of narcolepsy patients,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> intestinal microbiota changes may not be as obvious as at the beginning of the disease. Yet, due to the rarity of the disease and inadequate inspection equipment, narcolepsy is usually diagnosed in a later stage;</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> thus, it is difficult to collect stool samples from disease onset.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">LEfSe analysis identified statistically significant biomarkers between the two groups. It revealed that the relative abundance of </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> was higher than that in the HC group, while the relative abundance of </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Blautia, Barnesiellaceae, Barnesiella, Phocea, Lactococcus, Coriobacteriia, Coriobacteriales, Ruminiclostridium_5</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Bilophila</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> were lower than that in HC group. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> is a conditional pathogen and a pro-inflammatory bacterium found in the human intestine and respiratory tract, where it can cause bronchitis, pneumonia, meningitis, and other infectious diseases.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35–37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Blautia</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> is a gut microbial genus that produces butyric acid and acetic acid and has an anti-inflammatory effect.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The increase of </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and the decrease of </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Blautia</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> further suggest that the incidence of NT1 is related to the inflammatory response.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">A previous study suggested that Coriobacteriia was associated with depressive symptoms in an inflammation model of depression,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Phocea</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> has been associated with anxiety and motor function in Parkinson’s rats.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Therefore, we speculated that emotional problems in NT1 patients might be related to these two bacteria.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Previous studies also found that the number of </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Barnesiella</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> was positively correlated with lean body weight in mice (ie, fat-free body weight, mostly bone and muscle).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Blautia</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> was negatively correlated with visceral fat accumulation,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and significantly decreased in obese children.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Furthermore, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Bilophila</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Lactococcus</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> have been shown to be related to obesity.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The obesity in patients with NT1 may be mediated by the above four bacteria. Previous studies also found that intestinal </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella, Blautia</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Ruminiclostridium_5</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> are all associated with inflammatory response, and NT1 with a genetic susceptibility,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> infection induction</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and T cell-mediated autoimmune disease.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Gut microbiota can exert a great influence on the brain immune function through the brain-gut axis.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The changes in the abundance of intestinal flora mentioned above may be involved in the pathogenesis of NT1.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0004-S2003">
        <title>Correlation Between Clinical Features of NT1 and Gut Microbiota</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Since most patients with NT1 are accompanied by obesity, which is closely related to intestinal bacteria,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> we examined the relationship between obesity and intestinal bacteria of NT1, and BMI was not taken as a covariable in the present study. Partial correlation analysis was conducted between the different flora of NT1 and abnormal clinical features. We found that the Hcrt level was negatively correlated with the number of SOREMPs. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Coriobacteriales, Coriobacteriia</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Blautia</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> were negatively correlated with total sleep time; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Coriobacteriales</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Coriobacteriia</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> were negatively correlated with sleep efficiency; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Lactococcus</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> was positively correlated with stage 1 sleep and negatively correlated with sleep arousal index; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> was positively correlated with sleep latency.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Previous studies have shown that NT1 patients have fragmented sleep at night and are prone to frequent awakenings.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> A low level of Hcrt can easily lead to sleep-wake instability,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and sleep disruption may be one of the causes of daytime sleepiness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In this study, the content of Hcrt in the NT1 group was extremely low; Hcrt was negatively correlated with the number of SOREMPs, and the proportion of REM sleep at night was lower than that in the HC group, although there was no statistical difference. It is speculated that a low level of Hcrt leads to awakenings at night, frequent interruption of REM sleep at night, and more SOREMPs due to REM sleep pressure. At present, no study reported on sleep structure and the above different bacteria in NT1 patients. The different bacteria found in this study are mostly related to mood, obesity, and inflammation, and the association between these bacteria and sleep fragmentation is still unclear. In addition, inflammatory factors can lead to increased sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Further studies are needed to confirm whether inflammation-related bacteria in NT1 contribute to sleepiness symptoms. Furthermore, NT1 is a T-cell-mediated immune disease. Whether these inflammation-related bacteria have an important role in its onset needs to be confirmed in the acute phase of NT1. In this study, no statistically significant correlation was observed between depression score and mood-related microflora in NT1 patients, nor between BMI and obesity-related microflora, which may be related to the fact that there were no statistically significant differences in HAMD score and BMI between the two groups in the present study.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">At present, only a few studies reported on the intestinal microbiota in NT1 patients,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> while there is still a lack of research on the intestinal microbiota of narcolepsy in China. LeComte et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> found no statistically significant difference in alpha diversity between NT1 patients and the HC group, while beta diversity decreased in NT1 patients. Comparison of microbial abundance at different taxonomic levels revealed only a few differences in OTU levels, which were no longer statistically significant after adjusting for BMI values. This indicated that the overall intestinal microecology of NT1 patients does not significantly change, which is consistent with our conclusions. The reasons why Beta diversity analysis and differential microbial abundance analysis were inconsistent between these studies may be due to the following: first, recruited patients were from different countries; geographical location, ethnicity, diet, lifestyle, and other aspects may affect the composition of intestinal flora.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Second, the BMI of NT1 patients enrolled in a previous study</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> was higher than that of the control group, and the observed difference was statistically significant. Previous studies have found that obesity is closely related to the intestinal flora.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Finally, unlike their study, none of our patients had recently taken medication for narcolepsy. According to some estimation, more than a quarter of 1000 drugs we used, most of which were not antibiotics, are likely to affect gut flora.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This study has some advantages and limitations. The advantage of this study is that the diagnosis of the included patients was clear, and the Hcrt content of all the patients was less than 110pg/mL, which met the diagnostic criteria of NT1. All the patients came from our province, thus having similar dietary structures and no racial differences. None of the patients had recently taken drugs to treat NT1, ruling out the possible effects of drugs on intestinal microbes. The major study limitations are: firstly, the sample size was small; thus, a subgroup analysis was not carried out. However, the incidence of NT1 in the Chinese population has been reported to be only 0.033% (1 in 2500 people).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The rarity of the disease proves the rationality of this study to explore the intestinal microbiota of NT1 in China on a small scale. In addition, our study lacks a detailed assessment of the lifestyle and diet of the subjects, lacks collection of inflammatory indicators in blood or cerebrospinal fluid, and fails to successfully include the control group with positive HLA-DBQ1*0602 gene, which may further improve the influence of confounding factors and deepen understanding of intestinal microbiota in the pathogenesis of NT1.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In conclusion, we found some differences in intestinal flora structure between NT1 patients and normal people, thus providing a theoretical basis for future microecological therapy for narcolepsy. However, future larger sample size studies and different study designs need to be carried out to further clarify the possible pathogenesis and potential causality of intestinal flora in NT1 patients and explore the new treatment strategies.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We thank all the neurology faculty for helping recruiting suitable subjects for this study. I would like to thank teacher Shuai Chen and senior sister apprentice Jing Zhao for answering questions and guidance in my paper writing. Thanks to Dr. Shanjun Gao for providing us with a place to store stool samples. Finally, we are also grateful to all GENEWIZ employees involved in the 16SrRNA gene sequencing.</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The datasets used or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Ethics Statements</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The study was approved by the Ethics Committee of Henan Provincial People’s Hospital (No.2021141), and all participants signed written informed consent prior to participation. This study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0007">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">All authors declare no conflict of interest.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chabas</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Foulon</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gonzalez</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Eating disorder and metabolism in narcoleptic patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1267</fpage>–<lpage>1273</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/30.10.1267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17969460</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Roth</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dauvilliers</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mignot</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Disrupted nighttime sleep in narcolepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>955</fpage>–<lpage>965</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.3004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23997709</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Parmar</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yeh</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Korczak</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Depressive symptoms, sleep patterns, and physical activity in adolescents with narcolepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>8</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsz111</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Medicine AAOS</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">International Classification of Sleep Disorders: Diagnostic and Coding Manual</italic></source>. <edition>3nd</edition> ed. <year>2014</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Latorre</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kallweit</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Armentani</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>T cells in patients with narcolepsy target self-antigens of hypocretin neurons</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nature</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>562</volume>(<issue>7725</issue>):<fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-018-0540-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30232458</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pedersen</surname>
<given-names>NW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holm</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kristensen</surname>
<given-names>NP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>CD8+ T cells from patients with narcolepsy and healthy controls recognize hypocretin neuron-specific antigens</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Commun</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>837</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-019-08774-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30783092</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cla</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adamantidis</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burdakov</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Narcolepsy - clinical spectrum, aetiopathophysiology, diagnosis and treatment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>519</fpage>–<lpage>539</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31324898</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tafti</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hor</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dauvilliers</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>DQB1 locus alone explains most of the risk and protection in narcolepsy with cataplexy in Europe</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.3300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24381371</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liblau</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vassalli</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seifinejad</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tafti</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Hypocretin (orexin) biology and the pathophysiology of narcolepsy with cataplexy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>318</fpage>–<lpage>328</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(14)70218-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25728441</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aran</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nevsimalova</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Elevated anti-streptococcal antibodies in patients with recent narcolepsy onset</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>979</fpage>–<lpage>983</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/32.8.979</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19725248</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dauvilliers</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Montplaisir</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cochen</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Post-H1N1 narcolepsy-cataplexy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1428</fpage>–<lpage>1430</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/33.11.1428</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21102981</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Warby</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Narcolepsy onset is seasonal and increased following the 2009 H1N1 pandemic in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>70</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>410</fpage>–<lpage>417</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ana.22587</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21866560</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Koepsell</surname>
<given-names>TD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Longstreth</surname>
<given-names>WT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ton</surname>
<given-names>TG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Medical exposures in youth and the frequency of narcolepsy with cataplexy: a population-based case-control study in genetically predisposed people</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1 Pt 1</issue>):<fpage>80</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.2009.00756.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19732319</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Böttger</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Rapid determination of bacterial ribosomal RNA sequences by direct sequencing of enzymatically amplified DNA</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">FEMS Microbiol Lett</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>1–2</issue>):<fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.1989.tb03617.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2482222</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Qin</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raes</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A human gut microbial gene catalogue established by metagenomic sequencing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nature</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>464</volume>(<issue>7285</issue>):<fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20203603</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rooks</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garrett</surname>
<given-names>WS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Gut microbiota, metabolites and host immunity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Immunol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>341</fpage>–<lpage>352</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nri.2016.42</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27231050</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Turnbaugh</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ley</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mahowald</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Magrini</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mardis</surname>
<given-names>ER</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gordon</surname>
<given-names>JI</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>An obesity-associated gut microbiome with increased capacity for energy harvest</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nature</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>444</volume>(<issue>7122</issue>):<fpage>1027</fpage>–<lpage>1031</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature05414</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17183312</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Krueger</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Opp</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and microbes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int Rev Neurobiol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>131</volume>:<fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>225</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27793219</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Poroyko</surname>
<given-names>VA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carreras</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khalyfa</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Chronic sleep disruption alters gut microbiota, induces systemic and adipose tissue inflammation and insulin resistance in mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>35405</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep35405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27739530</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zeng</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Gut microbiome remodeling induces depressive-like behaviors through a pathway mediated by the host’s metabolism</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>786</fpage>–<lpage>796</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2016.44</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27067014</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Badran</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mashaqi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gozal</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The gut microbiome as a target for adjuvant therapy in obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Expert Opin Ther Targets</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1263</fpage>–<lpage>1282</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14728222.2020.1841749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33180654</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cryan</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Riordan</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sandhu</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peterson</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dinan</surname>
<given-names>TG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The gut microbiome in neurological disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>194</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(19)30356-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31753762</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lecomte</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barateau</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pereira</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Gut microbiota composition is associated with narcolepsy type 1</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurol Neuroimmunol Neuroinflamm</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e896</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/NXI.0000000000000896</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33037102</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Beneficial effect of GABA-rich fermented milk on insomnia involving regulation of gut microbiota</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Microbiol Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>233</volume>:<fpage>126409</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micres.2020.126409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31927503</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mignot</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lammers</surname>
<given-names>GJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ripley</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The role of cerebrospinal fluid hypocretin measurement in the diagnosis of narcolepsy and other hypersomnias</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1553</fpage>–<lpage>1562</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archneur.59.10.1553</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12374492</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mignot</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Young</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Finn</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Nocturnal sleep and daytime sleepiness in normal subjects with HLA-DQB1*0602</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>347</fpage>–<lpage>352</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10341385</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Segata</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Izard</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Waldron</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Metagenomic biomarker discovery and explanation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Genome Biol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>R60</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2011-12-6-r60</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21702898</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schuld</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hebebrand</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Geller</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pollmächer</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Increased body-mass index in patients with narcolepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>355</volume>(<issue>9211</issue>):<fpage>1274</fpage>–<lpage>1275</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(05)74704-8</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Inocente</surname>
<given-names>CO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lavault</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lecendreux</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impact of obesity in children with narcolepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">CNS Neurosci Ther</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>521</fpage>–<lpage>528</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cns.12105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23574649</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rocca</surname>
<given-names>FL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pizza</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ricci</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Plazzi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Narcolepsy during childhood: an update</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropediatrics</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>198</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0035-1550152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25961600</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mandrekar</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>St</surname>
<given-names>LEK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Silber</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kotagal</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Comorbidities in a community sample of narcolepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>14</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2017.11.1125</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29482805</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kallweit</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schmidt</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bassetti</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Patient-reported measures of narcolepsy: the need for better assessment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>737</fpage>–<lpage>744</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.6596</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28162143</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Rosenberg Russell,Hirshkowitz Max,Rapoport David M, Kryger Meir. The role of home sleep testing for evaluation of patients with excessive daytime sleepiness: focus on obstructive sleep apnea and narcolepsy. Sleep Med. 2019; 56:80–89.doi:10.1016/j.sleep.2019.01.014</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Thorpy</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krieger</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Delayed diagnosis of narcolepsy: characterization and impact</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>502</fpage>–<lpage>507</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2014.01.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24780133</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hui</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ip</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ling</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A multicentre surveillance study on the characteristics, bacterial aetiologies and in vitro antibiotic susceptibilities in patients with acute exacerbations of chronic bronchitis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Respirology</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>532</fpage>–<lpage>539</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1843.2011.01943.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21299688</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Achouiti</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Vos</surname>
<given-names>AF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van ‘T Veer</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Receptor for Advanced Glycation End Products (RAGE) serves a protective role during Klebsiella pneumoniae - induced pneumonia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e0141000</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0141000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26824892</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liao</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Characterization of the blood and cerebrospinal fluid microbiome in children with bacterial meningitis and its potential correlation with inflammation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">mSystems</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e0004921</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSystems.00049-21</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34100633</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Benítez-Páez</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gómez</surname>
<given-names>DPEM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>López-Almela</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moya-Pérez</surname>
<given-names>Á</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Codoñer-Franch</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sanz</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Depletion of blautia species in the microbiota of obese children relates to intestinal inflammation and metabolic phenotype worsening</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">mSystems</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSystems.00857-19</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hua</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhan</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Role of Actinobacteria and Coriobacteriia in the antidepressant effects of ketamine in an inflammation model of depression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pharmacol Biochem Behav</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>176</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>100</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbb.2018.12.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30528936</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jang</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yeom</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ahn</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Acupuncture inhibits neuroinflammation and gut microbial dysbiosis in a mouse model of Parkinson’s disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Behav Immun</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>641</fpage>–<lpage>655</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2020.08.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32827699</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Everard</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lazarevic</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Derrien</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Responses of gut microbiota and glucose and lipid metabolism to prebiotics in genetic obese and diet-induced leptin-resistant mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2775</fpage>–<lpage>2786</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/db11-0227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21933985</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fielding</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reeves</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jasuja</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barrett</surname>
<given-names>BB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lustgarten</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Muscle strength is increased in mice that are colonized with microbiota from high-functioning older adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Exp Gerontol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>127</volume>:<fpage>110722</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exger.2019.110722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31493521</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ozato</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saito</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Blautia genus associated with visceral fat accumulation in adults 20–76 years of age</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">NPJ Biofilms Microbiomes</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>28</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41522-019-0101-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31602309</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jiao</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baker</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nugent</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Gut microbiome may contribute to insulin resistance and systemic inflammation in obese rodents: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiol Genomics</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>244</fpage>–<lpage>254</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physiolgenomics.00114.2017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29373083</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dahl</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rivero</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lambert</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Diet, nutrients and the microbiome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Prog Mol Biol Transl Sci</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>171</volume>:<fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>263</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32475524</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Picchioni</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mignot</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harsh</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The month-of-birth pattern in narcolepsy is moderated by cataplexy severity and may be independent of HLA-DQB1*0602</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1471</fpage>–<lpage>1475</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/27.8.1471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15683136</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shimada</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miyagawa</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Toyoda</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tokunaga</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Honda</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Epigenome-wide association study of DNA methylation in narcolepsy: an integrated genetic and epigenetic approach</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>4</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsy019</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sarkanen</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alakuijala</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Julkunen</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Partinen</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Narcolepsy associated with pandemrix vaccine</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Neurol Neurosci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>43</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11910-018-0851-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29855798</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vuorela</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Freitag</surname>
<given-names>TL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leskinen</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Enhanced influenza A H1N1 T cell epitope recognition and cross-reactivity to protein-O-mannosyltransferase 1 in Pandemrix-associated narcolepsy type 1</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Commun</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>2283</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-22637-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33863907</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Morais</surname>
<given-names>LH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schreiber</surname>
<given-names>HL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mazmanian</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The gut microbiota-brain axis in behaviour and brain disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>255</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-020-00460-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33093662</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fei</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>An opportunistic pathogen isolated from the gut of an obese human causes obesity in germfree mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">ISME J</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>880</fpage>–<lpage>884</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ismej.2012.153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23235292</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>van Son</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koekkoek</surname>
<given-names>LL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>La Fleur</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Serlie</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nieuwdorp</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The role of the gut microbiota in the gut-brain axis in obesity: mechanisms and future implications</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Mol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2993</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms22062993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33804250</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hansen</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kornum</surname>
<given-names>BR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jennum</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep-wake stability in narcolepsy patients with normal, low and unmeasurable hypocretin levels</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2017.01.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28522076</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Harsh</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peszka</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hartwig</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mitler</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Night-time sleep and daytime sleepiness in narcolepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>316</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2869.2000.00217.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11012872</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0055">
        <label>55.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gupta</surname>
<given-names>VK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paul</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dutta</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Geography, ethnicity or subsistence-specific variations in human microbiome composition and diversity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1162</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2017.01162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28690602</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0056">
        <label>56.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Maier</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pruteanu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuhn</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Extensive impact of non-antibiotic drugs on human gut bacteria</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nature</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>555</volume>(<issue>7698</issue>):<fpage>623</fpage>–<lpage>628</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature25979</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29555994</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0057">
        <label>57.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wing</surname>
<given-names>YK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>RH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lam</surname>
<given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ho</surname>
<given-names>CK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fong</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leung</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The prevalence of narcolepsy among Chinese in Hong Kong</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>578</fpage>–<lpage>584</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ana.10162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12112103</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
