<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34795545</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">8593898</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">266240</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S266240</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Review</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Understanding the Impact of the COVID-19 Pandemic, Lockdowns and Social Isolation on Sleep Quality</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">O’Regan et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">O’Regan et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3809-022X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>O’Regan</surname>
            <given-names>David</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4976-8101</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Jackson</surname>
            <given-names>Melinda L</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2291-6952</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Young</surname>
            <given-names>Allan H</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2152-9694</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Rosenzweig</surname>
            <given-names>Ivana</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Sleep Disorders Centre, Guy’s and St Thomas’ Hospital, GSTT NHS</institution>, <addr-line>London</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Faculty of Life and Sciences Medicine, King’s College London</institution>, <addr-line>London</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Turner Institute for Brain and Mental Health, Monash University</institution>, <addr-line>Melbourne</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>School of Academic Psychiatry, IoPPN, King’s College London</institution>, <addr-line>London</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label><institution>Sleep and Brain Plasticity Centre, CNS, IoPPN, King’s College London</institution>, <addr-line>London</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Ivana Rosenzweig <institution>Sleep and Brain Plasticity Centre, Department of Neuroimaging, Institute of Psychiatry, Psychology and Neuroscience</institution>, <addr-line>Box 089, De Crespigny Park</addr-line>, <addr-line>London</addr-line>, <addr-line>SE5 8AF</addr-line>, <country>UK</country> Email ivana.1.rosenzweig@kcl.ac.uk</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>11</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>13</volume>
      <fpage>2053</fpage>
      <lpage>2064</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2021 O’Regan et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>O’Regan et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The uncertain, ever-changing and an ongoing nature of the COVID-19 pandemic means that it may take some time before we can fully appreciate the negative effect of the pandemic and lockdown on our sleep and mental health. It is increasingly recognised that in the aftermath of pandemic, several persistent sleep, neuropsychiatric and physical sequelae may continue long after the pandemic is over. A body of evidence to date also highlights a significant disparity in sleep and mental health difficulties in specific vulnerable groups in the community, with different temporal profiles and sleep issues that are reported. In this perspective, we argue for a possible mechanistic impact of the COVID-19 pandemic, with its imposed restrictions and social isolation on sleep quality. We similarly discuss some of the potential international differences, as well as similarities, behind reported idiosyncratic biological vulnerabilities that may have contributed to the genesis of sleep issues. Lastly, we propose some possible implementations and innovations that may be needed in restructuring of sleep disorders services in order to benefit recovering COVID-19 patients.</citation_analysis></p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>sleep</kwd>
        <kwd>insomnia</kwd>
        <kwd>hypersomnia</kwd>
        <kwd>lockdown</kwd>
        <kwd>COVID-19 pandemic</kwd>
        <kwd>social isolation</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="2"/>
        <ref-count count="94"/>
        <page-count count="12"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">During the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic across the globe, public health measures have been implemented to reduce community transmission of the virus, including stay-at-home orders, quarantine, and social distancing measures.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> These measures have had a profound economic and social impact, including disruption to employment and education.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Moreover, these restrictions have also had important neuropsychiatric consequences for the population as a whole, with forced social isolation leading to an increase in reported psychiatric symptoms, including stress, anxiety and depression for all individuals.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1–4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> It has been suggested that this relationship seems to be moderated by the loneliness associated with prolonged periods of lockdown, and maladaptive changes in lifestyle, including disturbed sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1–3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The notion that such a global event would lead to a further global pandemic of disturbed sleep in wide swathes of the population is perhaps unsurprising, given that sleep is pivotal for recovery and physiologic adaptation to the waking experiences.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The bidirectional relationship between sleep and emotional brain function appears to be supported by the findings of studies that build on long-standing clinical observations of co-occurring mood and sleep disorders.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Over the last two years, impressive global scientific effort has been undertaken to examine the clinical sequelae and biology of the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) virus, with increasing awareness that SARS-CoV-2 can affect the central and peripheral nervous system.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In a recent meta-analytical estimate of point prevalence of neurological or neuropsychiatric symptoms, sleep disorders were recognized as one of the most frequently reported symptoms, with a 23.5-point prevalence,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> similar to depression and headache estimates.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The heterogeneity of reported neuropsychiatric symptoms precludes us from drawing conclusions about the potential differential mechanistic platforms behind the detrimental biological effects of isolation and heightened stress versus those potentially solely exacerbated by the SARS-CoV-2 infection. The resulting effects and subsequent sleep issues in both cases are most likely due to a complex interplay of a myriad of biological and environmental factors, including: electrolyte abnormalities, liver inflammation, impaired renal function, impaired oxygenation, hyper-inflammation, and isolation due to public health concerns.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Moreover, current evidence suggests that idiosyncratic factors, including, for example, pre-morbid psychiatric illness, may be both a risk factor for and a consequence of COVID-19.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In a pre-COVID-19 study that analyzed sleep data from 41,094 participants,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> socio-economic disadvantage, ethnic minority background, shift work, unhealthy lifestyle, poor health, depressive symptoms and obesity were highlighted as the major risk factors associated with poor sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> It has also been suggested that around a third of the total effect of socio-economic deprivation on poor sleep may be mediated through depressive symptoms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Thus, vulnerable individuals appear to be at greatest risk of developing sleep problems due to these multiple contributors, and may experience both acute and long-term sleep and other neuropsychiatric disorders.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In this perspective review, we draw on evidence from various lines of ongoing research to assess how the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic, imposed restrictions and social isolation have impacted sleep quality. We evaluate how different countries and particular conditions, including idiosyncratic biological vulnerabilities, have contributed to the genesis of sleep issues, and we consider possible implementations and innovations needed in restructuring of sleep disorder services to benefit recovering COVID-19 patients.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Sleep and Neuropsychiatric Complications of the COVID-19 Pandemic, Lockdown, Infection and Vaccination</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>COVID-19 Pandemic and Lockdown</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">One of the earliest studies of the effects of COVID-19 pandemic reported findings from a survey of 2254 participants, aged 16–75 years.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The findings echoed a general mood pervasive in the United Kingdom (UK) in May 2020, just a few months after the UK government announced lockdown measures.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> This survey for the first time suggested a possible significant short (and long) term impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on the quality of sleep and anxiety levels in the UK.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In the survey, six out of ten people reported suffering from disturbed, unrefreshing sleep, of both shorter and longer duration, with unusually vivid dreams.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> A slightly later UK cross-sectional online survey-based study on adults living through the COVID-19 pandemic similarly found that 69.4% of 843 participants had disturbed sleep patterns.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Of those, less than half (44.7%) had refreshing sleep, 45.6% were sleepier than before the lockdown and 65.2% reported an impact on their mental health, with 25.9% reporting drinking more alcohol during the lockdown.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Of note is that respondents with suspected COVID-19 were also found to have more vivid nightmares and abnormal sleep rhythms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> These findings were mirrored by an Italian online web-based study of 5988 adults, also undertaken during lockdown, which revealed that disturbed sleep patterns in part predicted higher dream recall, as well as nightmares.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Other important psycho-social predictors of nightmares in this study included: anxiety, depression, those who had stopped working, and those who had friends/relatives who were infected by or who had died of COVID-19</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>13</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. As discussed further below, when taken together, these findings are in keeping with the continuity hypothesis of dreaming.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Very early on, we, and others, argued that some of those reported sleep symptoms (eg vivid dreams) possibly reflected the biological response to the extraordinary stress and uncertainty that the populace was facing.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16–19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> For example, it is known that rapid eye movement (REM) sleep structure, during which most of our dreaming occurs, changes first during chronic stress, and more so than any other measured sleep characteristic.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Moreover, REM sleep has been suggested to play a role in recalibrating the sensitivity and specificity of the brain’s response to emotional events on both ends of positive and negative spectrum, suggesting a bidirectional impact of any such REM sleep disturbance on affected individuals.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Similarly, Steenblock et al argued for a link between the ongoing SARS-COV-2 outbreak and the neuroendocrine stress axis.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> They warned of uncertain long-term outcomes for those who have been actually infected, as well as for those who are not necessarily infected themselves, but who may suffer lasting consequences as a result of loss, grief, isolation, deprivation, and other psychological outcomes of ongoing quarantine or shelter in place measures.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> These groups include health care workers, and others whose lives were severely affected.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> From earlier coronavirus outbreaks, it has been evident that survivors and health care workers are at increased risk of developing mental illness years after the outbreak.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> It has been argued that such long-lasting impacts might be due to morphological changes in the brain and in the organs of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> with the added complexity of widely differing gender responses to stress. Worryingly, it has also been suggested that permanent epigenetic changes in stem cells may occur due to actual infection, as well as that they may result from the different forms of severe stress,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> further suggesting likely profound and long-term effects of the current pandemic.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>COVID-19 Infection</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Studies to date have also suggested that microvascular infarcts and haemorrhages, which are part of the systemic coagulopathy and vasculopathy of COVID-19, may be critical in the development of encephalopathy, delirium and other neurological and psychiatric manifestations of SARS-CoV-2 infection.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The consensus on whether disturbances of higher mental function occur predominantly without direct infection of the central nervous system neurons has not yet been reached; however, it does appear that the virus can enter the brain,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> when it may infect vascular and immune cells.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The direct SARS-CoV-2 invasion of the CNS likely occurs at the blood-brain barrier via transcellular migration through host endothelial cells, paracellular migration through tight junctions, and an immune system “Trojan horse” cell passing through the blood-brain barrier.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our group has recently proposed that a relatively unique fingerprint of sleep and ultradian rhythms disturbance, along with heightened levels of anxiety, during SARS-CoV-2 infection may in some patients result from viral binding to neuronal angiotensin-converting-enzyme-2 (ACE2)-receptors in a specific part of the brain’s hypothalamic paraventricular nucleus (PVN) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> It is known that SARS-CoV-2 can directly decrease ACE2 activity and lead to cell toxicity in other tissues.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> This interaction is believed to subsequently lead to a myriad of symptoms, from increased blood pressure to kidney failure.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Arguably, any such potential direct or indirect SARS-CoV-2 effect on the PVN circuitry, a major brain computational hub that ensures timely processing of multiple physiologic signals, would significantly affect pivotal short-term biological rhythms and sleep patterns, resulting in increased, debilitating and misdirected anxiety.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The schematic illustration of the basic neuronal organization of the paraventricular nucleus (PVN) of the hypothalamus depicting its purported role in a four-step model of neurocircuitry of anxiety. On the left, a four-step model by Calhoon and Tye is shown: according to this model external events are detected, interpreted, evaluated, and responded to by succeeding levels of highly interconnected neural circuits. Reproduced by permission from Springer Nature, Nat Neurosci, Resolving the neural circuits of anxiety, Calhoon GG, Tye KM. 2015;18(10):1394–1404. Copyright © 2015, Nature Publishing Group, a division of Macmillan Publishers Limited.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0092" ref-type="bibr">92</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Events are further interpreted as threatening or nonthreatening depending on the balance between opposing circuits; when the balanced is shifted toward projections interpreting events as threatening, this leads to anxiety. On the right, PVN’s neurocircuitry is depicted. Afferent inputs to the nucleus arrive from many important integrative centers of the medulla, pons and hypothalamus. Subfornical organ is among major inputs with identified angiotensin release acting directly on magnocellular and parvocellular neurons, or indirectly via intranuclear circuitry that includes inhibitory Gamma-aminobutyric-acid (GABA) (red) and excitatory glutamate (green) interneurons. Changes within paraventricular angiotensin subcircuitries are described under stress condition and are reflected on release of stress hormone and arousal. GABA interneurons have been shown to express angiotensin-converting-enzyme-2 (ACE2),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0093" ref-type="bibr">93</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and as such might be targeted by severe-acute-respiratory-syndrome-coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2). The majority of GABA interneurons have been localized to the halo zone surrounding the PVN, and their role as an additional gatekeeper and integrator in controlling the excitability of PVN outputs has been proposed.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0094" ref-type="bibr">94</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Any changes in the PVN circuitries, due to their major control over most of neuro-endocrine axes and neuronal autonomic centers may cause robust alteration in homeostatic regulation, and through influence on regulatory brain centers impact on sleep and wakefulness, increased propensity to trigeminal autonomic cephalalgias and alteration of ultradian rhythms.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-2053-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: Reproduced from Rosenzweig I, Mitrečić D, Petanjek Z, et al. Does damage to hypothalamic paraventricular nucleus underlie symptoms of ultradian rhythm disorder and an increased anxiety in coronavirus disease 2019? <italic toggle="yes">Croatian Medical Journal</italic>. 2020;61(4):377–380. Copyright © 2020 by the Croatian Medical Journal. All rights are reserved. Creative Commons Attribution License<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>.</attrib><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: ad, anterodorsal nucleus of the BNST; ACE2, angiotensin-converting-enzyme-2; AHA, anterior hypothalamic area; BLA, basolateral amygdala; BNST, bed nucleus of the stria terminalis; CeA, central amygdala; CeL, lateral subdivision of the central amygdala; CeM, centromedial subdivision of the amygdala; DVC, dorsal vagal complex; GABA, Gamma-aminobutyric-acid; IL, infralimbic division of the mPFC; LH, lateral hypothalamus; LS, lateral septum; mPFC, medial prefrontal cortex; NAc, nucleus accumbens; ov, oval nucleus of the BNST; PAG, periaqueductal gray; PB, parabrachial nucleus; PL, prelimbic division of the mPFC; PVH/PVN, paraventricular nucleus of the hypothalamus; SARS-CoV-2, severe-acute-respiratory-syndrome-coronavirus-2; v, ventral BNST; vHPC, ventral hippocampus; vPallidum, ventral pallidum; VTA, ventral tegmental area.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Unsurprisingly, the data regarding the long-term cognitive consequences of COVID-19 is still lacking, but one study of 279 patients hospitalized with COVID-19 found that, three months after discharge, 34% reported significant memory loss and 28% described impaired concentration.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Comparable findings have been observed following infection with other coronaviruses, in which 20% reported cognitive deficits months to years after initial infection.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In keeping with this, Taquet et al,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> who have recently reported results from a large USA dataset, showed that in the six months after SARS-CoV-2 infection, about a third of these individuals had a neurological or psychiatric disorder, more than comparative figures for influenza.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Most of these heterogenic neurological or psychiatric disorders were more common in patients who had COVID-19 than in those who had influenza and those who had other respiratory tract infections.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Another study that examined the differential psychological impact of COVID-19 infection in 7917 participants, of whom 49.7 were healthcare professionals with a high representation of female participants,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> reported suicidal thoughts in 32% of respondents.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Healthcare professionals reported mild depression and anxiety in higher proportions to other respondents.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Increasing age and female gender were linked to higher compliance with governmental advice on COVID-19, whereas higher education, homeowners, key worker status, high alcohol, drug use and participants with pre-existing suicidal thoughts were linked to lower compliance with governmental advice.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Moreover, a striking psychological impact on the wellbeing of frontline healthcare professionals was demonstrated, with many clinicians increasingly raising concerns about future retainment as well as recruitment to medical specialty and healthcare sector.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>COVID-19 Vaccination</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Finally, another potentially controversial side to the ongoing pandemic is the possible unknown long-term effect of different COVID-19 vaccines, for which the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein was a major target.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> It is clear that the development of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein-based COVID-19 vaccine has been one of the major scientific and medical breakthroughs of the 21st century, which has provided much-needed hope on how to end the current pandemic. However, the limited findings of several in vitro and post-mortem studies suggest that the recombinant SARS-CoV-2 spike protein S1 subunit could be potentially sufficient to promote cell signaling without the remaining viral components.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Similarly, at present, the insertional mutagenesis safety of mRNA-based vaccines remains largely unresolved.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Going forward, it will be pivotal to keep evaluating the data from SARS-CoV-2 infected individuals, as well as from the healthy individuals who received the spike protein-based vaccines, with further stringent investigations of the effects of the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein in appropriate animal models.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Taken together, the data to date strongly suggest that monitoring of all affected populations for an extended time following the current pandemic might be needed.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>The Effects of Pandemic and Lockdown on Sleep, Circadian Timing and Mental Health Across the Globe</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The COVID-19 pandemic and its associated lockdown(s) have evidently resulted in restrictive lifestyle changes,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> with alterations in important zeitgebers, such as light exposure, meals, social interactions, and exercise resulting in further disruption of chronobiological rhythms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Confinement to homes, which doubled as new workplaces, with simultaneous increase in responsibilities, such as home-schooling</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> additionally occurred in an anxious milieu, with fears regarding contracting COVID-19, employment security, finances, and concerns about the welfare of loved ones.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Many of these anxieties were further fueled by a constant deluge of ever-changing news and government information, leading some to nickname the crisis “an information pandemic”.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The concomitant impact of these lifestyle changes has provided the perfect storm to adversely impact sleep quality, by individually affecting each of the three sleep regulatory processes: the homeostatic sleep drive, the circadian rhythm, and the arousal system.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">During the very early days of the pandemic, in the early part of 2020, an interesting dichotomy with regard to reported changes in sleep was noted around the globe. Studies from Europe, US and UK have reported an increase in sleep opportunity, sleep duration and reduced “social jetlag” during the pandemic.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34–37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Such positive changes are most likely due to alterations in pressurized social and environmental factors, including changes in employment practices, such as remote and flexible working.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Smartphone data of 2.9 million nights of sleep recordings taken from participants across different continents indicated a sudden increase in sleep duration during the early stages of the pandemic, compared to the same time a year earlier.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In addition to increases in sleep duration, changes to sleep timing have also been observed. In one global survey, nearly three quarters of respondents indicated that their sleep patterns have changed as a result of lockdowns, with the majority indicating that their sleep and wake times were delayed compared to before the pandemic, and 43% of respondents indicating that their current sleep timing was more in line with their body clock.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Increasing flexibility in sleep-wake routines resulting from stay-at-home orders has clearly been of benefit to many in society who would have otherwise suffered with reduced sleep opportunity due to occupational and lifestyle commitments. However, for others, being afforded greater flexibility in sleep timing appears to have resulted in more irregular sleep-wake timing, which is known to have adverse effect on academic performance and health outcomes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Indeed, despite some initial benefits that were reported in some sections of western society as the pandemic progressed, the majority of populace has overwhelmingly described disturbed sleep patterns, and diminished sleep quality in comparison to pre-pandemic sleep patterns across the globe.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In one global survey, 73% of respondents reported poor sleep quality, scoring more than five on the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> with around 57% of respondents indicating that their sleep was worse currently compared to before the pandemic.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> This is in line with other prevalence estimates of poor sleep of around 50–55% from Italy,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> however much lower levels were reported around the same time in China (36%).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> These differing rates are likely due to the predominantly female respondents in some surveys, potentially amplifying the prevalence rates of poor sleep. This highlights the limitations of rapid data collection of convenience samples, which may not be representative of the population. Importantly, poor sleep quality has been linked to poorer mental health, both pre-pandemic and in the recent pandemic literature.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In the same global study, it has been shown that individuals who scored more than eight points on the PSQI had a three-fold increased prevalence of significant anxiety, stress and depressive symptoms, even when controlling for pandemic-related factors and demographics.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> While further longitudinal studies are needed to uncover the directionality of these associations, it would appear that addressing poor sleep during lockdowns may help to mitigate some of the adverse mental health effects.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Moreover, for those who were home confined during lockdown, circadian rhythm disruption,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> compounded by increased digital screen time</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> has adversely affected sleep timing and quality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Increased daytime napping, also seen during home confinement, has been shown to reduce sleep pressure (ie the homeostatic sleep drive), resulting in delayed bedtimes, and prolonged sleep onset latency.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Arguably, later bedtimes can also adversely impact slow wave sleep, and its purported function of enabling the glymphatics clearance of brain toxins,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> as well as impact on the overall sleep quality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Thus, circadian and homeostatic factors that interact to regulate sleep have all been adversely affected by lockdown.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">When exploring differences between countries in terms of the rates of sleep difficulties or mental health symptoms, little difference emerged despite dramatic differences in infection rates and COVID-19 related deaths across countries</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> (also see </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Respondents from countries with high case numbers did report higher stress levels, although the effect size was small.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> An interesting case study by Czeisler et al explored the impact on sleep and mental health in respondents from Victoria, Australia – a city with one of the longest and most stringent lockdowns globally (112 days) with relatively low SARS-CoV-2 case numbers (0.32%).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Compared to the status before the pandemic, during Stage 4 restrictions in September 2020 participants reported spending more time in bed and having more trouble sleeping, with one third of respondents reporting anxiety or depressive symptoms and one in ten reporting suicide ideation occurring over the last 30 days.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Around 21% of respondents reported insomnia symptoms, slightly higher than that reported in April 2020 near the start of lockdown.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Critically, suicide ideation was 1.86-fold more prevalent in those with insomnia symptoms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Victorians, who endorsed higher mental health symptoms, had a shorter sleep duration (&lt;six hours), spent more time in bed, had more trouble falling asleep and reported maintaining a less regular sleep-wake schedule.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> On a positive note, those who adapted their behavior and were able to keep more regular sleep times and avoid COVID-19 media coverage had a lower prevalence of depression and anxiety symptoms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> This study provided a unique perspective on the impact of lockdown on sleep and mental health symptoms, suggesting that these effects may not transient, as well as that individual idiosyncratic factors might play a significant role in the valence of the reported outcomes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Stress, depression, anxiety, and insomnia symptoms across countries with the top five number of respondents by insomnia group (n = 2525). Error bars indicate 95% confidence intervals.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-2053-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: PSS, perceived stress scale; STAI-6, 6-item state anxiety inventory; PHQ-9, patient health questionnaire-9 item; SCI, sleep condition indicator.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Mediating Factors and Vulnerable Groups</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">A body of evidence to date similarly highlights a significant disparity in sleep and mental health difficulties in specific groups in the community. For instance, it has been reported that in South Africa, the lockdown has caused substantial economic hardship, especially among poor and vulnerable people, with possible important long-term consequences.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Moreover, restrictions on movement and the risk of contracting COVID-19 in health care facilities in South Africa have brought major reductions in the use of health services, thereby compromising continuity of care for people with HIV, tuberculosis, and chronic noncommunicable diseases.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The COVID-19 pandemic has also had a particularly significant impact on people with Alzheimer’s disease (AD) and other dementias internationally.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> This vulnerable population has been shown to be particularly susceptible not just to SARS-CoV-2 infection, but also to the negative effects of the measures taken worldwide to control the spread of the virus, with loneliness and isolation aggravating and accelerating the clinical picture.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Internationally, an overwhelming trend towards later bedtimes, delayed sleep onset, a reduction in total sleep time and quality, has been reported together with increased daytime napping during lockdowns.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Loneliness, uncertainty, depression and COVID-19 related-worries were only some of the important psycho-social drivers in underlying these changes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> These changes were more pronounced in younger people, women, those with a pre-existing neurologic and psychiatric conditions, unpaid caregivers and frontline workers, those who were unemployed, and in those who lived in less supportive welfare states,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> suggesting that these groups may be more vulnerable to the acute and longer term effects of the pandemic.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Younger adults (under 45 years) appeared to be more affected during the pandemic, and higher levels of stress, anxiety and depressive symptoms were reported in that age group by comparison to older age groups.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In addition, loneliness and financial difficulties have been linked to the higher rates of mental health symptoms in this age group.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Reflecting the pre-pandemic sex disparity in insomnia prevalence, women increasingly appear to be more affected by lockdown in terms of their sleep. In a longitudinal study in Italy, insomnia severity and mental health symptoms were reported to be greater in women than men during the early stages of lockdown,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and this finding closely echoes other reports across the globe.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Interestingly, however, in follow-up surveys and as the lockdown continued, the gender-gap narrowed across all measures.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Thus, the impact of prolonged lockdown may have differential temporal effects on men and women, which may necessitate differential therapeutic approaches.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Historically and during the pandemic, poor sleep has been linked to greater financial difficulties, greater disability, and an increase in alcohol consumption.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Behavioral factors are also likely to directly impact sleep during lockdowns. For instance, a decrease in sunlight exposure, daily exercise and increased phone usage before bedtime have been linked to poorer sleep quality during lockdown.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The interactions between sleep, diet, substance use and exercise are complex, with changes in one domain likely to impact the others.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> For example, we know that inadequate sleep is likely to promote poorer health behaviors, such as reducing the motivation to exercise and to eat healthily.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Moreover, those with poorer sleep during lockdown may be tempted to self-medicate with alcohol</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and/or other illicit substances,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> in hopes of improving their sleep. Unfortunately, such strategies merely worsen sleep, and further accelerate or initiate insomnia.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> An association between alcohol abuse and the risk of violent offending has previously also been shown, with particular relevance for vulnerable sections of the society, including those with premorbid psychiatric disorders.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Many of these health behaviors have been shown to be affected by the psychological status and social connectedness of the individual, both of which have been adversely affected by lockdown.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> For many, lonely days mean lonely nights, resulting in poor sleep quality, with subsequent adverse effects on other health behaviors.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Social isolation can potentially also lead to a precarious state of chronic heightened anxiety that can increase individual’s vulnerability to coercion and abuse during the pandemic.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Indeed, poorer sleep quality and higher levels of loneliness have been found to mediate the relationship between stress and mental health symptoms (depression, anxiety), highlighting the critical, but modifiable, impact of sleep on mental health during lockdown.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Pragmatic Focus on Sequelae of Insomnia and Hypersomnia</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Insomnia symptoms frequently manifest in the face of acute life changes or stressors, such as pandemics,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> and unsurprisingly, studies conducted during the COVID-19 pandemic have overwhelmingly and consistently shown a significant increase in insomnia symptoms, ranging from 18% to 63%.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Whilst some of these insomnia symptoms may be categorized as mild, it has been well accepted that transient sleep disturbances can later lead to chronic insomnia disorders.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> A recent study by Meaklim et al reported on difference in mental health symptoms in individuals with pre-existing insomnia, individuals who had developed insomnia symptoms during the pandemic and healthy sleepers.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> For individuals with post-pandemic insomnia symptoms, 77% believed that factors surrounding the pandemic triggered their insomnia symptoms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Those who developed insomnia symptoms during the pandemic also had higher levels of stress, anxiety and depressive symptoms compared to individuals with pre-existing insomnia symptoms, or compared to those who were sleeping well (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Paradoxically, 25–28% of individuals with pre-existing insomnia disorder reported clinically meaningful improvements in sleep quality during the pandemic,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> suggesting that changes in sleep in response to the stressor of the pandemic are not uniform across individuals. While the reasons for this are likely to be multi-faceted, reduction of social and occupational pressure and attenuation of negative mood states have been proposed as potential mechanisms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Moreover, individual experiences of lockdown can vary considerably, and for some people with insomnia, lockdown restrictions may have created a beneficial environment, reducing the stress of work and social commitments. Indeed, a qualitative synthesis of personal experiences during lockdown revealed that those with better sleep quality used more positive language, indicative of social support and positive well-being (eg “friend”).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Some clinicians have argued that enhancement of social support, and an increased social cohesion in some societies during lockdown might have helped to buffer predominantly negative impacts of the pandemic on sleep and well-being.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">A meta-analysis of 177 published studies revealed that insomnia symptoms were most prevalent in healthcare professionals (43%), which further indicated that age, gender, country and marital status did not impact prevalence rates.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> As already mentioned, health professionals, especially frontline workers who regularly care for COVID-19 infected patients, may be at higher risk of insomnia, because of increased fear of risk of infection and death, as well as irregular and more frequent work schedules.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0073" ref-type="bibr">73–75</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> For other “essential” workers besides healthcare, earlier wake times, and reduced total sleep times were also seen, when compared to “non-essential” workers.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">There is a paucity of published research regarding lockdown and hypersomnolence, although the data from surveys around the globe clearly suggest that decreased sleep quality has been accompanied by both the decreases, and increases in sleep duration during the pandemic.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Historically, hypersomnolence has been seen as a direct consequence of viral infection and/or treatment in pandemics;</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0077" ref-type="bibr">77–79</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and such neuropsychiatric consequences may be delayed ie it may be too early to judge the fallout of COVID-19 in this regard.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Indirectly, the increased stress experienced by people during lockdown, may lead to hypersomnolence; either as a coping mechanism, or as part of a mental health disorder such as depression or Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> For those who are home confined in lockdown, excessive daytime somnolence may also be a way of escaping social isolation, loneliness and/or boredom.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Moreover, some people with insomnia present with excessive daytime sleepiness as their principal symptom, and may under-appreciate the effect of poor nocturnal sleep quality and/or maladaptive sleep-related behaviors in driving this.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Finally, many patients do not differentiate between hypersomnolence, tiredness and fatigue, and may use these terms interchangeably; and/or confuse hypersomnolence with clinophilia.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0085" ref-type="bibr">85</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> An appreciation of the bio-psycho-social determinants of reported hypersomnolence will be essential for clinicians in the post-lockdown era, as we are likely to face an increase in atypical sleep and neuropsychiatric presentations.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref></citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusions and Suggestions for Post-COVID Sleep Disorder’s Clinical Infrastructure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Our scientific understanding of the impact of COVID-19 continues to evolve rapidly, with a concomitant influence on the provision of clinical sleep services and new therapeutic recommendations.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> It is increasingly recognized that in the aftermath of SARS-CoV-2 infection/pandemic-related traumatic experiences, several persistent sleep, neuropsychiatric and physical sequelae may continue long once the pandemic is over.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In addition, due to the complexity of COVID-19 and its treatment, some affected patients may require longitudinal follow-up, most appropriately delivered by the interdisciplinary post-COVID-19 clinics that should ideally include sleep physicians.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Such post-COVID-19 clinics should aim to provide care in a systematic and carefully coordinated fashion across multiple specialties with complementary expertise (i.e., internal medicine, psychiatry, sleep medicine, neuropsychology and physical therapy), with further accelerated access to cardiology, nephrology, infectious disease, pain specialists, pulmonary, geriatrics, neurology, nutrition, occupational health and other specialists.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> This unique design should also help facilitate exceptional teaching and international research opportunities.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Going forward, shared clinical databases and open access to clinical research data, with an emphasis on educational outreach to other healthcare professionals and the wider community should be encouraged and nurtured.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">These educational projects and outreaches should be preferably coordinated by international and national sleep societies, which should all work together to address the sleep difficulties incurred during lockdown, by advocating good sleep practices (e.g., minimizing pre-bed screen exposure, setting a fixed rising time, morning light exposure and exercise),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0087" ref-type="bibr">87</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> as well as looking after mental, emotional and social health.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Many of these recommendations have already received media attention, but await research and validation.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0085" ref-type="bibr">85</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Managing the sheer number of people reporting sleep difficulties, and associated health and functioning sequelae will be challenging. As we have seen with other pandemics, insomnia and associated daytime dysfunction persist long after the threat of infection has passed.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Non-pharmacological techniques, like digital Cognitive Behavioral Therapy for Insomnia (dCBT-I) have been successful during lockdown, improving insomnia measures and daytime function.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Further validation of the provision of these therapeutic modalities, including digital therapeutics, and an expansion to other sleep disorders,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> is now urgently required in order to stem the tsunami of lockdown-associated sleep difficulties and its consequences. Future clinical trials are similarly needed to clarify the optimal treatment strategies for sleep and other potentially long-term neuropsychiatric impacts of COVID-19.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Finally, on the individual level, one of the rare silver linings of the pandemic is that it allowed a significant minority to take a step back and to reflect on how they live and sleep, and particularly how they work, and some of those insights have been reported as potentially life-changing.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> These are the types of insights that can enable people to stay resilient in the face of adversity, and it will be important to try to implement these strategies into our new normal. Workplaces may need to think about adopting more flexibility in terms of working from home, or flexible work hours in industries that permit this, so that employees can better align their work and sleep with their own natural body clocks – which will make them happier and more productive in the long run.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors wish to thank Dr Prerna Varma and Ms Hailey Meaklim (Australia) for their leadership of the Sleep in the Time of COVID surveys, and Ms Meaklim for creating the figure for this manuscript. The authors further wish to thank all the members of the Sleep Disorders Centre at Guy’s Hospital (London, UK) for all their unwavering dedication to their patients during the COVID-19 pandemic time.</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0006">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Professor Young’s independent research is funded by the National Institute for Health Research (NIHR) Biomedical Research Centre at South London and Maudsley NHS Foundation Trust and King’s College London. Professor Allan H Young reports personal fees from Lundbeck, grants, personal fees, from Janssen, grants, personal fees, from Livanova, personal fees from Sunovion, grants from Compass, grants, personal fees from Novartis, personal fees from Sumitomo Dainippon Pharma, personal fees from Bionomics, personal fees from Allegan, outside the submitted work; and Employed by King’s College London; Honorary Consultant SLaM (NHS UK) Deputy Editor, BJPsych Open Paid lectures and advisory boards for the following companies with drugs used in affective and related disorders: Astrazenaca, Eli Lilly, Lundbeck, Sunovion, Servier, Livanova, Janssen, Allegan, Bionomics, Sumitomo Dainippon Pharma, COMPASS Consultant to Johnson &amp; Johnson Consultant to Livanova Received honoraria for attending advisory boards and presenting talks at meetings organised by LivaNova. Principal Investigator in the Restore-Life VNS registry study funded by LivaNova. Principal Investigator on ESKETINTRD3004: “An Open-label, Long-term, Safety and Efficacy Study of Intranasal Esketamine in Treatment-resistant Depression.” Principal Investigator on “The Effects of Psilocybin on Cognitive Function in Healthy Participants” Principal Investigator on “The Safety and Efficacy of Psilocybin in Participants with Treatment-Resistant Depression (P-TRD)” UK Chief Investigator for Novartis MDD study MIJ821A12201 Grant funding (past and present): NIMH (USA); CIHR (Canada); NARSAD (USA); Stanley Medical Research Institute (USA); MRC (UK); Wellcome Trust (UK); Royal College of Physicians (Edin); BMA (UK); UBC-VGH Foundation (Canada); WEDC (Canada); CCS Depression Research Fund (Canada); MSFHR (Canada); NIHR (UK). Janssen (UK) No shareholdings in pharmaceutical companies.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest. The views expressed are those of the authors and not necessarily those of the NHS, the NIHR, or the Department of Health.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Meaklim</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Junge Moira</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Varma</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Finck W</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jackson M</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pre-existing and post-pandemic insomnia symptoms are associated with high levels of stress, anxiety and depression globally during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2085</fpage>–<lpage>2097</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.9354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33985647</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rogers</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Watson</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Badenoch</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. et al. <article-title>Neurology and neuropsychiatry of COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis of the early literature reveals frequent CNS manifestations and key emerging narratives</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</italic></source>;<year>2021</year>:<page-range>jnnp-2021-326405</page-range>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jnnp-2021-326405</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Numbers</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brodaty</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effects of the COVID-19 pandemic on people with dementia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41582-020-00450-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33408384</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nakamura</surname>
<given-names>ZM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nash</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laughon</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosenstein</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Neuropsychiatric complications of COVID-19</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Psychiatry Rep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>25</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11920-021-01237-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33725218</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nollet</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hicks</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCarthy</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>REM sleep’s unique associations with corticosterone regulation, apoptotic pathways, and behavior in chronic stress in mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>116</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>2733</fpage>–<lpage>2742</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1816456116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30683720</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rosenzweig</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Glasser</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Polsek</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leschziner</surname>
<given-names>GD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morrell</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep apnoea and the brain: a complex relationship</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Respir Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>404</fpage>–<lpage>414</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(15)00090-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25887982</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jackson</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tolson</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bartlett</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berlowitz</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Varma</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barnes</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Clinical depression in untreated obstructive sleep apnea: examining predictors and a meta-analysis of prevalence rates</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2019.03.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31525678</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Helbok</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chou</surname>
<given-names>SH-Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beghi</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>NeuroCOVID: it’s time to join forces globally</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>805</fpage>–<lpage>806</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(20)30322-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32949535</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Solomon</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Neurological infection with SARS-CoV-2 - the story so far</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41582-020-00453-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33414554</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fatima</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bucks</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mamun</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep trajectories and mediators of poor sleep: findings from the longitudinal analysis of 41,094 participants of the UK Biobank cohort</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>120</fpage>–<lpage>127</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.10.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33157426</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Duffy</surname>, <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>How the UK is Sleeping Under Lockdown [Press Release]</article-title>. <publisher-name>King’s College London</publisher-name>; <year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Perez-Carbonell</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meurling</surname>
<given-names>IJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wassermann</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impact of the novel coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic on sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Thorac Dis</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>Suppl 2</issue>):<fpage>S163</fpage>–<lpage>S175</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/jtd-cus-2020-015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33214921</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Scarpelli</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alfonsi</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mangiaruga</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Pandemic nightmares: effects on dream activity of the COVID-19 lockdown in Italy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e13300</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.13300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33547703</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Barrett</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dreams about COVID-19 versus normative dreams: trends by gender</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Dreaming</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>216</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/drm0000149</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Scarpelli</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gorgoni</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alfonsi</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The impact of the end of COVID confinement on pandemic dreams, as assessed by a weekly sleep diary: a longitudinal investigation in Italy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>:<fpage>e13429</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.13429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34288197</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dzierzewski</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dautovich</surname>
<given-names>ND</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ravyts</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perez</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Soto</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Donovan</surname>
<given-names>EK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia symptoms during the COVID-19 pandemic: an examination of biopsychosocial moderators</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2021.02.018</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Florea</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Topalidis</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hauser</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep during COVID-19 lockdown: a cross-cultural study investigating job system relevance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biochem Pharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>191</volume>:<fpage>114463</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bcp.2021.114463</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33577893</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rosenzweig</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mitrečić</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petanjek</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Does damage to hypothalamic paraventricular nucleus underlie symptoms of ultradian rhythm disorder and an increased anxiety in coronavirus disease 2019?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Croat Med J</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>61</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>380</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3325/cmj.2020.61.377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32881437</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Steenblock</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Todorov</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kanczkowski</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) and the neuroendocrine stress axis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1611</fpage>–<lpage>1617</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41380-020-0758-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32382135</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Goldstein</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Walker</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The role of sleep in emotional brain function</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Annu Rev Clin Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>679</fpage>–<lpage>708</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-clinpsy-032813-153716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24499013</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Suzuki</surname>
<given-names>YJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gychka</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>SARS-CoV-2 spike protein elicits cell signaling in human host cells: implications for possible consequences of COVID-19 vaccines</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vaccines (Basel)</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>36</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33440640</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Garrigues</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Janvier</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kherabi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Post-discharge persistent symptoms and health-related quality of life after hospitalization for COVID-19</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Infect</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>81</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e4</fpage>–<lpage>e6</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2020.08.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32853602</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Taquet</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Geddes</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Husain</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luciano</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harrison</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>6-month neurological and psychiatric outcomes in 236 379 survivors of COVID-19: a retrospective cohort study using electronic health records</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>416</fpage>–<lpage>427</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2215-0366(21)00084-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33836148</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rathod</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pallikadavath</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Young</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Psychological impact of COVID-19 pandemic: protocol and results of first three weeks from an international cross-section survey - focus on health professionals</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Affect Disord Rep</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>100005</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jadr.2020.100005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33313579</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Suzuki</surname>
<given-names>YJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nikolaienko</surname>
<given-names>SI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dibrova</surname>
<given-names>VA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>SARS-CoV-2 spike protein-mediated cell signaling in lung vascular cells</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vascul Pharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>137</volume>:<fpage>106823</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vph.2020.106823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33232769</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Suryawanshi</surname>
<given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koganti</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Agelidis</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patil</surname>
<given-names>CD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shukla</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dysregulation of cell signaling by SARS-CoV-2</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Trends Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>224</fpage>–<lpage>237</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tim.2020.12.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33451855</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Domazet-Lošo</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">mRNA Vaccines: Why is the Biology of Retroposition Ignored?</italic></source></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Galli</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reglero</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bartolini</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Visioli</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Better prepare for the next one. Lifestyle lessons from the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PharmaNutrition</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>100193</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phanu.2020.100193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32382499</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Altena</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baglioni</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Espie</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Dealing with sleep problems during home confinement due to the COVID-19 outbreak: practical recommendations from a task force of the European CBT-I Academy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e13052</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.13052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32246787</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gupta</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grover</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Basu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Changes in sleep pattern and sleep quality during COVID-19 lockdown</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Indian J Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>62</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>370</fpage>–<lpage>378</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/psychiatry.IndianJPsychiatry_523_20</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33165382</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kearsley</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duffy</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The COVID-19 information pandemic: how have we managed the surge?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Anaesthesia</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>993</fpage>–<lpage>996</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/anae.15121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32406517</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Leger</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beck</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fressard</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Verger</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peretti-Watel</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>; <collab>Group C</collab>. <article-title>Poor sleep associated with overuse of media during the COVID-19 lockdown</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>10</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsaa125</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Simpson</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Manber</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Treating Insomnia during the COVID-19 pandemic: observations and perspectives from a behavioral sleep medicine clinic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>573</fpage>–<lpage>575</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15402002.2020.1765781</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32426998</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Blume</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schmidt</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cajochen</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of the COVID-19 lockdown on human sleep and rest-activity rhythms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Biol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>R795</fpage>–<lpage>R797</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32693067</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wright</surname>
<given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Linton</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Withrow</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep in University students prior to and during COVID-19 stay-at-home orders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Biol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>R797</fpage>–<lpage>R798</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2020.06.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32693068</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Robbins</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Affouf</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weaver</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Estimated sleep duration before and during the COVID-19 pandemic in major metropolitan areas on different continents: observational study of smartphone app data</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Med Internet Res</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e20546</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/20546</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33493126</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Beck</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leger</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cortaredona</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Verger</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peretti-Watel</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>; <collab>group C</collab>. <article-title>Would we recover better sleep at the end of Covid-19? A relative improvement observed at the population level with the end of the lockdown in France</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>119</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.11.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33422813</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Salfi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lauriola</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>D’Atri</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Demographic, psychological, chronobiological, and work-related predictors of sleep disturbances during the COVID-19 lockdown in Italy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>11416</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-90993-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34075173</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Staller</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Randler</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Changes in sleep schedule and chronotype due to COVID-19 restrictions and home office</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Somnologie (Berl)</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>137</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Varma</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burge</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meaklim</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Junge</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jackson</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Poor sleep quality and its relationship with individual characteristics, personal experiences and mental health during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>11</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph18116030</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Phillips</surname>
<given-names>AJK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clerx</surname>
<given-names>WM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Brien</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Irregular sleep/wake patterns are associated with poorer academic performance and delayed circadian and sleep/wake timing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>3216</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-03171-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28607474</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mariani</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Redline</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep irregularity and risk of cardiovascular events</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>991</fpage>–<lpage>999</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2019.12.054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32138974</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cellini</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Canale</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mioni</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Costa</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Changes in sleep pattern, sense of time and digital media use during COVID-19 lockdown in Italy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e13074</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.13074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32410272</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lan</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Perceived stress and sleep quality among the non-diseased general public in China during the 2019 coronavirus disease: a moderated mediation model</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>339</fpage>–<lpage>345</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.05.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32482485</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Franceschini</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Musetti</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zenesini</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Poor sleep quality and its consequences on mental health during the COVID-19 lockdown in Italy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>574475</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2020.574475</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33304294</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sultana</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tasnim</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hossain</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Purohit</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Digital screen time during the COVID-19 pandemic: a public health concern</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">F1000Research</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12688/f1000research.50880.1</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jacob</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trott</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The association between screen time and mental health during COVID-19: a cross sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>292</volume>:<fpage>113333</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32738551</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Salfi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amicucci</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Corigliano</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Changes of evening exposure to electronic devices during the COVID-19 lockdown affect the time course of sleep disturbances</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>9</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsab080</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Voitsidis</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gliatas</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bairachtari</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia during the COVID-19 pandemic in a Greek population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>289</volume>:<fpage>113076</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113076</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nedergaard</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goldman</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Glymphatic failure as a final common pathway to dementia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Science</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>370</volume>(<issue>6512</issue>):<fpage>50</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abb8739</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33004510</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Borbely</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Daan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wirz-Justice</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deboer</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The two-process model of sleep regulation: a reappraisal</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>143</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26762182</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Đogaš</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lušić Kalcina</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pavlinac Dodig</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The effect of COVID-19 lockdown on lifestyle and mood in Croatian general population: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Croat Med J</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>61</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>318</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3325/cmj.2020.61.309</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32881428</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Czeisler</surname>
<given-names>MÉ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wiley</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Facer-Childs</surname>
<given-names>ER</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Mental health, substance use, and suicidal ideation during a prolonged COVID-19–related lockdown in a region with low SARS-CoV-2 prevalence</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychiatr Res</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>140</volume>:<fpage>533</fpage>–<lpage>544</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2021.05.080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34174556</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Abdool Karim</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The South African response to the pandemic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>382</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>e95</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMc2014960</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32469479</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0055">
        <label>55.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cellini</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Conte</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Rosa</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Changes in sleep timing and subjective sleep quality during the COVID-19 lockdown in Italy and Belgium: age, gender and working status as modulating factors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>112</fpage>–<lpage>119</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.11.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33348298</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0056">
        <label>56.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Czeisler</surname>
<given-names>MÉ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lane</surname>
<given-names>RI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petrosky</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Mental health, substance use, and suicidal ideation during the COVID-19 pandemic - United States, June 24- 30, 2020</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>32</issue>):<fpage>1049</fpage>–<lpage>1057</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm6932a1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32790653</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0057">
        <label>57.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rossell</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Neill</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Phillipou</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>An overview of current mental health in the general population of Australia during the COVID-19 pandemic: results from the COLLATE project</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>296</volume>:<fpage>113660</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33373808</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0058">
        <label>58.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Salfi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lauriola</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amicucci</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Gender-related time course of sleep disturbances and psychological symptoms during the COVID-19 lockdown: a longitudinal study on the Italian population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurobiol Stress</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>100259</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ynstr.2020.100259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33102641</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0059">
        <label>59.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Matias</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dominski</surname>
<given-names>FH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marks</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Human needs in COVID-19 isolation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Health Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>871</fpage>–<lpage>882</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1359105320925149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32375564</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0060">
        <label>60.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Baron</surname>
<given-names>KG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Culnan</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep and Healthy Decision Making</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>; <year>2019</year>:<fpage>359</fpage>–<lpage>369</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0061">
        <label>61.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ramalho</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adiukwu</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gashi Bytyci</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Alcohol and tobacco use during the COVID-19 pandemic. A call for local actions for global impact</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>634254</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2021.634254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33679487</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0062">
        <label>62.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Doraiswamy</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheema</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Al Mulla</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mamtani</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>COVID-19 lockdown and lifestyles – a narrative review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes"><ext-link xlink:href="http://Med&#xA0;Pharmacol" ext-link-type="uri">Med Pharmacol</ext-link></italic></source>. <year>2021</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.20944/preprints202011.0532.v2</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0063">
        <label>63.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stein</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Friedmann</surname>
<given-names>PD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Disturbed sleep and its relationship to alcohol use</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Subst Abus</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1300/J465v26n01_01</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0064">
        <label>64.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kudumija Slijepcevic</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jukic</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Novalic</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zarkovic-Palijan</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Milosevic</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosenzweig</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Alcohol abuse as the strongest risk factor for violent offending in patients with paranoid schizophrenia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Croat Med J</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>156</fpage>–<lpage>162</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3325/cmj.2014.55.156</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24778102</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0065">
        <label>65.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bu</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Steptoe</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fancourt</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0066">
        <label>66.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chaudhury</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Samudra</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>COVID-19 lockdown: psychological effects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Med J Dr DY Patil Vidyapeeth</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>580</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/mjdrdypu.mjdrdypu_230_20</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0067">
        <label>67.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cacioppo</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hawkley</surname>
<given-names>LC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berntson</surname>
<given-names>GG</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Do lonely days invade the nights? Potential social modulation of sleep efficiency</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>384</fpage>–<lpage>387</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0956-7976.2002.00469.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12137144</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0068">
        <label>68.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rosenzweig</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Vignette on Canetti, crowds, and the self in times of COVID-19</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Croat Med J</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>61</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>308</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3325/cmj.2020.61.307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32881427</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0069">
        <label>69.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Acharibasam</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chireh</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Menegesha</surname>
<given-names>HG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Assessing anxiety, depression and insomnia symptoms among Ebola survivors in Africa: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e0246515</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0246515</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33544772</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0070">
        <label>70.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pieh</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Budimir</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Delgadillo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barkham</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fontaine</surname>
<given-names>JRJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Probst</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mental health during COVID-19 lockdown in the United Kingdom</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychosom Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>83</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>328</fpage>–<lpage>337</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PSY.0000000000000871</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33009276</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0071">
        <label>71.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Alimoradi</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Broström</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsang</surname>
<given-names>HWH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep problems during COVID-19 pandemic and its’ association to psychological distress: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">EClinicalMedicine</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>100916</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.100916</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34131640</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0072">
        <label>72.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kocevska</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blanken</surname>
<given-names>TF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Someren</surname>
<given-names>EJW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rösler</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep quality during the COVID-19 pandemic: not one size fits all</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>86</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.09.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33126035</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0073">
        <label>73.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ferri</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guadi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marcheselli</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Balduzzi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Magnani</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Di Lorenzo</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The impact of shift work on the psychological and physical health of nurses in a general hospital: a comparison between rotating night shifts and day shifts</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Risk Manag Healthc Policy</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/RMHP.S115326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27695372</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0074">
        <label>74.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mohanty</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kabi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mohanty</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Health problems in healthcare workers: a review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Family Med Prim Care</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>2568</fpage>–<lpage>2572</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31548933</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0075">
        <label>75.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fatima</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bucks</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mamun</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Shift work is associated with increased risk of COVID-19: findings from the UK Biobank cohort</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>e13326</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33686714</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0076">
        <label>76.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Blume</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schmidt</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cajochen</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of the COVID-19 lockdown on human sleep and rest-activity rhythms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Biol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>R795</fpage>–<lpage>R797</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32693067</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0077">
        <label>77.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Manjunatha</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Math</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kulkarni</surname>
<given-names>GB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chaturvedi</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The neuropsychiatric aspects of influenza/swine flu: a selective review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ind Psychiatry J</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0972-6748.102479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23271861</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0078">
        <label>78.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Economo</surname>
<given-names>CV</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Encephalitis lethargica, its sequelae and treatment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Med Assoc</italic></source>. <year>1932</year>;<volume>98</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>255</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.1932.02730290071039</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0079">
        <label>79.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Troyer</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kohn</surname>
<given-names>JN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hong</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Are we facing a crashing wave of neuropsychiatric sequelae of COVID-19? Neuropsychiatric symptoms and potential immunologic mechanisms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Behav Immun</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>87</volume>:<fpage>34</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2020.04.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32298803</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0080">
        <label>80.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Salfi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>D’Atri</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tempesta</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferrara</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleeping under the waves: a longitudinal study across the contagion peaks of the COVID-19 pandemic in Italy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e13313</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.13313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33687798</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0081">
        <label>81.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Barateau</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lopez</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Franchi</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dauvilliers</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Hypersomnolence, hypersomnia, and mood disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Psychiatry Rep</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>13</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11920-017-0763-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28243864</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0082">
        <label>82.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Selsick</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Regan</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disorders in psychiatry</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BJ Psych Advan</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>283</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/bja.2018.8</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0083">
        <label>83.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Duggan</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McDevitt</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whitehurst</surname>
<given-names>LN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mednick</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>To nap, perchance to DREAM: a factor analysis of college students’ self-reported reasons for napping</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>153</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15402002.2016.1178115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27347727</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0084">
        <label>84.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lichstein</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilson</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Noe</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aguillard</surname>
<given-names>RN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bellur</surname>
<given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Daytime sleepiness in insomnia: behavioral, biological and subjective indices</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>693</fpage>–<lpage>702</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/17.8.693</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7701180</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0085">
        <label>85.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Becker</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Overview of sleep management during COVID-19</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2021.04.024</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0086">
        <label>86.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jauhar</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lai</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bonoldi</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Early intervention in psychosis during the COVID-19 pandemic: Maudsley recommendations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Neuropsychopharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>130</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.euroneuro.2021.02.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33642195</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0087">
        <label>87.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Morin</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carrier</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bastien</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Godbout</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Canadian</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Circadian</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and circadian rhythm in response to the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Can J Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>111</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>654</fpage>–<lpage>657</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17269/s41997-020-00382-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32700231</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0088">
        <label>88.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Datta</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tripathi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and Covid-19</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurol India</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0028-3886.310073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33642266</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0089">
        <label>89.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Magill</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Siegel</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pike</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The mental health of frontline health care providers during pandemics: a rapid review of the literature</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatr Serv</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1260</fpage>–<lpage>1269</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ps.202000274</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33019857</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0090">
        <label>90.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Arnedt</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Conroy</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mooney</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Furgal</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eisenberg</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Telemedicine versus face-to-face delivery of cognitive behavioral therapy for insomnia: a randomized controlled noninferiority trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>1</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsaa136</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0091">
        <label>91.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>O’Regan</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nesbitt</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Biabani</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A novel group cognitive behavioural therapy approach to adult non-rapid eye movement parasomnias</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychiatry</italic></source>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2021.679272</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0092">
        <label>92.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Calhoon</surname>
<given-names>GG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tye</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Resolving the neural circuits of anxiety</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1394</fpage>–<lpage>1404</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.4101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26404714</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0093">
        <label>93.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mukerjee</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sato</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zsombok</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lazartigues</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>ACE2 and ADAM17 interaction regulates the activity of presympathetic neurons</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>74</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1181</fpage>–<lpage>1191</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.119.13133</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31564162</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0094">
        <label>94.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ferguson</surname>
<given-names>AV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Latchford</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Samson</surname>
<given-names>WK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The paraventricular nucleus of the hypothalamus - a potential target for integrative treatment of autonomic dysfunction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Expert Opin Ther Targets</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>717</fpage>–<lpage>727</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1517/14728222.12.6.717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18479218</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
