<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34899001</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">8653846</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">330770</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S330770</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Use of CPAP Machines in the Perioperative Setting in Ambulatory Surgical Centers</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Marull et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Marull et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Marull</surname>
            <given-names>Javier</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4927-6492</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Vachon</surname>
            <given-names>M Jonathan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Buitran</surname>
            <given-names>Dylan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Macaluso</surname>
            <given-names>Amy</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line>Dallas</addr-line>, <addr-line>TX</addr-line>, <addr-line>75390</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>University of California Irvine</institution>, <addr-line>Irvine</addr-line>, <addr-line>CA</addr-line>, <addr-line>92697</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Javier Marull <institution>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line>1801 Inwood Road, 2nd Floor Outpatient Surgery Center</addr-line>, <addr-line>Dallas</addr-line>, <addr-line>TX</addr-line>, <addr-line>75390</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>
<phone>Tel +1 214-403-4592</phone> Email javier.marull@utsouthwestern.edu</corresp>
        <fn id="ft0001">
          <label>*</label>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">These authors contributed equally to this work</citation_analysis></p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>04</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>13</volume>
      <fpage>2137</fpage>
      <lpage>2140</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2021 Marull et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Marull et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec sec-type="intro" id="s2001">
          <title>Introduction</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Obstructive sleep apnea is a common sleep-related breathing disorder that is associated with significant perioperative complications. In 2012 and 2017, Society of Ambulatory Anesthesia and Society of Anesthesia and Sleep Medicine published consensus statements for the selection of patients with OSA scheduled for ambulatory surgery. Despite these recommendations, the need for a CPAP device in the immediate postoperative period at ambulatory surgical centers remains controversial because these ambulatory patients are healthier and have fewer complications. This study aims to investigate the compliance rate with this recommendation among busy ASCs.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We created a survey to investigate if ASCs require patients to bring their CPAP devices to the facility. The survey measured compliance rates of ASCs to SAMBA’s recommended guidelines of having CPAP machines available.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The survey had a response rate of 60.9% encompassing 408,147 cases among 1946 providers. Of the facilities that responded, only 59.7% of them required their patients to bring their CPAP devices on the day of surgery. Out of the 67 facilities that responded, only 25.37% reported using a CPAP machine postoperatively within the past 2 years, with the highest CPAP usage at one facility being 20 times in that 2-year period.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Discussion</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">This would mean that 40.3% of ASCs that did respond do not have access to a CPAP device on-site and may possibly lack the proper equipment needed to handle these complications. The frequency and fatality rate associated with postoperative respiratory complications requiring a CPAP device are still inconclusive, making the need for CPAP devices during perioperative management controversial. Studies further in-depth are therefore necessary to assess postoperative complications that require the use of a CPAP device to determine the urgency of ASCs implementing SAMBA’s recommendations.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>obstructive sleep apnea</kwd>
        <kwd>perioperative care</kwd>
        <kwd>postoperative care</kwd>
        <kwd>CPAP</kwd>
        <kwd>compliance</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="1"/>
        <ref-count count="7"/>
        <page-count count="4"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) plays a significant role in the planning of perioperative management of patients. OSA is characterized by recurrent episodes of partial (hypopnea) or complete (apnea) interruption in breathing during sleep, and symptoms include loud snoring, nocturnal awakening, and daytime sleepiness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Physically, patients with OSA commonly have a wider neck circumference and a smaller pharyngeal space, leading to airway obstruction that can pose a significant challenge in perioperative management. Its etiology is multifactorial, and management is predicated on the severity of obstruction.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">OSA has been linked to causing certain cardiovascular diseases such as hypertension, coronary artery disease, and atrial fibrillation. Classically, OSA is treated with weight loss management and a Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP) machine, which provides a constant positive pressure through the pharyngeal space, stimulating muscle activity in the pharynx, allowing for more airflow.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The risks associated with perioperative management of patients with OSA include ineffective mask ventilation and intubation, postoperative airway obstruction, and other complications resulting from comorbid conditions.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Asphyxiation and aspiration are the major risks in the perioperative management of patients with OSA, as many medications used by anesthesiologists depress muscle activity and suppress arousal responses, resulting in the airway being inaccessible during operations.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In 2012 and 2017, SAMBA (Society of Ambulatory Anesthesia) and SASM (Society of Anesthesia and Sleep Medicine) published consensus statements for the selection of patients with OSA scheduled for ambulatory surgery.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Despite these guidelines, the need for a CPAP device in the immediate postoperative period remains controversial. At many ASCs, CPAP devices are not currently being used because the patients at these facilities are healthier and usually have only mild-to-moderate OSA. Also, patients may forget to bring the CPAP device or it is not feasible for them to bring it for the same-day surgery. Many anesthesiologists have observed that the CPAP machines are not being used at the ASCs as recommended. Reasons for the noncompliance with the recommendations include the quick emergence and recovery of the patients for the faster day surgery cases, and these patients are only in the PACU for an average of 1 hour postoperatively at ASCs. This study aims to investigate the compliance rate with this recommendation among busy ambulatory surgery centers (ASC) who mainly have healthy patients with mild-to-moderate OSA or those with OSA and well-managed comorbidities, as the need for CPAP machines in the postoperative period at these ASCs remains unclear. To this end, we decided to conduct a survey of medical directors of ASCs throughout the United States (US).</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We created a survey to investigate if the ASCs that accept OSA patients require the patients to bring their CPAP devices to the facility (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="ut0001" ref-type="table">Box 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). Additionally, we inquired if those ASCs used CPAP devices in the immediate postoperative period within the past 2 years. The survey was validated by five practitioners of busy ASCs to confirm whether any of the questions were difficult to understand or to answer via email, and a reminder email was sent if no response was received within a month. The results of the survey were analyzed using spreadsheets and presented as percentages.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="ut0001"><label>Box 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Survey to Investigate if the ASCs That Accept OSA Patients Require Patients to Bring Their CPAP Devices to the Facility. Additionally, We Inquired if Those ASCs Used CPAP Devices in the Immediate Postoperative Period Within the Past 2 Years</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Questions Asked in the Survey to the ASCs</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of surgical procedures per year.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of anesthesiologists/anesthesia providers.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Do you have patients with OSA in your facility? If yes, please proceed with the next question.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Do you ask your patients to bring their CPAP machine to the ASC? If not, why?</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">How often have you had to use a CPAP machine in your facility in the past 2 years?</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The survey had a response rate of 60.9% (67 of 110 ASC medical directors that submitted the survey), encompassing 408,147 cases among 1946 providers. Of the facilities that responded, only 59.7% of them required their patients to bring their CPAP devices on the day of surgery. Out of the 67 facilities that responded, only 25.37% (17/67) reported using a CPAP machine postoperatively within the past 2 years, with the highest CPAP usage being 20 times at one facility during that 2-year period.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion/Conclusion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Obstructive Sleep Apnea is a respiratory condition that increases the risk of CV disease, notably atrial fibrillation, hypertension, and coronary artery disease. Perioperatively, it also increases the risk for ineffective mask ventilation and intubation, postoperative airway obstruction, asphyxiation, and aspiration. In 2012 and 2017, SAMBA (Society of Ambulatory Anesthesia) and SASM (Society of Anesthesia and Sleep Medicine) published consensus statements for the selection of patients with OSA scheduled for ambulatory surgery.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The recommendations include:
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><list list-type="order"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Patients with a known diagnosis of OSA and optimized comorbid medical conditions can be considered for ambulatory surgery if they are able to use the CPAP device in the postoperative period.</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Patients with presumed diagnosis of OSA, based on screening tools such as the STOP-Bang questionnaire and optimized comorbid conditions can be considered for ambulatory surgery if postoperative pain can be managed predominantly with non-opioid analgesic techniques. It is not necessary to postpone surgery in this patient population.</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">OSA patients with non-optimized comorbid conditions may not be ideal candidates for ambulatory surgery.</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Patients receiving preoperative CPAP should be instructed to bring their CPAP device to the ambulatory care facility unless one is available at the facility.</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Continued use of PAP therapy at previously prescribed settings is recommended during periods of sleep, both preoperatively and postoperatively. Adjustments may need to be made to the settings to account for perioperative changes such as facial swelling, fluid shifts, recent pharmacotherapy, and pulmonary function.</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The survey we conducted showed that 59.7% of the ASC facilities (40) that responded adhered to SAMBA’s recommendations, having access to CPAP devices on-site to treat immediate postoperative complications in patients with OSA (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="ut0001" ref-type="table">Box 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). This would mean that 40.3% of ASCs (27/40) that did respond do not have access to a CPAP device on-site and, as a result, may possibly lack the proper equipment needed to handle these complications. However, approximately 75% of the ASCs that followed SAMBA’s recommendations by having CPAP available did not actually use the CPAP device postoperatively within the last two years. The highest reported CPAP usage rate was only 20 times in that 2-year period at one facility. The frequency and fatality rate associated with postoperative respiratory complications requiring a CPAP device at ASCs with healthier OSA patients are still inconclusive, making the need for CPAP devices during perioperative management at these facilities controversial. Therefore, more in-depth studies are necessary to assess postoperative complications that require the use of a CPAP device in order to determine the urgency of ASCs implementing SAMBA’s recommendations. A proposal for correction of this problem of not using the CPAP devices at the ASCs as recommended could include the following:
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Bring a permanent hospital CPAP and get approval by Biomed,</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Train nurses how to use the CPAP device,</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Assign PACU nurses one to one with OSA patients,</citation_analysis></p></list-item><list-item><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Keep OSA patients in PACU longer.</citation_analysis></p></list-item></list></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Other considerations for future OSA studies for postoperative treatment will also need to include the new hypoglossal nerve stimulator devices (Inspire) as treatment considerations for OSA in the perioperative period.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Compliance rate of ASCs that responded to the survey of SAMBA’s recommendations for the perioperative management of patients with OSA (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">ASC’s compliance with SAMBA recommendations for perioperative management of patients with OSA.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-2137-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Contents have not been published elsewhere, and the paper is not being submitted elsewhere.</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Ethics Statement</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Approval was not required for this research by an institutional review board or ethics committee due to a survey that was sent to medical directors of ambulatory surgery centers and reviews of medical charts were not necessary.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0006">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>De Backer</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea/hypopnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Panminerva Med</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>195</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23676959</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>171</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>ITC81</fpage>–<lpage>ITC96</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/AITC201912030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31791057</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chowdhury</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wedderburn</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duffy</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Greenough</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>CPAP review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Pediatr</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>171</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1441</fpage>–<lpage>1448</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00431-011-1648-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22173399</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fassbender</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Herbstreit</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eikermann</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Teschler</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peters</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea-a perioperative risk factor</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Dtsch Arztebl Int</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>113</volume>(<issue>27–28</issue>):<fpage>463</fpage>–<lpage>469</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3238/arztebl.2016.0463</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27476705</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hillman</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Loadsman</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Platt</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eastwood</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea and anaesthesia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>459</fpage>–<lpage>471</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2004.07.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15556378</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Joshi</surname>
<given-names>GP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ankichetty</surname>
<given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gan</surname>
<given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Society for ambulatory anesthesia consensus statement on preoperative selection of adult patients with obstructive sleep apnea scheduled for ambulatory surgery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Anesth Analg</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>115</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1060</fpage>–<lpage>1068</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1213/ANE.0b013e318269cfd7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22886843</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Joshi</surname>
<given-names>GP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Preoperative screening and assessment of patients with obstructive sleep apnea: perspectives from ASA, SAMBA and SASM</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">ASA Monit</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
