<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34992481</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">8714019</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">344842</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S344842</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Frequency‑Specific Regional Homogeneity Alterations and Cognitive Function in Obstructive Sleep Apnea Before and After Short-Term Continuous Positive Airway Pressure Treatment</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Li et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Li et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6631-123X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Haijun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Lan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kong</surname>
            <given-names>Linghong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Panmei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zeng</surname>
            <given-names>Yaping</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Kunyao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xie</surname>
            <given-names>Wei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shu</surname>
            <given-names>Yongqiang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Xiang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Peng</surname>
            <given-names>Dechang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Medical Imaging Center, The First Affiliated Hospital of Nanchang University</institution>, <addr-line>Nanchang City</addr-line>, <addr-line>Jiangxi Province</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>PET Center, The First Affiliated Hospital of Nanchang University</institution>, <addr-line>Nanchang City</addr-line>, <addr-line>Jiangxi Province</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Jiangxi Provincial Institute of Parasitic Diseases Control</institution>, <addr-line>Nanchang City</addr-line>, <addr-line>Jiangxi Province</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Dechang Peng <institution>The First Affiliated Hospital of Nanchang University</institution>, <addr-line>No. 17, Yongwai Zheng Street, Donghu District</addr-line>, <addr-line>Nanchang City</addr-line>, <addr-line>330006</addr-line>, <addr-line>Jiangxi Province</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>
<phone>Tel +86 79186427560</phone> Email pengdcdoctor@163.com</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>24</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>13</volume>
      <fpage>2221</fpage>
      <lpage>2238</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2021 Li et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Li et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Previous studies have demonstrated abnormal local spontaneous brain activity in the conventional frequency bands (0.01–0.08 Hz) in obstructive sleep apnea (OSA). However, it is not clear whether these abnormalities are associated with the specific frequency band of low-frequency oscillations or whether it can be improved with a continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) treatment. This study aimed to investigate the regional homogeneity (ReHo) in specific frequency at baseline (pre-CPAP) and after one month of CPAP adherence treatment (post-CPAP) in OSA patients.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Twenty-one patients with moderate-to-severe OSA and 21 age- and sex-matched healthy controls (HCs) were included in the final analysis. ReHo was calculated in three different frequency bands (typical frequency band: 0.01–0.1 Hz; slow-5 band: 0.01–0.027 Hz; slow-4 band: 0.027–0.073 Hz), respectively. A partial correlational analysis was performed to assess the relationship between altered ReHo and clinical evaluation.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">OSA patients revealed increased ReHo in the brainstem, bilateral inferior temporal gyrus (ITG)/fusiform, and right-cerebellum posterior lobe (CPL), and decreased ReHo in the bilateral inferior parietal lobule (IPL), right superior temporal gyrus (STG), and left precentral gyrus (PG) compared to HC groups in different frequency bands. Significantly changed ReHo in the bilateral middle temporal gyrus (MTG), PG, medial frontal gyrus (MFG), supplementary motor area (SMA), CPL, IPL, left superior frontal gyrus (SFG), ITG, MTG, and right STG were observed between post-CPAP and pre-CPAP OSA patients, which was associated with specific frequency bands. The altered ReHo in specific frequency bands was correlated with Montreal cognitive assessment score, Epworth sleepiness scale, and apnea hypopnea index in pre-CPAP OSA patients.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">These findings indicate that OSA has frequency-related abnormalities of spontaneous neural activity before and after short-term CPAP treatment, which might contribute to a better understanding of local neural psychopathology and may serve as potential biomarkers for clinical CPAP treatment.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>obstructive sleep apnea</kwd>
        <kwd>treatment</kwd>
        <kwd>frequency band</kwd>
        <kwd>local connectivity</kwd>
        <kwd>resting-state functional magnetic resonance imaging</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="8"/>
        <table-count count="13"/>
        <ref-count count="54"/>
        <page-count count="18"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA), characterized by repeated partial collapse and obstructions of the upper airway leading to intermittent hypoxia, hypercapnia, and sleep fragmentation, is one of the most common sleep disorders and affects at least 4% of middle-aged women and 6% of middle-aged men.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> The cognitive impairments, including memory, learning, attention, and executive function that may cause difficulties in work performance and increase the risk of industrial and vehicular accidents and reduce the quality of life, are recognized as clinical consequences of OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> If OSA patients are not treated for cognitive impairment, they should be considered a moderate risk for Alzheimer’s disease.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Progressive changes in sleep structure and quality, as well as changes in cerebral blood flow, neurovasculature and neurotransmitter, may lead to cognitive deficits in OSA patients.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Previous studies found OSA-related brain alterations especially in brain regions responsible for cognitive and emotional functions, which are primarily thought to be caused by oxidative stress, ischemia- reperfusion injury, and an increase in sympathetic vasoconstriction associated with hypoxemia.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, the exact neural mechanisms of cognitive impairment in OSA patients are complex and unclear.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) is one of the most important treatments widely used for OSA. Numerous studies have shown that effective treatments not only alleviate daytime sleepiness and reduce nocturnal symptoms but also improve neurocognitive abnormalities.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Although the effectiveness of CPAP therapy has been widely recognized, it does not completely reverse cognitive symptoms in all patients. Some studies have suggested that the varying degrees of neuronal damage caused by chronic intermittent hypoxia may be the reason for the different responses of OSA patients receiving the same CPAP therapy.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Other studies suggest that the results may be related to selected neuropsychological tests, which vary in sensitivity to treatment effects.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, the underlying neural mechanisms of the CPAP therapy response are poorly understood.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Neuroimaging methods could explore changes in the brain caused by CPAP therapy and provide new insights into the cognitive response after CPAP therapy. There is growing evidence that OSA-related brain morphological changes can be ameliorated by CPAP therapy. Rosenzweig et al reported that the right thalamus showed hypertrophy with improved ESS and delayed memory scores after one month of CPAP therapy, which suggested that short-term CPAP therapy can lead to adaptive changes in neurocognitive structures associated with decreased sleepiness and improved memory in OSA patients.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Another long-term CPAP treatment (18.2 ± 12.4 months) study found neocortical and cerebellar atrophy in untreated OSA patients and showed that increased brain volume largely overlapped with the initial atrophy. This study provides neuroimaging evidence of the positive effects of long-term CPAP therapy on OSA patients.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> A study found that the impairment of white matter (WM) integrity in multiple brain regions associated with cognitive impairment and mood in OSA patients was partially improved by 3 months of CPAP, whereas WM abnormalities were almost completely reversed in all affected areas after 12 months of CPAP therapy in OSA patients with good compliance, suggesting that the recovery of cognitive deficits after treatment is consistent with the presence of reversible structural nerve damage in OSA patients receiving CPAP treatment.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Single-photon emission computed tomography (SPECT) found that complete reversal of regional cerebral blood flow (rCBF) decline was observed in the angular, medial orbitofrontal and cerebellum regions, and partial reversal of rCBF decline was observed in the prefrontal and limbic regions responsible for executive, affective, and memory function after more than 6 months of CPAP treatment.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> These studies indicated that partial brain volume and rCBF in OSA patients could be reversed after CPAP treatment. However, there are few studies on spontaneous brain activity related to CPAP therapy in OSA patients.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Compared to other resting-state fMRI methods, such as seed-based functional connectivity,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> independent component analysis</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, and large-scale brain network analysis,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> regional homogeneity (ReHo), which measures the synchronization between a given voxel and its nearest neighbour and reflects the temporal homogeneity of the regional blood oxygen level-dependent (BOLD) signal, is an objective and noninvasive neuroimaging technology.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Due to its multiscale characteristics in frequency, sensitivity, reproducibility and reliability, it is increasingly widely used in neuropsychiatric disorders.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Some studies have detected low-frequency oscillation activities in the conventional frequency band (0.01–0.08 Hz) that are thought to reflect spontaneous neuronal activities. Our previous study found that OSA patients showed abnormal local spontaneous activity in multiple brain regions including the frontal lobe, precuneus and angular gyrus, superior parietal lobule, and cerebellum.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, Zuo et al showed that the low-frequency oscillation of BOLD signals is sensitive to specific frequency bands in different brain regions and divided into four subbands [slow-2 (0.198–0.25 Hz), slow-3 (0.073–0.198 Hz), slow-4 (0.027–0.073 Hz), and slow-5 (0.01–0.027 Hz)].</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Research has shown that the slow-3 and slow-2 bands mainly reflect the white matter signals and the high-frequency physiological noise, while the slow-4 and slow-5 bands mainly reflect the oscillating amplitude signal associated with gray matter. Several studies have investigated the effects of different bands of local spontaneous brain activity.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, it is unclear whether frequency-specific ReHo methods provide more information than conventional frequency bands or whether CPAP responses are frequency-specific in OSA patients.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Based on the above questions, we hypothesized that OSA patients had frequency-specific local spontaneous brain activity abnormalities, and those brain activity abnormalities could be partially reversed after CPAP treatment, which was related to cognitive function. To test this hypothesis, we first used the voxel-level ReHo method to explore local spontaneous brain activity changes in OSA patients before and after CPAP treatment (one-month follow-up) in different frequency bands. Then, the relationship between changed ReHo and clinical features was examined using partial correlation analysis in OSA patients.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Patients</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This study is a short-term longitudinal study, and OSA patient recruitment is shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. Healthy controls (HC) were assessed only at baseline. The HC group was recruited through advertising from the community. All OSA patients were recruited from August 2020 to June 2021 from the sleep monitoring room at the otolaryngology department or respiratory department of the First Affiliated Hospital of Nanchang University. The diagnostic criteria for OSA were according to the American Academy of Sleep Medicine Clinical Practice Guideline for adult obstructive sleep apnea in 2017.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The inclusion criteria for OSA include apnea–hypopnea index (AHI) &gt;15, age 20–60 years, right-handedness, and received standard CPAP therapy for at least 1 month with compliance ≥4 h/night and at least 5 days a week. The exclusion criteria for all subjects were as follows: 1) sleep disorders other than OSA; 2) history of respiratory diseases, hypertension, diabetes, and previous CPAP treatment; 3) history of central nervous system disease, including neurodegenerative disease, epilepsy, brain tumours, and traumatic brain injury; 4) abuse of illicit drugs or current intake of psychoactive medications; 5) MRI contraindications, such as metallic implants in the body, and claustrophobia; 6) image artifacts; and 7) loss to follow-up. Finally, 21 OSA patients and 21 HCs were included in the analysis. We obey the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki. The approval for the study was provided by the Medical Ethics Committee of the First Affiliated Hospital of Nanchang University [No.2020(94)]. The participants signed written informed consent forms for this study.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Schematic of recruiting procedures for the OSA patients in this study.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-2221-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Polysomnography</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Before polysomnography (PSG) monitoring, all subjects were asked not to drink alcohol or coffee. All participants underwent overnight PSG (from 10 PM to 6 AM the next morning) using the Respironics LE-Series physiological monitoring system (Alice 5 LE, Respironics, Orlando, FL, USA) at baseline. The PSG monitoring included a standard electrocardiogram, electrooculogram, electromyogram, electrocardiogram, body position, oral and nasal airflow, thoracic and abdominal respiratory movements, snoring, and oxygen saturation (SaO2), and sleep latency, total sleep time, sleep efficiency, sleep stages, arousal, and respiratory events were recorded. See our previous study for details.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> According to the AASM manual, hypopnea was defined as a 30% or greater drop in airflow, lasting ≥10 seconds, accompanied by 4% or greater oxygen desaturation. Obstructive apnea was described as a continuous reduction in airflow ≥90% for ≥10 seconds along with evident respiratory effort. The AHI was defined as the sum of apnea and hypopnea events per hour during sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Neuropsychological Assessment</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">All OSA patients completed the entire neuropsychological assessment at baseline and the one-month follow-up, including the Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA), Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS), Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI), Hamilton Anxiety Scale (HAMA) and Hamilton Depression Scale (HAMD). The MoCA, including naming, visual space and executive function, attentional, language, delayed memory, abstraction, and orientation, was used to assess cognitive function. The MoCA total score is 30, with a score below 26 considered cognitive impairment, and one point is added as a correction if the years of education are less than 12.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The ESS is a very simple questionnaire for the self-assessment of daytime sleepiness, including eight different conditions, each with a score of 0 to 3, and the total score ranges from 0 to 24. The PSQI was used to evaluate the sleep quality of the subjects in the last month. It consists of 19 self-assessment and 5 other-assessment items, and the total score ranges from 0 to 21. A higher score represented worse sleep quality. The HAMA and HAMD were used to assess anxiety and depression. In general, HAMA scores greater than 14 indicated clinically significant anxiety symptoms. A MAHD score &lt;7 is normal, a score from 7 to 17 indicates possible depression, and a total score of 17 to 24 indicates definitely depressed, severe depression with an overall score &gt;24.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP) Treatment</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All OSA patients received standard CPAP therapy for at least 1 month with compliance ≥4 h/night and at least 5 days a week. They were all sent home using an auto-adjustment model of CPAP ventilator (YH-480, Yuwell, Jiangsu, China), which can detect breathing levels and automatically adjust the pressure needed. The treatment pressure of the ventilator was set at 4–20 cm H</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">O, and the treatment pressure needed was set automatically. Adherence at home was objectively reported by the built-in SIM card of the ventilator, which can upload user data in real time through wireless transmission function, including duration of use and AHI, mask leakage, blood oxygen, etc.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>MRI Data Acquisition</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All participants were acquired on a 3.0 Tesla MRI system with an 8-channel phased-array head coil (Siemens, Munich, Germany) between 7 p.m. and 9 p.m. They were sleeping at a normal time the night before the Scan. First, conventional axial T2-weighted imaging (repetition time (TR) = 4000 ms, echo time (TE) = 113 ms, thickness = 5 mm, gap = 1.5 mm, FOV = 220 mm × 220 mm, slices = 19) and axial T1-weighted imaging (TR = 250 ms, TE = 2.46 ms, thickness = 5 mm, gap = 1.5 mm, field-of-view (FOV) = 220 mm × 220 mm, slices = 19) were performed. High-resolution three-dimensional T1-weighted images were obtained by using a brain volume sequence (TR = 1900 ms, TE = 2.26 ms, thickness = 1.0 mm, gap = 0.5 mm, FOV = 250 mm × 250 mm, matrix = 256 × 256, flip angle = 9°, 176 sagittal slices). Finally, rs-fMRI data were collected using an echo-planar imaging sequence with the following parameters: TR = 2000 ms, TE = 30 ms, flip angle = 90°, FOV = 230 mm × 230 mm, matrix = 64, thickness = 4 mm, gap = 1.2 mm. Each brain volume consisted of 30 axial sections, and each functional run comprised 240 volumes. During MRI scans, all subjects were asked to close their eyes, stay as still as possible, not to think about anything, and not to fall asleep. Foam pads and earplugs were used to reduce patient head movement and scanner noise. Two senior radiologists read the images to exclude gross lesions and motion artifacts.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2006">
        <title>fMRI Data Preprocessing</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Based on MATLAB2018b (MathWorks, Natick, MA, USA), Statistical Parametric Mapping (SPM12, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk/spm/software/spm12/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk/spm/software/spm12/</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) and Data Processing &amp; Analysis for Brain Imaging (DPABI, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="http://rfmri.org/dpabi" ext-link-type="uri">http://rfmri.org/dpabi</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) software were used for image preprocessing. Image preprocessing mainly includes the following steps: remove the first 10 time points; slice-time corrected and three-dimensional head motion corrected; T1 segmentation with the Diffeomorphic Anatomical Registration Through Exponentiated Lie algebra (DARTEL) and spatial normalization to register rs-fMRI datasets to the Montreal Neurological Institute spatially normalized and resampled to 3 mm × 3 mm × 3 mm voxels; regression of white matter, cerebrospinal fluid, whole-brain signal, and Friston 24-parameters model (6 head motion parameters, 6 head motion parameters one time point before, and the 12 corresponding squared items); Finally, we performed bandpass filtering (0.01–0.1 Hz, 0.01–0.027 Hz, 0.027–0.073 Hz), respectively. See our previous study for more details.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2007">
        <title>ReHo Calculation</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The ReHo value was calculated across the whole brain with Kendall’s coefficient of concordance (at a given voxel with the time series of its 26 nearest neighbours)</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> in a voxel-wise way at three different frequency bands (0.01–0.1 Hz, 0.01–0.027 Hz, 0.027–0.073 Hz). ReHo maps from three frequency bands for each subject were obtained. Then, to reduce the global effects of variability across subjects, ReHo maps for each individual were divided by the global mean ReHo value, and spatially smoothed with a Gaussian kernel (full width at half maximum = 6 mm). The individual ReHo maps were generated via Fisher’s r-to-z standardization. Ultimately, szReHo maps were used for statistical analysis.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2008">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">For demographic and clinical data, the Kolmogorov–Smirnov test was used to test the normality of the data. Two-sample </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-test were used to compare intergroup difference (pre-CPAP OSA vs HC) for normally distributed data. The paired-sample t-tests were used to compare the difference between the post- and pre-CPAP OSA patients.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">For the voxel-based szReHo maps, one-sample t-tests were calculated in the two groups to identify the spatial distribution in three different frequency bands, respectively. Two-sample t-tests were performed between pre-CPAP OSA patients and HCs in the typical frequency band with BMI and educational years as covariates using DPABI (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="http://rfmri.org/dpabi" ext-link-type="uri">http://rfmri.org/dpabi</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) software in MATLAB2018b (MathWorks, Natick, MA, USA). Then, we performed a two-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) on ReHo using SPM12 software with group (pre-CPAP OSA patients and HC) as a between-subject factor and frequency band (slow-4 and slow-5) as a repeated measures factor to examine the effects of group and frequency band. The F-map of the group main effect and “frequency by group” interactions effect were obtained. Post hoc </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">-test was analysed between pre-CPAP OSA patients and HCs in the slow-4 and slow-5 bands, respectively. Pair-sample t-tests were used to compare the difference on ReHo z-values between the post- and pre-CPAP OSA patients. All clusters were reported with a voxel-level threshold of P &lt; 0.01 and cluster-level of P &lt; 0.05, two tailed, GRF correction.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The mean ReHo z-values of abnormal brain regions were correlated with clinical evaluation using partial correlational analyses with BMI and educational years as covariates in OSA patients. P &lt; 0.05 was considered to be statistically significant.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The demographic and clinical data of the two groups are shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. There were no significant differences in age or sex between the OSA patients and the HC groups. The OSA patients showed significantly increased scores for AHI, BMI, ESS, HAMA, HAMD, and PSQI, but decreased scores for nadir SaO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, and MoCA compared to HCs. After one month of CPAP treatment follow-up, the MoCA was increased significantly (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">), but the ESS (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">), HAMA, HAMD, and PAQI were reduced significantly compared to pre-CPAP OSA patients.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Population and Clinical Characteristics of Particpants</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Charateristic</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HC Groups (N=21)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-CPAP OSA (N=21)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-CPAP OSA (N=21)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sup>a</sup> value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sup>b</sup> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender (male/female)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20/1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210/1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20/1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.1±8.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.1±8.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, Kg/m<sup>2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1±1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3±3.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.2±4.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.770</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education, years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1±3.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4±3.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI, /h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5±1.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.4±19.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nadir SaO<sub>2</sub>, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.0±3.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.8±13.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SaO<sub>2</sub> &lt; 90%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3±0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0±17.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESS, scores</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8±1.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8±5.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5±3.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MoCA, scores</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.5±1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.1±3.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.9±2.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MoCA: visual space and execution</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4±0.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6±0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8±1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.384</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MoCA: naming</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0±0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9±0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8±0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.306</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.162</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MoCA: delayed memory</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0±1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9±1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0±1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MoCA: attentional function</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7±0.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2±1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3±1.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.553</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.833</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MoCA: language</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8±0.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3±0.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1±0.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.214</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MoCA: abstract</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9±0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6±0.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5±0.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.057</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.428</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MoCA: orienteering</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0±0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5±1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8±0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.352</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.261</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HAMA, scores</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4±2.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1±4.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0±3.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HAMD, scores</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1±1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4±2.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9±1.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI, scores</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6±1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4±3.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3±2.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: P</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>a</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, two-sample </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-test between pre-CPAP OSA patients and HCs; P</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>b</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, pair </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-test between post- and pre-CPAP OSA patients. SaO2 &lt; 90%, percentage of total sleep time spent at oxygen saturation less than 90%.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: ESS, Epworth sleepiness scale; MoCA, Montreal Cognitive Assessment; HAMA, Hamilton Anxiety Scale; HAMD, Hamilton Depression Scale; PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The MoCA score were changed between post- and pre-CPAP OSA patients. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) Each OSA patient changes. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) The mean value of MoCA.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-2221-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The ESS score were changed between post- and pre-CPAP OSA patients. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) Each OSA patient changes. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) The mean value of ESS.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-2221-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Spatial Distribution Pattern of ReHo in OSA Patients and HC Groups</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">For ReHo, we found that there were highly similar spatial distribution patterns of ReHo in the typical frequency band (0.01–0.1 Hz), slow-4 band (0.027–0.073 Hz), and slow-5 band (0.01–0.027 Hz) between OSA patients and HC groups and higher ReHo z-values in some regions, including the bilateral posterior cingulate cortex (PCC)/precuneus, inferior parietal lobule (IPL), inferior temporal gyrus (ITG), and medial prefrontal cortices (MPFC), which were the core subregions of the default mode network (DMN) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0004" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Highly similar spatial distribution patterns of ReHo were found at the group level for healthy controls (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) and OSA patients (pre-CPAP (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) and post-CPAP (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>C</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">)) in the typical frequency band (0.01–0.1 Hz), slow-4 frequency band (0.027–0.073 Hz), and slow-5 frequency band (0.01–0.027 Hz).</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-2221-g0004" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>ReHo Changes in the Typical Frequency Band (0.01–0.1 Hz)</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The pre-CPAP OSA patients showed reduced ReHo z-values in the right IPL, and exhibited increased ReHo z-values in the brainstem, bilateral ITG, and fusiform gyrus (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5A</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). To eliminate the effect of having only one female subject, we compared 20 male OSA patients with 20 male HC groups in typical frequency bands (0.01–0.1 Hz), highly similar results were found (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=344842.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Figure S1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">), which indicated that the results were stable and reliable.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Significant Altered ReHo in Typical Frequency Band (0.01–0.1 Hz) Between the Pre-CPAP OSA Patients and HC Groups (Two Sample </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-Test)</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Brain Regions</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">BA</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">MNI Coordinates</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">t-Scores</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Cluster Size</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brainstem</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.935</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">462</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right inferior temporal gyrus, fusiform</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.394</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">202</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left inferior temporal gyrus, fusiform</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.224</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">315</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right inferior parietal lobule</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.076</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">122</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Note</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: All clusters were reported with a voxel-level threshold of P &lt; 0.01, GRF correction, and cluster-level of P &lt; 0.05, two tailed.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0005" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Two-sample </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-test in the typical frequency band (0.01–0.08 Hz) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). The results were obtained by a 2×2 two-way ANOVA analysis (group: baseline OSA patients and HC; frequency band: slow-4 and slow-5), Main effects of group (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">); Main effects of frequency band (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>C</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">); Interaction between frequency bands and groups (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>D</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). The post hoc two-sample </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-test for the slow-4 frequency band (0.027–0.073 Hz) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>E</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) and slow-5 frequency band (0.01–0.027 Hz) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>F</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). All results were reported at voxel-level p &lt; 0.01 and cluster-level p &lt; 0.05, GRF corrected.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-2221-g0005" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>ReHo Changes in Specific Frequency Band</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">To detect the frequency-specific changes in ReHo, we performed a two-way 2 × 2 ANOVA analysis. A significant main effect of the group was presented in the brainstem, bilateral cerebellum posterior lobe (CPL), right ITG and fusiform lobe, and bilateral IPL (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5B</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). The main effect of frequency was located in the bilateral MTG and STG, bilateral MFG and right IPL (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5C</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). There were no significant interactions between groups and frequency band (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5D</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Significant Altered ReHo in Main Effect of Group (Pre-CPAP OSA and HC Groups)</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Brain Regions</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">BA</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">MNI Coordinates</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">F Scores</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Cluster Size</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brainstem, Right cerebellum posterior lobe</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.036</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1047</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right inferior temporal gyrus, fusiform</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.943</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left cerebellum posterior lobe</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.027</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right inferior parietal lobule</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.706</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left inferior parietal lobule</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">116</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Note</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: All clusters were analyzed using a two-way ANOVA with a voxel-level threshold of P &lt; 0.01, GRF correction, and cluster-level of P &lt; 0.05, two tailed.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Further post </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">-test results in the slow-4 and slow-5 are shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5E</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">F</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. The same altered brain regions were observed in the brainstem, and right CPL in both bands. The OSA patients showed lower ReHo z-values in the right superior temporal gyrus (STG), left precentral gyrus (PG) and left IPL in the slow-4 band, and exhibited higher ReHo z-values in the bilateral ITG and fusiform gyrus, but lower ReHo z-values in the right IPL in the slow-5 band.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Significant Altered ReHo at Specific Frequency Bands Between the Pre-CPAP OSA Patients and HCs (Two Sample </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-Test)</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Brain Regions</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">BA</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">MNI Coordinates</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">t-Scores</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Cluster Size</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Slow-5 frequency band (0.01–0.027 Hz)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brainstem, Right cerebellum posterior lobe</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.554</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1756</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right superior temporal gyrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left precentral gyrus</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.096</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left inferior parietal lobule</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.646</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">112</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Slow-4 frequency band (0.027–0.073 Hz)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brainstem</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.563</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">262</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right cerebellum posterior lobe</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.226</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right inferior temporal gyrus, fusiform</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.241</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">193</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left inferior temporal gyrus, fusiform</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.635</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right inferior parietal lobule</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Note</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: All clusters were reported with a voxel-level threshold of P &lt; 0.01, GRF correction, and cluster-level of P &lt; 0.05, two tailed.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2005">
        <title>ReHo Changes Between Post- and Pre-CPAP OSA Patients</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Paired-sample t-tests were used to compare the difference on the ReHo between the post- and pre-CPAP OSA patients in the three different frequency bands. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> shows significantly changed ReHo in three different frequency bands. The detailed abnormal brain regions are shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Tables 5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0006" ref-type="table">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. In the post-CPAP OSA patients, significantly increased ReHo in left middle temporal gyrus (MTG), left inferior temporal gyrus (ITG), right STG, MTG, bilateral supplementary motor area (SMA), and reduced ReHo in right CPL, left SFG, right MFG and bilateral IPL in the typical frequency band (0.01–0.1 Hz) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6A</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). Higher ReHo in the right STG and SMA and lower ReHo in the left SFG were observed in the slow-4 band (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6B</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). Increased ReHo in the left MTG, bilateral PG, right MFG, and right SMA and reduced ReHo in the left CPL, right MFG, and bilateral IPL were revealed in the slow-5 band (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6C</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) compared to the pre-CPAP OSA patients. The CPAP treatment-related altered brain regions are shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6D</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">, which partially overlap with the brain regions detected in the comparison between the pre-CPAP OSA patients and the HC group. We extracted the average ReHo for each changed cluster, as shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. Interestingly, in post-CPAP OSA patients, the increased ReHo z-value was higher than that in the HC group, while the decreased ReHo z-value was lower than that in the HC group.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0005"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Significant Altered ReHo at Typical Frequency Band (0.01–0.1 Hz) Between the Post-CPAP OSA Patients and Pre-CPAP OSA (Paired Sample </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-Test)</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Brain Regions</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">BA</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">MNI Coordinates</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">t-Scores</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Cluster Size</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left middle temporal gyrus, inferior temporal gyrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.863</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right superior temporal gyrus, middle temporal gyrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.762</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bilateral supplementary motor area</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right cerebellum posterior lobe</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.495</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">206</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left superior frontal gyrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.230</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right inferior parietal lobule</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">206</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left inferior parietal lobule</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right middle frontal gyrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.017</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0006"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Note</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: All clusters were reported with a voxel-level threshold of P &lt; 0.01, GRF correction, and cluster-level of P &lt; 0.05, two tailed.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0006"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Significant Altered ReHo at Specific Frequency Bands Between the Post- and Pre-CPAP OSA (Paired Sample </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-Test)</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Brain Regions</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">BA</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">MNI Coordinates</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">t-Scores</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Cluster Size</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Slow-5 frequency band (0.01–0.027 Hz)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left middle temporal gyrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.201</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right precentral gyrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.958</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">112</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right middle frontal gyrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.459</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right supplementary motor area</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.197</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left precentral gyrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.211</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left cerebellum posterior lobe</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.892</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right medial frontal gyrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.474</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right inferior parietal lobule</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.291</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">237</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left inferior parietal lobule</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.791</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Slow-4 frequency band (0.027–0.073 Hz)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right superior temporal gyrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.082</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right supplementary motor area</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.436</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left superior frontal gyrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.709</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0007"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Note</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: All clusters were reported with a voxel-level threshold of P &lt; 0.01, GRF correction, and cluster-level of P &lt; 0.05, two tailed.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0006" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Pair sample </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-test in the typical frequency band (0.01–0.08 Hz) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">), the slow-4 frequency band (0.027–0.073 Hz) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">), and slow-5 frequency band (0.01–0.027 Hz) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>C</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) between pre- and post-CPAP OAS patients. The CPAP treatment-related changes of the ReHo in the three different frequency bands in OSA patients (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>D</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). All results were reported at voxel-level p &lt; 0.01 and cluster-level p &lt; 0.05, GRF corrected.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-2221-g0006" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0007" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Mean ReHo z-value of HC, pre- and post-CPAP OSA patients in altered brain regions, which were compared before and after CPAP treatment in OSA patients in three different frequency band. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) typical frequency band; (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) slow-4 band; (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>C</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) slow-5 band.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-2221-g0007" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2006">
        <title>Correlations Between Altered ReHo z-Values and Clinical Assessment</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In pre-CPAP OSA patients, the MoCA was significantly correlated with the mean ReHo z-value of the right IPL (r = 0.673, P = 0.001) in the typical frequency band, and the right IPL (r = 0.748, P &lt; 0.001) in the slow-4 band. Significant correlations between the ESS and mean ReHo z-value of right ITG and Fus (r = 0.462, P = 0.035) in typical frequency band, and brainstem (r = 0.462, P = 0.035) in slow-5 was found. The mean ReHo z-value of brainstem (r = 0.479, P = 0.028), right ITG and Fus (r = 0564, P = 0.008), left ITG and Fus (r = 0.590, P = 0.005) in typical frequency band, and right ITG (r = 0.517, P = 0.016), Left TIG (r = 0.503, P = 0.020) in slow-4 band, brainstem (r = 0.467, P = 0.033) and left IPL in slow-5 band showed significant correlations with severity of OSA (AHI) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0008" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0008" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In the pre-CPAP OSA patients, significant correlations between the mean ReHo z-value with between-subgroup differences (pre-CPAP OSA patients vs HC groups) and clinical assessment.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-2221-g0008" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: ReHo, regional homogeneity; IPL, inferior parietal lobule; ITG, inferior temporal gyrus; Fus, Fusiform; MoCA, Montreal cognitive assessment; ESS, Epworth sleepiness scale.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">To the best of our knowledge, this was the first study to explore changes in spontaneous brain activity and brain response to short-term CPAP therapy in OSA patients using voxel-based ReHo in three different frequency bands. In the typical frequency band, we found that pre-CPAP OSA patients showed increased ReHo in the brainstem, bilateral ITG/fusiform, and lower ReHo in the right IPL. The main effects of the group of ANOVA analysis in the bilateral brainstem, bilateral CPL, bilateral IPL, right ITG and fusiform were found. Interestingly, with the exception of increased ReHo in the brainstem and right CPL in both slow-4 and slow-5, lower ReHo in right STG, left PG and left IPL in slow-5, lower ReHo in right IPL, and higher ReHo in bilateral ITG/fusiform in slow-4 were observed. After one month of CPAP treatment, spontaneous brain activity was reversed in some brain regions, such as the bilateral CPL, right STG, and left PG. At the same time, we found increased ReHo in the bilateral SMA, left MTG/ITG, right MFG, and right PG, and reduced ReHo in the left SFG and bilateral IPL in post-CPAP OSA patients. The slow-5 band was more sensitive in detecting abnormal spontaneous brain activity in post-CPAP OSA patients. Meanwhile, we found a significant correlation between abnormal ReHo in multiple brain regions and MoCA, ESS, and AHI. These results suggested that OSA-related spontaneous brain activity was related to specific frequency bands. Meanwhile, the CPAP therapy can partially reverse the spontaneous activity of abnormal brain regions and partially produce adaptive compensatory changes in OSA. Altogether, abnormal changes in frequency-specific ReHo provided not only additional information for understanding the underlying neural mechanisms but also provided possible imaging markers for clinical CPAP therapy.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Obesity and male sex were the main risk factors for OSA. In the current study, BMI of OSA patients was significantly higher than that of healthy controls. There were 20 male OSA and only one female OSA patients. Previous studies have suggested that obesity and gender differences may affect resting brain activity.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> To confirm that our findings were primarily due to OSA rather than obesity or gender differences, we compared the intergroup differences in ReHo with BMI and educational years as covariates and performed a repeatability analysis comparing 20 male OSA patients with 20 male HC groups in typical frequency bands (0.01–0.1 Hz). These results are highly similar, which suggested that ReHo changes in OSA patients are caused by OSA itself rather than sex.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Compared with HCs, the pre-CPAP OSA patients showed increased ReHo in the brainstem in three bands. However, no significant changes were observed before and after CPAP treatment in OSA patients. The brainstem is an important central structure for sympathetic nerve activity and is highly connected to other cortical and subcortical regions involved in breathing and sleep. Respiration originates from the central processor of the brainstem and consists of driving downstream premotor neurons to supply spinal respiratory motor neurons, which in turn innervate cranial motoneurons to the muscles of the upper airway.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> It is well established that muscle sympathetic nerve activity is regulated by respiration. Previous studies have reported increased gray matter volume and brain activity in the brainstem associated with increased muscle sympathetic nerve activity in OSA patients.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The coupling between respiratory rhythm and sympathetic output may result from the interaction between brainstem circuits since its transsection significantly attenuates the respiratory regulation of sympathetic output.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> An increased fractional anisotropy value in normal-appearing white matter of the brainstem was observed after 3 months of CPAP treatment,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and muscle sympathetic nerve activity coupled with BOLD signal intensity within the brainstem returned to control levels after 6 months of CPAP treatment.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Another study confirmed that structural and functional changes in the brainstem could be restored after 6 months of CPAP therapy and were maintained after 12 months of CPAP therapy in OSA patients.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Consistent with these findings, we found significantly increased ReHo in the brainstem in OSA patients at baseline and increased ReHo in the typical band and slow-5 band was correlated with AHI. The respiratory chemosensitivity that drives automatic control of the upper airway is decreased, and muscle sympathetic nerve activity is decreased during sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Therefore, we speculate that sleep disruption in OSA patients leads to hypercapnia, which in turn stimulates respiratory chemosensitivity and increases sympathetic nerve activity, resulting in increased spontaneous brainstem brain activity. The lack of significant differences before and after CPAP therapy may be due to the short duration of treatment (one month).</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The role of the cerebellum in sleep is unclear, but one study has shown that the cerebellum is involved in the regulation of the sleep-wake cycle.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Some scholars have begun to pay attention to changes in the cerebellum in OSA patients. For instance, increased cerebellar gray matter volume was reported in OSA patients.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> One functional connectivity study demonstrated decreased functional connectivity between the left cerebellum and hippocampus.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Park et al found that OSA showed cerebellar network integration and cerebrocerebellar connectivity was impaired in OSA patients, which may participate in cognitive decline.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The cerebellum was susceptible to hypoxia or ischaemia. Consistent with our previous findings,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> we reconfirmed that increased ReHo in the right CPL in both slow-4 and slow-5 bands was observed in pre-CPAP OSA patients, which may be a compensatory response to hypoxia. The increase in local functional connectivity (ReHo) in the cerebellum may be related to the hypertrophic gray matter volume, leading to the decreased network connectivity in cerebrocerebellar in OSA patients. As we expected, our results showed that increased ReHo in the CPL was restored in the typical band after CPAP treatment, suggesting that CPAP therapy can reverse brain damage. Interestingly, we found that ReHo values in the right CPL in slow-5 were positively correlated with AHI, suggesting that it was related to the severity of the disease. Spontaneous abnormal brain activity in the cerebellar may be a compensatory response to hypoxia and may provide a new neuroimaging marker for OSA patients.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In the present study, OSA patients showed decreased ReHo in the bilateral IPL before and after CPAP treatment in different bands. The IPL is one of the core hubs of the DMN that is involved in several higher cognitive domains, including autobiographical memory,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> episodic memory,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> mind wandering or daydreaming,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and collection and evaluation of information.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Previous studies have described cortical thinning in the left IPL, which was correlated with respiratory arousal, suggesting that sleep fragmentation may cause brain tissue damage in IPL.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The moderated to severe OSA patients showed a decrease FC value in bilateral IPL compared with mild group, suggesting that DMN was disrupted in OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Our previous studies reported reduced degree centrality in left IPL and were negatively correlated with the AHI and AI, which indicated that sleep fragmentation may be a potential factor for abnormal network of IPL.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Similar to previous studies, we found decreased ReHo in the bilateral IPL in OSA patients, and ReHo z-values in right IPL in slow-4 and typical bands were positively correlated with the MoCA, which may disrupt higher cognitive processes. Unexpectedly, the ReHo of IPL did not improve but further decreased after CPAP treatment, which may be an illusion after short-term CPAP therapy due to the treatment adaptation process.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In addition, higher ReHo in the bilateral ITG and fusiform in the slow-4 and typical band were found in pre-CPAP OSA. The higher ReHo in the right STG and MTG in typical band was observed in post-CPAP OSA patients. The temporal lobe is responsible for processing auditory information and is also involved in memory and emotion. Recent research revealed that OSA exhibited loss of white matter integrity in the temporal lobe and hippocampus, which was correlated with impaired memory dysfunction.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> It has been reported that FC abnormalities in the right hippocampus and right STG and MTG in OSA are negatively correlated with performance of information processing speed, which may probably contribute to the development of cognitive dysfunction.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Our previous study found an increase in rs-FC between the left IFG and bilateral ventrolateral amygdala in OSA patients, reflecting the potential adaptive compensation mechanism for the decline in emotion functions.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> A study reported decreased mean diffusivity and increased functional anisotropy in the temporal lobes and fusiform gyrus, and increased CBF in the ITG was found in OSA with six weeks of CPAP treatment, suggesting that CPAP therapy can recover OSA-induced brain injury.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The elevated ReHo in the right STG and MTG may reflect a repair mechanism activation in our study. Furthermore, higher ReHo in the bilateral ITG and fusiform were positively correlated with the AHI. The potential causal relationship remains unclear and requires further exploration.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In the current study, we also found that some brain regions with normal brain activity at baseline showed increased ReHo after CPAP therapy. These brain regions include the bilateral SMA, MFG, right PG, and left SFG. The SMA and PG are core subregions of the sensorimotor network. Recent research reported that OSA patients showed decreased ReHo in the right SMA and PG, left SFG and MFG, and were negatively correlated with cognitive impairment, suggesting that frontal lobe dysfunction is an important neuropathophysiological mechanism of neurocognitive deficits.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Previous studies have reported cortical thinning</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and reduced functional connectivity</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> of the bilateral PG associated with sensorimotor function in OSA. Another study found impaired local functional specialization and integration of sensorimotor networks in OSA patients.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> These results suggested that OSA sensorimotor network abnormalities may be caused by repeated hypoxemia injury and upper respiratory tract collapse that further impairs sensorimotor function.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> In our study, no abnormality of spontaneous brain activity in sensorimotor areas was found at baseline. The inconsistency with other results may be due to the difference in the subjects’ population and the fMRI acquisition parameters in the resting state and the difference in the frequency band. However, we found significantly increased ReHo in those brain regions after CPAP treatment, which may be due to the early repair of neuronal spontaneous activity by CPAP treatment.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In our study, after CPAP treatment, the most interesting finding was that OSA patients showed abnormal spontaneous activity in multiple brain regions in typical bands, and these regions had a frequency-specific distribution. Higher ReHo in the right and right SMA, and lower ReHo in the left SFG were only observed in the slow-4 band. However, OSA patients exhibited more widespread alterations in the slow-5 band in the bilateral MFG, PG, IPL, left CPL, and right SMA, suggesting that the slow-5 band was more sensitive to detecting abnormal intrinsic brain activity. However, the relationships and specific physiological functions of the slow-4 and slow-5 bands are not fully understood. Previous studies have shown that low-frequency oscillations reflect the integration of large-scale neural networks. Yu et al observed higher amplitude of low-frequency fluctuation in a widespread range of cortical regions in the slow-5 band than in the slow-4 band.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> This is similar to what we have previously found in COPD patients.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Therefore, we suggest that future studies on brain networks in OSA patients should include the influence of specific frequency bands.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Limitations</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">There are some limitations. First, this was a short-term CPAP therapy, and the effects of long-term CPAP therapy need to be further explored. We only explored the changes in local brain connections (ReHo) in different frequency bands, and the whole brain function network connections were not clear. Finally, there were relatively few patients after CPAP treatment, especially females, so we did not distinguish between sleepiness improvement and subjective residual daytime sleepiness by ESS. In the future, a multicenter, large-sample long-term follow-up study should be conducted to explore changes in whole-brain network connectivity in OSA patients.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In summary, the present study used voxel-based ReHo to investigate OSA-related spontaneous brain activity changes in three different frequency bands before and after short-term CPAP therapy. OSA patients showed frequency-specific abnormal alterations of ReHo in multiple brain regions, and some of these alterations could be reversed by short-term CPAP therapy. These findings suggested that multiband ReHo provides additional information for understanding the underlying neural mechanisms of OSA-related cognitive impairment, and can provide potential imaging markers for clinical treatment. In addition, future studies should consider the effects of different frequency bands on brain networks.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This study was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (Grant Nos. 81860307 and 81560285), the Natural Science Foundation Project of Jiangxi, China (Grant Nos. 20202BABL216036, 20181ACB20023, and 20171BAB205070), Education Department Project of Jiangxi Province, China (Grant Nos. 700544006 and GJJ190133), and Department of Health Project and Jiangxi Province, China (Grant No. 20181039).</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0007">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors declare no potential conflicts of interest in this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Franklin</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lindberg</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea is a common disorder in the population-a review on the epidemiology of sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Thorac Dis</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1311</fpage>–<lpage>1322</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3978/j.issn.2072-1439.2015.06.11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26380759</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Olaithe</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bucks</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hillman</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eastwood</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cognitive deficits in obstructive sleep apnea: insights from a meta-review and comparison with deficits observed in COPD, insomnia, and sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2017.03.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28760549</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Andrade</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bubu</surname>
<given-names>OM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Varga</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Osorio</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The relationship between obstructive sleep apnea and Alzheimer’s disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Alzheimers Dis</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>s1</issue>):<fpage>S255</fpage>–2<lpage>70</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/JAD-179936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29782319</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rosenzweig</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morrell</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The impact of sleep and hypoxia on the brain: potential mechanisms for the effects of obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Opin Pulm Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>565</fpage>–<lpage>571</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MCP.0000000000000099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25188719</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jelic</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Padeletti</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kawut</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Inflammation, oxidative stress, and repair capacity of the vascular endothelium in obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circulation</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>117</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>2270</fpage>–<lpage>2278</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.107.741512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18413499</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lanfranchi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Somers</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>K. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea and vascular disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Respir Res</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>315-319</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/rr79</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11737928</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Marshall</surname>
<given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barnes</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Travier</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Continuous positive airway pressure reduces daytime sleepiness in mild to moderate obstructive sleep apnoea: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Thorax</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>61</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>430</fpage>–<lpage>434</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thx.2005.050583</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16467072</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Antic</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Catcheside</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buchan</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The effect of CPAP in normalizing daytime sleepiness, quality of life, and neurocognitive function in patients with moderate to severe OSA</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>119</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/34.1.111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21203366</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weaver</surname>
<given-names>TE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhong</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>White matter structural differences in OSA patients experiencing residual daytime sleepiness with high CPAP use: a non-Gaussian diffusion MRI study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2018.09.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30445240</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ferini-Strambi</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marelli</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Galbiati</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Castronovo</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of continuous positive airway pressure on cognition and neuroimaging data in sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Psychophysiol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>89</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>212</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpsycho.2013.03.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23570950</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rosenzweig</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Glasser</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crum</surname>
<given-names>WR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Changes in neurocognitive architecture in patients with obstructive sleep apnea treated with continuous positive airway pressure</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ebiomedicine</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>229</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ebiom.2016.03.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27322475</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Joo</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suh</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>ST</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hong</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of long-term treatment on brain volume in patients with obstructive sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hum Brain Mapp</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>395</fpage>–<lpage>409</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.23038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26503297</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Castronovo</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scifo</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Castellano</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>White matter integrity in obstructive sleep apnea before and after treatment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1465</fpage>–<lpage>1475</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.3994</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25142557</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seo</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kang</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of continuous positive airway pressure on regional cerebral blood flow in patients with severe obstructive sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>122</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2016.03.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28366323</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nie</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gong</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nie</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Abnormal resting-state functional connectivity within the default mode network subregions in male patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropsych Dis Treat</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>212</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NDT.S97449</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Qin</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Altered resting-state brain activity in obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>651</fpage>–<lpage>659</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.2620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23633747</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Palomares</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Woo</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Disrupted functional brain network organization in patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Behav</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e00441</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/brb3.441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27099802</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tian</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Regional homogeneity approach to fMRI data analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroimage</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>394</fpage>–<lpage>400</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2003.12.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15110032</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zuo</surname>
<given-names>XN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Regional homogeneity: a multimodal, multiscale neuroimaging marker of the human connectome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroscientist</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>486</fpage>–<lpage>505</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1073858415595004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26170004</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dai</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gong</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nie</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Altered intrinsic regional brain activity in male patients with severe obstructive sleep apnea: a resting-state functional magnetic resonance imaging study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropsych Dis Treat</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1819</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NDT.S67805</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zuo</surname>
<given-names>XN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Di Martino</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kelly</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The oscillating brain: complex and reliable</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroimage</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>1432</fpage>–<lpage>1445</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2009.09.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19782143</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yin</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Frequency-specific alterations of regional homogeneity in subcortical stroke patients with different outcomes in hand function</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hum Brain Mapp</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>4373</fpage>–<lpage>4384</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.24277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29972261</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lou</surname>
<given-names>YT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>XL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Frequency-Specific regional homogeneity alterations in Tourette syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>543049</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2020.543049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33391040</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kapur</surname>
<given-names>VK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Auckley</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chowdhuri</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Clinical practice guideline for diagnostic testing for adult obstructive sleep apnea: an American Academy of Sleep Medicine clinical practice guideline</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>479</fpage>–<lpage>504</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.6506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28162150</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nasreddine</surname>
<given-names>ZS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Phillips</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bdirian</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The Montreal Cognitive Assessment, MoCA: a brief screening tool for mild cognitive impairment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Geriatr Soc</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>695</fpage>–<lpage>699</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1532-5415.2005.53221.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15817019</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xin</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Abnormal intrinsic functional hubs and connectivity in stable patients with COPD: a resting-state MRI study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Imaging Behav</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>573</fpage>–<lpage>585</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11682-019-00130-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31187474</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dai</surname>
<given-names>XJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gong</surname>
<given-names>HH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>YX</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Gender differences in brain regional homogeneity of healthy subjects after normal sleep and after sleep deprivation: a resting-state fMRI study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>720</fpage>–<lpage>727</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2011.09.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22503940</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>GW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>FX</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Abnormal regional neural activity and reorganized neural network in obesity: evidence from resting-state fMRI</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Obesity</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1283</fpage>–<lpage>1291</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/oby.22839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32510870</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abdala</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Borgmann</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rybak</surname>
<given-names>IA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paton</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Brainstem respiratory networks: building blocks and microcircuits</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Trends Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>152</fpage>–<lpage>162</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tins.2012.11.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23254296</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lundblad</surname>
<given-names>LC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fatouleh</surname>
<given-names>RH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hammam</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mckenzie</surname>
<given-names>DK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macefield</surname>
<given-names>VG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Henderson</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Brainstem changes associated with increased muscle sympathetic drive in obstructive sleep apnoea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroimage</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>103</volume>:<fpage>258</fpage>–<lpage>266</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2014.09.031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25255048</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baekey</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dick</surname>
<given-names>TE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paton</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pontomedullary transection attenuates central respiratory modulation of sympathetic discharge, heart rate and the baroreceptor reflex in the in situ rat preparation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Exp Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>93</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>803</fpage>–<lpage>816</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/expphysiol.2007.041400</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18344259</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Salsone</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caligiuri</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Castronovo</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Microstructural changes in normal-appearing white matter in male sleep apnea patients are reversible after treatment: a pilot study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurosci Res</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2646</fpage>–<lpage>2656</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jnr.24858</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34197014</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lundblad</surname>
<given-names>LC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fatouleh</surname>
<given-names>RH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mckenzie</surname>
<given-names>DK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macefield</surname>
<given-names>VG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Henderson</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Brain stem activity changes associated with restored sympathetic drive following CPAP treatment in OSA subjects: a longitudinal investigation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurophysiol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>114</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>893</fpage>–<lpage>901</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jn.00092.2015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25995345</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Henderson</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fatouleh</surname>
<given-names>RH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lundblad</surname>
<given-names>LC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mckenzie</surname>
<given-names>DK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macefield</surname>
<given-names>VG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of 12 months continuous positive airway pressure on sympathetic activity related brainstem function and structure in obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>90</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnins.2016.00090</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27013952</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Benarroch</surname>
<given-names>EE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Brainstem integration of arousal, sleep, cardiovascular, and respiratory control</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>91</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):<fpage>958</fpage>–<lpage>966</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000006537</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30355703</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Delrosso</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoque</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The cerebellum and sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurol Clin</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>893</fpage>–<lpage>900</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ncl.2014.07.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25439287</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fatouleh</surname>
<given-names>RH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hammam</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lundblad</surname>
<given-names>LC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Functional and structural changes in the brain associated with the increase in muscle sympathetic nerve activity in obstructive sleep apnoea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroimage Clin</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>283</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nicl.2014.08.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25379440</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Aberrant hippocampal network connectivity is associated with neurocognitive dysfunction in patients with moderate and severe obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>580408</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fneur.2020.580408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33362692</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>HR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cha</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Joo</surname>
<given-names>EY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Altered cerebrocerebellar functional connectivity in patients with obstructive sleep apnea and its association with cognitive function</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsab209</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dai</surname>
<given-names>XJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gong</surname>
<given-names>HH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nie</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Altered intrinsic regional brain activity in male patients with severe obstructive sleep apnea: a resting-state functional magnetic resonance imaging study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1819</fpage>–<lpage>1826</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NDT.S67805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25278755</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buckner</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carroll</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Self-projection and the brain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Trends Cogn Sci</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tics.2006.11.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17188554</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cabeza</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dolcos</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Graham</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nyberg</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Similarities and differences in the neural correlates of episodic memory retrieval and working memory</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroimage</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>330</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/nimg.2002.1063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12030819</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mason</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Norton</surname>
<given-names>MI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Horn</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wegner</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grafton</surname>
<given-names>ST</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macrae</surname>
<given-names>CN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Wandering minds: the default network and stimulus-independent thought</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Science</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>315</volume>(<issue>5810</issue>):<fpage>393</fpage>–<lpage>395</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1131295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17234951</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gusnard</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raichle</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raichle</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Searching for a baseline: functional imaging and the resting human brain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>685</fpage>–<lpage>694</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35094500</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11584306</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Joo</surname>
<given-names>EY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jeon</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>ST</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hong</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Localized cortical thinning in patients with obstructive sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1153</fpage>–<lpage>1162</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.2876</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23904675</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Guan</surname>
<given-names>WT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>ZC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>HX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Altered regional brain activity of functional connectivity in patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Zhonghua Yi Xue Za Zhi</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>1095</fpage>–<lpage>1100</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3760/cma.j.issn.0376-2491.2019.14.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30982259</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Abnormal intrinsic functional hubs in severe male obstructive sleep apnea: evidence from a Voxel-Wise degree centrality analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e164031</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0164031</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>HL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>White matter alteration and autonomic impairment in obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>293</fpage>–<lpage>302</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.8186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31992402</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Abnormal resting-state functional connectivity of amygdala subregions in patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>977</fpage>–<lpage>987</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NDT.S191441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31114206</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Maresky</surname>
<given-names>HS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shpirer</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Klar</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Levitt</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sasson</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tal</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Continuous positive airway pressure alters brain microstructure and perfusion patterns in patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2018.12.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30897457</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shan</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Reduced regional homogeneity and neurocognitive impairment in patients with moderate-to-severe obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>75</volume>:<fpage>418</fpage>–<lpage>427</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.09.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32980663</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mayer</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dematteis</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pepin</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Peripheral neuropathy in sleep apnea. A tissue marker of the severity of nocturnal desaturation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>159</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>219</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/ajrccm.159.1.9709051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9872841</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chien</surname>
<given-names>YL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>HL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Frequency-specific alternations in the amplitude of low-frequency fluctuations in schizophrenia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hum Brain Mapp</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>627</fpage>–<lpage>637</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.22203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23125131</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Intrinsic low-frequency oscillation changes in multiple-frequency bands in stable patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Imaging Behav</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1922</fpage>–<lpage>1933</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11682-020-00385-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32880076</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
