<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35210891</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">8863345</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">339639</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S339639</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Sleep Homeostasis and Night Work: A Polysomnographic Study of Daytime Sleep Following Three Consecutive Simulated Night Shifts</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Pedersen et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Pedersen et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4313-3711</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Pedersen</surname>
            <given-names>Torhild T</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3982-5486</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Sunde</surname>
            <given-names>Erlend</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wisor</surname>
            <given-names>Jonathan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mrdalj</surname>
            <given-names>Jelena</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pallesen</surname>
            <given-names>Ståle</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Grønli</surname>
            <given-names>Janne</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Biological and Medical Psychology, Faculty of Psychology, University of Bergen</institution>, <addr-line>Bergen</addr-line>, <country>Norway</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Psychosocial Science, Faculty of Psychology, University of Bergen</institution>, <addr-line>Bergen</addr-line>, <country>Norway</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Sleep and Performance Research Center and Department of Translational Medicine and Physiology, Elson S. Floyd College of Medicine, Washington State University</institution>, <addr-line>Spokane</addr-line>, <addr-line>WA</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Norwegian Competence Center for Sleep Disorders, Haukeland University Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Bergen</addr-line>, <country>Norway</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label><institution>Optentia Research Focus Area, North-West University</institution>, <addr-line>Vanderbijlpark</addr-line>, <country>South Africa</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Torhild T Pedersen, <phone>Tel +4797007718</phone>, Email torhild.pedersen@uib.no</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>18</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <fpage>243</fpage>
      <lpage>254</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>04</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2022 Pedersen et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Pedersen et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Millions of people work at times that overlap with the habitual time for sleep. Consequently, sleep often occurs during the day. Daytime sleep is, however, characterized by reduced sleep duration. Despite preserved time spent in deep NREM sleep (stage N3), daytime sleep is subjectively rated as less restorative. Knowledge on how night work influences homeostatic sleep pressure is limited. Therefore, we aimed to explore the effect of three consecutive simulated night shifts on daytime sleep and markers of sleep homeostasis.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Patients and Methods</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We performed continuous EEG, EMG and EOG recordings in the subjects’ home setting for one nighttime sleep opportunity, and for the daytime sleep opportunities following three consecutive simulated night shifts.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">For all daytime sleep opportunities, total sleep time was reduced compared to nighttime sleep. While time spent in stage N3 was preserved, sleep pressure at sleep onset, measured by slow wave activity (1–4 Hz), was higher than nighttime sleep and higher on day 3 than on day 1 and 2. Elevated EEG power during daytime sleep was sustained through 6 h of time in bed. Slow wave energy was not significantly different from nighttime sleep after 6 h, reflecting a less efficient relief of sleep pressure.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Adaptation to daytime sleep following three consecutive simulated night shifts is limited. The increased homeostatic response and continuation of sleep pressure relief even after 6 h of sleep, are assumed to reflect a challenge for appropriate homeostatic reduction to occur.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>shift work</kwd>
        <kwd>daytime sleep</kwd>
        <kwd>sleep regulation</kwd>
        <kwd>spectral analysis</kwd>
        <kwd>sleep homeostasis</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="4"/>
        <ref-count count="50"/>
        <page-count count="12"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The human brain and body are naturally programmed to stay awake during the day and to sleep at night. Yet, sleeping during the day can be a necessary part of life, as millions of people work at hours that overlap with the habitual time for sleep. It is reported that shifting the main sleep period to daytime due to night work reduces total sleep time</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and causes poor and non-restorative sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Sleep loss and non-restorative sleep have significant adverse short- and long-term health consequences</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and may impair cognitive functioning.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Quantitative EEG studies of daytime sleep have mostly been performed following one single night shift,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5–10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> although there are a few exceptions. One study investigated daytime sleep in both permanent night shift workers and rotating shift workers after 6 night shifts,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and one laboratory study looked at 6 daytime sleep periods after 7 simulated night shifts.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Most of these studies generally support the subjective perception of poor quality of daytime sleep and show that night shift workers normally have a shorter sleep onset latency, albeit with reduced total sleep time compared to ordinary nighttime sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">According to the classification of American Academy of Sleep Medicine (AASM), deep nonrapid eye movement (NREM) sleep, stage N3, is defined as a predominance of slow waves and is often referred to as slow wave sleep (SWS).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> SWS is thought to be the most restorative stage of sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Absolute time spent in SWS, in contrast to stages N1 and N2, is preserved during different sleep opportunities, including daytime sleep after night work. The preservation of time spent in SWS is taken as evidence that this stage is centrally important for the dissipation of sleep pressure, but at the same time not subject to change as a function of sleep pressure.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7–10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> By contrast, the oscillatory activities of cerebral cortex circuits during SWS change as a function of sleep pressure. Using spectral analysis, EEG dynamics of the cortex during SWS are measured by slow wave activity (SWA), representing power density typically in the 0.5–4 Hz range. SWA increases with time in wakefulness and declines during sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The frontal cortex is particularly sensitive to sleep dependent modulation of slow waves, whereas more posterior areas (central and occipital) also reflect circadian modulation of SWA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">An important issue to consider is that the intensity of SWA can be masked by total sleep time, given that the longer time in sleep, the smaller is the increase in SWA,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and vice versa. This aspect is especially relevant when sleep periods are of different lengths, or if time spent in one sleep stage varies within an analysis interval. Slow wave energy (SWE) adds information on the amount of SWA obtained across a given sleep period. SWE and SWA will, therefore, describe somewhat different aspects of the sleep homeostatic function. The rise rate of SWA during sleep reflects the sleep pressure accumulated in prior wake, whereas values of SWE at the end of sleep indicate the extent to which sleep pressure has dissipated in that sleep session.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Studies on night shift work that include quantitative information about SWA during daytime SWS are sparse. Most often the information includes both light NREM sleep (stage N2) and deep NREM sleep (stage N3). One study on rotating shift workers found no change, neither in SWA nor SWE during daytime sleep following </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">one single</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> night shift, compared to nighttime sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> An accumulation of sleep debt after consecutive night shifts (2, 4 or 7 night shifts in a row) has been found by the use of actigraphy in police officers.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, it is still not known how consecutive night shifts affect the dynamics of SWA and SWE in SWS (stage N3).</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">To date, the cost of repeated partial sleep restriction on sleep EEG is better described. The results are somewhat ambiguous. Some studies report that repeated partial sleep restriction does not increase SWA and thus does not cause an increased homeostatic sleep response. Participants in these studies were exposed to sleep restrictions either for 2 nights during the first 4 h of the habitual bedtime,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> or 14 nights with 8, 6 or 4 h sleep opportunity.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Other studies report increased SWA after 4 and 5 nights with 4 h sleep opportunities,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22–24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and increased SWE compared to baseline sleep,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> independent of whether the sleep opportunities were early (23:00–03:00 h) or late (03:00–07:00 h/04:00–08:00 h) in the night. Findings from animal models are also inconsistent. In two different studies, twenty hours of sleep deprivation followed by a 4 h sleep opportunity across 5 days has been found to induce no compensatory response of SWA,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and an increased SWA compared to baseline.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Other animal studies on sleep restriction and simulated night shift work did not find any differences in SWA between the experimental conditions.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">According to recent recommendations from an expert panel on shift work, no more than three night shifts in a row should be included in a rotating shift schedule to avoid circadian disruption, risks of injuries and potential long-term health risks.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> SWS and SWA are closely related to various fundamental health parameters, such as modulation of endocrine release and reduction of sympathetic nervous activity,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> prevention of cognitive impairment</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and memory consolidation.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Thus, it is conceivable that changes in quantitative EEG parameters of daytime sleep may very well contribute to health and safety risks.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The present study aimed to investigate daytime sleep EEG following one night shift period consisting of three consecutive simulated night shifts. Based on the literature, we hypothesized an accumulation of sleep debt throughout the night shift period, but a preserved time spent in SWS during daytime sleep after the night shifts. To examine the effect of three consecutive simulated night shifts on changes in the restorative slow waves, we quantified the dynamics of SWA and SWE during stage N3. We hypothesized that changes in cortical slow waves would be more pronounced in frontal EEG derivations and more prominently observed after accumulation of sleep debt and after the 3rd night shift.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Eligible participants were students recruited by flyers or e-mail at the University of Bergen, Norway. Prior to enrollment, a screening procedure was performed to ensure fulfillment of the following criteria: age 19–30 y; Body Mass Index (BMI) &lt;30; not pregnant; not travelled &gt;1 time zone and no night work &lt;1 month before study; no use of tobacco/nicotine, caffeine and/or alcohol during the study; good to excellent self-reported health; no current or relevant history of psychiatric, neurological, heart, lung or sleep disorders/diseases; no use of medications (except contraceptives); no eye diseases; normal color vision; habitual sleep duration of 6–10 h per night; usual wake time between 06:00 and 10:00 h; and no extreme chronotype according to the short Morningness-Eveningness Questionnaire.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">A total of 36 subjects (24 females) provided written informed consent and attended an enrollment session at the laboratory, three days prior to the simulated night shifts. Of these, 19 participants (12 females) were recruited to have polysomnographic (PSG) recordings during a baseline night, simulated night shifts and the following daytime sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Of a total of 19 recruited participants, 2 withdrew from the study before the start of the night shift period, leaving 17 participants (11 females). One withdrew from the study after the first night shift and sleep recording was unavailable for a second participant due to technical issues. This resulted in 15 participants (11 females, 22.2±2.2 years; mean ±SD), each with PSG-recordings for three consecutive daytime sleep periods. In addition, one participant was excluded for D2 due to short sleep duration (&lt;2 h), and due to technical issues PSG data for D3 was missing from another participant. Of these, 12 participants had one baseline night of sleep recording.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Participants completing the study protocol received a financial compensation of approximately 400 EURO. The experiment was conducted according to the declaration of Helsinki and was approved by the Norwegian Regional Committee for Medical and Health Research Ethics (No. 2016/1903). According to the Norwegian Law on Research Ethics, Institutional Review Boards are not assigned in the process of approving research on human subjects.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Design and Procedure</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The study was conducted from September 2017 to February 2018. We used a repeated measurement design, consisting of three consecutive simulated night shifts (23:00 to 07:00 h) in a laboratory (see Sunde et al for study protocol).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Three days prior to the first night shift, participants were instructed to keep a regular sleep schedule based on their habitual sleep timing, with the exception of the third day where sleep was not habitual due to melatonin saliva sampling at home by the participants, ending 1 h after habitual bedtime (see Sunde et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> for dim-light melatonin onset saliva sampling procedure). Actigraphy (Actiwatch 2, Philips Respironics, The Netherlands) and sleep diary verified adherence to the sleep criteria. The participants were allowed to nap before shifts, but not after 20:00 h and/or longer than 2 h.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The simulated night shift portion of the experiment was performed in a room (30 m</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) with no windows, consisting of eight similar workstations separated by partition walls. Each participant had a desktop computer where the screens were covered with a foil (Metolight SFG-10; Asmetec, Germany) filtering out all wavelengths &lt;520 nm. The experimental room was equipped with 20 ceiling mounted LED-luminaires (Modul R 600 LED CCT/RGB MP; Glamox Luxo Lighting AB, Sweden). Light exposure was measured at each workplace using a calibrated spectroradiometer (GL Spectis 1.0 T Flicker; GL Optic, Poland). Measurements were conducted 120 cm from the floor, vertically, facing the same direction as the participants while seated.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">During simulated night shifts, participants were exposed to standard full spectrum (~4000 K) light, with a mean intensity of ~90 lux (~57 melanopic lux) from 23:00 to 05:00 h, and 190 lux (~132 melanopic lux) from 05:00 to 07:00 h. The current study was part of a larger project including a bright light condition.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Laboratory Procedures During Simulated Night Shifts</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All participants entered the experimental room at 23:00 h and started the night shift at 23:30 h, after 30 min of adaptation to lighting. During the night shifts, participants mainly performed various neurobehavioral performance tests and answered questionnaires. A main test battery (lasting ~20 min) was completed five times during each night shift at 23:30, 01:00, 02:30, 04:00 and 05:30 h. The main test battery included a Psychomotor Vigilance Task (PVT) and a Digit Symbol Substitution Test (DSST), but other tests were also performed during the shifts, including a Reversal Learning Task, a Working Memory Scanning Task, a Task Switching Test and a Numerosity Discrimination Task. When not being occupied with cognitive tests and/or questionnaires, participants had short breaks and were allowed to engage in quiet activities, such as reading and talking. Participants stayed in the laboratory during the whole night shift, except for toilet breaks. For further details, see Sunde et al.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Polysomnographic Recordings</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">An ambulatory PSG-equipment was used to provide one recording of the participants’ ordinary nighttime sleep prior to the night shift period, and for continuous EEG recording during the simulated night shifts and the following daytime sleep. Only the sleep data is presented here. The sleep periods were recorded at home, where participants were able to self-select sleep time.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The PSG data were recorded using SOMNOmedics PSG+ ambulatory devices (SOMNOmedics, GmbH, Randersacker, Germany) and stored at 256 Hz. The analogue low-pass filter was limited to 35 Hz and the high-pass filter to 0.2 Hz. The PSG recordings were performed according to the AASM guidelines.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The six unipolar EEG derivations of the international 10–20 system (F3:M2, F4:M1, C3:M2, C4:M1, O1:M2, O2:M1) were recorded from scalp electrodes (CNSAC Gold Cup EEG electrodes, MedShop GmbH, Austria) with contralateral mastoid references and a common forehead reference used as a default across all electrodes.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Electromyogram (EMG) was recorded with submental electrodes with a reference electrode placed on the mentalis muscle. For male participants where submental placement was difficult due to facial hair, EMG electrodes were placed over the masseter. Electrooculogram (EOG) was recorded from electrodes placed at the outer canthus of both eyes approximately 1 cm lateral and 1 cm above (E2) or below (E1) the midline, with M2 as the reference electrode. The impedance of EEG and EOG electrodes was kept below 5 kOhm, and below 10 kOhm for EMG electrodes.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Polysomnographic- and EEG Data Analyses</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The Domino software (version 2.9.0) was used for sleep stage scoring. Scoring of sleep stages (wake, N1, N2, N3 and REM sleep) was performed according to the AASM guidelines.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> All recordings were scored visually in 30 sec epochs by a trained researcher. The start and end of each sleep recording were determined by subjects’ markers of lights-off and lights-on.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">For a qualitative analysis of sleep, EEG power was calculated for each sleep stage in 1 Hz bins from 1 to 20 Hz using Fast Fourier transformation. Furthermore, SWA (1–4 Hz) and SWE (the amount of SWA obtained across a given time period) during stage N3 was calculated from each of three EEG derivations (F4:M1, C4:M1, O2:M1).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2006">
        <title>Subjective Rating of Sleep Quality and Daytime Functioning</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">As part of a sleep diary completed during the study, participants were asked to rate their daytime functioning and sleep quality. Using a Likert scale ranging from 1, “very good”, to 5, “very poor”, participants were instructed to rate their daytime functioning just before going to bed. As part of the daytime functioning, participants were told to include the night shift, as they were awake during the nights and slept during the day. As a subjective measure of sleep quality, participants were asked to rate their sleep, using a Likert scale ranging from 1, “very light”, to 5, “very deep”.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2007">
        <title>Statistics</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Linear mixed models (LMM) were used to analyze sleep parameters, SWA, SWE and distribution of 1–20 Hz for difference between daytime sleep and nighttime sleep. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Sleep period</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> (N: nighttime sleep; D1: daytime sleep after 1st night shift; D2: daytime sleep after 2nd night shift; D3: daytime sleep after 3rd night shift) was set as a fixed effect and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">participant</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> as a random effect. In addition, for analyses of SWA and SWE </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">time bin</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> (90 min, 180 min, 270 min and 360 min) and their interaction was set as fixed effects, and for analyses of the distribution of 1–20 Hz, each 1 Hz bin and their interaction were included as fixed effects. The Least Significant Difference (LSD) was used to assess differences between levels of fixed factors in sleep and wake parameters. Cohen's d was calculated as a measure of the effect size.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Data are presented as mean ± SEM unless otherwise stated. All statistical analyses were performed with IBM SPSS Statistics, version 25.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Unaffected Scores on Self-Reported Sleep Quality</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The participants rated their sleep quality as not to be affected by night work (F (3,43) = 1.46, p = 0.24). Despite the absence of a perceived effect on sleep quality, the participants rated their daytime functioning after daytime sleep poorer than after nighttime sleep (F (3,40) = 3.13, p = 0.036), both after D1 (0.73 ± 0.34, p = 0.036; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.54) and D2 (0.94 ± 0.32, p = 0.006; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.75). After D3, the daytime functioning was no longer rated significantly poorer than after nighttime sleep (0.63 ± 0.34, p = 0.074; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.43).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>PSG Assessed Nighttime Sleep</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">During nighttime sleep, all participants displayed a typical organization of sleep and wakefulness, with the mean lights off at 23:58 ± 0:17 h (mean ± SEM) and sleep onset at 00:10 ± 0:17 h. The mean light on time was 08:08 ± 0:19 h. The amounts and durations of the different sleep stages were typical of values expected for nighttime sleep; ~7.5 h TST, including 6.9% N1, 41.9% N2, 23.7% N3 and 27.5% REM sleep. Approximately 5% of the time spent in bed was awake. See more details in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep parameters. Data from nighttime sleep (N) (n=12) and three successive daytime sleep periods (D1–D3) (n = 15, all days). The values are in minutes, expressed as mean ± SEM. **p&lt;0.01, *p &lt; 0.05, compared to nighttime sleep.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-243-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Accumulation of Sleep Debt but Preserved Time Spent in Deep NREM Sleep Following Three Consecutive Simulated Night Shifts</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The simulated night shifts ended at 07:00 h. The mean time for lights off was 07:29 ± 0:04 h (mean ± SEM), mean sleep onset was 07:35 ± 0:05 h and mean lights on at 14:09 ± 0:15 h.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Total sleep time was shorter during daytime sleep compared to nighttime sleep (F (3,54) = 3.36, p = 0.025), following all three night shifts (D1: −73.2 ± 28.9 min, p = 0.014, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=0.96; D2: −74.1 ± 28.9 min, p=0.013, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=0.97; D3: −80.3 ± 28.9 min, p=0.007, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=1.05). In total, the cumulative sleep debt was 227.6 min after a night shift period consisting of three shifts. See </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Changes in sleep architecture during daytime sleep were indicative of an increased sleep propensity. The latency to sleep was shorter (F (3,54) = 2.9, p = 0.043) at D1 (−4.6 ± 2.2 min, p = 0.046, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.81), D2 (−5.6 ± 2.2 min, p = 0.016, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 1.00) and D3 (−6.0 ± 2.2 min, p=0.010, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=1.1) compared to nighttime sleep. The latency to stage N3 was not different from nighttime sleep (F (3,41) = 0.8, p = 0.51; D1: −0.2 ± 5.6 min, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.01; D2: −6.6 ± 5.5 min, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.43; D3: −4.7 ± 5.6 min, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.30). Notably, time spent in N3 was not significantly shorter compared to nighttime sleep (F (3,43) = 0.9, p = 0.45; D1: −0.9 ± 7.6 min, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.02; D2: −10.4 ± 7.6 min, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.39; D3: −7.1 ± 7.5 min, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.28).</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep was more consolidated after night shifts, as number of transitions between wake and sleep and between the different sleep stages, indicated by the transition-index, was significantly lower (F (3,40) = 3.1, p = 0.036) on D2 (−2.5 ± 0.94, p = 0.012, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.61) and D3 (−1.9 ± 0.94, p = 0.050, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> = 0.51) than nighttime sleep. No significant differences between daytime sleep and nighttime sleep were found regarding wake after sleep onset (WASO) (F (3, 39) = 2.1, p = 0.12; D1: 6.9 ± 6.7 min, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.32; D2: 5.9 ± 6.6 min, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.23; D3: −8.1 ± 6.9 min, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.54), number of arousals (F (3, 38) = 1.2, p = 0.33; D1: −0.30 ± 0.60, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.00; D2: −0.94 ± 0.59, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.36; D3: −0.04 ± 0.59, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.12) or sleep efficiency (F (3, 40) = 2.4, p = 0.084; D1: −2.12 ± 1.67, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.40; D2: −1.32 ± 1.67, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.32; D3: 1.87 ± 1.66, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.64).</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Thus, these data indicate that three consecutive simulated night shifts are followed by an accumulated sleep debt, increased sleep propensity but preserved time spent in N3.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Duration of stage N3 affects the estimation of the homeostatic parameters; therefore, we assessed whether episode duration changed between nighttime sleep and consecutive daytime sleep. We found no significant change in stage N3 episode duration for each 90-min bout in D1-D3 compared to nighttime sleep (F’s (3,37) &lt;0.9, p &gt; 0.4).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Tendency to Shortened REM Sleep Latency and Duration During Daytime Sleep</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Latency to REM sleep was not significantly different between daytime sleep and nighttime sleep (F (3,44) = 2.2, p = 0.10), though latencies were shorter on D1-D3 with medium-to-large effect sizes (D1: −23.3 ± 11.8 min, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.69; D2: −19.3 ± 11.8 min, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.57; D3: −28.7 ± 11.7 min, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.85).</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Time spent in REM sleep was close to significance (F (3,44) = 2.7, p = 0.057), where less time in REM sleep on D1-D3 showed medium-to-large effect sizes (D1: −30.9 ± 11.3 min, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.97; D2: −22.8 ± 11.3 min, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.71; D3: −15.1± 11.3 min, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.47). See </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The data suggest a trend towards a more rapid transition to REM sleep, but shortened time in REM sleep, during daytime sleep opportunities.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2005">
        <title>Simulated Night Shifts Profoundly Increase SWA in Stage N3 from D1 to D3</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The N3 EEG spectra (1–20 Hz range) during daytime sleep were affected by night shifts, and the changes were frequency-specific (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). Delta (&lt;5 Hz) activity was increased in the frontal derivation during the first 90-min window (F (57,1005) = 5.1, p &lt;0.0001). Delta and theta (&lt;7 Hz) activities were significantly enhanced compared to nighttime sleep in the central derivation (F (57,1005) = 7.2, p &lt; 0.0001). Significant changes in the occipital region included delta, theta and alpha activity (&lt;11 Hz) (F (57,1005) = 6.4, p &lt;0.0001). The average EEG power in N3 after 6 h of sleep exhibited a similar pattern (see </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, lower panel). Notably, the N3 EEG spectra were more affected after the third night shift as indicated by significantly higher EEG power in D3 compared to D1 and D2.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Effect of consecutive night shifts on the electroencephalographic power profiles in stage N3 during (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) the first 90-min interval of sleep (n=14), and (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) the fourth 90-min interval of sleep prior to awakening (n=7). Data from nighttime sleep (N) and three successive daytime sleep periods (D1–D3). Values represent mean ± SEM in the 1 to 20 Hz range across the sleep period. Black lines indicate significant difference from nighttime sleep (N) (p&lt;0.05). Dashed lines indicate significant differences among daytime sleep periods (D3 vs both D1 and D2) (p’s&lt;0.05).</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-243-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">To examine how consecutive night shifts change the slow oscillations during sleep, we measured SWA in N3, averaged across 90 min windows (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). SWA was highest at the beginning and declined during time of sleep, in line with the homeostatic process. Notably, in all daytime sleep periods (D1-D3), SWA was significantly higher compared to nighttime sleep throughout the whole sleep period, in all three cortical regions (all p &lt; 0.0001), except for the last 90 min at D1 (p &gt; 0.05). Moreover, the increase in SWA was pronounced and significantly higher at D3 than D1 (p &lt; 0.05) and D2 (except for the last 90 min) (p &lt; 0.05), revealing a significant inter-day build-up of sleep debt.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Slow wave activity in stage N3. Data from nighttime sleep (N) and three successive daytime sleep periods (D1-D3). Upper panel (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) slow wave activity (SWA) averaged across 90-min intervals. Values are presented as mean ± SEM. Data in frontal, central and occipital derivations. Black lines indicate significant difference from night sleep (p’s&lt;0.05). Note that in the fourth 90-min interval there is only a significant difference between D2/D3 and nighttime sleep. Dashed lines indicate higher EEG power in D3 compared to D1 and D2 (p’s&lt;0.05). Lower panel (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) The build-up of SWA the first 90 min in D1–D3. Data are presented as % change from N in 30-min intervals.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-243-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">A sensitive indicator of sleep pressure is the change in the dynamics of SWA during the first NREM sleep period. Changes in the rise of SWA in the initial part of daytime sleep periods compared to nighttime sleep are illustrated in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. Here, the percent increase in SWA of the three first 30 min bouts clearly indicates an intensified sleep pressure during D1, D2 and D3, and that the frontal derivation is particularly sensitive to sleep pressure changes. It is concluded that daytime sleep revealed a more rapid manifestation of SWA at the onset of stage N3 than nighttime sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Higher delta power at the beginning and through the duration of 6 h of sleep may be a result of increased need to discharge slow wave sleep during daytime sleep. To address the efficiency of SWA in relieving sleep pressure, we measured SWE in N3 (the EEG power times minutes spent in N3) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). During the first 90 mins of sleep, on all days, SWE was significantly higher compared to nighttime sleep levels, across all cortical areas (p’s &lt; 0.01) (frontal, D1: +7869.6 µV</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">*min; D2: +6536.8 µV</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">*min; D3: +9659.3 µV</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">*min; central, D1: +5330.2 µV</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">*min; D2: +5201.4 µV</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">*min; D3: +7445.0 µV</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">*min; and occipital, D1: +3410.9 µV</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">*min; D2: +2970.6 µV</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">*min; D3: +4502.5 µV</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">*min). During the last four 90-min intervals of daytime sleep (from 270 min after sleep onset to 360 min), SWE was no longer significantly different from nighttime sleep in any of the cortical areas. Nonetheless, the cumulative SWE discharged across the entire 6 h recording was significantly elevated during daytime sleep relative to nighttime sleep in the frontal (F (3,31) = 3.6, p = 0.025), central (F (3,31) = 3.4, p = 0.031) and occipital (F (3,33) = 3.0, p = 0.042) derivation, respectively.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0004" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Slow wave energy in N3. Data from nighttime sleep (N) and three successive daytime sleep periods (D1–D3). Slow wave energy (SWE) averaged across 90-min intervals. Values are presented as mean ±SEM. Data in frontal, central and occipital derivations. Black lines indicate significant difference in D1/D2/D3 vs nighttime sleep (p’s&lt;0.05). Note in the second 90-min interval there is only a significant difference between D3 and nighttime sleep.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-243-g0004" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This study shows that the impact of a night shift period consisting of three consecutive simulated night shifts on daytime sleep varies across sleep parameters, EEG power spectra and objective markers of homeostatic sleep responses. Regardless of preserved time in the deep NREM sleep, adaptation to daytime sleep was limited. Sleep debt accumulated across days and the sleep propensity increased, both at sleep onset and after 6 h of sleep. Notably, the intensifying of SWA was pronounced after the 3rd night shift. These findings imply that mechanisms of sleep are less likely to adapt to night shift work, at least in the short term.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Support for this contention comes from comparisons to ordinary nighttime sleep, and of the sleep/wake measures within the three consecutive daytime sleep periods. The homeostatic drive for sleep (indicated by latency to enter sleep and the rate of rise of SWA) was higher compared to nighttime sleep and became increasingly altered across the simulated night shift period. Additionally, the sleep debt accumulated as time spent sleeping was lowest at D3. Other quantitative EEG field</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7–10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and laboratory</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> studies after one single night shift report a reduced total sleep time of &gt;1.5 h. However, laboratory studies looking at sleep after 6 night shifts have reported some conflicting results. Dahlgren</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> found reduced total sleep time in both permanent and rotating shift workers, supporting our findings, though Lamond et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> found that total sleep time was not significantly different from nighttime sleep across 6 daytime sleep periods. One explanation for the enhanced sleep duration in the study by Lamond et al could be that the participants were shielded from social and environmental disturbances throughout the experiment. Disturbed sleep after simulated night shift work is also supported by an animal model of shift work, where simulated night shift work in the resting phase reduces total sleep time in the active phase.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The principal challenge with night work is to obtain enough and restorative sleep during the day. Important restorative functions occur during all stages of sleep, whereas SWS is suggested to play a major role in energy conservation and in nervous system recuperation. The present study suggests a preserved time spent in stage N3 throughout the simulated night shift period, where only minor deviations from ordinary nighttime sleep were found (from −1 min at D1 to −7 min at D3). This is in line with studies on sleep following one single night shift,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7–10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and two studies on daytime sleep following 6 night shifts,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> where time spent in SWS was found to be preserved.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In addition to time spent in N3, the continuity of this sleep stage is of importance to the restorative effect of sleep. Grønli et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> found that rats housed in moving running wheels during their normal resting phase showed reduced NREM sleep episode-length compared to those housed in moving running wheels during their normal active phase. It should be mentioned that SWS (stage N3) is not a distinguished sleep stage in rodents. However, as in humans, SWA oscillates in synchrony with the NREM-REM sleep cycles, though with a shorter periodicity due to brain size.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The present study found no such difference in the continuity of stage N3 between daytime sleep and nighttime sleep. However, our characterization of the EEG of deep NREM sleep suggests that the restorative function is highly affected during a night shift period. Both the spectral profiles in the 1–20 Hz range (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">), changes in SWA in the first and fourth 90-min intervals of sleep (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">), and SWE in the first half of the recording (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) were elevated across all the different cortical areas, compared to nighttime sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">After three consecutive night shifts, our data show that sleep intensity in the first 90-min interval of sleep (+33% from D1 to D3) and the fourth 90-min interval of sleep (+25% from D1 to D3) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) increases profoundly, supporting the concept that night shift work induces a compensatory response of SWA, similar to that found following repeated partial sleep restriction.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> This finding demonstrates a clear cumulative alteration in the homeostatic sleep response in the context of consecutive night shifts.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">The increased sleep pressure at the end of the daytime sleep period relative to nighttime sleep contrasts with the participants subjective rating of a sleep quality non-affected by night shift work. SWE would be a reasonable measure of the efficiency to relieve sleep pressure.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> At the beginning of daytime sleep, SWE was significantly higher than nighttime sleep. This would be expected since SWE is calculated based on SWA, and SWA was significantly increased in the first 90 min of sleep. However, after 6 h of daytime sleep, SWE was no longer significantly different from nighttime sleep (see </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). Since SWA was found to be increased after 6 h of sleep, reduced </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">time</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> spent in stage N3 at the end of the sleep period could explain these findings, indicating a less efficient relief of sleep pressure. Still, the total cumulative SWE discharged across 6 h of sleep was increased in all daytime sleep recordings relative to the baseline night.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The quantitative EEG response to consecutive night shifts was slightly higher in the frontal than in the central and occipital areas. Similar findings of globally increased EEG power density of the lower frequencies, but with a frontal dominance, are also reported after 40 h of sleep deprivation</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and after 5 days of repeated partial sleep restriction with a 4 h sleep opportunity.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The frontal dominance reflects the increased sensitivity of the EEG derived from this cortical region to perturbations of sleep homeostasis relative to more posterior regions.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Moreover, all participants in the present study performed in-laboratory tests using visual modalities, lasting approximately 20 min, five times during each shift. Visual tests actively engage the occipital cortex, and the EEG responses may also be a result of local, use-dependent sleep homeostatic processes induced by cognitive workload and visual neural processing during the shift.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Still, the global effects of EEG observed after insufficient sleep may reflect multiple changes, in terms of the drive to initiate sleep, consequences of sleep loss and sleep regulatory processes. Altered network dynamics after a night shift period manifested at the behavior or metabolic level have not yet been described.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Restorative functions of sleep are thought to be important for efficient daytime functioning. Accordingly, the participants rated their daytime functioning to be poorer after D1 and D2 than after nighttime sleep. However, after D3, the daytime functioning was rated to be similar to after nighttime sleep. This change in the perception of daytime functioning contrasts with the objective findings of accumulated sleep debt and increased homeostatic sleep response. There are several possible explanations for such discrepancy. First, impaired daytime functioning is maintained, at least in part, by subjective perception of sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Since the participants rated their sleep quality not to be affected by night shift work, this may influence the perception of daytime functioning. Secondly, the intensified SWA may reflect increased recuperative response to sleep loss, resulting in the feeling of being rested. Thirdly, the perception of daytime functioning may be influenced by the incentive effect, through expectations of a day off and the recognition of termination of the night-shift period.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Shift-work disorder is classified as a circadian sleep-wake disorder.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The perturbed circadian function experienced by shift workers is extensively reported (i.e.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) and better studied than the perturbed homeostatic function. If, how and to what degree the sleep homeostatic response is affected by night work has been surprisingly little studied. Most studies have concluded that the time spent in SWS/stage N3 is preserved; however, absolute time in SWS/stage N3 does not reflect homeostatic response and sleep pressure. Our results suggest that there are constraints on the dissipation of homeostatic sleep pressure during sleep following consecutive night shifts and document a need for further investigation of perturbed homeostatic functions during night shift work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Strengths and Limitations</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The present study is, to our knowledge, the first using EEG during a night shift period consisting of multiple simulated night shifts, contributing to a better understanding of sleep dynamics and sleep homeostatic responses.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">In order to enhance the ecological validity of the results, PSG was monitored in the usual home sleep setting. However, home recordings of sleep increase the risk of technical errors, and external factors may very well disrupt the sleep, which could have been avoided in a laboratory setting. Furthermore, the current study allowed the participants to self-select sleep time after each night shift and napping between the night shifts to mimic daytime sleep opportunities, similar to the real-life night-shift workers. Both components, sleeping in a safe environment and napping, may modulate the sleep pressure.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Oscillations in the 0.5–1 Hz range exhibit sleep/wake dependent homeostatic changes,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> but are distinct from oscillations in the 1–4 Hz range, both in terms of their sources</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and their temporal dynamics</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> across sleep. The EEG SWA was calculated in the 1–4 Hz range due to limited options in the analysis software. Therefore, we cannot rule out that information about changes in the 0.5–1 Hz range could contribute to more knowledge about the homeostatic response to consecutive night shifts.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In the European health sector, 78% of the night shift workers are women,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> thus parallel to the gender distribution in our study. Even so, future studies should ensure a more equal gender distribution, exploring the possible gender-differences in tolerance to night shift work. Our participants were young adults from a student population, and do not necessarily reflect the “average” night shift worker. Field or laboratory studies including actual night shift workers, and a larger distribution of age, are thus warranted.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Additional considerations are the restricted number of PGS devices available, participant dropouts, and technical issues, all of which lowered the sample size (n = 15) weakening the statistical power. This is reflected by some non-significance despite medium-to-large effect sizes for the main effects of the LMM analyses on parameters like latency to- and time spent in REM sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">In summary, adaptation to daytime sleep following three consecutive simulated night shifts is limited. Compared to nighttime sleep, total sleep time was reduced, resulting in a cumulative sleep loss. Although time spent in stage N3 was preserved, the sleep intensity was markedly altered. There was a substantial increase in a global compensatory homeostatic response, as indicated by elevated EEG power, particularly in the low-frequency range of the frontal, central and occipital cortex. A considerably increased sleep intensity was observed after the 3rd successive night shift. After 6 h of sleep, the level of SWE did not deviate from nighttime sleep, reflecting an insufficient relief from sleep pressure. Future studies should further investigate these processes in night shift periods longer than three shifts, during quick rotation shifts and importantly in the recovery-days after night shift periods.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The circadian system, through its interactions with homeostatic processes even at the cellular level, does play a role in facilitating the generation of SWA. A perturbed circadian rhythm may disturb cellular processes in the brain that underlie sleep homeostasis, and thereby affect the generation of SWA. For instance, the synaptosomal-associated Protein, 25 kDa (SNAP-25) serves both as a driver of circadian rhythmicity</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and a regulator of sleep-dependent slow wave activity.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> A question to be asked is whether the sleep homeostatic response remains or reaches a peak level after three night shifts, and if this is regulated by an allostatic process (at the level of cellular physiology, sleep EEG and/or other physiological responses) when facing additional sleep loss.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0007">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Åkerstedt</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Shift work and disturbed sleep/wakefulness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Occup Med</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/occmed/kqg046</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ganesan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Magee</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stone</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The impact of shift work on sleep, alertness and performance in healthcare workers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>4635</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-40914-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30874565</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Banks</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dinges</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Behavioral and physiological consequences of sleep restriction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>03</volume>(<issue>05</issue>):<fpage>519</fpage>–<lpage>528</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.26918</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Van Dongen</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maislin</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mullington</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dinges</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The cumulative cost of additional wakefulness: dose-response effects on neurobehavioral functions and sleep physiology from chronic sleep restriction and total sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/26.2.117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12683469</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Matsumoto</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep patterns in hospital nurses due to shift work: an EEG study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Waking Sleeping</italic></source>. <year>1978</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>173</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tilley</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilkinson</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Warren</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Watson</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drud</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The sleep and performance of shift workers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hum Factors</italic></source>. <year>1982</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>641</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/001872088202400601</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7160851</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Åkerstedt</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kecklund</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knutsson</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Spectral analysis of sleep electroencephalography in rotating three-shift work</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Scand J Work Environ Health</italic></source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>330</fpage>–<lpage>336</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5271/sjweh.1694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1947919</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Torsvall</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Akerstedt</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gillander</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knutsson</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep on the night shift: 24‐hour EEG monitoring of spontaneous sleep/wake behavior</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychophysiology</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>352</fpage>–<lpage>358</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8986.1989.tb01934.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2756085</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Torsvall</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Åkerstedt</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gillberg</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Age, sleep and irregular work hours: a field study with electroencephalographic recordings, catecholamine excretion and self-ratings</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Scand J Work Environ Health</italic></source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>196</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20120585</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Smith-Coggins</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosekind</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hurd</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buccino</surname>
<given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Relationship of day versus night sleep to physician performance and mood</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Emerg Med</italic></source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>928</fpage>–<lpage>934</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0196-0644(94)70209-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7978567</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dahlgren</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Adjustment of circadian rhythms and EEG sleep functions to day and night sleep among permanent night workers and rotating shiftworkers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychophysiology</italic></source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>391</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8986.1981.tb02469.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7267920</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lamond</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dorrian</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roach</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The impact of a week of simulated night work on sleep, circadian phase, and performance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Occup Environ Med</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e13</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/oem.60.11.e13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14573724</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Berry</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brooks</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gamaldo</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harding</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marcus</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vaughn</surname>
<given-names>BV</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The AASM manual for the scoring of sleep and associated events</article-title>. <source>Rules, Terminology and Technical Specifications</source>. <publisher-loc>Darien, Illinois</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</publisher-name>; <year>2012</year>:<fpage>2012</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dijk</surname>
<given-names>D-J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Regulation and functional correlates of slow wave sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>2 suppl</issue>):<fpage>S6</fpage>–<lpage>S15</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.5.2S.S6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19998869</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Borbély</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A two process model of sleep regulation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hum Neurobiol</italic></source>. <year>1982</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>204</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7185792</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lazar</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lazar</surname>
<given-names>ZI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dijk</surname>
<given-names>D-J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Circadian regulation of slow waves in human sleep: topographical aspects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroimage</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>116</volume>:<fpage>123</fpage>–<lpage>134</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2015.05.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25979664</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Banks</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Dongen</surname>
<given-names>HP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maislin</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dinges</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Neurobehavioral dynamics following chronic sleep restriction: dose-response effects of one night for recovery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1013</fpage>–<lpage>1026</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/33.8.1013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20815182</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Skorucak</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arbon</surname>
<given-names>EL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dijk</surname>
<given-names>D-J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Achermann</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Response to chronic sleep restriction, extension, and subsequent total sleep deprivation in humans: adaptation or preserved sleep homeostasis?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>7</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsy078</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dijk</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beersma</surname>
<given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Daan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bloem</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van den Hoofdakker</surname>
<given-names>RH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Quantitative analysis of the effects of slow wave sleep deprivation during the first 3 h of sleep on subsequent EEG power density</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Arch Psychiatry Neurol Sci</italic></source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>236</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>323</fpage>–<lpage>328</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3678290</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Garde</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nabe-Nielsen</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jensen</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kristiansen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sørensen</surname>
<given-names>JK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hansen</surname>
<given-names>ÅM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effects of the number of consecutive night shifts on sleep duration and quality</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Scand J Work Environ Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>446</fpage>–<lpage>453</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5271/sjweh.3885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32055864</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Brunner</surname>
<given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dijk</surname>
<given-names>D-J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tobler</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Borbély</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effect of partial sleep deprivation on sleep stages and EEG power spectra: evidence for non-REM and REM sleep homeostasis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Electroencephalogr Clin Neurophysiol</italic></source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>492</fpage>–<lpage>499</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0013-4694(90)90136-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1693894</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Åkerstedt</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kecklund</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ingre</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lekander</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Axelsson</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep homeostasis during repeated sleep restriction and recovery: support from EEG dynamics</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>222</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/32.2.217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19238809</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Goel</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Banks</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mignot</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dinges</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>PER3 polymorphism predicts cumulative sleep homeostatic but not neurobehavioral changes to chronic partial sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e5874</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19516903</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Brunner</surname>
<given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dijk</surname>
<given-names>D-J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Borbély</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Repeated partial sleep deprivation progressively changes the EEG during sleep and wakefulness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>100</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/16.2.100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8446828</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laposky</surname>
<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bergmann</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Turek</surname>
<given-names>FW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Repeated sleep restriction in rats leads to homeostatic and allostatic responses during recovery sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>25</issue>):<fpage>10697</fpage>–<lpage>10702</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0610351104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17548824</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Leemburg</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vyazovskiy</surname>
<given-names>VV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olcese</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bassetti</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tononi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cirelli</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep homeostasis in the rat is preserved during chronic sleep restriction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>107</volume>(<issue>36</issue>):<fpage>15939</fpage>–<lpage>15944</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1002570107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20696898</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lancel</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kerkhof</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of repeated sleep deprivation in the dark-or light-period on sleep in rats</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiol Behav</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>297</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0031-9384(89)90130-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2756014</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Grønli</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meerlo</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pedersen</surname>
<given-names>TT</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A rodent model of night-shift work induces short-term and enduring sleep and electroencephalographic disturbances</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Biol Rhythms</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>48</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0748730416675460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28013579</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Garde</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Begtrup</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bjorvatn</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>How to schedule night shift work in order to reduce health and safety risks</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Scand J Work Environ Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>557</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32895725</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Van Cauter</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spiegel</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tasali</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leproult</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Metabolic consequences of sleep and sleep loss</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>S23</fpage>–<lpage>S28</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1389-9457(08)70013-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18929315</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bellesi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Riedner</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garcia-Molina</surname>
<given-names>GN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cirelli</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tononi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Enhancement of sleep slow waves: underlying mechanisms and practical consequences</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Syst Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>208</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25389394</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rasch</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Born</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>About sleep’s role in memory</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiol Rev</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physrev.00032.2012</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Adan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Almirall</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Horne &amp; Östberg morningness-eveningness questionnaire: a reduced scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pers Individ Dif</italic></source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>253</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0191-8869(91)90110-W</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sunde</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mrdalj</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pedersen</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Role of nocturnal light intensity on adaptation to three consecutive night shifts: a counterbalanced crossover study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Occup Environ Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>77</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>255</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/oemed-2019-106049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32019847</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Statistical Power Analysis for the Behavioral Sciences</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Academic press</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Franken</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tobler</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Borbély</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Varying photoperiod in the laboratory rat: profound effect on 24-h sleep pattern but no effect on sleep homeostasis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol</italic></source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>269</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>R691</fpage>–<lpage>R701</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpregu.1995.269.3.R691</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cajochen</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Foy</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dijk</surname>
<given-names>D-J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Frontal predominance of a relative increase in sleep delta and theta EEG activity after sleep loss in humans</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Res Online</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11382884</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Krone</surname>
<given-names>LB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yamagata</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blanco-Duque</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A role for the cortex in sleep–wake regulation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1210</fpage>–<lpage>1215</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41593-021-00894-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34341585</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huber</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deboer</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tobler</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Topography of EEG dynamics after sleep deprivation in mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurophysiol</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>84</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1888</fpage>–<lpage>1893</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jn.2000.84.4.1888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11024081</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Goel</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abe</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Braun</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dinges</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cognitive workload and sleep restriction interact to influence sleep homeostatic responses</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1745</fpage>–<lpage>1756</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.4164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25364070</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Semler</surname>
<given-names>CN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harvey</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Misperception of sleep can adversely affect daytime functioning in insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Res Ther</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>843</fpage>–<lpage>856</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15896282</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Haslam</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The incentive effect and sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1983</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>362</fpage>–<lpage>368</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/6.4.362</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6665399</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sateia</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>International classification of sleep disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>146</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1387</fpage>–<lpage>1394</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.14-0970</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25367475</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Roden</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koller</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pirich</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vierhapper</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Waldhauser</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The circadian melatonin and cortisol secretion pattern in permanent night shift workers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol</italic></source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>265</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>R261</fpage>–<lpage>R267</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpregu.1993.265.1.R261</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sack</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blood</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lewy</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Melatonin rhythms in night shift workers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>434</fpage>–<lpage>441</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/15.5.434</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1455127</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Åkerstedt</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wright</surname>
<given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep loss and fatigue in shift work and shift work disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Clin</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>257</fpage>–<lpage>271</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20640236</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hubbard</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gent</surname>
<given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoekstra</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Rapid fast-delta decay following prolonged wakefulness marks a phase of wake-inertia in NREM sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Commun</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-16915-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31911652</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Steriade</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nunez</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amzica</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A novel slow (&lt; 1 Hz) oscillation of neocortical neurons in vivo: depolarizing and hyperpolarizing components</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>3252</fpage>–<lpage>3265</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8340806</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Parent-Thirion</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Biletta</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cabrita</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Eurofound: sixth European working conditions survey—overview report (2017 update)</article-title>. <publisher-name>Publications Office of the European Union, Luxembourg Google Scholar</publisher-name>. <year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Oliver</surname>
<given-names>PL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sobczyk</surname>
<given-names>MV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maywood</surname>
<given-names>ES</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Disrupted circadian rhythms in a mouse model of schizophrenia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Biol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>314</fpage>–<lpage>319</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2011.12.051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22264613</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
