<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35228825</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">8881930</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">342137</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S342137</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>High Dream Recall Frequency is Associated with Increased Creativity and Default Mode Network Connectivity</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Vallat et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Vallat et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1779-7653</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Vallat</surname>
            <given-names>Raphael</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Türker</surname>
            <given-names>Başak</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nicolas</surname>
            <given-names>Alain</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ruby</surname>
            <given-names>Perrine</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Lyon Neuroscience Research Center (CRNL), INSERM UMRS 1028, CNRS UMR 5292, Université Claude Bernard Lyon 1, Université de Lyon</institution>, <addr-line>Lyon</addr-line>, <addr-line>F-69000</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Raphael Vallat, <institution>Department of Psychology, University of California</institution>, <addr-line>2121 Berkeley Way</addr-line>, <addr-line>Berkeley</addr-line>, <addr-line>CA</addr-line>, <addr-line>94720-1650</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>, <phone>Tel +510-642-5292</phone>, Email raphaelvallat@Berkeley.edu</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>22</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <fpage>265</fpage>
      <lpage>275</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2022 Vallat et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Vallat et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec sec-type="intro" id="s2001">
          <title>Introduction</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Several results suggest that the frequency of dream recall is positively correlated with personality traits such as creativity and openness to experience. In addition, neuroimaging results have evidenced different neurophysiological profiles in high dream recallers (HR) and low dream recallers (LR) during both sleep and wakefulness, specifically within regions of the default mode network (DMN). These findings are consistent with the emerging view that dreaming and mind wandering pertain to the same family of spontaneous mental processes, subserved by the DMN.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">To further test this hypothesis, we measured the DMN functional connectivity during resting wakefulness, together with personality and cognitive abilities (including creativity) in 28 HR and 27 LR.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">As expected, HR demonstrated a greater DMN connectivity than LR, higher scores of creativity, and no significant difference in memory abilities. However, there was no significant correlation between creativity scores and DMN connectivity.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Discussion</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">These results further demonstrate that there are trait neurophysiological and psychological differences between individuals who frequently recall their dreams and those who do not. They support the forebrain and the DMN hypotheses of dreaming and leave open the possibility that increased activity in the DMN promotes creative-thinking during both wakefulness and sleep. Further work is needed to test whether activity in the DMN is causally associated with creative-thinking.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>dream recall</kwd>
        <kwd>creativity</kwd>
        <kwd>resting state</kwd>
        <kwd>functional connectivity</kwd>
        <kwd>default mode network</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>LABEX CORTEX (ANR-11-LABX-0042) of Université de Lyon</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was partly performed within the framework of the LABEX CORTEX (ANR-11-LABX-0042) of Université de Lyon, within the program ANR-11-IDEX-0007.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="2"/>
        <table-count count="3"/>
        <ref-count count="57"/>
        <page-count count="11"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">While dreaming has long been equated with rapid eye movement (REM) sleep, it is now well established that dreaming can occur in any sleep stage and is therefore not exclusive to a specific global vigilance state.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1–3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> As of today, no (neuro)physiological correlates of dreaming are known, which means that one cannot know for sure whether someone is actually dreaming or not at a specific moment of sleep. Consequently, most empirical investigations of dreaming have been based on dream reports collected after the awakening of the dreamer. Even then, a fundamental limitation of dream research is that the absence of a dream recall does not necessarily mean the absence of dreaming.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Dream recall is driven by both </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">state</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">trait</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> components, as described in recent integrative models of dream recall.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Examples of state components include the sleep stage and arousal levels prior to awakening, as well as the salience of the dream, while trait components refer to person-specific factors that are associated with a higher or lower ability to recall dreams (eg, personality traits).</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Focusing on the latter, prior works have highlighted several neurophysiological differences between high dream recallers (HR) and low dream recallers (LR), not only during sleep but also during wakefulness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7–10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> A PET study from our team showed an increased regional cerebral blood flow in HR as compared to LR in the temporo-parietal junction (TPJ) and in the medial prefrontal cortex (MPFC) during REM sleep, N3 sleep and wakefulness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In a second study conducted on an independent set of participants, we also observed an increased fMRI functional connectivity between the nodes of the DMN and memory regions 5 minutes post awakening in HR as compared to LR.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Consistent with these findings, lesions of these same areas (TPJ and MPFC) are associated with a global or partial cessation of dream recall, even in absence of any concurrent sleep disturbances.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> These converging results suggest that TPJ and MPFC play a key role in dream production or recall. These two regions and the posterior cingulate cortex/precuneus (PCC) are core nodes of the default mode network (DMN), a set of functionally coupled brain regions involved in mind wandering, self-related thoughts, inferential reasoning, future envisioning and episodic memory;</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> for a meta-analysis see.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The finding of a higher spontaneous activity within the DMN, along with a higher functional connectivity at awakening between its core regions in HR compared to LR</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> support the hypothesis of a global differential cognitive and brain functioning between high and low dream recallers. This idea was first put forward by Schonbar,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> who postulated that high dream recall is part of a general lifestyle characterized by creativity, divergent thinking and introspection. Several subsequent studies have supported this hypothesis by showing significant correlations between DRF and creativity,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16–18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and between DRF and personality traits such as openness to experience and thin boundary structure</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18–21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, with the strength of these correlations ranging from </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=0.10 to </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=0.40 depending on the study. These observations fit well with the emerging view that dreaming and creative-thinking both pertain to the same family of spontaneous mental processes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Indeed, several works indicate that dreaming and creativity may both involve regions of the DMN, and especially the prefrontal areas.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23–28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> With regards to sleep, studies have found that DMN functional connectivity changes across the sleep stages,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> severely weakening during deep NREM sleep (which is typically associated with no or little dream recall) and conversely increasing to a hyper-associated state during REM sleep – the sleep stage from which the proportion of dream recall upon awakening is highest. These findings have led to the hypothesis that DMN activity during sleep may be the substrate of dreaming.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Regarding creativity, a growing body of evidence suggests that creativity scores (in particular divergent thinking) positively correlate with DMN activation,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> as well as with the functional coupling between the DMN and executive regions.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In sum, the available data suggests that high dream recall frequency is related on the one hand to the activity of the DMN, and on the other hand to an increased creativity. To further test this hypothesis, we assessed DMN functional connectivity and psychological factors (personality traits, cognitive abilities and creativity) in HR and LR participants. As primary predictions, we expected to observe 1) a higher functional connectivity within the DMN in HR compared to LR, 2) higher creativity scores in HR and 3) a significant correlation between DMN connectivity and creativity. Second, based on prior results, we also expected to observe significant differences in personality between HR and LR,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> yet no difference in cognitive abilities.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This study is a reanalysis of the data published in Vallat et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> to assess the links between DRF, DMN functional connectivity and creativity.</citation_analysis></p>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Behavioral and neurophysiological data were acquired from 55 healthy subjects (27 females, mean age = 22.55, standard deviation = 2.41, range = 19–29) having normal sleep characteristics and body mass index (habitual sleep time per night, 7.7 ± 0.9 hours; body mass index, 22.1 ± 2.6 kg/m</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The subjects were informed of the study through an announcement sent to the mailing list of Lyon University, which briefly described the study and included a link to a questionnaire concerning sleep and dream habits.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Subjects were selected if they reported and subsequently confirmed during a phone interview: 1) having a high or low DRF (DRF superior to five dream recalls per week and inferior to two dream recalls per month respectively) 2) having a regular sleep-wake schedule, no difficulty to fall asleep, being occasional or frequent nappers and having preferentially already done an MRI brain scan in the past few years. Importantly, the subjects were unaware that DRF was the main criterion for inclusion in the study. Among the 55 participants, 28 of them were high dream recallers (HR; mean DRF = 6.6 ± 0.7 dream reports per week) and 27 were low dream recallers (LR; mean DRF = 0.2 ± 0.1 dream reports per week). Apart from the DRF (p &lt; 0.001), the two groups did not significantly differ in age, sex ratio, body mass index (BMI), habitual sleep duration and education.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Participants had no history of neurological and psychiatric disorders, and had no sleep disturbances. They provided written informed consent according to the Declaration of Helsinki and received monetary compensation for their participation. The Lyon Neuroscience Research Centre (main affiliation of the authors) does not have an ethics committee, and therefore the protocol was reviewed by an independent ethics committee from the nearby cancer research and medical center (CCPPRB, Centre Leon Berard, Lyon, France). Sample size was not based on an explicit power analysis but instead on previous neuroimaging works from our group that have shown significant physiological differences between HR and LR using a smaller or similar sample size.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Procedure</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Participants arrived in the sleep unit of Le Vinatier Hospital at 8 pm the night before the scanning session. Participants had to put on an actigraphic watch (Actigraph, Pensacola, USA) upon arrival and could freely read and watch movies after the behavioral tests described below were administered by R.V. They were allowed to sleep for 3 hours between 5 and 8 am in a bed of the sleep unit. Actigraphic measures allowed us to assess time asleep and ensure that the average sleep duration of the two groups did not differ. Indeed, no between-group difference in actigraphy-derived sleep duration was observed during the 3 hours sleep slot (HR = 149.9 ± 19.2 min; LR = 155.6 ± 9.3; p = 0.164). This partial sleep deprivation was done to increase the likelihood of sleep in the MR scanner in the subsequent afternoon nap. In the morning, the participants read or were on the internet. The scanning session started after an early lunch (around 11.30 am) at the neuroimaging center (CERMEP). During the first half hour, experimenters installed an MRI compatible EEG cap (EASYCAP</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>®</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) on the participant’s head. Participants were then settled in the MRI scanner at about 1.20 pm (1.17 pm ± 13 min). During the eye tracker calibration, a comic was presented. Prior to the first resting state scan, participants performed the first descending subtraction task (DST). The instructions for the resting state acquisition were to remain awake and look at a central fixation cross on the screen. At the end of the scan, participants were informed that they would be left alone without stimulation in the dark for the next 45 min and that they could sleep if they wanted to. At the end of the nap slot, participants were awakened, if they were sleeping, by calling their first name. Then, the second resting state scan was acquired just before the second DST. During the following 10 minutes, subjects were asked to recall the dream they may have had during the nap and the comic they read during the eye tracking calibration. Then, the third resting state scan and DST was performed about 25 min after awakening. Finally, an 8-min T1 anatomical scan was acquired. For more details on the experimental procedure, please refer to.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Data Collection</title>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3001">
          <title>MRI Acquisition</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">MRI scans were obtained from a MAGNETOM Prisma 3.0 T scanner (Siemens Healthcare, Erlangen, Germany) at the Primage neuroimaging platform (CERMEP). Structural MRIs were acquired with a T1-weighted (0.9-mm isotropic resolution) MPRAGE sequence and functional MRI data with a T2*-weighted 2D gradient echo planar imaging sequence (EPI) with 180 volumes (TR/TE: 2000/25 ms; flip angle: 80°; voxel size: 2.68 × 2.68 × 3 mm; slices: 40, duration: 6 minutes). Functional and anatomical scans were performed using a 20-channel head coil. The coil was foam-padded to improve subject comfort and restrict head motion. Furthermore, to ensure that the participants were not closing their eyes during the resting state scans, eye movements were monitored during the experiment using an EyeLink 1000 fMRI eye tracking system (SR Research Ontario, Canada). Eye position was calibrated at the beginning of the experiment and monitored throughout.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3002">
          <title>Behavioral Tests</title>
          <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3002-s4001">
            <title>BFI</title>
            <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The Big Five Inventory (BFI) is a self-report inventory designed to measure the Big Five personality dimensions,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> which have been typically labelled as O (Openness to experience), C (Conscientiousness), E (Extraversion), A (Agreeableness), N (Neuroticism). We used the validated French version (BFI-Fr</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">); which includes 45 items presenting a collection of statements concerning interpersonal relationships and personality. Each item is scored on a 5-point Likert-type response scale, ranging from “strongly disagree” (1) to “strongly agree” (5).</citation_analysis></p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3002-s4002">
            <title>STAI</title>
            <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI) is a self-report inventory consisting of 40 items pertaining to anxiety affect.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The STAI purports to measure one’s conscious awareness at two extremes of anxiety affect, labeled state anxiety (A-state), and trait anxiety (A-trait), respectively. The A-Trait and A-State scales comprise 20 items each, scored on a 4-point Likert-type response scale. Scores range from 20 to 80, with higher scores suggesting greater levels of anxiety.</citation_analysis></p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3002-s4003">
            <title>PQSI</title>
            <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PQSI) is a self-rated questionnaire, which assesses sleep quality and disturbances over a one-month time interval.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> It comprises 19 individual items concerning among others subjective sleep quality, sleep latency, sleep duration and daytime dysfunction. Higher scores at the PQSI indicate poorer sleep quality.</citation_analysis></p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3002-s4004">
            <title>MEM-III</title>
            <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The MEM-III is the validated French version of the Wechsler Memory Scale (WMS-third edition, WMS-III).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> We used a subtest to assess immediate and delayed memory. Participants were read two stories and asked, after each story, to say out loud everything they could remember about the story. The experimenter rated how many items the participants were able to recall (maximum 25). Twenty-five minutes later, the subjects were asked again to recall the two stories (delayed memory). The subjects were not aware that they would have to recall the stories at any point after the initial recall. For both immediate and delayed recall, scores were summed across the two stories and therefore range from 0 to 50, with higher scores reflecting greater memory performances.</citation_analysis></p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3002-s4005">
            <title>Digit Span</title>
            <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Individual memory abilities were also assessed using a digit span task, which measures the working memory’s number storage capacity. Participants were asked to repeat a sequence of numerical digits, the length of which increases at each trial. Digit span was assessed first forwards (maximum score 16) and then backwards (maximum score 14). The digit span index was obtained by summing the two scores. Higher scores (maximum 30) indicate higher working memory abilities.</citation_analysis></p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3002-s4006">
            <title>Guildford’s Alternative Uses Task</title>
            <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The Guildford Uses Task</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> is a creativity test in which participants are asked to list as many alternative uses as possible for an everyday object. Participants were shown images of three objects (a pen, a mug, a chair) in a randomized order and subsequently asked to enumerate for 2 minutes as many alternative or unusual uses they could think of for this object. The fluency index is the total number of responses averaged across the three items. Higher scores indicate higher creativity. Additionally, we computed for each subject and each object the number of rare uses (top 10% rarest uses: uses found by 5 or less participants, top 20% rarest uses: uses found by 10 or less participants). The rare uses index is the total number of rare uses averaged across the three items. Here again, higher scores indicate higher creativity.</citation_analysis></p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>fMRI Data Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">EEG and eye tracking data were used to make sure that the participants did not sleep during any of the three resting state fMRI scans. One subject (HR) was excluded from the MRI analysis because of a technical failure during MRI acquisition, leading to a total of 27 HR and 27 LR. As the failure only concerned MRI acquisition, the behavioral and cognitive measures of this participant were still included in the analysis. For the remaining subjects, preprocessing and quality check were performed using standard routine in SPM12 software (Wellcome Department of Imaging Neuroscience). Preprocessing included functional realignment, slice-time correction, coregistration to structural scan, spatial normalization and spatial smoothing using a 6 mm full-width at half-maximum isotropic Gaussian kernel filter. Individual T1 images were segmented into gray matter, white matter and cerebrospinal fluid tissue maps. Functional and structural images were then normalized to MNI152 space (Montreal Neurological Institute). Functional images underwent artifact and motion regression in the Artifact Detection Toolbox using the following criteria to define outliers: global signal intensity changes greater than 9 standard deviations and movement exceeding 2 mm. SPM motions parameters and outliers were subsequently included as covariates in connectivity analyses.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Connectivity analyses were performed on the concatenated resting-state scans (3 scans × 6 minutes = 18 minutes resting-state data) using the CONN toolbox version 17f.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> As the aim of this study was to compare the DMN connectivity during resting-state between HR and LR, we selected four main regions of interest (ROIs) corresponding to the core nodes of the DMN (see </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). These include the Posterior Cingulate Cortex (PCC; center of mass in MNI coordinates: 1, −61, 38), the Medial Prefrontal Cortex (MPFC; 1, 55, −3) and bilateral Lateral Parietal cortices (LP; left: −39, −77, 33, right: 47, −67, 29). These regions are implemented within the CONN Toolbox version 17f as part of a parcellation atlas of the main brain networks, obtained by applying an independent component analysis on 467 subjects from the Human Connectome Project.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Increased default mode network connectivity in high dream recallers (HR) compared to low dream recallers (LR). (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) Schematic illustration of the four main nodes of the default mode network (DMN) included in the functional connectivity analysis. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) Mean pairwise connectivity of the DMN for HR (red) and LR (black), obtained by averaging for each subject all the pairwise correlation values within the default network. The average DMN connectivity was significantly higher in HR than in LR. Error bars represent the 95% confidence intervals. *p &lt; 0.05. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>C</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) Left grey panel. Functional connectivity matrix representing the mean pairwise correlation coefficient between regions of the DMN in HR and LR. Right. Between-group statistical comparison (two-sided </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">-test corrected for multiple comparisons using the false discovery rate). The connectivity between the right lateral parietal and medial prefrontal cortex was significantly higher in HR than in LR.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-265-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The connectivity analysis included the following steps: first, we performed a denoising step including a regression of the six motion correction parameters and their corresponding first-order temporal derivatives, as well as a component-based strategy (aCompCor</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> to identify and remove physiological confounds that are unlikely to be related to neural activity). The resulting BOLD time series were band-pass filtered (0.008–0.09 Hz) to further reduce noise and increase sensitivity.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Then, Pearson’s correlation coefficients were calculated for each pairwise connection across the four nodes of the DMN, resulting in a single skew-symmetric connectivity matrix with six correlation coefficients for each subject. These values were normalized using a Fisher’s </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-to-</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">Z</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> transformation and then compared between HR and LR (two-sided </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">-tests corrected for multiple comparisons using the Benjamini–Hochberg method to decrease the false discovery rate (FDR, p&lt;0.05). Finally, the average within-DMN connectivity (average of all pairwise correlations within the DMN) was calculated and compared between groups.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Statistics</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">As several studies reported a higher creativity in HR than in LR, between-group comparisons of the fluency index and rare uses index were achieved using one-tailed </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">-test (p&lt;0.05). Similarly, as we expected HR to demonstrate a higher DMN functional connectivity than LR based on previous findings from our team, between-group comparison of the average DMN functional connectivity was achieved using a one-tailed </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">-test. All the other comparisons were achieved using two-sided </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-tests. All statistical analyses were performed in the Pingouin 0.5.0 package for Python.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Behavioral Tests</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Results of the cognitive and personality tests are reported in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. First, we did not find any significant differences in the memory abilities of HR and LR, as measured by the MEM-III scale, the digit span task and the recall of the comics presented in the scanner (number of words reported during free recall: HR, 230 ± 118, LR, 180 ± 98, p = 0.09; answer to the questions asking about the content of the story, on a scale from 0 to 10: HR, 5.7 ± 1.9, LR, 5.2 ± 2.5, p = 0.42). Second, there was no significant difference in the PSQI score. Third, there was no difference in the state and trait anxiety levels, as measured by the STAI self-report scale. Fourth, the Big Five personality dimensions were not significantly different between the two groups; however, there was a tendency (p=0.07) for a higher agreeableness score in HR than in LR, a dimension related to the tendency to be compassionate and cooperative rather than suspicious and antagonistic towards others.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Between-Group Differences in Cognitive and Personality Assessments</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">High Recallers (HR)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low Recallers (LR)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BFI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">- Openness to experience</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8 ± 0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7 ± 0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.61</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">- Conscientiousness</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3 ± 0.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6 ± 0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.17</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">- Extraversion</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4 ± 0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3 ± 0.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.59</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">- Agreeableness</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0 ± 0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7 ± 0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.07</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">- Neuroticism</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9 ± 0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 ± 0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.19</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">STAI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">- State anxiety</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.5 ± 8.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.9 ± 8.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.13</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">- Trait anxiety</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.7 ± 10.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.9 ± 9.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.31</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MEM-III</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">- Immediate recall</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.4 ± 4.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.9 ± 7.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.76</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">- Delayed recall</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.8 ± 5.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.7 ± 6.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.96</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PQSI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8 ± 2.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3 ± 1.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.44</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digit span</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6 ± 3.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.4 ± 3.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.37</italic></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Note</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: All p-values derived from two-sided independent </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-tests.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: BFI, Big Five Inventory; STAI, State-Trait Anxiety Inventory; PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Finally, we observed significant between-group differences in creativity scores. HR had a higher fluency index at the Guildford’s alternate uses task (HR = 8.2 ± 2.4 uses per object, LR = 7.2 ± 2.3, T(53) = 1.68, p = 0.049, Cohen’s d = 0.45; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). Furthermore, HR also reported a significantly greater number of rare uses, both when considering the 10% rarest uses (HR = 3.1 ± 1.6 rare uses per object, LR = 2.3 ± 1.5, T(53) = 1.77, p = 0.041, d = 0.48) and the 20% rarest uses (HR = 4.4 ± 1.9 rare uses per object, LR = 3.5 ± 1.8, T(53) = 1.88, p = 0.033, d = 0.51; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Creativity score in high dream recallers (HR) and low dream recallers (LR). (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) Box plot of the average number of uses per object found by HR (red) and LR (black) during the Guildford’s alternate uses task (also referred to as the fluency index). HR reported significantly more uses than LR. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) Box plot of the average number of uses reported by 10 or less participants per object (ie top 20%) found by HR (red) and LR (black). HR reported significantly more rare uses than LR. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>C</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) Significant correlation between the fluency index at the Guildford’s task and the openness to experience personality dimension measured using the BFI questionnaire. All plots share the same y-ticks, ranging from 0 to 16. *p&lt;0.05.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-265-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">As could be expected from previous results,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> creativity was also positively correlated with the “openness to experience” personality dimension of the BFI questionnaire (fluency index: </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.41, p = 0.002, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2C</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">; top 20% rarest uses: </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.42, p = 0.001; top 10% rarest uses: </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.33, p = 0.014; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=342137.zip" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). Noteworthy, these significant associations were mostly driven by the HR group. Indeed, the correlations between openness to experience and creativity measures were significant in the HR group (all ps &lt;0.017), but not in the LR group (all ps &gt;0.14; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=342137.zip" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Functional Connectivity</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The mean DMN functional connectivity in the scans of the 3 time points considered was higher in HR than in LR (HR = 0.64 ± 0.14, LR = 0.56 ± 0.16, T(52) = 1.81, p = 0.038; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). The DMN connectivity matrices for each group with pairwise connectivity color coded by strength are presented in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1C</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. Between-group comparisons of the connectivity matrices indicated a greater connectivity in HR between the MPFC and right LP (T(52) = 2.70, p-FDR = 0.028, p-unc = 0.009).</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We did a second analysis using only the resting state scan 1 and 3 to test that the group effect was not driven by the scan acquired at awakening during possible sleep inertia (resting state scan 2, see).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> We found that the between-group difference in average DMN connectivity was no longer significant (p=0.24), but the functional connectivity between the MPFC-LP was very close to significance (p-FDR=0.0537).</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We then tested whether increased DMN connectivity predicts higher creativity scores. There was no significant correlation between the average DMN connectivity and any of the creativity scores (fluency index, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = −0.002, p = 0.99; top 20% rarest uses: </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.036, p = 0.080, top 10% rarest uses: </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.11, p = 0.45). This was also true when looking separately at HR and LR (all p’s &gt; 0.325).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Consistent with our predictions, HR demonstrated an increased functional connectivity within the DMN – specifically between the MPFC and TPJ – and scored higher than LR on measures of creative-idea generation. Furthermore, no other between-group differences in cognitive abilities (including memory) were observed. However, contrary to our third prediction, there was no significant correlation between DMN connectivity and creativity scores.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">With regards to functional connectivity, our results are consistent with a previous PET study from our team that showed, in an unrelated sample of 41 participants, a higher cerebral blood flow in HR compared to LR in these two same regions during both sleep and wakefulness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Both these studies are also in line with clinical reports showing that lesions in the TPJ and MPFC lead to a cessation of dream recall.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> These converging results provide therefore strong evidence that the ability to recall dreams is linked to the activity within these two brain regions. In line with these results, several other studies of our team evidenced that HR and LR have a differential neurophysiological profile. We showed that HR have a larger amplitude of brain responses to auditory novel stimuli during both sleep and wakefulness, as well as an increased duration of intra-sleep wakefulness and nocturnal awakenings, regardless of sleep stage, and without any other differences in the micro- or macro-structure of sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> We also recently evidenced an increase of neurophysiological markers of bottom-up and top-down attentional processes in HR during wakefulness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our findings also confirm previous studies reporting an association between creativity and DRF.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16–18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The effect size that we observed in this sample (Cohen’s d ≈ 0.50, which translates to a correlation coefficient of </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">=0.24) is consistent with prior reports (ranging from </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=0.10 to </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=0.40). This association between creativity and dream recall is of particular interest given that the generation of creative ideas is thought to be supported by a preferential recruitment of regions of the DMN, and particularly of the MPFC.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24–28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> This large overlap of brain regions involved in dreaming and creativity was noticed by Christoff</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> who proposed that creative thought and dreaming are part of the same “family of spontaneous-thought processes”. In the same direction, Barrett</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> recalled a long-standing hypothesis that “dreaming is essentially our brain thinking in another neurophysiologic state – and therefore it is likely to solve some problems on which our waking minds have become stuck”. Several historical anecdotes and studies have indeed reported that dream content per se often contains solutions of unsolved problems and can be a source of insight.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49–52</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our results strengthen previous findings showing for the first time in the same study increased creativity and DMN connectivity in HR vs LR. Building on these results and previous ones, we argue here that high dream recallers have a specific cognitive and brain functioning profile, involving greater baseline activity and functional connectivity in regions of the DMN, which might in turn promote creativity and dreaming abilities in these individuals.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Along with the consistent positive association between DRF and creativity, studies have often reported a substantial correlation between creativity and openness to experience</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and between DRF and several personality traits, including openness to experience,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> thin boundaries (ie, propensity to being more open, trustworthy, vulnerable, and sensitive;</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and anxiety).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> While we could replicate the correlation between creativity and openness to experience in our sample, we did not observe a statistically significant difference in personality traits between HR and LR. It may be explained by the fact that the association between DRF and personality traits is not ubiquitous in the literature (eg,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">), and, when present, is often very weak (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">≈0.1–0.2).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Therefore, our study may have been underpowered to detect such subtle personality differences between HR and LR.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The general idea that differential DRF is linked to traits factors was first introduced by Schonbar</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> in her so-called lifestyle hypothesis. While she did not explain the underlying mechanisms, she postulated that high dream recall is part of a general lifestyle characterized by “creativity, rich fantasy, introversion, introspection, field independence and divergent thinking”.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Our findings of a higher creativity and DMN connectivity in HR compared to LR argue in favor of this model. However, and contrary to our initial hypothesis, we did not find a significant correlation between creativity and DMN connectivity. Such a null finding does not prove the definite lack of an association between DMN and creativity. Our study may have been underpowered to evidence such an effect, especially if the latter is only present in HR, as observed for the correlation between openness to experience and creativity measures. Further research is therefore needed to confirm or refute the theory that increased basal DMN connectivity in HR may promote creativity (for example, with a larger sample size and/or with other measures of creativity). Moreover, future works could test whether DRF-enhancing methods (such as keeping a dream diary;</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) would result in increased creativity scores and DMN functional connectivity in a pre/post design within the same individuals, preferentially low dream recallers. If confirmed, DRF-enhancement methods could potentially become a creativity-enhancement method.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Limitations</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">First, an important limitation of this study is that the participants were partially sleep-deprived during all the resting-state fMRI scans, and possibly in a severe state of sleep inertia during the second resting-state scan. A previously published analysis of the same dataset has shown that HR have increased DMN functional connectivity compared to LR during the second resting-state scan.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> We therefore ran a second analysis excluding the second resting state scan, which revealed that the group difference in average DMN functional connectivity was not significant anymore – although the pairwise connectivity between the MPFC and LP was close to significance. This indicates that the main effect of a higher DMN connectivity in HR is only present when including the second resting-state scan, which likely contains a high carry-over effect from prior sleep. This would suggest that the main effect of higher DMN activity in HR is more pronounced during sleep and/or the awakening process rather than during fully installed wakefulness. However, a previous study from our team on an unrelated sample has found a higher PET activation in the DMN in HR compared to LR during both sleep and resting wakefulness,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> which supports the idea of a higher basal DMN activity in HR regardless of the vigilance state. Still, it remains to be tested whether the observed between-group differences in fMRI DMN connectivity replicate when participants are not sleep deprived during the resting-state scans. According to the available data, it may be hypothesized that DMN connectivity is increased in HR, and that this effect is maximum during sleep and/or when sleep intrudes into wakefulness.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Second, creativity was assessed using the well-validated task of divergent thinking (the Alternate Use Task [AUT],</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). Prior works on DRF and creativity have used different tasks or questionnaires,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> and one strength of this study was thus to replicate previous results with a new/different measure of creativity. However, using several tasks to assess creativity (eg, Remote Associates Test to measure convergent thinking, or questionnaires) may have led to a fuller picture of the association between DMN connectivity and creativity. Indeed, creativity is certainly a complex and multifaceted ability that involves several cognitive processes and traits (eg, memory, associative reasoning, flexibility, etc) combined in various proportions across individuals. The simple task that was used in this study may thus not have captured the proper/pertinent variable related to DMN connectivity.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors would like to thank Morgane Hamon, Franck Lamberton and Danielle Ibarrola for substantial help in data collection and analysis, as well as Jamila Lagha for her help in administrative work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">REM, rapid eye movement; HR, high dream recallers; LR, low dream recallers; DRF, dream recall frequency; DMN, default mode network; MPFC, medial prefrontal cortex; TPJ, temporo-parietal junction; LP, lateral parietal; PCC, posterior cingulate cortex.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Data and Python scripts are available from the corresponding author upon request.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0008">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">All authors made substantial contributions to conception and design, acquisition of data, or analysis and interpretation of data; took part in drafting the article or revising it critically for important intellectual content; agreed to submit to the current journal; gave final approval of the version to be published; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0009">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Solms</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dreaming and REM sleep are controlled by different brain mechanisms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Brain Sci</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<page-range>843–850;discussion 904–1121</page-range>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0140525X00003988</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schwartz</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dang-Vu</surname>
<given-names>TT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ponz</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duhoux</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maquet</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dreaming: a neuropsychological view</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Schweizer Archiv Neurologie Psychiatrie</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>156</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>426</fpage>–<lpage>439</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ruby</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Experimental research on dreaming: state of the art and neuropsychoanalytic perspectives</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>286</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2011.00286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22121353</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ruby</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The neural correlates of dreaming have not been identified yet. Commentary on “The neural correlates of dreaming. Nat Neurosci. 2017.”</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Front Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1109</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnins.2020.585470</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Schredl</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Researching Dreams: The Fundamentals</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name>; <year>2018</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Vallat</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Content and Frequency of Dream Reports: Psychological and Neurophysiological Correlates</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Université de Lyon</publisher-name>; <year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Eichenlaub</surname>
<given-names>J-B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nicolas</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Daltrozzo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Redouté</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Costes</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruby</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Resting brain activity varies with dream recall frequency between subjects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropsychopharmacology</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1594</fpage>–<lpage>1602</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/npp.2014.6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24549103</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Eichenlaub</surname>
<given-names>J-B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bertrand</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morlet</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruby</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Brain reactivity differentiates subjects with high and low dream recall frequencies during both sleep and wakefulness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cereb Cortex</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1206</fpage>–<lpage>1215</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/bhs388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23283685</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vallat</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lajnef</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eichenlaub</surname>
<given-names>J-B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Increased evoked potentials to arousing auditory stimuli during sleep: implication for the understanding of dream recall</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Hum Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>132</issue>):<fpage>132</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnhum.2017.00132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28377708</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vallat</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nicolas</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruby</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Brain functional connectivity upon awakening from sleep predicts interindividual differences in dream recall frequency</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>12</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsaa116</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Solms</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">The Neuropsychology of Dreams: A Clinico-Anatomical Study</italic></source>. <publisher-name>L. Erlbaum Associates</publisher-name>; <year>1997</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gusnard</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raichle</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raichle</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Searching for a baseline: functional imaging and the resting human brain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>685</fpage>–<lpage>694</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35094500</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11584306</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Raichle</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>MacLeod</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Snyder</surname>
<given-names>AZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Powers</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gusnard</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shulman</surname>
<given-names>GL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A default mode of brain function</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>98</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>676</fpage>–<lpage>682</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.98.2.676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11209064</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Legrand</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruby</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>What is self-specific? Theoretical investigation and critical review of neuroimaging results</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Rev</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>116</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>252</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0014172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19159156</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schonbar</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Differential dream recall frequency as a component of“ life style”</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Consult Psychol</italic></source>. <year>1965</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>468</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/h0022464</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5318262</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fitch</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Armitage</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Variations in cognitive style among high and low frequency dream recallers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pers Individ Dif</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>869</fpage>–<lpage>875</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0191-8869(89)90022-6</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schredl</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Creativity and dream recall</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Creat Behav</italic></source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>16</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/j.2162-6057.1995.tb01420.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schredl</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wittmann</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ciric</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Götz</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Factors of home dream recall: a structural equation model</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>141</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2869.2003.00344.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12753350</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hartmann</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Boundaries of dreams, boundaries of dreamers: thin and thick boundaries as a new personality measure</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatr J Univ Ott</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>557</fpage>–<lpage>560</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2813637</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schredl</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kleinferchner</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gell</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dreaming and personality: thick vs. thin boundaries</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Dreaming</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>223</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/h0094456</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schredl</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ciric</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Götz</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wittmann</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dream recall frequency, attitude towards dreams and openness to experience</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Dreaming</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>153</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1025369311813</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Christoff</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Irving</surname>
<given-names>ZC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fox</surname>
<given-names>KCR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spreng</surname>
<given-names>RN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Andrews-Hanna</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mind-wandering as spontaneous thought: a dynamic framework</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>718</fpage>–<lpage>731</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn.2016.113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27654862</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>William domhoff</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The neural substrate for dreaming: is it a subsystem of the default network?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Conscious Cogn</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1163</fpage>–<lpage>1174</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.concog.2011.03.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21450492</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ellamil</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dobson</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beeman</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Christoff</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Evaluative and generative modes of thought during the creative process</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroimage</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>1783</fpage>–<lpage>1794</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.08.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21854855</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jung</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mead</surname>
<given-names>BS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carrasco</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Flores</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The structure of creative cognition in the human brain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Hum Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>330</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnhum.2013.00330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23847503</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Beaty</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benedek</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilkins</surname>
<given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Creativity and the default network: a functional connectivity analysis of the creative brain at rest</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropsychologia</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>92</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2014.09.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25245940</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mok</surname>
<given-names>LW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The interplay between spontaneous and controlled processing in creative cognition</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Hum Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>663</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnhum.2014.00663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25221497</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Beaty</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benedek</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaufman</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Silvia</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Default and executive network coupling supports creative idea production</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>10964</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep10964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26084037</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Picchioni</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duyn</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Horovitz</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and the functional connectome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroimage</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>80</volume>:<fpage>387</fpage>–<lpage>396</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2013.05.067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23707592</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Domhoff</surname>
<given-names>GW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fox</surname>
<given-names>KCR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dreaming and the default network: a review, synthesis, and counterintuitive research proposal</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Conscious Cogn</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>342</fpage>–<lpage>353</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.concog.2015.01.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25723600</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Qiu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Increased resting functional connectivity of the medial prefrontal cortex in creativity by means of cognitive stimulation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cortex</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>92</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cortex.2013.09.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24188648</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Takeuchi</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taki</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hashizume</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The association between resting functional connectivity and creativity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cereb Cortex</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2921</fpage>–<lpage>2929</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/bhr371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22235031</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vallat</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meunier</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nicolas</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruby</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Hard to wake up? The cerebral correlates of sleep inertia assessed using combined behavioral, EEG and fMRI measures</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroimage</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>184</volume>:<fpage>266</fpage>–<lpage>278</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2018.09.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30223060</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vallat</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eskinazi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nicolas</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruby</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and dream habits in a sample of French college students who report no sleep disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e12659</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29405504</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>John</surname>
<given-names>OP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Srivastava</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Big Five trait taxonomy: history, measurement, and theoretical perspectives</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Handbook Personal</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>1999</issue>):<fpage>102</fpage>–<lpage>138</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Plaisant</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Courtois</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Réveillère</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mendelsohn</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>John</surname>
<given-names>OP</given-names></string-name>. <part-title>Factor structure and internal reliability of the French Big Five Inventory (BFI-Fr). Convergent and discriminant validation with the NEO-PI-R</part-title>. In: <source><italic toggle="yes">Annales Médico-Psychologiques, Revue Psychiatrique</italic></source>. Vol. <volume>168</volume>. <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>; <year>2010</year>:<fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Spielberger</surname>
<given-names>CD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gorsuch</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lushene</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Manual for the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Palo Alto, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Consulting Psychologists Press</publisher-name>; <year>1970</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>CF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monk</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berman</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kupfer</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0165-1781(89)90047-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2748771</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Wechsler</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. Wechsler Memory Scale (WMS-third edition, WMS-III). <source><italic toggle="yes">MEM-III: Échelle Clinique de Mémoire de Wechsler</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Éditions du Centre de psychologie appliquée</publisher-name>; <year>2001</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Guildford</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Christensen</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Merrifield</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilson</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Alternate Uses: Manual of Instructions and Interpretation</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Orange, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sheridan Psychological Services</publisher-name>; <year>1978</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Whitfield-Gabrieli</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nieto-Castanon</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Conn: a functional connectivity toolbox for correlated and anticorrelated brain networks</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Connect</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>141</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/brain.2012.0073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22642651</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Behzadi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Restom</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liau</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>TT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A component based noise correction method (CompCor) for BOLD and perfusion based fMRI</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroimage</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2007.04.042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17560126</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Weissenbacher</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kasess</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gerstl</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lanzenberger</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moser</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Windischberger</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Correlations and anticorrelations in resting-state functional connectivity MRI: a quantitative comparison of preprocessing strategies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroimage</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1408</fpage>–<lpage>1416</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2009.05.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19442749</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vallat</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pingouin: statistics in Python</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JOSS</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>31</issue>):<fpage>1026</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01026</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vartanian</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wertz</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Flores</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Structural correlates of openness and intellect: implications for the contribution of personality to creativity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hum Brain Mapp</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>2987</fpage>–<lpage>2996</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.24054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29656437</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ruby</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Masson</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chatard</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>High dream recall frequency is associated with an increase of both bottom-up and top-down attentional processes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cereb Cortex</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/bhab445</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dietrich</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kanso</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A review of EEG, ERP, and neuroimaging studies of creativity and insight</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Bull</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>136</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>822</fpage>–<lpage>848</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0019749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20804237</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Barrett</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dreams and creative problem-solving</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann NY Acad Sci</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>1406</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>64</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nyas.13412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28640937</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Dement</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Some Must Watch While Some Must Sleep</italic></source>. Vol. <volume>37</volume>. <publisher-name>San Francisco Book Co.</publisher-name>; <year>1976</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Barrett</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The “committee of sleep”: a study of dream incubation for problem solving</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Dreaming</italic></source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>122</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/h0094375</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Maquet</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruby</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Psychology: insight and the sleep committee</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nature</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>427</volume>(<issue>6972</issue>):<fpage>304</fpage>–<lpage>305</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/427304a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14737153</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Edwards</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruby</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malinowski</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bennett</surname>
<given-names>PD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blagrove</surname>
<given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dreaming and insight</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>979</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2013.00979</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24550849</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schonbar</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Some manifest characteristics of recallers and nonrecallers of dreams</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Consult Psychol</italic></source>. <year>1959</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>414</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/h0047400</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tart</surname>
<given-names>CT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Frequency of dream recall and some personality measures</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Consult Psychol</italic></source>. <year>1962</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>467</fpage>–<lpage>470</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/h0046056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13993376</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0055">
        <label>55.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schredl</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dream recall frequency and openness to experience: a negative finding</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pers Individ Dif</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1285</fpage>–<lpage>1289</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0191-8869(02)00013-2</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0056">
        <label>56.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schredl</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dream recall: research, clinical implications and future directions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Hypn</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>72</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0057">
        <label>57.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schredl</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Questionnaires and diaries as research instruments in dream research: methodological issues</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Dreaming</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1013890421674</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
