<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35444482</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">9015051</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">239622</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S239622</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Review</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Examining the Relationship Between Sleep Quality, Social Functioning, and Behavior Problems in Children with Autism Spectrum Disorder: A Systematic Review</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Whelan et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Whelan et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9794-6246</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Whelan</surname>
            <given-names>Sally</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mannion</surname>
            <given-names>Arlene</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Madden</surname>
            <given-names>Azeem</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8929-3812</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Berger</surname>
            <given-names>Fine</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Costello</surname>
            <given-names>Rachel</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1858-4038</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Ghadiri</surname>
            <given-names>Saeid</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Leader</surname>
            <given-names>Geraldine</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Irish Center for Autism and Neurodevelopmental Research (ICAN), School of Psychology, National University of Ireland</institution>, <addr-line>Galway</addr-line>, <country>Ireland</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Sally Whelan, <institution>Irish Center for Autism and Neurodevelopmental Research (ICAN), School of Psychology, National University of Ireland</institution>, <addr-line>Galway</addr-line>, <country>Ireland</country>, <phone>Tel +35 391493434</phone>, Email geraldine.leader@nuigalway.ie</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>14</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <fpage>675</fpage>
      <lpage>695</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>06</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2022 Whelan et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Whelan et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Over forty percent of autistic children experience poor sleep quality, and social interaction difficulties are a core characteristic of autism. However, the relationship between sleep quality and social functioning and behavior remains poorly understood. This systematic review examined the evidence concerning the impact of sleep quality on the social functioning and behavior problems in autistic children and adolescents. It also identified key related factors and evaluated how this issue has been researched to date. Seven key journals were hand-searched and five databases were systematically searched, using keywords. Titles and abstracts of 4123 items were screened against eligibility criteria by two researchers. Relevant studies were retained if they were peer-reviewed empirical papers, published in English between 2000 and 2021. Then, the full text of 97 papers was screened and if they met the eligibility criteria, their reference lists were hand-searched. Forty-six studies were included in the final review. Data were systematically extracted and two authors critically appraised the strengths and weaknesses of studies using Critical Appraisal Skills Programme tools. Key themes were identified, because a meta-analysis was not possible due to the studies’ heterogeneity. The review identified that sleep quality and social functioning are associated with one another and there is a small amount of evidence that a bi-directional causal relationship may exist. Evidence suggests that several nights of suboptimal sleep duration and a lack of deep continuous sleep negatively impact externalizing and internalizing behavior. Sleep quality is also reduced by anxiety and sensory sensitivity. However, longitudinal studies with larger samples are needed to establish causality. Future research needs to examine confounding factors and to develop consensus regarding best-practice processes for the objective measurement of sleep with autistic children. Additional research also needs to further examine the consequences of poor sleep quality on internalizing behavior, and the impact of socio-cultural practices.</citation_analysis></p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>autism spectrum disorder</kwd>
        <kwd>night waking</kwd>
        <kwd>insomnia</kwd>
        <kwd>behavior</kwd>
        <kwd>anxiety</kwd>
        <kwd>bedtime resistance</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>did not receive any grant from any funding agency</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>This research did not receive any grant from any funding agency.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="1"/>
        <table-count count="5"/>
        <ref-count count="86"/>
        <page-count count="21"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Autism is a neurodevelopmental disorder with a prevalence rate of 1 in every 68 children.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Autism is characterized by the core features of repetitive behaviors, restricted interests, affective and social interaction difficulties.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Social functioning has been defined as “the ability to navigate through the social world and form and maintain relationships that involve one’s home, school, or workplace” (p2).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> It can be challenging for autistic children to satisfy roles within an environment, relationships with family and friends, and social activities.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Autistic children differ in several ways from neuro-typical (NT) children regarding their social functioning.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> They may be less likely to look towards social stimuli</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> or to initiate and share attention jointly with other people,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and individuals may exhibit less ability to recognize emotions, interpret vocal and visual cues,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and imitate behavior based on social cues.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Furthermore, autistic children use different strategies to process facial information, emphasizing features and the mouth rather than focusing on the eyes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Social functioning is also impacted by motivation, perception, anxiety, social skills, and emotional challenges.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep problems include dyssomnias that disturb the quality, amount, timing of sleep, including difficulty falling or staying asleep, excessive daytime sleepiness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> They also include parasomnias that involve physiologic events or behaviors that interrupt sleep, including arousal and partial arousal disorders or during the transition between sleep stages.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Sleep problems in children have been operationalized in research in terms of bedtime resistance, sleep onset delay, sleep duration, sleep anxiety, night-time waking, parasomnias, sleep-disordered breathing, and daytime sleepiness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Between 25% and 40% of NT children experience sleep disturbances and these have been associated with decreased social functioning in middle childhood and preadolescents</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and in children aged 18–42 months.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> A systematic review of studies that involved children aged 5–12 years found that shorter sleep duration was associated with internalizing and externalizing behavioral problems and having less complex cognitive skills and executive functioning ability.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Positive relationships between sleep quality/quantity, and better cognitive and/or behavioral outcomes have also been found for children aged 2–5 years.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Sleep disturbances occur in 40–83% of autistic children.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20–23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> A recent meta-analysis examined studies that had measured sleep objectively using polysomnography (PSG) or actigraphy. This study found small but significant differences between autistic children and NT children regarding their sleep parameters. These differences included shorter total sleep time (TST), longer sleep onset latency (SOL), and reduced sleep efficiency (SE). However, there was no significant difference between the total sleep time (TST) in autistic children without intellectual disability (ID) and their NT peers.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Díaz-Roman et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> also conducted a meta-analysis of studies that included both subjective and objective sleep measures. They found that when sleep was subjectively measured, autistic children had significantly higher sleep anxiety, sleep onset delay, sleep onset latency, bedtime resistance, night awakenings, sleep-disordered breathing, parasomnias, and daytime sleepiness. The results determined using objective measures revealed autistic children had lower TST, a lower percentage of rapid eye movement (REM) sleep, longer SOL, lower SE, than the NT group.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In autistic children, poor sleep quality is negatively associated with physical and psychosocial wellbeing and quality of life,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and it is associated with behavior problems</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and higher levels of hyperactivity, social withdrawal, and irritability.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Higher rates of externalizing and internalizing behavior are also associated with lower levels of social functioning in autistic children and adolescents</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and NT children.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, the impact of sleep quality on social functioning and behaviour problems, and the factors that moderate these relationships remain poorly understood. Further examination of this topic is warranted because sleep quality is a potentially modifiable predictor of social functioning and problematic behavior. Detailed knowledge about these relationships could inform caregivers, therapists, and clinicians who seek to improve the well-being of autistic children.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This systematic review aimed to increase understanding of the relationships between sleep quality and the social functioning and behavior problems of autistic children and adolescents. Its objectives were to examine the current evidence and identify the factors that underlie and mediate this relationship, and evaluate how this relationship has been examined to date.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Search Strategy</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The key search terms listed in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> were identified using the patient, intervention, comparison, outcome search strategy tool.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Keywords and MeSH terms were used and adapted according to the requirements of the following databases and as they were searched: Medline, PubMed, Scopus, Psych Info, and the Web of Science. In addition, the following journals were
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Key Word Search Terms</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Population</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Outcomes/Phenomenon of Interest</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autism</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AND Children</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AND Sleep Quality</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AND Social Functioning and Behavior</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">“autism” OR autistic’ OR pervasive develop*’ OR ASD OR<break/>“Asperger*” OR “autism spectrum disorder”</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adolescent* OR you* OR bab* OR infant* OR juvenile* OR kid* OR teen* OR toddler* OR child*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nap* OR rest* OR sleep* OR “sleep duration” OR “night waking” OR “restless sleep” OR “poor sleep” OR “sleep disturbance” OR bedtime Or “wake time” OR “Sleep problem*”OR “sleep anxiety” OR “sleep latency” Or insomnia OR “sleep quality” OR “sleep efficiency”</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">“daytime disfunction” OR behavio* OR active* Or perform* OR action* OR “challenging behavio*” OR “social functioning” OR “communicat*” OR “gesture*” OR verbal* OR nonverbal OR non verbal</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Note</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: *Search includes all the words beginning with the preceding letters.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">hand-searched for articles that met the eligibility criteria which is summarized in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: Sleep, Sleep Medicine, Behavioral Sleep Medicine, Nature and Science of Sleep Journal; Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders, Autism, Autism and Research. Initial searches were limited to papers published between the years 2000–2021, and older articles were identified through hand searching the reference lists of articles that met the inclusion criteria. Papers were included if they were peer-reviewed empirical studies, published in English. They also needed to involve children diagnosed with any type of autism and to focus on sleep quality and social functioning. These searches identified 5270 items that were imported into an Endnote database. After duplicates were removed there were 4119 items.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Eligibility Criteria</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inclusion</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exclusion</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peer-reviewed empirical studies published in English.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Papers that are unpublished, theoretical, review articles, case report articles.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Participants diagnosed with any type of autism, with or without ID and ADHD. The diagnosis can be parent reported.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Participants must be children aged 0–17 years as part or all the population studied.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Studies involving adults aged 18 years and over.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Studies must focus on sleep quality – duration, night waking, falling asleep, or staying asleep.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Studies that do not focus on sleep quality.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Studies using any design and methodology.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Studies must focus on social functioning or social functioning was included as an outcome.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Studies that do not focusing on social functioning and/or behavior problems.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Study Selection</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Firstly, two researchers worked independently (FB, RC), screening the title and abstract of each item against the eligibility criteria. This resulted in the retention of 97 papers, with 87% inter-rater reliability between researchers. Then, researchers (AM, SW) reviewed the papers on which FB and RC disagreed, and decided upon their eligibility. Following this, FB and RC independently screened the full-text of 97 papers, which resulted in an inter-rater reliability of 88%. SW and AM reviewed and discussed any papers on which there was disagreement and determined their eligibility. Finally, the reference lists of relevant papers were hand-searched for additional papers. The PRISMA flow diagram below (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) summarizes the results of the paper selection processes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">PRISMA Flow Diagram.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-675-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: Adapted from: Liberati A, Altman D, Tetzlaff J et al. The PRISMA statement for reporting systematic reviews and meta-analyses of studies that evaluate health care interventions: explanation and elaboration. <italic toggle="yes">Journal of Clinical Epidemiology</italic>. 2009;62(10)e1-e34. Creative Commons<xref rid="cit0086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Data Extraction and Quality Assessment</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Two researchers (AM, SW) collaborated to extract details from the included studies, using a bespoke template table designed according to the review aims. Due to the heterogeneity of the studies, it was not possible to conduct a meta-analysis. Instead, the study contents were repeatedly examined and themes were identified.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The quality of the studies included in the review was assessed by researchers (RC, SG), who worked independently using the Critical Appraisal Skills Programme (CASP-uk.net) checklists, as recommended by World Health Organisation guidelines.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The CASP checklists are designed to assess the quality of research against criteria relevant to the design of the study under assessment. The CASP checklist for randomized controlled trials (RCTs) and the checklist for quantitative cohort studies include 12 points and the checklist for studies using qualitative methodology includes 10 points.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> summarizes the content of the 46 studies that were included in the review and their key findings in relation to how sleep quality relates to social functioning and behavior in autistic children. The critical appraisal of the studies revealed that the methodological quality of these peer-reviewed studies ranged between moderate and high ratings on the CASP checklists. Due to the design of the studies, this review applied the RCT, Quantitative Cohort, and Qualitative checklists. The one qualitative study included in the review was rated 9 on the CASP Qualitative checklist; the four RCT studies were rated as between 10 and 12 using the CASP RCT checklist; the remaining 41 studies were rated as between 7 and 12 on the CASP Quantitative Cohort studies checklist. The inter-rater reliability between researchers’ ratings during the quality appraisal was initially high at 86% and after discussions between researchers that also involved SW, 100% agreement was achieved.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0003" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Study Details (Abbreviations Key Below)</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study ID</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aims</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Participant Details</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD Diagnosis</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Design and Methods</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Measures</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Key Results for ASD Participants</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CASP</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aathira et al (2017)<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> India</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimated prevalence and type of sleep problems associated with ASD severity, IQ, behavioral problems.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=71), M (80.28%), aged 3–10, <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 5.3 SD = 1.8.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM IV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-Sectional<break/>2-yr study in teaching hospital.<break/>Parents were shown PSG prior to testing on for 1 night.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DP3, CBCL, CARS, CSHQ, cut-off 41, differentiated good sleepers and poor sleepers, PSG undertaken by N=48 (67.61%).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor sleepers had significantly more behavioral problems than good sleepers (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.004).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abel et al (2018)<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> USA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examined the associations bet. sleep and challenging behaviors for average and night-to-night fluctuations.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=39), M (84.62%), aged 2–10, M = 5.43, SD = 2.26.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCQ</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-Sectional Behavioral treatment center. Parents instructed how to use the actigraph.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daytime challenging behavior by the child’s clinicians, Sleep diaries, actigraph.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative affect was associated with WASO (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001) but not TST. Night waking associated with one additional negative affect per hour of waking (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Allik et al (2006)<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Sweden</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compared ASD &amp; NT on sleep/wake behavior symptoms and problems.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=32), M (87.5%), aged 8.5–12.8 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 10.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Independent clinician and ICD-10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-Sectional Parents reported sleep patterns mail or clinic visits, teachers responded, via mail.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASSQ, SDQ, Actigraph, Sleep diaries.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Children with insomnia showed higher hyperactivity (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>= 0.04) and emotional symptoms rated by parents (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.009) and teachers (p= 0.03), and lower pro-social behavior (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.04).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anders et al (2012)<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> USA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examined relationships bet. sleep and daytime behaviors in comparison populations.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=68), M (81%), aged 2–5.5 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 47 Months SD = 10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADOS &amp; ADI-R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longitudinal. Weeklong recordings completed enrolment, 3 and 6 months. After each recording week, parents reported sleep patterns.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Child Behavior Checklist CBCL, Actigraph, Sleep diaries, CSHQ.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Actigraph determined sleep problems not associated with behavior problems or daytime sleepiness. Parental reported of bedtime resistance associated with more daytime sleepiness (<italic toggle="yes">ps</italic> &lt; 0.01) and behavior problems (<italic toggle="yes">ps</italic> &lt; 0.01).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chong et al (2021)<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> USA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Documented daytime electro-dermal activity (EDA) to explore their relations with sleep dysregulation/deficiency</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=13), M (80%), aged 3–9, <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 6.11 SD = 2.04 regulated sleep group (RegS) (n=6), dysregulated sleep group (DysS) (n=7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCQ, with a (&gt;11) cut-off point</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional<break/>Children recruited from 5 ABA treatment centers (N=5).<break/>Each child had received 20 hours per week ABA therapy.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VABS-II, Actigraphy, Sleep diaries.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DysS group had higher Social communication scores (<italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 17.6, SD = 4.28) than RegS (<italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 22.5, SD = 6.35) and were older (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01). No definitive conclusions due to small sample.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohen et al (2017)<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> USA, Australia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examined if sleep can predict adaptive functioning and ASD symptoms.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=106), M (82.08%), aged 5–17 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 14.77 SD = 3.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM IV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longitudinal<break/>2 residential schools, caregivers instructed how to record the children’s sleep quality.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VABS-II, Structured observations of sleep at 15–30 minute intervals.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">“Unstable” sleepers showed greater significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01) greater impairment in IQ scores and adaptive functioning. Socialization, communication compared to “Stable” sleepers.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohen et al (2018)<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> USA, Australia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Measured a predictive relationship bet. night-to-night sleep and day-to-day behavioral fluctuations.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=67), Caucasian (88%), Hispanic (4.5%), Asian (4.5%), Native American (4.5%).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM IV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longitudinal<break/>Participants from 2 residential schools. Sleep observed at 15–30 minute intervals. Clinician observed and recorded behavior during 1-on-1 daytime care.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VABS-II.<break/>Structured observations of sleep and behavior.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The accuracy of predicting behavior from prior sleep increased with the number of nights used to make the prediction. A significant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) predictive relationship bet. priorsleep and daytime behavior in 81% of participants. Real-time fluctuations in sleep are important.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delahaye et al (2014)<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> USA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Investigate the relationship bet. HRQoL &amp; sleep problems within the context of ASD characteristics.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=86), M (83.72%), aged 4–12 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 7.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM IV &amp; ADOS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-Sectional.<break/>Parents were recruited from an autism specialty clinic located at one of 3 centers. Parents notified firstly by phone.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBCL &amp; HRQoL, CSHQ, sleep-disordered breathing, daytime sleepiness</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shorter sleep duration (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = −0.36, p &lt; 0.001), greater sleep anxiety (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = −0.29, p = 0.01) and parasomnias (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = −0.29, p &lt; 0.01), had a consistent negative relationship with psychosocial aspects of HRQoL.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fadini et al (2015)<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> Portugal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Investigated patterns of sleep and behavioral profiles in ASD children and adolescents.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=45), M (78%), aged 4–18 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 9.7 SD = 4.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM V, ATA &amp; CARS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional<break/>Questionnaires completed by parents and caregivers. And genetic tests completed.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBCL, SDSC.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive correlation bet. thought problems and arousal disorders (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.42, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05), excessive somnolence (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.45, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) and bet. Excessive somnolence and behavioral problems (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.41, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fletcher et al (2017)<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> Australia, UK</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examined the association bet. individual changes in sleep profiles, anxiety, bedtime routines over 1-yr.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=21) M (81%), aged 6–13 Baseline <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 106.67 SD = 26.83 months Follow-up <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 120.52 SD = 29.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM IV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longitudinal<break/>Actigraphs posted and documents emailed. Parents provided instruction. Movie vouchers given to child participants.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SWQ-P, CSHQ, Actigraph &amp; Sleep diaries.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Those with increased frequency of maladaptive behaviors over time had increased SOL (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.30, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.037; Fisher’s <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> to z transformation, <italic toggle="yes">Z</italic> = 0.48, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.63). Improved sleep problems over 1 yr characterized by reduced sleep anxiety (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>= 0.58, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001; Fisher’s r to z transformation, Z = 0.17, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.34).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gunes et al (2019)<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> Turkey</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Investigated the relationship bet. sleep difficulties and clinical symptoms of ASD.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=112) M (72.3%), aged 2–18 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 8.06 SD = 3.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM V, CARS &amp; dev. histories</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional.<break/>Assessments by a child dev. specialist and experienced psychologist. Sleep and social functioning parent-reported. If Denver II Test &amp; WISC-R not possible used dev. histories, clinical symptoms observations, and average academic functioning.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AuBc, ABC-C &amp; CARS, CSHQ.<break/>Denver II Test on children under 6 yrs. WISC-R full-scale on children over 6 yrs.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CARS total score correlated with Bedtimeresistance (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.19, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.048) and night wakings (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.20, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.045). No significant correlation bet. CSHQ scores and AuBC &amp; AbBC total scores. Inattentiveness was significantly higher in children with CSHQ &gt;56 (<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>(110) = −1.98,= <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.045).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Goldman et al (2009)<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> USA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Determined if sleep concerns and objective measures are associated with daytime behavior.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=42) M (90%), aged 4–10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADOS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-Sectional Recruited from Vanderbilt University Medical Center subspecialty clinics and the community</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCQ, CBCL, RBS–R, CSHQ, 2 consecutive nights of PSG &amp; actigraphy monitoring video and EEG.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor sleepers had significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) more inattention and hyperactivity than good sleepers. WASO correlated with hyperactivity (r = 0.48, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.04) and sleep fragmentation correlated with RRB (r = 0.69, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Goldman et al (2011)<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> USA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Identified variation in sleep-behavior across childhood-adolescence.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=1784) M (84%), aged 3–18 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 6.7 SD = 3.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADOS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-Sectional.<break/>Divided into good sleeper and poor sleeper and age cohorts &lt;5 yrs, 5 to &lt;7 yrs, 7 to &lt;11 yrs, &gt;11 yrs.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCQ, CSHQ.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50% poor sleepers had problems with attention, social interaction, language, hyperactivity, sensory issues, anxiety, eating and self-stimulatory behaviors. 75% poor sleepers had problems with attention span, social interactions. 1-unit increase on the parasomnia scale associated with 20% increase in the odds (95% CI) of problem regarding anxiety, sensory issues, aggression, hyperactivity, attention, mood swings, and SIB.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Henderson et al (2011)<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> USA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examined the complexity of relations among routines general and bedtime, sleep quality and externalizing behaviors in ASD.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=58) M (86.2%), aged 6–12 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 9.0 SD = 2.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CSBQ</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross- Sectional.<break/>$5 donated to an autism research foundation for participation.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBCL, BRQ, CSHS, CSWS.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Consistency of bedtime routines was significantly positively correlated with sleep quality (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.45, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt;0.001) and sleep quality was significantly negatively correlated with externalizing behavior (r = −0.39, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hoshino et al (1984)<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> Japan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To clarify the pathophysiological meaning of sleep disturbance.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=75) M (86.6%), aged 3–15 years <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>=6 years 7 months.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychiatrist used WHO &amp; Kanner criteria.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychiatrist Examination.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day following sleep disturbance children took long naps (n = 26), loosing temper or low mood (n = 23), hyperactive (n = 9), Inactivity (n = 6), Isolationism (n = 3).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Johnson et al (2018)<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> USA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Assessed whether children with PS have greater daytime behavioral problems its impact on parental stress.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=177) M (87.6%), aged 3–7 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 4.7 SD = 1.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM IV, ADOS, ADI-R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCT −24-week<break/>Parents randomized to Parent Training or Parent Education Program.<break/>Questionnaires completed at study enrolment.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC, CSHQ. PSI.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor sleepers had significantly higher irritability (t(2.85), <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.005), hyperactivity/noncompliance (t(3.11), <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.002) than good sleepers.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kang et al (2020)<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examined the relationship bet. sleep disturbances and emotional/ behavioral problems, and repetitive behavior</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=252), M (80.6%), aged 3–6 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 5.13 SD = 0.097</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM V &amp; CARS.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-Sectional Excluded if diagnosis of chronic illness, or mental disorder, or medications that could interfere with sleep.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SDQ, CSHQ, PPVT-C (completed by N=114 children, parents completed RBQ-2).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Highly significant correlations (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001) bet. SDQ, CSHQ scores and sleep onset delay. Later had most ability to explain the variance (17.3%) in total SDQ score (adjusted R2 = 0.173). Moderate significant correlation (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01) bet. sleep anxiety and SDQ.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kelmanson et al (2020)<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> Russia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evaluated sleep disturbances and their associations with emotional/ behavioral problems</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=18), All males aged 5 yrs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No Details provided</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-Sectional.<break/>Parents requested to fill in questionnaire.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBCL, CSHQ.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emotional behavioral problems were poor predictors of sleep disturbance but the latter predicted probability of anxiety and affective problems.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kirkpatrick et al (2019)<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> Ireland</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Used a qualitative approach to explore parental perceptions of insomnia.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=15) M (93.3%), aged 4–12 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 8 SD = 2.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parent reported</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-Sectional.<break/>Study advertised with posters adverts in social media groups and websites and support services.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CSHQ, Focus groups (n=2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Children (86%) experienced sleep anxiety that resulted in delayed bedtimes, night waking, and disruptive night behaviors. Poor sleep resulted in reduced daytime interactions (60%), aggressive outbursts (26%) and limited educational opportunities (87%).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Krakowiak et al (2008)<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> USA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examined sleep characteristics using large sample comparing ASD, NT, and Children with Developmental Delay.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=303), M (55.16%), aged 2–5 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 3.6 SD = 0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADI-R &amp; ADOS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case-Control Study<break/>Data collected from California birth records, telephone interviews, clinic visit, and parent-administered questionnaires.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VABS, The CHARGE Sleep History parent-reported questionnaire, (similar to CSHQ).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parents reported poor sleep affected child’s daily functioning (21%) and family functioning (23%). Sleep disturbances not associated with cognitive and/or adaptive delays.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lambert et al (2016)<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> Canada</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Assessed sleep and sleep-daytime functioning relationships in ASD children without subjective sleep Complaints</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=11), aged 6–13 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>=10.27 SD=2.24.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADI-R &amp; ADOS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional.<break/>Participants screened via a telephone interviews. Participants resumed their normal daily activities the morning after PSG.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBCL, CSHQ, sleep agendas, PSG (2 consecutive nights- 1st night for adaptation, data from 2nd night).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of SWS negatively correlated with reciprocal social interaction score ADOS (r = −0.807, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.003) and positively correlated with repetitive behavior (r = 0.714, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.02). Low amounts of SWS were associated with high levels of internalized behaviors (r = −0.41, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.046).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MacDuffie et al (2020)<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> USA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characterized sleep patterns and associations with brain dev. in children at risk/low risk of ASD and those who did/did not have ASD.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=38), M (76%), aged 0–2, M=23.6 SD=3.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADOS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longitudinal.<break/>Infants assessed at 6, 12, 24 months. MRI scans, parent-report measures, and measures of cog. and adaptive functioning.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADOS, IBQ-R, VABS.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep problems were not significantly related to social-affective symptoms severity (r<sub>8</sub> = 0.26, p = 0.15). Children with more sleep problems had higher trajectory of repetitive behavior over time (χ<sup>2</sup>(1) = 5.59, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.02).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Malhi et al (2019)<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref> India</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examined association of sleep disturbances with daytime behavioral difficulties in ASD children.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=60), M (85%), aged 4–12 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 6.1 SD = 2.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM V</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional. Dev. behavioral, and sleep history taken. Parents asked typical time bed and wake times, total sleep duration at night, and the number of times child wakes at night, and total duration of night awakening.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DP 3, CSHQ.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep dysfunction had a significant relationship with daytime reported behavior difficulties (r = 0.53, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.01).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Malow et al (2012)<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref><break/>USA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Assessed dose–response, tolerability, safety, feasibility of Melatonin Supplement.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=24), M (83.3%), aged 3–10 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>=5.9 SD = 1.9/2.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">States children had an ASD clinical diagnosis details not provided</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCT- 14-week intervention.<break/>Week1 (baseline), parents given 1-hour sleep ed. During week 2 acclimation) children given inert liquid before bedtime. Children given melatonin (1mg) before bedtime for 14-weeks, increased to max. 9mg until satisfactory response.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBCL, Sleep diaries and Actigraphy.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">After treatment there were significant decreases (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) in sleep latency, affective problems and social withdrawal. Significant decreases in ADHD (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.006), Stereotyped behavior (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.008) and Difficult child (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.003). Sleep duration significantly increased (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Manelis-Baram et al (2021)<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> Israel</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examined the longitudinal relationship bet. sleep disturbances and sensory sensitivities.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=103) M (76%), aged 3–5 Time 1 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 3.04 SD = 1.12, Time 2<italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 4.47 SD = 1.19.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADOS-2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longitudinal.<break/>Convenience sample at 2 separate time points. Quantified changes in sleep disturbance and Sensory Profile scores by subtracting Time 2 scores from Time 1 scores.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADOS-2, CSHQ, SP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longitudinal changes in sleep disturbances correlated significantly with sensory sensitivities (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.42, p &lt; 0.001) but not changes in ASD severity (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> (57) = −0.04, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.75).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">May et al (2015)<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> Australia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examined changes in sleep disturbances over 1 yr and relations bet. dev. change in sleep and behavioral problems.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=46) M (52.17%), aged 7–12 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>=9.84 SD=1.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM IV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longitudinal.<break/>Parents completed questionnaires at baseline and 1yr later).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SRS, CSHQ.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep quality scores from Time 1 and 2 respectively correlated significantly (p &lt; 0.01) with anxiety (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.585; 0.701), social responsiveness (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.581; 0.455) and aggression (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.281; 0.261).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mazurek et al (2019)<xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref> USA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examined the chronicity and longitudinal relations of sleep problems and co-occurring symptoms.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=437) M (82.61%), aged 2–10 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>=5.07; SD=2.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM IV &amp; ADOS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longitudinal. Participants evaluated by clinicians. Participants assessed in accordance with relevant measures at baseline then 3.8 years later.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBCL, CSHQ.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep problems significantly correlated (p &lt; 0.01) with aggression (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.431), anxiety (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.582), somatic complaints (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.435), Sensory over-responsivity (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = −0.602).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">McLay et al (2021)<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref> New Zealand, USA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Investigated the effects of function- based behavioral sleep interventions on ASD severity, behavior, parent relationship and sleep quality, depression, anxiety, stress.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=41), aged 2–18 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>=7; SD=3.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Verified by psychologist, psychiatrist, or pediatrician.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCT.<break/>These data were collected from child and adult participants who completed the initial clinical assessment and the prescribed treatment and questionnaires administered pre- and post-intervention.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBCL, GARS. VABS-II PSQI.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate sleep intervention effect for social interaction (ES = − 0.51, PSES = 74%). Small effect for emotional response (ES = − 0.35; PSES = 61%), social communication (ES = − 0.25; PSES = 66%). Improved internalizing (PSES =73%) and externalizing behaviors (PSES = 69%).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutluer et al (2016)<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref> Turkey</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Investigated sleep problems to identify the risk/protective behavioral factors.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=64), M (79.68%), aged 6–18 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 11.66 SD = 3.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM V</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-Sectional.<break/>Assessments completed by researchers.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC, PSQ, CARS, ABC, PSQ, CBCL.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Behavior problems correlated significantly with sleep problems (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.597, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) Social withdrawal and inappropriate speech variables were significantly correlated with sleep problems.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Naito et al (2019)<xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref> Japan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Investigated the time course of body movements at night and their relationship with social ability.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=17), M (76.47%), aged 5–8 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>=6.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM V, ADOS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pilot Study.<break/>Accelerometer attached to the waist for 3 nights.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SRS, Vineland-11 MBS, Accelerometer.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Higher rate of body movement at 0.5 to 1 hour after onset of body stillness was associated with lower social ability (r = −0.507, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.036) and maladaptive behavior (r = −0.529, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.028).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ng et al (2020)<xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref> USA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Assessed associations bet. sleep disturbances and externalizing/ internalizing problems, ADHD &amp; social impairment.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=28), ASD &amp; ADHD (n=57), aged 7–17 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 11.18 SD = 2.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM V, ADOS-2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective Study.<break/>Informant inventories administered during child’s evaluation.<break/>Participants had not been previously diagnosed with sleep apnea.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBCL, PSQ. Psychiatric, Neuropsychological, Speech and Language evaluations.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">In ASD and ADHD group sleepiness concerns correlated with externalizing problems (r = 0.39, p = 0.003). No associations bet. behavioral ratings and sleep in ASD group (rs &lt; 0.36, ps &gt; 0.061). Sleep factors contributed the variance in externalizing problems (17%), hyperactivity/impulsivity (16%), in attention (15%).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Papadopoulos et al (2019)<xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref> Australia UK</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evaluated efficacy of a brief behavioral sleep intervention program.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=61), ADHD-ASD (n=28) M (89%), Intervention, n=33 usual care aged 5–13 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>=10.05 SD=1.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnosed by questioning parents.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCT.<break/>Measures administered baseline and 3 and 6 months. Intervention 2 face-to-face sleep consultations. 2 follow-up tel calls 2 weeks apart with trained clinician</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parent &amp; teacher-reported SDQ, CSHQ, PedsQL, DASS, Sleep diary.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Difficult daytime behavior significantly correlated with sleep problems r = 0.42, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01, night waking r = 0.49, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01, and poorer sleep quality r = 0.45, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>=&lt; 0.01.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patzold et al (1998)<xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref> Australia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examined the specificity of sleep problems and their. Relationship with daytime behavior.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=38) M (81%), aged 44–152 months SD=31.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM-III criteria.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14-day parental reported sleep diary. DBC, CBCL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Behavior problems correlated significantly with sleep problems (r = 0.42, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01), poorer sleep quality (r = 0.45, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01), night waking (r = 0.49, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phung &amp; Goldberg (2017)<xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref> USA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examined the association bet. nocturnal sleep problems and daytime sleepiness in relation to quality of peer relationships.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=19), M (84.2%), aged 5–13 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>=16.88 SD=2.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCQ &amp; ADOS-2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross- sectional.<break/>Home visit, adolescents completed surveys and instructed re. actigraph sleep watch. 2nd visit materials collected and participants compensated.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NRI-RQV, Actigraphy 7 nights, SHS, Sleep diary.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Night-time and daytime sleep-wake problems were significantly associated with discordant relationships (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.59, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01). Poor sleep associated with more perceived conflict with peers and daytime sleepiness.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saré &amp; Smith (2020)<xref rid="cit0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref> USA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examined relationship bet. sleep problems and autistic behavior.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=29,276) M (80%), aged &lt;18 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>=8.6 SD=4.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCQ</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross- sectional.<break/>Analyzed data from SPARK database</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCQ.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significant association bet. repetitive behaviors and sleep problem (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001) Slightly stronger association in females vs males.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Schreck et al (2004)<xref rid="cit0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref> USA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examined sleep problems and relations to the expression of ASD features.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=55), aged 5–12 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>=8.2 SD=2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GARS Autism Quotient ≥ 80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross- sectional.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GARS, BEDS.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shorter sleep duration predicted difficulties with social interactions (R<sup>2</sup> = 0.12, p &lt; 0.01) and ASD diagnostic characteristics (R<sup>2</sup> = 0.11, p &lt; 0.02). Communication problems were significantly related to periods of screaming during the night (R<sup>2</sup> = 0.18; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Schroder et al (2019)<xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref> France, USA, Netherlands, UK, Israel</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examined effects of melatonin MedPRM on behavior and caregiver well=being outcomes in ASD children with insomnia.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=125), M (75%) Placebo n=65 M n=47 (72.31%), aged 2–17 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>=8.4; SD=4.24 n=60 MedPRM Aged 2–17 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>=9; SD=4.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM IV/V</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCT.<break/>2-week single-blind placebo run. If impaired sleep participants randomly assigned to placebo/ drug group for 13 weeks as double-blind treatment. Dose for efficacy 2mg, 5mg, 10mg.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SDQ, Sleep diaries.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">After the 13 weeks treatment sleep improved in 41% children and there were significant improvements of SDQ mean behavior attributes (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.077). Significant improvement in externalizing (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.021) but not internalizing behavior (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.770)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Segawa et al 1992<xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref> Japan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examined the effects of early disturbances in the S-W cycle on behavioral abnormalities.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD n=27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM II-R By Psychiatrists.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longitudinal. Monthly or Bimonthly recording for 4 years. Parents educated how to encourage developing a 24-hour cycle.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychiatrist examination and parent sleep/wake diary.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">In most children, stabilization of the sleep-waking cycle occurred before improved behavior but no significant correlation bet. age of improvement in sleep and behaviors.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thenhausen et al (2017)<xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref> Germany</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Investigated sleep problems in individuals with ASD and Asperger’s Syndrome (AS).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=15) M (86.7%), aged 10–17 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 14.32 SD=3.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Independent psychiatrist and psychologist</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pilot Study. Information sheet and questionnaires given by therapists to parents at home and returned personally or via mail.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SRS, SDSC.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The total sleep disturbance score correlated significantly with impairments in social communication (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.55, p &lt; 0.05), social anxiety (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.64, p &lt; 0.05), and the overall autism index (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.56, p &lt; 0.05).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tudor et al (2012)<xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref><break/>USA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examined the relationships bet. sleep problems and ASD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=109) M (83.49%), aged 3–18 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 7.06 SD = 2.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Independent pediatricians and psychologists</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-Sectional. Trained staff visited home for 1.5 hr. assisted mothers to<break/>complete questionnaires.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GARS, CSHQ.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep onset delay was strongest predictor of communication deficit, stereotyped behavior, and autism severity. The parasomnias sub-scale significantly correlated with communication (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.28, p &lt; 0.055), social Interaction (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.21, p &lt; 0.05). Social interaction significantly correlated with Night waking (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.26, p &lt; 0.01) and sleep-disordered breathing (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.19, p &lt; 0.05).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tyagi et al (2018)<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> India</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Explored sleep problems and their association with behaviors, and comorbidities.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=74) M (82%), aged 3–12 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>=4.8; SD=1.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCQ, M-CHAT-R/F</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-Sectional.<break/>Excluded if on medications affecting sleep or chronic illness.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DP-3, The Conners ADHD Rating Scale-3, VABS-II, SDSC.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep problems significantly associated hyperactivity (OR = 10.2, 95% CI 3.34–31.2, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and internalizing (OR = 1.09 95% CI 1.02–1.156, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.009) and externalizing (OR = 1.078 95% CI 1.02–1.13, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.004) behavior.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Veatch et al (2017)<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> USA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examined relationship bet. shorter sleep duration and ASD symptomatology</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=2713) M (86%), aged 4–18 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>=9.04 SD=3.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM V, ADI-R, ADOS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-Sectional.<break/>Data analyzed from Simons Simplex Collection.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADI-R, ADOS, CBCL.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Social/ communication impairment ADI-R negatively correlated with parent-reported sleep duration (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = −0.19, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 1×10<sup>−5</sup>). Shorter sleep duration moderately correlated with Increased social affect scores (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = −0.06, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 1.8×10<sup>−2</sup>). Short duration was associated with hyperactivity (OR = 2.90, 95% CI = 1.66, 5.06, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; =1.0×10<sup>−4</sup>).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wang et al (2016)<xref rid="cit0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref><break/>China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characterized sleep disturbances and examined associated behavioral factors.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=60) M (83.3%), aged 6 −17 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 11.53 SD = 2.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM IV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-Sectional.<break/>Participants recruited from a school for children with special needs.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SDQ, CSHQ.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total CSHQ correlated significantly with total SDQ (r = 0.51, p &lt; 0.001), hyperactivity (r = 0.47, p &lt; 0.001), emotional symptoms (r = 0.34, p = 0.008), conduct problems (r = 0.38, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.003).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yang et al (2018)<xref rid="cit0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref><break/>China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examined association. bet. gastrointestinal, sleep problems and behavior and risk factors.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=169) M (85.8%), aged 3 −12 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 8.6 SD = 4.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM IV, ADI-R, ADOS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-Sectional.<break/>Research Center of Harbin Medical University.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC, VABS, PDDSQ, SRS, CSHQ, VABS, PPVT, CARS, CABS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Children with and without sleep disturbances significantly differed in socialization item scores of VABS (p = 0.004), ABC scores PDDSQ scores, SRS total scores, social cognition and social Communication item scores of SRS respectively.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yavuz-Kodat et al (2020)<xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref><break/>France</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Determined the relative contribution of sleep and circadian rest–activity rhythm to problem behaviors.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASD (n=52) M (78.85%), aged 3–10 <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 5.39 SD = 1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADOS, ADI-R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-Sectional.<break/>Children included regardless of dev. delay or ID. Excluded if on unstable medication and if traveled over 2 time zones in preceding 3 months.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC-C, VABS, CSHQ, Actigraphy, NPCRA using rest-activity data.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The higher irritability and stereotypic behaviors group slept continuously (−60 min, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.04) and (−75 min, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.006) respectively than those with less irritability and stereotypic behaviors.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: ABC, Aberrant Behavior Checklist; ABC-C, Aberrant Behavior Checklist-Community; ADI-R, Autism Diagnostic Interview, Revised; ADOS, Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule; ASSQ, Autism Spectrum Screening Questionnaire; ATA, Assessment of Autistic Behavior; AuBc, Autism Behavior Checklist; BRQ, Bedtime Routines Questionnaire; BISQ, the Brief Infant Sleep Questionnaire; ICSD BEDS, a sleep problem questionnaire constructed from items from the International Classification of Sleep-disorders; CABS, Clancy Autism Behavior Scale; CARS, Childhood Autism Rating Scale; CBCL, Child Behavior Checklist Score; CSHQ, Children’s Sleep Habits Questionnaire; CSHS, Children’s Sleep Hygiene Scale; CSWS, Children’s Sleep–Wake Scale; DISCD, Diagnostic Interview for Social &amp; Communication Disorders; DP3, Development Profile 3; DSM IV, Fourth Edition criteria; DSM V, Fifth Edition criteria; ES, effect size; HRQoL, Health-Related Quality of Life; IBQ-R, the Infant Behavior Questionnaire–Revised; M-CHAT-R/F, Modified Checklist for Autism in Toddlers, Revised; NPCRA, Non-Parametric Circadian Rhythm Analysis; NRI-RQV, Network of Relationships Inventory-Relationship Qualities Version; PCQ, Parental Concerns Questionnaire; PDDSQ, Pervasive Developmental Disorders Screening Questionnaire; PPVT-C, Peabody Picture Vocabulary Test-Chinese edition; PSI, Parenting stress index- short form; PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index; PSQ, Paediatric sleep questionnaire; PedsQL 4.0, Pediatric Quality of Life Inventory 4.0; PSES, Percent Superiority Effect Size; RBQ-2, Repetitive Behavior Questionnaire-2; RBS-R, Repetitive Behavior Scale–Revised; SCQ, Social Communication Questionnaire; SDSC, Sleep Disturbance Scale for Children; SDQ, Strengths &amp; Difficulties Questionnaire; SHS, Sleep Habits Survey; SP, Sensory Profile; SRS, Social Responsiveness Scale; SWQ-P, Social Worries Questionnaire- Parent Version; VABS-II, Vineland Adaptive Behavior Scale-Second Edition; ABA, Applied Behavioral Analysis; ASD, Autism Syndrome Disorder; Bet., between; Cog., cognitive; Dev., developmental; EEG, electroencephalogram; ICD-10, International Classification of Diseases; ID, intellectual disability; PSG, polysomnography; NT, neurotypical; TST, total sleep time; WASO, wake after sleep onset.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis></p>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Relationships Between Sleep Quality, Social Functioning and Behavior Problems</title>
        <sec id="s0003-s2001-s3001">
          <title>Externalizing Behavior Problems</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">There is substantial evidence that externalizing behavior problems can be associated with sleep problems</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> and multiple hierarchical regressions have been used to show that they can be statistically predicted by sleep quality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Fadini et al,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> using parental reports, found sleep disorders, particularly arousal disorder and excessive daytime sleepiness, correlated with behavioral problems. This finding concurs with Aathira et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> which measured sleep prospectively with a small sample, using one night of PSG. This study found that poor sleepers had a mean Child Behavior Checklist Score of 63.8 (60.8 to 66.8) whereas good sleepers scored a mean of 57.8 (53.0 to 62.5)(P ¼ 0.004). Malhi et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> also found a significant relationship between sleep dysfunction and daytime behavior difficulties (r = 0.53, P = 0.01), and autistic children with sleep problems (t = 2.42, P = 0.018) had significantly more behavioral difficulties (M = 15.67, SD = 6.10) than those without sleep problems (M = 9.50, SD = 3.01). Several studies have found that sleep problems are significantly associated with irritability, hyperactivity, inattentiveness,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> and aggression, which parents attributed to tiredness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Sleep disturbance has also been identified as a predictor of attention deficit, hyperactivity, and oppositional defiant behavior.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Allik et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> found that 31.2% of their sample of autistic children, without ID, had insomnia. These children had more teacher-reported hyperactivity symptoms than those without insomnia. Goldman et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> also found that the poor sleeper group within their sample showed more inattention and hyperactivity, and they had higher scores on compulsive and ritualistic scales in comparison to the good sleeper group. Goldman et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> also found that 50% of the poor sleeper group had problems with attention, social interaction, language, hyperactivity, sensory issues, eating behaviors, and self-stimulatory behavior, in comparison 50% of the good sleeper group who only reported problems in language, attention, and social interaction. The characteristics of good sleepers versus poor sleepers have also been examined in an RCT.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In this RCT, the poor sleeper group had significantly higher daytime behavioral problems including, hyperactivity, stereotypical behaviors, and more irritability. However, Lambert et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> found that SWS positively correlated with the score of the ADI-R subscale for repetitive behavior (r = 0.714, p = 0.02), a positive association was difficult to explain.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2001-s3002">
          <title>Internalizing Behavior Problems</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep disturbances have been associated with anxiety</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and emotional problems.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Lambert et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> used data collected through parent-reported questionnaires, daily sleep diaries, and laboratory PSG (2 nights). Their results showed that the amount of slow-wave sleep (SWS) correlated negatively with the amount of Internalizing behaviors (r = −0.41, p = 0.046), and the reciprocal social interaction score ADOS (r = −0.807, p = 0.003). Sleep latency, which was defined as the first occurrence of 10 consecutive minutes of stage 1 sleep or the first epoch of any other sleep stage, and SWS were associated with low levels of internalizing behavior and the social functioning of children as determined through ADOS measurements. Poor sleep quality is also associated with lower mood.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Kirkpatrick et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> examined the impact of insomnia, using focus groups (n = 2) that involved family members (n = 15). Their findings revealed that 26% percent of parents said that tiredness negatively impacted the mood of their children. Some evidence suggests that lower sleep quality may lead to poor prosocial behavior and social withdrawal.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> One study examined the association between sleep problems and the quality of peer relationships.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> This involved a small sample of verbally fluent autistic adolescents (n = 19) that measured seven nights’ sleep using actigraphy. The questionnaires, but not the actigraph data indicated significant associations between sleep problems and discordant peer relationships (0.59 p &lt; 0.01). Participants with more sleep problems reported discord with peers but the closeness of peer relationships was not significantly associated with sleep quality. They concluded that autistic adolescents can be vulnerable to negativity in peer relationships when they experience sleep problems and that they may have difficulty regulating social interaction.</citation_analysis></p>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In one study, social withdrawal, and stereotypic behaviors accounted for 17% and 36% of the variance, respectively, in sleep disturbances.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> It has also been suggested that the need for social interaction can decrease with increased sleep problems.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2001-s3003">
          <title>Aspects of Sleep Quality</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Particular aspects of sleep quality including sleep onset delay/sleep latency, short sleep duration, and shorter continuous sleep have been associated with social functioning.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> For example, Tudor et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> found a positive correlation between stereotyped behavior with sleep onset delay (0.31 p &lt; 0.01), and social interaction (0.40 p &lt; 0.01). Sleep duration also correlated with stereotyped behavior (0.32 p &lt; 0.01) and social Interaction (0.33 p &lt; 0.01). Also, when controlling for the variance contributed by other sleep problems, sleep onset delay (pr = 0.27, p &lt; 0.01) and night wakings (pr = 0.22, p &lt; 0.05) were significantly strong predictors of stereotypical behaviors.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></citation_analysis></p>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">There is some evidence that shorter sleep latency relates to poorer social functioning. Naito et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> examined the relationship between body movements at night and social ability, in a small sample of relatively young autistic children (n = 17) arguing that movement would correspond to periods of light rather than deep sleep. Dissimilar to previous studies that used PSG, they measured the body movement of participants sleeping in their own homes for 3 nights using an accelerometer attached to the waist. They found that a higher rate of body movement at 0.5 to 1 hour after onset body stillness was associated with lower social ability. They suggested that higher social symptoms severity was associated with shorter latency in the first nocturnal peak of movement and in the latter half of the night. This study did not evaluate motor function or measure the amount of daytime activity that may impact movements at night and they did not measure body movements for 5 nights, which is optimal to estimate body movement patterns.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></citation_analysis></p>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Other evidence indicates that the duration of uninterrupted continuous sleep is important. Delahaye (2014) found the largest correlations were between sleep duration and quality of life total (−0.36, p &lt; 0.001), and psychosocial summary (−0.36, p &lt; 0.001) scores, when they investigated the relationship between sleep problems and quality of life, child age, gender, autism diagnosis, internalizing and externalizing behavior, and autism severity. Furthermore, extremely short sleep duration increased core autism symptom severity</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and a short duration of uninterrupted sleep may be more impactful than sleep latency.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> These results concur with those of Yavuz-Kodat et al,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> who examined the relationship between sleep, circadian rest-activity rhythm to problem behaviors. This study found children with shorter continuous sleep had high irritability in comparison with those with lower irritability (−60 min, p = 0.04), and high stereotypic behaviors compared to children with fewer stereotypies (−75 min, p = 0.006). Shorter continuous sleep was 60 minutes shorter in the higher irritability group and 75 minutes shorter in the higher stereotypy group. Yavuz-Kodat et al determined that children with shorter continuous sleep completed approximately one less complete sleep cycle of REM and non-REM sleep. Further evidence of the importance of uninterrupted sleep can be found in a study that evaluated the effects of slow-release melatonin treatment on sleep and behavior.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Schroder et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> found a modest correlation between the number of difficulties experienced by participants and increase in total sleep time from baseline (Spearman’s rank correlation R − 0.229 p = 0.024). Schroder et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> attributed this to the increased duration of uninterrupted sleep (Spearman’s rank correlation R − 0.21 p = 0.047) but not with the shortening of sleep latency (Spearman’s rank correlation R 0.09 p = 0.379). Taking the slow-release melatonin drug resulted in the Ped- PRM-treated participants sleeping for an average of 57.5 minutes longer. The placebo group had an increase of 9.14 minutes longer. The sleep latency of the Ped- PRM-treated participants decreased by 39.6 minutes on average compared to 12.5 minutes with placebo.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2001-s3004">
          <title>Evidence Suggesting Causal Relationships</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Studies that have examined the relationship between sleep quality and social functioning longitudinally or with social functioning and behavior problems as outcomes during the evaluation of sleep interventions provide evidence that suggests improving sleep quality may improve these outcomes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> For example, Malow et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> conducted an RCT that used parental reporting and no placebo to assess the response, tolerability, safety of a slow-release Melatonin. After 14 weeks, sleep latency significantly decreased and there were significant improvements in sleep duration, social withdrawal, affective, and ADHD subscales. Another double-blind RCT evaluated the efficacy of prolonged-release melatonin mini-tablets (PedPRM; 2–5 mg) in improving sleep onset, duration, and child behavior.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Participants had either autism or Smith-Magenis syndrome (n = 125). After 13-weeks, melatonin effectively improved sleep quality and behavior in comparison to a placebo. There were statistically significant improvements in externalizing behavior, which decreased on average − 0.70 units in the Ped- PRM-treated (N = 54), compared to worsening with an increase of 0.13 units in the placebo-treated group (N = 49). In addition, 53.7% of patients in the PedPRM group improved by 1 or more units on externalizing behavior score compared to 27.7% in the placebo group (Odds ratio 3.0; p = 0.008). However, there was no significant difference in the mean scores of attributes that related to Internalizing behaviors (peer relationships and emotional behavior). Overall, 47% of subjects had a reduction of 1 or more in total strengths and difficulties score in the PedPRM group, compared to 27.1% in the placebo group (p = 0.035). This suggests that hyperactivity/inattention may be relatively more responsive to the sleep improvements that result from treatment with melatonin than Internalizing behaviors. However, it is noteworthy that this study was powered to detect differences in effects on sleep but not behavior. Papadopoulos et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> conducted an RCT pilot study that evaluated the efficacy of a brief behavioral sleep intervention on sleep and child functioning. Participants who were children with an ADHD-Autism co-diagnosis were randomized to the sleep intervention group (n = 28), or the group receiving usual care (n = 33). This study assessed the mean difference in change scores between baseline to 3 and 6 months between the groups. They found that the intervention group improved emotional functioning to a greater degree according to parent reports at 3 months: (mean difference = −1.0, 95% CI = [−2.0, −0.1]; ES = −0.6, p = 0.04), and teacher reports at 3 months (mean difference =−1.2, 95% CI = [−2.3, −0.1]; ES = −0.5, p = 0.04). However, by 6 months, there was no significant difference in emotional functioning, but teacher reports suggested there was an improvement in conduct problems. Small improvements in peer relationships at 6 months were detected by both parents and teachers (mean difference = −0.6, 95% CI = [−1.6, 0.4]; ES = −0.3, p = 0.22) and teacher report (mean difference = −1.0, 95% CI = [−2.3, 0.3]; ES = −0.4, p = 0.11). Papadopoulos et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> concluded that the intervention resulted in large improvements in sleep and moderate improvements in behavioral function at 3 and 6 months.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Related Factors</title>
        <sec id="s0003-s2002-s3001">
          <title>The Severity of Autism Core Symptoms</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Some studies have examined social functioning focusing on the severity of autism symptoms. These studies provide mixed evidence concerning the relationship between sleep quality and the autism severity. The majority of studies have found that a positive association exists between them.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> For example, Sare &amp; Smith (2020),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> in a study involving secondary data analysis of a large parent-reported data set (n = 19,104), found a strong association between sleep problems and the severity of autism-related behaviors. However, in two studies, sleep disturbance scores did not correlate with autism severity</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> and in another, a small amount of variance in daytime symptoms was explained by sleep problems.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref></citation_analysis></p>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The evidence suggests that hyper-arousal and increased sensitivity to stimuli in the sleep environment are associated with sleep disturbance.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Manelis-Baram et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> found that the sensory sensitivity score exhibited the strongest correlation with sleep duration, and sleep disturbances correlated with sensory problems correlated (r = 0.57, p &lt; 0.001), sensation avoiding (r = 0.49, p &lt; 0.001), low registration (r = 0.37, p &lt; 0.001), and sensation seeking (r = 0.24, p = 0.014) scores. Further evidence of the relationship between sensitivity and sleep problems was obtained through a study that found significant associations between sleep problems and increased seeking, touch, movement processing patterns, conduct, and attentional responses to sensory processing.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Mazurek et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> also found sleep problems correlated with sensory over-responsivity, and the study results suggested that sensory over-responsivity was a longitudinal predictor of sleep problems and inattention/hyperactivity in very young, but not older children.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2002-s3002">
          <title>Cognitive Ability</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Several studies found that the relationship between sleep quality and social functioning exists regardless of cognitive ability and the presence/absence of ID.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In contrast, a small number of studies found that the quantity and quality of sleep are associated with cognitive performance</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and that the presence of ID was an important predictor in the relationship between sleep quality and emotional and behavioral disturbance.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Krakowiak et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> also found, in a large population-based study, that lower cognitive and adaptive function is associated with increased delayed sleep onset, night awakening, and shorter sleep duration. In addition, two other studies found that individuals with an unstable sleep phenotype had a relatively lower IQ and adaptive functioning level than those with a stable phenotype.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2002-s3003">
          <title>Anxiety</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">There is some evidence that anxiety contributes to the association between sleep and social functioning.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, Mazurek et al’s</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> results did not indicate a significant predictive relationship between anxiety and sleep problems after accounting for covariates, even though anxiety correlated with sleep in both older and younger children. However, a causal relationship between anxiety and sleep quality was described by eighty-six percent of parents (n = 13) in one study.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Parents said that their children experienced sleep-related anxiety that resulted in delayed bedtimes, unwanted co-sleeping, night awakening disruptive night-time behaviors.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> They reported that children were afraid to sleep alone, anxious about darkness, worried about forthcoming events or school and that this anxiety contributed to reduced and poor quality sleep. Therefore, anxiety may impact sleep quality by delaying sleep onset and pre-bedtimes routines.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Indeed, the consistency of pre-bedtime routines can be negatively associated with externalizing behaviors (b = 0.55, t(110) = 6.76, p &lt; 0.001) and sleep quality. The consistency of routines is related to problematic pre-bedtime behavior and bedtime resistance</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and children with higher irritability have more difficulties regarding bedtime routine.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Goldman et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> also found that this was a major concern by parents of children who were categorized as poor sleepers. Bedtime resistance was also identified as a risk factor for repetitive behavior in preschool autistic children and it explained a large proportion of variance in repetitive behavior scores (adjusted R2 = 0.206).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In addition, linear regression showed that bedtime resistance and sleep onset delay explained a large and considerable proportion of the variance in the total repetitive behavior score (20.6% and 17.3%), respectively.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2002-s3004">
          <title>Age</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">As suggested above, the relationship between sleep quality and social functioning may differ according to age and behavior problems and a later sleep midpoint of older children was associated with challenging behavior.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Veatch et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> evaluated the effects of age on associations of sleep duration and autism traits in children who were 4–5 years old (17.7%); primary school age (63.6%), and secondary school age (18.5%). This study found that age is significantly related to short sleep duration, anxiety, depression, Internalizing problems, and the severity scores for affective problems. Goldman et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> also found an association between parasomnias and behavior across the age span with an inverse relationship between age and behavior problems. However, in contrast, Johnson et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> found no age difference between good sleepers and poor sleepers in terms of disruptive behaviors, and parasomnias have been found to persist across an age range of 3–18 years.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Furthermore, even adjusted for age, poor sleepers were found to be at the highest risk of self-injurious behaviors.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2002-s3005">
          <title>Temporal Aspects</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">A few studies have examined the relationship between sleep and functioning over time. May et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> investigated the bi-directional relationship between sleep disturbance and behavioral, and emotional problems, longitudinally, at baseline (T1) and 1 year later (T2). At both time points, sleep problems correlated with social difficulties, aggression, and hyperactivity. These results concurred with Mazurek et al,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> who examined a large well-characterized sample of autistic children at baseline (T1) and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">M</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 3.8 years later (T2). Mazurek et al found that sleep problems were significantly associated with most co-occurring symptoms at T1 and T2.</citation_analysis></p>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">For individuals over time, the evidence varies as to whether the relationship between the trajectories of sleep problems and social functioning can persist over time. They can be persistent, but children with greater sleep problems at the second time point (aged 4) had higher trajectories for repetitive behaviors.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In addition, several studies identified a high degree of individual variability.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis></p>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">It is likely that the chronicity of disturbed sleep may have an accumulative effect on social functioning. Abel et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> used objective measures of sleep and behavior to explore night-to-night fluctuations in sleep patterns and challenging behavior, ie, whether challenging behavior would follow the day after a poor quality night’s sleep. This study found, using multilevel models for predictive analysis, that across eight nights, rather than a single night, sleep quality predicted the subsequent challenging behavior. This finding concurred with Cohen et al,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> who examined data from five days/nights measurement of sleep and challenging behaviors. They collected sleep data using structured observations and clinicians worked one on one with participants to observe and record behavior hourly each day for up to 21 hours. They found that the previous night’s sleep did not strongly predict next-day problem behaviors. Instead, behavior was affected after several nights of poor sleep, and the accuracy of predicting behavior increased with the number of nights measured. This finding concurs with qualitative research in which a participant parent said planned family trips to the cinema were canceled after: “a few late nights and early mornings. Well! He [the autistic child] can be awkward and it’s just not worth it” (Kirkpatrick et al, 2019, Parent 13 p. 64).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <sec id="s0004-s2001">
        <title>Summary of Key Findings</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The evidence presented in this review reveals that the social functioning and problem behaviors of autistic children, with or without ID, are associated with their sleep quality. A relatively small number of studies have evaluated social function and behavior problems as outcomes of sleep interventions, but these reveal evidence that suggests causal relationships and that social functioning may improve as sleep improves but that the improvements may be temporary.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Social functioning is associated with the tendency for autistic children to have shorter latency in the first nocturnal peak, less deep, and more fragmented sleep than those with NT.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Therefore, the relationship between sleep quality and social functioning is probably unique to autistic individuals.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">More specifically, chronic and accumulative poor sleep quality can increase externalizing behavior problems including hyperactivity and inattentiveness. However, a few of the study samples examined contained autistic participants who were also diagnosed with ADHD, and the majority of studies did not out rule the presence of ADHD. Therefore, definitive conclusions cannot be reliably drawn due to the high comorbidity rate between autism and ADHD.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The evidence also reveals that poor sleep is negatively associated with problematic Internalizing behavior, increased negative mood, and social withdrawal. However, further research needs to investigate the impact of sleep on Internalizing behavior as discussed below.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Overall, the evidence suggests that anxiety negatively impacts sleep onset, duration, and it increases sleep disturbance. Therefore, the relationship between sleep quality and social functioning is bi-directional. This is an important finding as anxiety disorders are common in autistic individuals with prevalence rates from 42% to 79%.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Related to anxiety, hyper-arousal and sensitivity are associated with sleep disturbance.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Hyper-arousal has also been associated with insomnia in autistic adults.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> This finding also supports the presence of a bi-directional relationship between sleep quality and social functioning in autistic children and it supports the hypothesis that particularly in young children, sleep disturbance and sensory sensitivities are likely to be co-dependent, and generated by interacting physiological mechanisms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">There is mixed evidence regarding the relationship between sleep quality and social functioning and its association with autism severity and age. On balance, the evidence reveals an association with the severity of autism symptoms, and that the relationship changes according to age. Previous related research has identified that autistic individuals have age-related variations in core symptom severity</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and sleep behavior.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The majority of studies reviewed used a cross-sectional research design and a small proportion were longitudinal.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54–56</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Therefore, there is little evidence with which to determine causality and its direction with any degree of certainty. It is also notable that only one study employed qualitative research methodology.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Most studies had relatively small sample sizes. However, there were a few large population-based studies.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Examining the relationship between sleep quality and social functioning is complex as it is impacted by comorbidities that are common and experienced by up to 46% of autistic individuals.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The studies reviewed varied hugely regarding which confounding factors researchers controlled for or excluded through participant selection. As discussed above, studies did not all exclude children with co-diagnosis of ADHD, and only some controlled for medical comorbidities,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and pharmacological agents.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> There was a similar variety regarding other confounding factors. For example, few studies assessed the impact of daytime sleep or daytime activities and none recorded whether participants slept in the same room as other children and if the latter had sleep problems.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Kelmanson et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> were an exception in recruiting only singletons without severe comorbidities.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Most of the studies relied on parental reporting for measuring sleep and/or behavior although three studies assessed daytime social functioning with teacher/caregivers reports that were blinded to the sleep quality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The use of parental reporting means most assessments were unblinded and were therefore, subject to reporter bias. Findings using parent-reported sleep measures can concur with those from objective measures.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> But, they do not always do so,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> and sleep duration is the most reliable sleep trait reported by parents.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Furthermore, the use of parental measures for behavior, and not including reports from child/adolescent participants, is likely to underestimate Internalizing behavior, emotion, anxiety, and feelings of sleepiness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Notably, only two studies in this review collected data directly from autistic adolescents.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Underestimation of Internalizing behavior is concerning particularly as self-injurious behavior is a high risk for poor sleepers of all ages</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and worry/rumination can predict the later development of Internalizing and externalizing problems in autistic children.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> But, it may be more problematic for adolescents because the reported somatic complaints of individuals increase over time with age.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> There are methodological challenges in involving people with autism who have an ID but these can be minimized to facilitate their participation in future research.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Only one study measured both sleep and social functioning objectively,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and two related studies used structured sleep and behavior observations.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The use of objective methods potentially reduces bias and several studies measured sleep objectively using actigraphy,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36–38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and PSG.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Moore et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> reviewed the literature and reported that actigraphy can underestimate SOL in autistic children, but that there is good compliance with this method and minimal data loss. The validity of actigraphy against PSG has been assessed in autistic children (n = 26) during one night in a hospital setting.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> This study found good agreement between measures for SOL, TST, and moderate agreement regarding WASO and SE. However, in this review, there was a large variation regarding whether sleep diaries were used to provide contextual data, how children and parents were prepared for PSG and actigraphy, and regarding the duration of the measurement. These are important considerations for the validity of measurements because usual sleep behavior may be distorted if it is measured in ways that are challenging for autistic children who have sensory issues and a preference for sameness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> PSG may be challenging because it involves sensors being attached to the face and scalp, and it requires children to sleep in an unfamiliar environment laboratory environment. Malow et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> found that autistic children who were poor sleepers had a significantly poorer SOL and SE in comparison to autistic good sleepers and NT control groups measured on one night by PSG. However, after subsequent nights of PSG measurement, there was less difference between the groups. Malow et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> recommended that the validity of PSG can increase if autistic children are acclimatized to PSG for two nights and then have their sleep measured during a third night in the laboratory.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2002">
        <title>Future Research</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Future research needs to explore further the impact of confounding variables on the relationship between sleep quality and social functioning. Doing so could be helpful through explaining the variability between individual children.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> For example, the onset of puberty may be a potential confounder</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and this has not been investigated to date. Other factors, including gastrointestinal symptoms,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> dietary and eating habits,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and breathing problems,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> have been afforded minimal attention. Future work should also clarify how gender impacts sleep quality and social functioning. Except for May et al,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> whose sample had a more equal gender ratio, the reviewed studies contained samples of predominantly males, as is typical within the autism population.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep quality and social functioning are both impacted by a mixture of internal and external factors, including interpersonal interactions.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> They are also associated with wider societal policies and cultural practices.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> To date, research has focused on issues that are personal to and within individual autistic children. Future research should explore the impact of wider socio-cultural factors in general, and specifically parental stress, the parent–child relationship, and co-sleeping practices. It can be comparatively more stressful to parent an autistic child than an NT child</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and this may be aggravated through a child’s poor sleep quality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> The use of mixed methods/qualitative research methodology may facilitate in-depth exploration of potential environmental and societal issues.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Sleep quality and social functioning have predominantly been studied using cross-sectional cohorts with data collected at one point in time. More longitudinal and prospective research are required to confirm causal relationships. These designs are also necessary to increase understanding of the trajectory over time and age. Knowledge from this research will facilitate clinicians to offer individualized interventions.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Future research using Delphi survey techniques</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0085" ref-type="bibr">85</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> would also be helpful to increase consensus regarding the management of confounding factors in future research and to facilitate the development of best practice guidelines regarding the use of actigraphy and PSG with autistic individuals.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2003">
        <title>Implications of Findings</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Because autistic children may have poor quality sleep and not complain about this,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> all parents of autistic children may benefit from receiving information that aims to increase sleep quality, because this is likely to maximize their child’s social functioning potential. Also, sleep quality should be assessed for autistic children who present to services with behavioral problems and sleep interventions should be integrated into treatment plans.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Limitations and Strengths</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This review used systematic and robust methods and the methodological strengths and weaknesses of studies were critically appraised using a recognized tool. However, the review only included studies published in English that focused on sleep quality, social functioning, and behavior problems. Therefore, some studies could have been excluded that might have been informative, particularly those that focused on related concepts including communication, and quality of life.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This review examined 46 studies to elucidate understanding of the relationship between sleep quality, social functioning, and behavior problems. Evidence revealed that poor sleep quality is associated with social functioning and behavior problems. A small amount of evidence suggests the existence of a bi-directional causal relationship between sleep quality and social functioning. Delayed sleep onset, reduced sleep duration, and fragmented sleep without continuous periods of uninterrupted sleep, over several days, appear to increase problematic externalizing and Internalizing behavior. However, anxiety, hyper-arousal, and sensitivity may negatively impact sleep quality. RCTs and prospective studies are required to establish causality. Future research also needs to further examine confounding factors, increase consensus for the objective measurement of sleep with autistic individuals, explore the impact of socio-cultural practices, and increase understanding about the Internalizing behavioral consequences of poor sleep quality.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0007">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">All the authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest in this research.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Goldman</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alder</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burgess</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Characterizing sleep in adolescents and adults with autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Autism Dev Disord</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1682</fpage>–<lpage>1695</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10803-017-3089-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28286917</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Christensen</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Braun</surname>
<given-names>KVN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baio</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence and characteristics of autism spectrum disorder among children aged 8 years—autism and developmental disabilities monitoring network, 11 sites, United States, 2012</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">MMWR Surveill Summaries</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.ss6513a1</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>American Psychiatric Association D, Association AP</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders: DSM-5</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Psychiatric Association</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pallathra</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Calkins</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parish‐Morris</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Defining behavioral components of social functioning in adults with autism spectrum disorder as targets for treatment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Autism Res</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>488</fpage>–<lpage>502</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/aur.1910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29341497</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Dawson</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bernier</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <part-title>Development of social brain circuitry in autism</part-title>. In: <string-name><surname>Coch</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dawson</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fischer</surname>
<given-names>KW</given-names></string-name>, editors. <source><italic toggle="yes">Human Behavior, Learning, and the Developing Brain: Atypical Development</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guildford Publications</publisher-name>; <year>2007</year>:<fpage>28</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dawson</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meltzoff</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Osterling</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rinaldi</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Neuropsychological correlates of early symptoms of autism</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Child Dev</italic></source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1276</fpage>–<lpage>1285</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1132265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9839415</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mundy</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sigman</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ungerer</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sherman</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Defining the social deficits of autism: the contribution of non‐verbal communication measures</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Child Psychol Psychiatr</italic></source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>657</fpage>–<lpage>669</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7610.1986.tb00190.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Golan</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baron-Cohen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hill</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Golan</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The “reading the mind in films” task: complex emotion recognition in adults with and without autism spectrum conditions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Soc Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17470910600980986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18633780</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nielsen</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carpenter</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Reflecting on imitation in autism: introduction to the special issue</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Exp Child Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>101</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>169</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jecp.2008.06.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18675429</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rosset</surname>
<given-names>DB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rondan</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Da Fonseca</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Santos</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Assouline</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deruelle</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Typical emotion processing for cartoon but not for real faces in children with autistic spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Autism Dev Disord</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>919</fpage>–<lpage>925</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10803-007-0465-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17952583</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Deruelle</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rondan</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gepner</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tardif</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Spatial frequency and face processing in children with autism and Asperger syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Autism Dev Disord</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/B:JADD.0000022610.09668.4c</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15162938</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bishop-Fitzpatrick</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mazefsky</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eack</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Minshew</surname>
<given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Correlates of social functioning in autism spectrum disorder: the role of social cognition</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Res Autism Spectr Disord</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rasd.2016.11.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28839456</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>El Shakankiry</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep physiology and sleep disorders in childhood</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Sci Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>101</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S22839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23616721</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mindell</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Owens</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carskadon</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Developmental features of sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Child Adolesc Psychiatr Clin N Am</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>695</fpage>–<lpage>725</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1056-4993(18)30149-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10553199</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Owens</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spirito</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McGuinn</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nobile</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep habits and sleep disturbance in elementary school-aged children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Develop Behav Pediatr</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004703-200002000-00005</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Foley</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weinraub</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep, affect, and social competence from preschool to preadolescence: distinct pathways to emotional and social adjustment for boys and for girls</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>711</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2017.00711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28588517</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tomisaki</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tanaka</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Watanabe</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The relationship between the development of social competence and sleep in infants: a longitudinal study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Child Adolesc Psychiatry Ment Health</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>53</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13034-018-0258-8</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Astill</surname>
<given-names>RG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van der Heijden</surname>
<given-names>KB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van IJzendoorn</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Someren</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep, cognition, and behavioral problems in school-age children: a century of research meta-analyzed</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Bull</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>138</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1109</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0028204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22545685</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Reynaud</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vecchierini</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heude</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Charles</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Plancoulaine</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and its relation to cognition and behaviour in preschool‐aged children of the general population: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e12636</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12636</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29164715</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tyagi</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Juneja</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jain</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep problems and their correlates in children with autism spectrum disorder: an Indian study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Autism Dev Disord</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1169</fpage>–<lpage>1181</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10803-018-3820-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30426347</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>May</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cornish</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Conduit</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rajaratnam</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rinehart</surname>
<given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep in high-functioning children with autism: longitudinal developmental change and associations with behavior problems</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15402002.2013.829064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24283751</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Veatch</surname>
<given-names>OJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sutcliffe</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Warren</surname>
<given-names>ZE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Keenan</surname>
<given-names>BT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Potter</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malow</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Shorter sleep duration is associated with social impairment and comorbidities in ASD</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Autism Res</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1221</fpage>–<lpage>1238</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/aur.1765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28301091</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vriend</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Corkum</surname>
<given-names>PV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moon</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>IM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Behavioral interventions for sleep problems in children with autism spectrum disorders: current findings and future directions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Pediatr Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1017</fpage>–<lpage>1029</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jpepsy/jsr044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21745808</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Elrod</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hood</surname>
<given-names>BS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep differences among children with autism spectrum disorders and typically developing peers: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Develop Behav Pediatr</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>166</fpage>–<lpage>177</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/DBP.0000000000000140</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Díaz-Román</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Delorme</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beggiato</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cortese</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep in youth with autism spectrum disorders: systematic review and meta-analysis of subjective and objective studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Evid Based Ment Health</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>146</fpage>–<lpage>154</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/ebmental-2018-300037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30361331</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Delahaye</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kovacs</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sikora</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The relationship between health-related quality of life and sleep problems in children with autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Res Autism Spectr Disord</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>292</fpage>–<lpage>303</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rasd.2013.12.015</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Allik</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Larsson</surname>
<given-names>J-O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smedje</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia in school-age children with Asperger syndrome or high-functioning autism</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC psychiatr</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-244X-6-18</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>CR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>DeMand</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Exploring sleep quality of young children with autism spectrum disorder and disruptive behaviors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2018.01.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29530371</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shea</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Payne</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Russo</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Brief report: social functioning predicts externalizing problem behaviors in autism spectrum disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Autism Dev Disord</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2237</fpage>–<lpage>2242</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10803-017-3459-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29423607</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bornstein</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hahn</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haynes</surname>
<given-names>OM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Social competence, externalizing, and internalizing behavioral adjustment from early childhood through early adolescence: developmental cascades</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Dev Psychopathol</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>717</fpage>–<lpage>735</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0954579410000416</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20883577</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Eriksen</surname>
<given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frandsen</surname>
<given-names>TF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The impact of patient, intervention, comparison, outcome (PICO) as a search strategy tool on literature search quality: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Med Library Assoc</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>106</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>420</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5195/jmla.2018.345</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Noyes</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Booth</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Flemming</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cochrane qualitative and implementation methods group guidance series—paper 3: methods for assessing methodological limitations, data extraction and synthesis, and confidence in synthesized qualitative findings</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>97</volume>:<fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2017.06.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29247700</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aathira</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gulati</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tripathi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence of sleep abnormalities in Indian children with autism spectrum disorder: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatr Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>62</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pediatrneurol.2017.05.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28739359</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Abel</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schwichtenberg</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brodhead</surname>
<given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Christ</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and challenging behaviors in the context of intensive behavioral intervention for children with Autism</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Autism Dev Disord</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>3871</fpage>–<lpage>3884</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10803-018-3648-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29931436</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Anders</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Iosif</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schwichtenberg</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goodlin-Jones</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and daytime functioning: a short-term longitudinal study of three preschool-age comparison groups</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Intellect Dev Disabil</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>117</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>290</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1352/1944-7558-117.4.275</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22809074</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chong</surname>
<given-names>PLH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ebel</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peo</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCormick</surname>
<given-names>EB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schwichtenberg</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep dysregulation and daytime electrodermal patterns in children with autism: a Descriptive Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Genet Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fulcher</surname>
<given-names>BD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rajaratnam</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Behaviorally-determined sleep phenotypes are robustly associated with adaptive functioning in individuals with low functioning autism</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-14611-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28127051</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fulcher</surname>
<given-names>BD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rajaratnam</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep patterns predictive of daytime challenging behavior in individuals with low‐functioning autism</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Autism Res</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>391</fpage>–<lpage>403</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/aur.1899</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29197172</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fadini</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lamônica</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fett-Conte</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Influence of sleep disorders on the behavior of individuals with autism spectrum disorder.Frontiers in human neuroscience</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Hum Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>397</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnhum.2015.00347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26217212</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fletcher</surname>
<given-names>FE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Foster-Owens</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Conduit</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rinehart</surname>
<given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Riby</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cornish</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The developmental trajectory of parent-report and objective sleep profiles in autism spectrum disorder: associations with anxiety and bedtime routines</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Autism</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>493</fpage>–<lpage>503</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1362361316653365</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27354432</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gunes</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ekinci</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feyzioglu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ekinci</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kalinli</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep problems in children with autism spectrum disorder: clinical correlates and the impact of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>763</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NDT.S195738</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31040675</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Goldman</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Surdyka</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cuevas</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adkins</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malow</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Defining the sleep phenotype in children with autism</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Dev Neuropsychol</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>560</fpage>–<lpage>573</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/87565640903133509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20183719</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Goldman</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McGrew</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Richdale</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clemons</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malow</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep is associated with problem behaviors in children and adolescents with autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Res Autism Spectr Disord</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1223</fpage>–<lpage>1229</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rasd.2011.01.010</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Henderson</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barry</surname>
<given-names>TD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bader</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jordan</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The relation among sleep, routines, and externalizing behavior in children with an autism spectrum disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Res Autism Spectr Disord</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>758</fpage>–<lpage>767</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rasd.2010.09.003</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hoshino</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Watanabe</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yashima</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaneko</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kumashiro</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>An investigation on sleep disturbance of autistic children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1819.1984.tb00353.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kang</surname>
<given-names>Y-Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>X-R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>G-F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Su</surname>
<given-names>-Y-Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>P-Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep problems influence emotional/behavioral symptoms and repetitive behavior in preschool-aged children with Autism spectrum disorder in the unique social context of China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front psychiatr</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>273</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2020.00273</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kelmanson</surname>
<given-names>IA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disturbances and their associations with emotional/behavioral problems in 5-year-old boys with autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Early Child Dev Care</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>56</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gilroy</surname>
<given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leader</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Qualitative study on parents’ perspectives of the familial impact of living with a child with autism spectrum disorder who experiences insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2019.01.032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31561172</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Krakowiak</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goodlin‐Jones</surname>
<given-names>BETH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hertz‐Picciotto</surname>
<given-names>IRVA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Croen</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hansen</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep problems in children with autism spectrum disorders, developmental delays, and typical development: a population‐based study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>206</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lambert</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tessier</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rochette</surname>
<given-names>A-C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scherzer</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mottron</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Godbout</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Poor sleep affects daytime functioning in typically developing and autistic children not complaining of sleep problems: a questionnaire-based and polysomnographic study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Res Autism Spectr Disord</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>94</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rasd.2015.11.010</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>MacDuffie</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Munson</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Greenson</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al.<article-title>Sleep problems and trajectories of restricted and repetitive behaviors in children with neurodevelopmental disabilities</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Autism Dev Disord</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<page-range>3844=3856</page-range>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10803-020-04438-y</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Malhi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaur</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Singhi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sankhyan</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep dysfunction and behavioral daytime problems in children with autism spectrum disorders: a comparative study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Indian J Pediatr</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>86</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>12</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12098-018-2731-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29951780</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Malow</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adkins</surname>
<given-names>KW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McGrew</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Melatonin for sleep in children with autism: a controlled trial examining dose, tolerability, and outcomes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Autism Dev Disord</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1729</fpage>–<lpage>1737</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10803-011-1418-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22160300</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Manelis-Baram</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meiri</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ilan</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep disturbances and sensory sensitivities co-vary in a longitudinal manner in pre-school children with autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Autism Dev Disord</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0055">
        <label>55.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mazurek</surname>
<given-names>MO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dovgan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Neumeyer</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malow</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Course and predictors of sleep and co-occurring problems in children with autism spectrum disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Autism Dev Disord</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>2101</fpage>–<lpage>2115</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10803-019-03894-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30684086</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0056">
        <label>56.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McLay</surname>
<given-names>LL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>France</surname>
<given-names>KG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blampied</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Collateral child and parent effects of function‑based behavioral interventions for sleep problems in children and adolescents with autism</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Autism Dev Disord</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0057">
        <label>57.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mutluer</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Karakoc Demirkaya</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abali</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Assessment of sleep problems and related risk factors observed in Turkish children with Autism spectrum disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Autism Res</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>536</fpage>–<lpage>542</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/aur.1542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26459217</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0058">
        <label>58.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Naito</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kikuchi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yoshimura</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Atypical body movements during night in young children with autism spectrum disorder: a pilot study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-43397-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30626917</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0059">
        <label>59.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ng</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heinrich</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hodges</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Do you really lose when you snooze? Sleep correlates of externalizing and attention problems among pediatric patients with ADHD, ASD, and comorbid diagnosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Ment Health Res Intellect Disabil</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>249</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/19315864.2020.1760973</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0060">
        <label>60.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Papadopoulos</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sciberras</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hiscock</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mulraney</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McGillivray</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rinehart</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The efficacy of a brief behavioral sleep intervention in school-aged children with ADHD and comorbid autism spectrum disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Atten Disord</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>341</fpage>–<lpage>350</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1087054714568565</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25646022</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0061">
        <label>61.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Patzold</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Richdale</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tonge</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>An investigation into sleep characteristics of children with autism and Asperger’s disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Paediatr Child Health</italic></source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>528</fpage>–<lpage>533</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1440-1754.1998.00291.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9928644</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0062">
        <label>62.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Phung</surname>
<given-names>JN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goldberg</surname>
<given-names>WA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Poor sleep quality is associated with discordant peer relationships among adolescents with Autism Spectrum Disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Res Autism Spectr Disord</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rasd.2016.11.008</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0063">
        <label>63.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Saré</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>CB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between sleep deficiencies with behavioral problems in autism spectrum disorder: subtle sex differences</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Autism Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1802</fpage>–<lpage>1810</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/aur.2396</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0064">
        <label>64.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schreck</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mulick</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>AF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep problems as possible predictors of intensified symptoms of autism</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Res Dev Disabil</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ridd.2003.04.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14733976</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0065">
        <label>65.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schroder</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malow</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maras</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Pediatric prolonged-release melatonin for sleep in children with autism spectrum disorder: impact on child behavior and caregiver’s quality of life</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Autism Dev Disord</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>3218</fpage>–<lpage>3230</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10803-019-04046-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31079275</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0066">
        <label>66.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Segawa</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Katoh</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Katoh</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nomura</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Early modulation of sleep parameters and its importance in later behavior</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Dys</italic></source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>223</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0067">
        <label>67.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Thenhausen</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuss</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wiater</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schlarb</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep problems in adolescents with Asperger syndrome or high-functioning autism</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Somnologie</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>28</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11818-016-0078-0</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0068">
        <label>68.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tudor</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoffman</surname>
<given-names>CD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sweeney</surname>
<given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Children with autism: sleep problems and symptom severity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Focus Autism Other Dev Disabl</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>254</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1088357612457989</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0069">
        <label>69.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep disturbances and associated factors in Chinese children with autism spectrum disorder: a retrospective and cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Child Psychiatry Hum Dev</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>248</fpage>–<lpage>258</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10578-015-0561-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26072264</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0070">
        <label>70.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>X-L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zou</surname>
<given-names>M-Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Are gastrointestinal and sleep problems associated with behavioral symptoms of autism spectrum disorder?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>259</volume>:<fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>235</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2017.10.040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29091821</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0071">
        <label>71.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yavuz-Kodat</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reynaud</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Geoffray</surname>
<given-names>-M-M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Disturbances of continuous sleep and circadian rhythms account for behavioral difficulties in children with autism spectrum disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1978</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm9061978</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0072">
        <label>72.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Acebo</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sadeh</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seifer</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Estimating sleep patterns with activity monitoring in children and adolescents: how many nights are necessary for reliable measures?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/22.1.95</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9989370</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0073">
        <label>73.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mannion</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leader</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep problems in autism spectrum disorder: a literature review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Rev J Autism Develop Disorders</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>101</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40489-013-0009-y</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0074">
        <label>74.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Kent</surname>
<given-names>RSE</given-names></string-name>. <part-title>Prevalence of anxiety in autism spectrum disorders</part-title>. In: <source><italic toggle="yes">Anxiety in Children and Adolescents with Autism Spectrum Disorder</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Academic Press, Elsevier Inc</publisher-name>; <year>2017</year>:<fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0075">
        <label>75.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baker</surname>
<given-names>EK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Richdale</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep patterns in adults with a diagnosis of high-functioning autism spectrum disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1765</fpage>–<lpage>1774</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.5160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26237770</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0076">
        <label>76.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>van den Bergh</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scheeren</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Begeer</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koot</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Geurts</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Age related differences of executive functioning problems in everyday life of children and adolescents in the autism spectrum</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Autism Dev Disord</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1959</fpage>–<lpage>1971</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10803-014-2071-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24562693</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0077">
        <label>77.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mannion</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leader</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>An investigation of comorbid psychological disorders, sleep problems, gastrointestinal symptoms and epilepsy in children and adolescents with autism spectrum disorder: a two year follow-up</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Res Autism Spectr Disord</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>20</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rasd.2015.11.002</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0078">
        <label>78.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bos</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Diamantopoulou</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stockmann</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Begeer</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rieffe</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Emotion control predicts internalizing and externalizing behavior problems in boys with and without an autism spectrum disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Autism Dev Disord</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>2727</fpage>–<lpage>2739</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10803-018-3519-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29512017</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0079">
        <label>79.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tager-Flusberg</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Plesa Skwerer</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Joseph</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Conducting research with minimally verbal participants with autism spectrum disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Autism</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>852</fpage>–<lpage>861</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1362361316654605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27354431</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0080">
        <label>80.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Frazier</surname>
<given-names>TW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krishna</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Klingemier</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beukemann</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nawabit</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ibrahim</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A randomized, crossover trial of a novel sound-to-sleep mattress technology in children with autism and sleep difficulties</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.6398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27784416</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0081">
        <label>81.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Moore</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Evans</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hanvey</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Assessment of sleep in children with autism spectrum disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Children</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>72</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/children4080072</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0082">
        <label>82.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yavuz-Kodat</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reynaud</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Geoffray</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Validity of actigraphy compared to polysomnography for sleep assessment in children with autism spectrum disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychiatr</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<fpage>551</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2019.00551</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0083">
        <label>83.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Malow</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marzec</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McGrew</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Henderson</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stone</surname>
<given-names>WL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Characterizing sleep in children with autism spectrum disorders: a multidimensional approach</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>1563</fpage>–<lpage>1571</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/29.12.1563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17252887</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0084">
        <label>84.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hoffman</surname>
<given-names>CD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sweeney</surname>
<given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lopez-Wagner</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hodge</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nam</surname>
<given-names>CY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Botts</surname>
<given-names>BH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Children with autism: sleep problems and mothers’ stress.</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Focus Autism Other Dev Disabl</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>165</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1088357608316271</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0085">
        <label>85.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hsu</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sandford</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Delphi technique: making sense of consensus</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pract Assess, Res, Eval</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>10</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0086">
        <label>86.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liberati</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Altman</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tetzlaff</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The PRISMA statement for reporting systematic reviews and meta-analyses of studies that evaluate health care interventions: explanation and elaboration</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>62</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e1</fpage>–<lpage>e34</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2009.06.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19631507</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
