<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35698589</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">9188338</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">365988</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S365988</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Identification of Novel Genetic Variants Associated with Insomnia and Migraine Comorbidity</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">An et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">An et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2659-0478</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>An</surname>
            <given-names>Yu-Chin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tsai</surname>
            <given-names>Chia-Lin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1138-5586</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Liang</surname>
            <given-names>Chih-Sung</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>Yu-Kai</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>Guan-Yu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tsai</surname>
            <given-names>Chia-Kuang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Yi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2105-7570</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Sy-Jou</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tsai</surname>
            <given-names>Shih-Hung</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hung</surname>
            <given-names>Kuo-Sheng</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Fu-Chi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Emergency Medicine, Tri-Service General Hospital, National Defense Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line>Taipei</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan, Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Neurology, Tri-Service General Hospital, National Defense Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line>Taipei</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan, Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Psychiatry, Beitou Branch, Tri-Service General Hospital, National Defense Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line>Taipei</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan, Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Center for Precision Medicine and Genomics, Tri-Service General Hospital, National Defense Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line>Taipei</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan, Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Fu-Chi Yang, <institution>Department of Neurology, Tri-Service General Hospital, National Defense Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line>Taipei</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan, Republic of China</country>, <phone>Tel +886-2-87923311 # 88078</phone>, <fax>Fax +886-2-87927174</fax>, Email fuji-yang@yahoo.com.tw</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>07</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <fpage>1075</fpage>
      <lpage>1087</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>01</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2022 An et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>An et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Although insomnia and migraine are often comorbid, the genetic association between insomnia and migraine remains unclear. This study aimed to identify susceptibility loci associated with insomnia and migraine comorbidity.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Patients and Methods</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We performed a genome-wide association study (GWAS) involving 1063 clinical outpatients at a tertiary hospital in Taiwan. Migraineurs with and without insomnia were genotyped using the Affymetrix Axiom Genome-Wide TWB 2.0. We performed association analyses for the entire cohort and stratified patients into the following subgroups: episodic migraine (EM), chronic migraine (CM), migraine with aura (MA), and migraine without aura (MoA). Potential correlations between SNPs and clinical indices in migraine patients with insomnia were examined using multivariate regression analysis.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The SNP rs1178326 in the gene </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">HDAC9</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> was significantly associated with insomnia. In the EM, CM, MA, and MoA subgroups, we identified 30 additional susceptibility loci. Multivariate regression analysis showed that SNP rs1178326 also correlated with higher migraine frequency and the Migraine Disability Assessment (MIDAS) questionnaire score. Finally, two SNPs that had been previously reported in a major insomnia GWAS were also significant in our migraineurs, showing a concordant effect.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In this GWAS, we identified several novel loci associated with insomnia in migraineurs in a Han Chinese population in Taiwan. These results provide insights into the possible genetic basis of insomnia and migraine comorbidity.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>insomnia</kwd>
        <kwd>migraine</kwd>
        <kwd>GWAS</kwd>
        <kwd>SNP</kwd>
        <kwd>gene</kwd>
        <kwd>comorbidity</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>the Ministry of Science and Technology of Taiwan</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Tri-Service General Hospital, Taiwan</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="open-funder-registry">10.13039/501100010425</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Academia Sinica</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="open-funder-registry">10.13039/501100001869</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported partly by grants from the Ministry of Science and Technology of Taiwan (grant numbers MOST 108-2314-B-016-023- and MOST 110-2314-B-016 −036 -MY2), Tri-Service General Hospital, Taiwan (grant numbers TSGH-D-109101, TSGH-D-110048, TSGH-C111-091), and Academia Sinica (grant numbers AS-40-05-GMM, AS-GC-110-MD02).</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="3"/>
        <table-count count="12"/>
        <ref-count count="56"/>
        <page-count count="13"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Insomnia and migraine are both important worldwide health problems. According to the Global Burden of Disease report, migraine is the sixth most troublesome disease worldwide and the most common neurological disease.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Migraine attacks are episodic headaches often associated with nausea, vomiting, and sound and light sensitivity that severely impair the quality of life of migraineurs and can even lead to disability. In addition, migraine is associated with several comorbidities, such as anxiety, depression, vascular accidents, epilepsy, restless legs syndrome, stress, and sleep disorders.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Insomnia, defined as the inability to initiate or maintain sleep, is nowadays the most common sleep disorder. It affects one-third of the adult population and remarkably reduces life satisfaction.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In addition, it is associated with various complications, such as heart disease, diabetes, gastrointestinal problems, and neurological disorders.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Numerous studies reported that migraineurs have worse sleep quality than non-migraineurs and high migraine frequency is considered related to a higher prevalence of poor sleep quality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In an epidemiologic study, primary headaches, including migraine and tension headaches, were significantly associated with insomnia comorbidities with an odds ratio (OR) of 1.4–1.7.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Moreover, it has been reported that sleep interruptions can trigger migraine attacks. Besides epidemiologic evidence, migraine and insomnia might share some pathophysiological mechanisms in a bidirectional relationship. Migraine and insomnia could be associated due to the dysregulation of nervous system pathways involved in both pathologies, such as in cortical spreading depression, the trigeminovascular system, hypothalamic orexinergic system, and several kinds of neurotransmitters which play a role as mediators.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7–9</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Recent studies have shown evidence of genetic contributions to migraine and insomnia respectively, but questions remain about the shared framework of genetic influence. A recent meta-analysis study comprising 22 genome-wide association studies (GWAS) identified that the genetic factors associated with a higher risk of migraine were enriched in genes expressed in vascular and smooth muscle tissues, supporting a vascular involvement in the etiology of migraine.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Eising et al integrated migraine GWAS data with high-resolution spatial gene expression data and identified five modules involved in migraine pathophysiology.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Furthermore, several genetic studies on pediatric migraine have reported polymorphisms associated with migraine.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Similarly, numerous studies have shown novel susceptibility genes associated with insomnia. Hammerschlag et al identified three loci and seven genes associated with insomnia.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Stein et al showed that single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNP)-based heritability for insomnia disorder significantly correlated with other psychiatric and physical disorders.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Furthermore, Jansen et al reported 202 loci identifying 956 genes associated with insomnia that highlighted key brain areas implicated in this disease.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Although the co-occurrence of migraine and insomnia is widely known, to the best of our knowledge, limited studies have investigated the shared genetic variants between them, especially in the Han Chinese population. Therefore, this study aimed to identify susceptibility loci associated with insomnia and migraine in the Han Chinese population in Taiwan. In addition, we stratified patients into the following subgroups: chronic migraine (CM) versus episodic migraine (EM), and migraine with aura (MA) versus migraine without aura (MoA). To date, whether migraine with and without aura have different genetic components remains controversial, as well as whether migraine chronification is associated with specific genetic variants and with more frequent and severe insomnia symptoms. Hence, our second aim was to investigate whether independent genetic variants are associated with insomnia in the migraine subgroups.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The study protocol was approved by the Institutional Review Board of the Tri-Service General Hospital (TSGH) (TSGHIRB No.: 2-108-05-038) and performed strictly following the Declaration of Helsinki. The study was performed between October 2018 and March 2021 in a cohort of 1063 patients recruited from the neurology outpatient department at the TSGH (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). All patients provided written informed consent prior to enrollment. Each study participant completed a screening questionnaire and was subsequently interviewed by a board-certified neurologist and headache specialist (FCY). The study sample was then divided into a group with CM (≥ 15 episodes per month; n = 189) or EM (&lt; 15 episodes per month; n = 874). In addition, 298 of the 1063 study participants had MA, and 765 had MoA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Flowchart of a two-step workflow of the phenotype association analysis.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-1075-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Participant Evaluation</title>
        <sec id="s0002-s2002-s3001">
          <title>Migraine</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Migraine was diagnosed according to the criteria in the third edition of the International Classification of Headache Disorders (ICHD-3).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Patients with secondary or other concomitant primary headache disorders were excluded. The clinical characteristics of all participants diagnosed with migraine, including aura symptoms, migraine duration (years), frequency (headache day/month), family history, and headache intensity, were documented.</citation_analysis></p>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">All patients completed a standardized demographic questionnaire and the Migraine Disability Assessment questionnaire (MIDAS),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Beck Depression Inventory (BDI),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS)</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> questionnaires. The MIDAS is a questionnaire with five items that assess headache-related disabilities over the previous three months. The four-point grading system was as follows: grade I (scores ranging from 0 to 5), little or no disability; grade II (scores ranging from 6 to 10), mild disability; grade III (scores ranging from 11 to 20), moderate disability; and grade IV (21 or greater), severe disability. The BDI scores range from 0 to 63, and individuals with scores ≥ 18 are classified as depressed. The HADS has seven items related to anxiety and depression and has a maximum individual subscale score of 21.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2002-s3002">
          <title>Insomnia</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Primary insomnia disorder was diagnosed according to the criteria in the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-5)</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> after an evaluation during a clinical interview. The clinical characteristics of all participants diagnosed with primary insomnia, including insomnia duration and insomnia severity, were documented. Medical and psychiatric disorders were evaluated via structured diagnostic interviews, physical examinations, blood tests (blood cell count, thyroid, renal, and hepatic function), and urine drug testing. Patients with secondary insomnia (eg, history of heart disease, stroke, nephritis, psychiatric disorders, hypersomnia, parasomnia, brain tumor, hematoma, drug- or alcohol-related, etc.) were excluded from the study.</citation_analysis></p>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All participants completed two brief self-rated questionnaires to assess their perception of insomnia severity using the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and the Insomnia Severity Index (ISI).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The PSQI estimates sleep quality over the previous month, including 19 self-rated items combined into seven components. It has a score range of 0–21, and a final score ≥ 6 indicates sleep disturbance. The ISI score is a seven-item self-rated questionnaire that evaluates the severity and impact of insomnia symptoms in the past month. Each ISI item is rated on a scale of 0–4. The total ISI score is divided into four categories: 0–7, no clinically significant insomnia; 8–14, subthreshold insomnia; 15–21, moderate insomnia; 22–28, severe insomnia.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Genotyping and Quality Control</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Peripheral blood samples from patients with migraine were isolated in 5-mL EDTA vacutainers (BD, Plymouth, UK). Genomic DNA was extracted using the QIAamp DSP DNA Mini Kit on the QIAsymphony platform (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany). DNA quality was measured using a NanoDrop One spectrophotometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). The DNA samples were applied to the Affymetrix Axiom Genome-Wide TWB 2.0 arrays, which contain approximately 752,921 probes for a total of 686,463 SNPs. Among these SNPs, approximately 446,000 SNPs are associated with the characteristics of background genotypes in Taiwanese; approximately 105,000 SNPs are clinically relevant, whereas the rest are associated with disease features, drug response, and metabolism. The signal CEL files generated from the Axiom TWB 2.0 SNP array were transformed to genotyping data (tped and tfam files) using a Genotyping Console (Affymetrix).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All patients with migraine were grouped into different subsets using our standard demographic questionnaire. In order to evaluate the genetic association between migraine risk and insomnia risk, we performed a genotype-association analysis using PLINK based on the migraine with insomnia and migraine without insomnia groups. The P-value and odds ratio (OR) of the phenotype association study were calculated to assess the variant relationship using the chi-square allelic test with one degree of freedom. To investigate how gender may affect the relationship between migraine and insomnia, we also analyzed the association between gender factors in all migraine cohorts. Additionally, migraineurs were stratified into four groups: EM, CM, MA, and MoA, and patients in each group were further divided into subgroups according to the presence or absence of insomnia. In addition, to validate the effect direction of the variants, we selected 255 variants from a major insomnia GWAS</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> present in our SNP microarray. Among these, we genotyped 25 variants in all patients to check the trend (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=365988.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). Finally, the significant P-values lower than 10</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>−6</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> were retrieved. Intergenic variants were excluded in the subsequent analyses. In addition, variants with a Minor Allele Frequency MAF (TWB) &lt; 0.25 and OR = 0, which represent common variants among the Taiwanese, were excluded. The remaining variants were annotated with NCBI based on the RefSeq database using ANNOVAR.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Demographics</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> shows the demographic metadata of all the participants, as well as those of the migraine subgroups with or without insomnia. There were no significant differences in the proportion of EM/CM, body mass index, and years of education among the groups of migraineurs with insomnia and migraineurs without insomnia. Nevertheless, all other parameters analyzed differed significantly between the two subgroups analyzed (P &lt; 0.05).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Demographic and Clinical Data</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">All Migraine</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">All Migraine</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">P-value</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Migraine without Insomnia</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Migraine with Insomnia</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Migraine cohort</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1063</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">164</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">899</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>With aura/without aura</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">298/765</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35/129</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">263/636</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0189</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>EM/CM</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">874/189</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">143/21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">731/168</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0757</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Migraine frequency (months)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.05±7.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.68±6.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.30±7.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.44E-03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Migraine duration (years)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.54±17.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.42±17.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.12±16.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sex (male/female)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">247/816</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49/112</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">198/704</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0245</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age (years)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.61±14.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.67±14.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.33±7.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00E-04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Body mass index</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.63±4.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.65±4.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.63±4.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Education (years)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.86±3.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.23±3.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.79±3.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.097</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MIDAS score</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.26±16.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.38±13.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.12±17.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.82E-06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSQI score</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.75±4.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.73±1.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.84±3.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.06E-208</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ISI score</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.88±6.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.37±3.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.04±5.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.75E-81</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>BDI score</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.87±8.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.04±6.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.75±9.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08E-20</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HADS-anxiety score</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.59±4.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.15±3.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.04±4.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19E-18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HADS-depression score</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.19±4.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.86±3.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.61±4.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.73E-19</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Note</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: P-values were calculated using Fisher’s exact test and the </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-test.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: EM, episodic migraine; CM, chronic migraine; MIDAS, Migraine Disability Assessment Scale; PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index; ISI, Insomnia Severity Index; BDI, Beck Depression Inventory; HADS, Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Association of Insomnia in All Migraine Cohorts</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We then conducted GWAS on migraineurs stratified depending on the presence or absence of the comorbidity insomnia. The analysis yielded one significant intronic variant with a P-value &lt; 1E-06, rs1178326 (P = 5.43E-07) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). The variant allele frequency in the insomnia group was 0.50%, whereas it was 3.94% in the non-insomnia group (OR = 0.12, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Association Between All Migraine Patients Grouped by the Presence or Absence of Insomnia</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">SNP</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Position (GRCh38.p12)</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">MAF</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">TWB</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Gene</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Type</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variant Change</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Variant Allele Frequency</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">OR</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insomnia Group</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Insomnia Group</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs1178326</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr7:18195234</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDAC9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T&gt;C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.94%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12 [0.05, 0.32]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.43E-07</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: All migraine patients were grouped based on insomnia and compared using PLINK. The significant variants were listed by empirical P-value &lt; 1E-6, with the allele frequency, odds ratio (OR), and 95% confidence interval.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: MAF, Minor allele frequency in the East Asian group in dbSNP; TWB, Minor allele frequency in the Taiwan Biobank.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The distribution of variant allele frequency of the variant in (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) all migraine cohort, (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>C</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) EM, and (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>D</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) MoA groups. Boxplots of distributions between groups and genotypes. The x-axis shows the genotype of the variants, and the y-axis indicates the phenotype. The abundance of each condition in the genotypes is marked above each bar. In the entire migraine cohort (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">), we found three different distributions of the variant rs1178326 (HDAC9). The genotype TT was associated with the insomnia group, whereas the genotype CT was associated with the non-insomnia group. The genotype CC is not shown in this study. In addition, for other groups in EM and MoA, we found a similar trend of distribution of variant rs17082263 (SCFD2) and rs143607843 (IQCG) in the EM group, and rs4876117 (DLGAP2) in the MoA group.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-1075-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">When analyzing gender-associated factors, we found that in both gender groups there was only one variant associated between gender and migraine: rs145888117 (P = 7.00E-07) for the male group and rs28535526 (P = 5.12E-07) for the female group (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=365988.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 2</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). The OR trend is similar to our finding (rs1178326) in all migraine cohorts; however, the variants are not in the same position.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Association in the Subgroups in EM/CM</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Additionally, we performed an association analysis to identify the potential genetic differences between migraineurs suffering from EM and CM with and without insomnia. Two genome-wide significant (P &lt; 10</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>−6</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) SNPs were identified in the EM group (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">), and 14 variants we identified in the CM group (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). Most of these variants were intronic and presented a MAF &lt; 5%. The frequency of the significant variants in the EM and CM groups was lower in the insomnia group than that in the non-insomnia group. The OR of all these variants was lower than one.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0003" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Association Between Insomnia Subgroups: EM, CM, MA, and MoA</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Groups</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">SNP</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Position (GRCh38.p12)</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">MAF</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">TWB</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Gene</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Type</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variant Change</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Variant Allele Frequency</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">OR</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insomnia Group</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Insomnia Group</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">EM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs17082263</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr4:53005816</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCFD2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C&gt;T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.46%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.093 [0.03,0.27]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs143607943</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr3:197898149</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0076</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IQCG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C&gt;T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.68%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032 [0.00,0.26]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.37E-07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="14" colspan="1">CM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs17009732</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr4:125465671</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FAT4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A&gt;G</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.67%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 [0,0.17]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.59E-09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs3785860</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr17:61286196</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BCAS3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T&gt;G</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 [0.01,0.20]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.01E-08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs117254988</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr17:81271302</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SLC38A10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G&gt;A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.15%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.67%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09 [0.03,0.26]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27E-07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs143572955</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr6:22054437</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CASC15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ncRNA_intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A&gt;G</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.67%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 [0.007,0.22]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28E-07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs113567972</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr5:152265953</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LINC01933</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ncRNA_intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G&gt;A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.33%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 [0.0028,0.24]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.46E-07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs150577542</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr7:103724411</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RELN</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-&gt;AT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.33%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 [0.003,0.24]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.46E-07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs76585997</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr7:129721275</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NRF1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G&gt;A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.33%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 [0.003,0.24]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.46E-07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs150819573</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr15:59507459</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FAM81A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G&gt;A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.33%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 [0.003,0.24]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.46E-07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs117776222</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr1:234086299</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SLC35F3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G&gt;A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.33%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 [0.003,0.24]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.86E-07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs76358129</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr5:152246648</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LINC01933</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ncRNA_intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T&gt;C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.33%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 [0.003,0.24]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.86E-07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs113929593</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr5:152265017</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LINC01933</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ncRNA_intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A&gt;G</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.33%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 [0.003,0.24]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.86E-07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs74526104</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr11:117575288</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.066</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSCAML1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A&gt;G</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.72%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12 [0.044,0.31]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.64E-07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs141086120</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chrX:65489841</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZC3H12B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C&gt;T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.23%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 [0.012,0.25]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.99E-07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs3094584</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr6:31416071</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.185</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.077</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MICA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Downstream</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G&gt;A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.76%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.33%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09 [0.03,0.29]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.50E-07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="13" colspan="1">MA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs3763971</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr11:34150834</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABTB2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Downstream</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G&gt;C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.049 [0.01,0.20]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.12E-09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs78345995</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr8:118640335</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0096</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SAMD12-AS1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ncRNA intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G&gt;C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039 [0.01,0.20]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51E-08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs74383774</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr11:11875451</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.087</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">USP47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C&gt;T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.24%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 [0.07,0.31]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90E-08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs12026894</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr1:245268001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.075</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">KIF26B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G&gt;A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.28%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16 [0.08,0.33]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.74E-08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs28382698</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chrX:55009628</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALAS2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A&gt;G</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.63%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.052 [0.01,0.22]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.54E-08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs76268860</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr10:69260819</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HKDC1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A&gt;G</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.09%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.097 [0.04,0.27]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.34E-08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs3120649</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr1:152311335</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FLG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exonic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G&gt;A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 [0.009,0.25]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.02E-07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs78315102</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr4:169932700</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LINC02275</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ncRNA_intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G&gt;A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 [0.009,0.25]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.02E-07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs77108059</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr10:14584991</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FAM107B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T&gt;A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 [0.009,0.25]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.02E-07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs190376766</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr14:61899133</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SYT16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T&gt;C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 [0.009,0.25]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.02E-07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs141176236</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr5:103529675</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LINC02115</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ncRNA_intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G&gt;A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.62%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12 [0.05,0.32]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.10E-07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs9365252</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr6:161113583</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAP3K4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C&gt;T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.57%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.58%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09 [0.03,0.29]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.95E-07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs12045578</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr1:245247818</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.076</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">KIF26B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G&gt;T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.97%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17 [0.07,0.37]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.50E-07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MoA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs4876117</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr8:1654231</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.059</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DLGAP2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G&gt;A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.14%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31 [0.20,0.50]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.03E-07</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: A phenotype association study was performed on all migraine cohorts of the insomnia group and then grouped based on four conditions: EM, CM, aura, and without aura. Significant variants with P-value &lt; 1E-6 are listed with the allele frequency, odds ratio (OR), and 95% confidence interval.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0006"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: EM, episodic migraine; CM, chronic migraine; MA, migraine with aura; MoA, migraine without aura; MAF, minor allele frequency of East Asian group in dbSNP; TWB, minor allele frequency in Taiwan Biobank.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Variant frequency and odds ratio (OR) in the subgroups episodic migraine (EM), chronic migraine (CM), migraine with aura (MA), and migraine without aura (MoA). The x-axis shows the genome-wide significant variants found in the association analysis of EM vs CM (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) and MA vs MoA (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">), also reported in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. The y-axis shows the variant allele frequency in the insomnia group. The diameter of the circles represents the OR of each variant.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-1075-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Association in the Subgroups in MA/MoA</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Moreover, we performed association analyses between the migraineurs with and without aura and with and without insomnia. In the MA group, 13 variants were genome-wide significant, whereas only one variant was significant in the MoA group (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). The patterns found in the MA/MoA group were similar to those in the EM/CM group, with odds ratios lower than one. Additionally, these variants related to migraineurs tended to occur more frequently in the non-insomnia group as compared to those in the insomnia group.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2005">
        <title>Multivariate Association Study</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We then performed a multivariate regression analysis on migraine frequency, MIDAS, ISI, BDI, HADS-anxiety, and HADS-depression scores. In all migraine cohorts, SNP rs1178326 showed a significant association between migraine frequency and MIDAS (P = 0.006, 0.004; OR = 0.73, 1.16; 95% confidence interval = 0.59–0.91, 1.05–1.28, respectively).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2006">
        <title>Replication Study</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Finally, we aimed to validate the results of a previous major GWAS on insomnia. For this purpose, we selected 25 loci present in a TWB2 SNP array (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=365988.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) and analyzed them in all migraineurs. Among the SNPs tested, rs10947428 and rs728017 were significantly different between insomnia and non-insomnia migraineurs (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). The odds ratios associated with both markers were lower than one (0.04 and 0.19, respectively), indicating that the variant allele seemingly appeared more frequently in the non-insomnia group rather than that in the insomnia group.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0004" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Replication of Findings in a Previous Major Insomnia GWAS</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">SNP</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Position (GRCh38.p12)</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">MAF</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">TWB</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Gene</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Type</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variant Change</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Variant Allele Frequency</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">OR</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Source</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insomnia Group</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Insomnia Group</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs10947428</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr6:33679281</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ITPR3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T&gt;C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.67%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 [0.0036,0.52]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.71E-04</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Jasen, P.R. et al. Nat Genet (2019)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs728017</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chr6:123971449</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.073</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NKAIN2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intronic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A&gt;G</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.03%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19 [0.042,0.88]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0007"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Note</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: The profiles of variants reported in a previous large GWAS were found in all migraine cohorts of the insomnia group.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0008"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: MAF, minor allele frequency of the East Asian group in dbSNP; TWB, minor allele frequency in the Taiwan Biobank.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Here, we analyzed 1063 migraineurs stratified into patients with and without insomnia and found that the rs1178326 variant in the </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">HDAC9</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> gene was significantly associated with insomnia. Additionally, we stratified the migraineurs depending on the frequency of the symptoms (EM vs CM) and the presence of an aura (MA vs MoA), further comparing differences between patients with and without insomnia in each subgroup. Two, 14, 13, and 1 SNP in the EM, CM, MA, and MoA groups, respectively, were significantly associated with insomnia. Multivariate regression analysis indicated that the SNP rs1178326 was also significantly associated with migraine frequency and MIDAS scores. Moreover, we replicated the association and the direction of the effects of two SNPs (rs10947428 in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">ITPR3</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and rs728017 in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">NKAIN2</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) that were significant in a previous insomnia GWAS.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In the demographic and clinical data (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">), the MIDAS, ISI, PSQI, HADS, and BDI questionnaire responses differed significantly between the two groups. Our results are consistent with previous studies, which have indicated that the co-existed comorbidity of anxiety and depression significantly correlates with a higher prevalence of poor sleep quality in migraineurs.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">HDAC9</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> encodes histone deacetylase 9 (HDAC9), a member of the class II HDAC family that plays key roles in numerous tissues by regulating histone phosphorylation, thereby shaping the transcriptional landscape. The human </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">HDAC9</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> gene is located on chromosome 7p21 and is highly expressed in the heart, muscles, and brain. HDAC9 has been implicated in numerous pathophysiological processes, including neurological disorders, cardiac growth, T-regulatory cell function, muscle differentiation, and cancers.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Several reports investigated the association between </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">HDAC9</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> and the risk of ischemic stroke or coronary artery disease in the Han Chinese population.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">HDAC9</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> gene deficiency may attenuate atherosclerosis and increase risk by altering ischemic brain responses and neuronal survival.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Recently, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">HDAC9</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> was reported as a potential causal link between insomnia and coronary artery disease.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Besides, a Mendelian randomization analysis showed that short sleep duration and frequent insomnia symptoms are associated with a subtype of ischemic stroke.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Sleep deprivation may increase HDAC expression in the hippocampus, adversely affecting structural and functional synaptic plasticity and memory formation, leading to spatial memory decline, which could be reversed by HDAC inhibition.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Therefore, we hypothesized that </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">HDAC9</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> is functionally involved in migraine and insomnia through the dysregulation of the cardiovascular system. Further research is necessary to elucidate the specific mechanism of the insomnia-related </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">HDAC9</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> variant in migraineurs.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In the EM group, we found two insomnia-related SNPs (rs17082263 in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">SCFD2</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and rs143607943 in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">IQCG</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). SCFD2 encodes Sec1 family domain-containing protein 2, a protein involved in protein transport and vesicle docking during exocytosis. Despite previous studies that implicated </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">SCFD2</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> as a susceptibility gene for insomnia,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> later studies failed to fully replicate these results.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">IQCG</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> encodes the IQ motif-containing G protein, which interacts with several proteins and contributes to regulating calcium and calmodulin-dependent protein kinase IV activity, neuronal polarized growth and plasticity, fertilization, mitosis, and cytoskeletal organization.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The SNP in rs9880989 in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">IQCG</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> was identified among the top ten susceptibility loci associated with migraine in bipolar disorder.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Although </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">IQCG</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> may also be involved in insomnia and migraine, further studies are warranted to unravel underlying mechanisms.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In the CM group, 14 SNPs were associated with insomnia. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">SLC38A10</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> encodes a member of the solute carrier (SLC) family. Hundreds of SLC genes have been identified in the brain, contributing to the transport of sugars, amino acids, vitamins, neurotransmitters, and inorganic/metal ions. SLC38A10 acts as a glutamate transporter and can affect neuronal viability by protecting against glutamate toxicity and oxidative stress.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Mounting evidence suggests that glutamate excitotoxicity contributes to migraine and insomnia.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> As glutamate transporters could be novel therapeutic targets, it is necessary to further explore the role of </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">SLC38A10</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> in these disorders. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">RELN</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> encodes reelin, an extracellular matrix glycoprotein controlling cell-cell interactions, critical for cell positioning and neuronal migration during brain development. Reelin is reportedly involved in several neuropsychiatric disorders, including schizophrenia, bipolar disorder, major depression, autism, and Alzheimer’s disease.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Reduced </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">RELN</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> expression may contribute to epilepsy pathogenesis and is considered a shared causal pathway between migraine and epilepsy.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">NRF1</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> encodes nuclear respiratory factor 1, which is involved in the transcription of oxidative phosphorylation components. NRF1 activates the expression of several metabolic genes and is upregulated during sleep deprivation.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Zhu et al demonstrated that </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">NRF1</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> positively regulates numerous circadian genes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Furthermore, Li et al identified that </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">NRF1</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> affects sleep initiation and may regulate the human GABA receptor subtype A β1 subunit gene in neurons, which is associated with epilepsy, autism, bipolar disorder, and schizophrenia.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Finally, we found three SNPs in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">LINC01933</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">, encoding a long non-coding RNA. A recent study reported altered expression of </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">LINC01933</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> in the brain, which was associated with sleeping-related loci 5 in the Neanderthal population.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Further studies are necessary to investigate the potential involvement of these genes in insomnia and the CM group.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In the MA group, we found 13 SNPs associated with insomnia. Two SNPs were in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">KIF26B</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, which encodes the Kinesin Family Member 26 B. Kinesins are transporters of membranous organelles in mammalian neurons.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In a GWAS of sleep duration, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">KIF26B</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> was reportedly associated with a short sleep duration of fewer than 6 hours.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In addition, Hautakangas et al performed a genome-wide meta-analysis of migraine and found a lead SNP in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">KIF26B</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">, although not significant in the MA subgroup.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">MAP3K4</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> encodes mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) kinase 4. MAPK pathways are involved in regulating calcitonin gene-related peptide (CGRP) release, a migraine-related neuropeptide secreted by the trigeminal ganglion.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Suppressing MAPK/NF‑кB signaling could attenuate migraine in a nitroglycerin-induced rat model.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Furthermore, Zhang et al found that substance P may activate MAPK pathways in satellite glial cells of the trigeminal ganglion, contributing to inflammatory orofacial pain associated with peripheral sensitization.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Moreover, substance P seemingly initiates and perpetuates cortical spreading depression, an electrophysiological phenomenon associated with MA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Additionally, substance P may influence the increase of REM latency and time awake, leading to a central arousing effect.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Overall, these studies support a potential link between MA and insomnia. Besides </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">KIF26B</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">MAP3K4</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">, other significant loci did not present a clear link between migraine and insomnia, highlighting the need for further research.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In the MoA group, we identified rs4876117 in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">DLGAP2</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> associated with insomnia. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">DLGAP2</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> encodes Discs Large Homolog Associated Protein 2. It was initially identified as a candidate gene for mental retardation and post-traumatic stress disorder affecting the hippocampus and was recently associated with schizophrenia and Alzheimer’s disease. DLGAPs are expressed in the postsynapse, interact with several proteins, and are involved in the function of NMDA, AMPA, and glutamate receptors.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In addition, Catusi et al studied patients with 8p23.2-pter microdeletions, suggesting that </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">DLGAP2</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> deregulation may influence other families of post-synaptic scaffolding proteins. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">DLGAP2</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> is considered a strong candidate for neurodevelopmental/behavioral phenotypes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Moreover, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">DLGAP2</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> was an affected gene in an established murine model of CM triggered by nitroglycerin. Disruption of glutamatergic and dopaminergic synapses and rhythmic processes in the trigeminal ganglia and the nucleus accumbens may be a mechanism associated with migraine but require further validation.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">When investigating the association between gender effects on migraineurs with insomnia, we found one variant in each gender, rs145888117 in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">CDC14B</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> for the male group and rs28535526 in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">TAFA5</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> for the female group. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">CDC14B</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> encodes Cell Division Cycle 14B, a member of the dual-specificity protein tyrosine phosphatase family, involved in the exit of cell mitosis and regulation of DNA damage repair.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Furthermore, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">CDC14B</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> was shown to exhibit oncogenic characteristics in mammals via Ras-MAPK cascade.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The association of </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">CDC14B</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> in male migraineurs with insomnia may need more validation via MAPK pathways. </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">TAFA5</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> encodes TAFA Chemokine Like Family Member 5, a member of the TAFA family, and was found highly expressed in the embryonic and postnatal mouse brain, especially in the hippocampus. Genetic deletion of </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">TAFA5</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> may contribute to an increase in depressive-like behaviors and significantly reduce glutamate release and neuronal activity in the hippocampus.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Whether migraine, insomnia, and depression share similar pathogenesis via </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">TAFA5</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, especially in females, is warranted for further validation.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Multivariate regression analysis showed that SNP rs1178326 in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">HDAC9</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> was also significantly associated with higher migraine frequency and MIDAS scores, a clue that this locus plays an important role in migraine with insomnia. Further larger studies are warranted to investigate </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">HDAC9</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> in the association of migraine and insomnia with their frequency and intensity.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">To validate our results, we selected 255 variants from a major insomnia GWAS</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> to the same SNP microarray. Out of 255, 25 SNPs in the TWB2 SNP arrays, SNPs rs10947428 in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">ITPR3</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and rs728017 in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">NKAIN2</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> were significantly detected in the migraine cohort of the insomnia group. Furthermore, although the allele frequencies in Taiwan Biobank and UK Biobank differed, our results are consistent with the previous study.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our study had several strengths. First, we had a carefully chosen population in which migraine and insomnia were diagnosed by qualified neurologists according to a strictly audited protocol. Second, we evaluated individuals using validated questionnaires, sleep quality, migraine frequency, and comorbidities like anxiety and depression. Multivariate regression analysis and stratified analysis of migraine subgroups enabled the investigation of the genetic association of insomnia in migraineurs. Third, Affymetrix’s Axiom Genome-Wide TWB 2.0 array covers a highly representative sample of the gene pool in Taiwan. Our results also showed different allele frequencies in other populations in previous major studies. Nonetheless, this study also had limitations. The statistical power was limited due to the relatively modest sample size. Further studies with larger sample sizes and a more diverse population are warranted to enhance external validity and extend these results in the future.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In conclusion, our study revealed that the SNP rs1178326 located in the </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">HDAC9</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> gene was significantly associated with insomnia in a cohort of migraineurs from the Han Chinese population in Taiwan. Furthermore, several novel susceptibility loci associated with insomnia were identified in subgroups EM, CM, MA, and MoA. These results provide insights into the possible genetic basis of insomnia and migraine. Further larger studies are warranted to investigate these genes in shared pathogenesis to obtain definitive evidence.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors thank the participants and investigators from Taiwan Precision Medicine Initiative, the Center for Precision Medicine and Genomics of Tri-Service General Hospital, National Defense Medical Center, and Genetics Generation Advancement Corporation for their assistance with genetic testing and statistical analysis.</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">All data are available from the corresponding author upon request.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis, and interpretation, or in all these areas; took part in drafting, revising, or critically reviewing the article; gave final approval of the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0008">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors declare that they have no competing interests in this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Global Burden of Disease Study C</collab>. <article-title>Global, regional, and national incidence, prevalence, and years lived with disability for 301 acute and chronic diseases and injuries in 188 countries, 1990–2013: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2013</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>386</volume>(<issue>9995</issue>):<fpage>743</fpage>–<lpage>800</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(15)60692-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26063472</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>YK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>GY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Associations between sleep quality and migraine frequency: a cross-sectional case-control study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Medicine</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>95</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>e3554</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000003554</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27124064</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>An</surname>
<given-names>YC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liang</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of Sex and adaptation on migraine frequency and perceived stress: a cross-sectional case-control study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>598</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fneur.2019.00598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31231306</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zeitlhofer</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schmeiser-Rieder</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tribl</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep and quality of life in the Austrian population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Neurol Scand</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>102</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>257</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1600-0404.2000.102004249.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11071111</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Byrne</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The relationship between insomnia and complex diseases-insights from genetic data</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Genome Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>57</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13073-019-0668-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31466529</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Uhlig</surname>
<given-names>BL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Engstrom</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Odegard</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hagen</surname>
<given-names>KK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sand</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Headache and insomnia in population-based epidemiological studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cephalalgia</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>745</fpage>–<lpage>751</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0333102414540058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24973418</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tiseo</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vacca</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Felbush</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Migraine and sleep disorders: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Headache Pain</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>126</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s10194-020-01192-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33109076</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dodick</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eross</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parish</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Silber</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Clinical, anatomical, and physiologic relationship between sleep and headache</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Headache</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>282</fpage>–<lpage>292</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1526-4610.2003.03055.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12603650</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Holland</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barloese</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fahrenkrug</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>PACAP in hypothalamic regulation of sleep and circadian rhythm: importance for headache</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Headache Pain</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>20</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s10194-018-0844-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29508090</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gormley</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Anttila</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Winsvold</surname>
<given-names>BS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Meta-analysis of 375,000 individuals identifies 38 susceptibility loci for migraine</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Genet</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>856</fpage>–<lpage>866</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27322543</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Eising</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huisman</surname>
<given-names>SMH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mahfouz</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Gene co-expression analysis identifies brain regions and cell types involved in migraine pathophysiology: a GWAS-based study using the Allen Human Brain Atlas</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hum Genet</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>135</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>425</fpage>–<lpage>439</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00439-016-1638-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26899160</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pellegrino</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garifallou</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Common variants at 5q33.1 predispose to migraine in African-American children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Med Genet</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>831</fpage>–<lpage>836</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jmedgenet-2018-105359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30266756</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Koute</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Michalopoulou</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Siokas</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Val66Met polymorphism is associated with decreased likelihood for pediatric headache and migraine</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurol Res</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32856546</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hammerschlag</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stringer</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Leeuw</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Genome-wide association analysis of insomnia complaints identifies risk genes and genetic overlap with psychiatric and metabolic traits</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Genet</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1584</fpage>–<lpage>1592</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28604731</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stein</surname>
<given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCarthy</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>CY</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Genome-wide analysis of insomnia disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2238</fpage>–<lpage>2250</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41380-018-0033-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29520036</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jansen</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Watanabe</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stringer</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Genome-wide analysis of insomnia in 1,331,010 individuals identifies new risk loci and functional pathways</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Genet</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>394</fpage>–<lpage>403</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-018-0333-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30804565</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Headache Classification Committee of the International Headache S</collab>. <article-title>The international classification of headache disorders, 3rd edition (beta version)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cephalalgia</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>808</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0333102413485658</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23771276</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stewart</surname>
<given-names>WF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lipton</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dowson</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sawyer</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Development and testing of the Migraine Disability Assessment (MIDAS) Questionnaire to assess headache-related disability</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>6 Suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>S20</fpage>–<lpage>S28</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.56.suppl_1.S20</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11294956</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Beck</surname>
<given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ward</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mendelson</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mock</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Erbaugh</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>An inventory for measuring depression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Gen Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>1961</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>561</fpage>–<lpage>571</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archpsyc.1961.01710120031004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13688369</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zigmond</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Snaith</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Psychiatr Scand</italic></source>. <year>1983</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>361</fpage>–<lpage>370</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0447.1983.tb09716.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6880820</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Regier</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuhl</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kupfer</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The DSM-5: classification and criteria changes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">World Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>92</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wps.20050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23737408</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>CF</given-names> 3rd</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monk</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berman</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kupfer</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Pittsburgh sleep quality index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0165-1781(89)90047-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2748771</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bastien</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vallieres</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morin</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Validation of the Insomnia Severity Index as an outcome measure for insomnia research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>307</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1389-9457(00)00065-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11438246</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vgontzas</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cui</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Merikangas</surname>
<given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Are sleep difficulties associated with migraine attributable to anxiety and depression?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Headache</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1451</fpage>–<lpage>1459</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1526-4610.2008.01175.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18624714</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yeung</surname>
<given-names>WF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>KF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>CY</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Relationship between insomnia and headache in community-based middle-aged Hong Kong Chinese women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Headache Pain</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>195</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10194-010-0199-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20186559</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yuan</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Radhakrishnan</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seto</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Histone deacetylase 9 (HDAC9) regulates the functions of the ATDC (TRIM29) protein</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Biol Chem</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>285</volume>(<issue>50</issue>):<fpage>39329</fpage>–<lpage>39338</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M110.179333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20947501</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guan</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The association between HDAC9 gene polymorphisms and stroke risk in the Chinese population: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>41538</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep41538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28145521</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dong</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yuan</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Polymorphism of HDAC9 gene is associated with increased risk of acute coronary syndrome in Chinese Han population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biomed Res Int</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>2016</volume>:<fpage>3746276</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2016/3746276</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27642596</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lane</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dashti</surname>
<given-names>HS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Biological and clinical insights from genetics of insomnia symptoms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Genet</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>387</fpage>–<lpage>393</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-019-0361-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30804566</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Korostovtseva</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Ischemic stroke and sleep: the linking genetic factors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cardiol Ther</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>349</fpage>–<lpage>375</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40119-021-00231-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34191267</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Duan</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Histone acetylation regulation in sleep deprivation-induced spatial memory impairment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurochem Res</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2223</fpage>–<lpage>2232</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11064-016-1937-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27161370</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bahler</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rhoads</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Calmodulin signaling via the IQ motif</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">FEBS Lett</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>513</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-5793(01)03239-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11911888</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Knott</surname>
<given-names>SV</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Investigating Susceptibility to Bipolar Disorder, Migraine and Epilepsy</italic></source>
<source>Doctoral dissertation</source>. <publisher-name>PhD degree in School of Medicine, Cardiff University</publisher-name>; <year>2016</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tripathi</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aggarwal</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fredriksson</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>SLC38A10 transporter plays a role in cell survival under oxidative stress and glutamate toxicity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Mol Biosci</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>671865</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmolb.2021.671865</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34026845</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gasparini</surname>
<given-names>CF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Griffiths</surname>
<given-names>LR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The biology of the glutamatergic system and potential role in migraine</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Biomed Sci</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23675283</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mormile</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mazzei</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vittori</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Michele</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Squarcia</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia and shift-work sleep disorder: a crosstalk between glutamate excitotoxicity and decreased GABAergic neurotransmission?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Biol Rhythms</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>340</fpage>–<lpage>341</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1479-8425.2012.00574.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Guidotti</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grayson</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caruncho</surname>
<given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Epigenetic RELN dysfunction in schizophrenia and related neuropsychiatric disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Cell Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>89</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fncel.2016.00089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27092053</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Eising</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>A Datson</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van den Maagdenberg</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferrari</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Epigenetic mechanisms in migraine: a promising avenue?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Med</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>26</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1741-7015-11-26</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23379668</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Basheer</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McKenna</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Strecker</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCarley</surname>
<given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Control of sleep and wakefulness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiol Rev</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>92</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1087</fpage>–<lpage>1187</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physrev.00032.2011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22811426</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mechanisms and Functional Roles of Nuclear Respiratory Factor 1 (NRF1) Binding Sites in the Human Genome</italic></source>
<source>doctoral dissertation</source>. <publisher-name>PhD degree in School of Public Health, University of Pittsburgh</publisher-name>; <year>2011</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cogswell</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hixson</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brooks-Kayal</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Russek</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Nuclear respiratory factor 1 (NRF-1) controls the activity dependent transcription of the GABA-A receptor Beta 1 subunit gene in neurons</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Mol Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>285</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnmol.2018.00285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30186109</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dannemann</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Milaneschi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yermakovich</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Neandertal introgression dissects the genetic landscape of neuropsychiatric disorders and associated behavioral phenotypes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">medRxiv</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>54</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aizawa</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sekine</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Takemura</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nangaku</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hirokawa</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Kinesin family in murine central nervous system</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cell Biol</italic></source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>119</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1287</fpage>–<lpage>1296</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.119.5.1287</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1447303</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lahtinen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Puttonen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vanttola</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A distinctive DNA methylation pattern in insufficient sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1193</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-38009-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30718923</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hautakangas</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Winsvold</surname>
<given-names>BS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruotsalainen</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Genome-wide analysis of 102,084 migraine cases identifies 123 risk loci and subtype-specific risk alleles</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">medRxiv</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>e34</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lei</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yuan</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Mitogen-activated protein kinase pathways are involved in the upregulation of calcitonin gene-related peptide of rat trigeminal ganglion after organ culture</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Mol Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12031-012-9772-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22528462</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lai</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lv</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ge</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Rhynchophylline attenuates migraine in trigeminal nucleus caudalis in nitroglycerin-induced rat model by inhibiting MAPK/NF-small ka, CyrillicB signaling</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Cell Biochem</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>461</volume>(<issue>1–2</issue>):<fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>212</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11010-019-03603-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31420791</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Activation of mitogen-activated protein kinases in satellite glial cells of the trigeminal ganglion contributes to substance P-mediated inflammatory pain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Oral Sci</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>24</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41368-019-0055-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31501412</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Richter</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eitner</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leuchtweis</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The potential of substance P to initiate and perpetuate cortical spreading depression (CSD) in rat in vivo</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>17656</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-36330-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30518958</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lieb</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ahlvers</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dancker</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of the neuropeptide substance P on sleep, mood, and neuroendocrine measures in healthy young men</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropsychopharmacology</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1041</fpage>–<lpage>1049</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0893-133X(02)00369-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12464461</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rasmussen</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rasmussen</surname>
<given-names>HB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Silahtaroglu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The DLGAP family: neuronal expression, function and role in brain disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Brain</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>43</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13041-017-0324-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28870203</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Catusi</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garzo</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Capra</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>8p23.2-pter microdeletions: seven new cases narrowing the candidate region and review of the literature</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Genes</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>652</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/genes12050652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33925474</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jeong</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moye</surname>
<given-names>LS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Southey</surname>
<given-names>BR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Gene network dysregulation in the trigeminal ganglia and nucleus accumbens of a model of chronic migraine-associated hyperalgesia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Syst Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>63</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnsys.2018.00063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30618656</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ha</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cdc14A and Cdc14B redundantly regulate DNA double-strand break repair</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Cell Biol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):<fpage>3657</fpage>–<lpage>3668</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.00233-15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26283732</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0055">
        <label>55.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A phosphatase turns aggressive: the oncogenicity of Cdc14B</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cell Cycle</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>2414</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/cc.10.15.15887</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0056">
        <label>56.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>FAM19A5/TAFA5, a novel neurokine, plays a crucial role in depressive-like and spatial memory-related behaviors in mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2363</fpage>–<lpage>2379</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41380-020-0720-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32317715</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
