<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35832389</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">9271684</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">369614</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S369614</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>High Rapid Eye Movement Sleep Apnea Hypopnea Index is Associated with Hypertension in Patients with Obstructive Sleep Apnea</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Wang et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Wang et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Le</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wei</surname>
            <given-names>Donghui</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Jing</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6058-4608</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Cao</surname>
            <given-names>Jie</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Xinxin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Respiratory and Critical Care, Tianjin Medical University General Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Tianjin</addr-line>, <country>The People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Endocrinology and Metabolism, Tianjin Medical University General Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Tianjin</addr-line>, <country>The People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Jing Zhang; Jie Cao, <institution>Department of Respiratory and Critical Care, Tianjin Medical University General Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Tianjin</addr-line>, <addr-line>300052</addr-line>, <country>The People’s Republic of China</country>, <phone>Tel +86 02260361612</phone>; <phone>Tel +86 02260361612</phone>, Email tjzyyzhangjing@163.com; tjcaojie@163.com</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>06</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <fpage>1249</fpage>
      <lpage>1258</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>06</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>29</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2022 Wang et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Wang et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) plays an important role in the pathogenesis of hypertension. The aim of this cross-sectional study was to explore the clinical and polysomnographic characteristics of OSA patients with hypertension and to explore the gender differences in the relationship between rapid eye movement (REM) OSA and hypertension.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Patients and Methods</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">A total of 808 patients with OSA at a tertiary hospital were enrolled in this study, and OSA patients were divided into groups presenting with or without hypertension. The clinical and polysomnographic characteristics were compared between the groups. Multivariate binary logistic analysis was performed to assess the association between REM OSA and hypertension.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">After adjustment for potential confounders, the risk of hypertension in patients with OSA increased with severity categories of apnea hypopnea index during rapid eye movement sleep stage (REM AHI) (OR = 1.61 for REM AHI ≥58.87 events/h relative to REM AHI &lt;30.50 events/h, 95% CI 1.07–2.42, P = 0.022). Consistent with this, when taken as a continuous variable, this association still remains significant (OR = 1.007, 95% CI 1.001–1.014, P &lt; 0.05). This effect was more pronounced in women patients, the OR for REM AHI ≥57.24 events/h relative to REM AHI &lt;30.36 events/h was 2.79 (95% CI, 1.16–6.73; P = 0.022); however, there was no significant difference in male patients.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">REM AHI was significantly and positively associated with hypertension in patients with OSA, and the effect was more pronounced in female patients.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>hypertension</kwd>
        <kwd>obstructive sleep apnea</kwd>
        <kwd>apnea hypopnea index during rapid eye movement sleep</kwd>
        <kwd>risk factor</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="3"/>
        <table-count count="9"/>
        <ref-count count="29"/>
        <page-count count="10"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) is a common sleep-related breathing disorder characterized by repeated partial or complete collapse of the upper airway. Nearly one billion adults 30 to 69 years of age worldwide reportedly have OSA, and the number of affected individuals is highest in China, followed by the United States, Brazil, and India.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> OSA poses a threat to the cardiovascular system due to its adverse effects of intermittent hypoxemia and hypercapnia, sleep fragmentation, increased oxidative stress, excessive inflammatory response and frequent changes in intrathoracic pressure, leading to increased overall morbidity and mortality rates.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Hypertension is one of the most prevalent cardiovascular diseases associated with OSA. It has been estimated that more than 50% of patients with OSA have underlying hypertension.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Moreover, the prevalence of OSA is greater than 30% among patients with hypertension, and as high as 80% among patients with resistant hypertension.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> OSA is also associated with essential hypertension (mild OSA: OR = 1.184; moderate OSA: OR = 1.316; severe OSA: OR = 1.561; all: </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">&lt;0.05).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> It is important to understand the pathophysiological link between OSA and hypertension, which can provide a theoretical basis for better prevention and treatment of hypertension in patients with OSA.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Repeated intermittent hypoxia and increased sympathetic activity are widely considered to be the major mechanisms by which OSA increases cardiovascular risk.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> It has been acknowledged that rapid eye movement (REM) sleep is associated with more frequent and prolonged apnea events, greater oxygen desaturation, and greater sympathetic activity than non-rapid eye movement (NREM) sleep, resulting in more frequent and greater fluctuations of blood pressure (BP).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Some studies have suggested a significant association between REM-OSA and hypertension.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9–12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Moreover, REM OSA occurs more often in women than in men due to the differences in airway structure and gender hormones.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> However, only few studies have focused on gender differences in the relationship between REM OSA and hypertension.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Therefore, the objective of this cross-sectional study was to investigate the clinical and polysomnographic characteristics of OSA patients with hypertension, as well as to explore the gender differences in the relationship between REM OSA and hypertension.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Study Subjects</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The medical records of a total of 808 patients diagnosed with OSA at the sleep center of Tianjin Medical University General Hospital from January 1, 2017, to December 31, 2020, were reviewed. Patients who fulfilled any of the following criteria were excluded: age &lt;18 years; severe cardiopulmonary or other diseases that may lead to hypoxia; previous treatment for sleep-disordered breathing; central/mixed sleep apnea diagnosed by polysomnography (PSG); incomplete data; and total sleep time &lt; 4h. The study protocol was approved by the Medical Ethics Committee of Tianjin Medical University General Hospital (IRB No.2020-WZ-091), and the procedures followed were in accordance with the principles of the Helsinki Declaration in 1995, as revised in 2013. The requirement for informed consent was waived because the patients’ information was extracted from electronic medical records at the sleep center, and the patients’ identities were maintained anonymous.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Covariates</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Demographic and anthropometric data, including gender, age, smoking habit, alcohol consumption, medical history, family medical history, height, weight, neck circumference (NC), waist circumference (WC), systolic blood pressure (SBP), and diastolic blood pressure (DBP), were obtained from medical records. Body mass index (BMI) was calculated as weight divided by the square of the height (Kg/m</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">), waist-to-height ratio (WHtR) was calculated as waist circumference divided by height, and A Body Shape Index (ABSI) was calculated using the following formula: ABSI = WC/(BMI</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2/3</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">*height</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>1/2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) (m</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>11/6</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Kg</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>−2/3</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Polysomnography</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Daytime sleepiness was assessed based on the Epworth sleepiness scale (ESS) score. Standard PSG (Alice 5 Diagnostic Sleep System; Philips Respironics, Bend, OR, USA) was performed at the sleep center of our hospital. Sixteen channels were used simultaneously to perform the following tests: electroencephalography, electrooculography, submental and leg electromyography, electrocardiography, airflow in the mouth and nose (thermistor, nasal pressure transducer), chest and abdominal respiratory efforts, blood oxygen saturation (pulse oximetry), snoring, and body position parameters. PSG data were automatically analyzed using a sleep analysis system and assessed by a professional polysomnographic technologist.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Definitions</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Apnea was defined as cessation of airflow for at least 10s with continued effort or lack of effort to breathe. Hypopnea was defined as a reduction in airflow accompanied by electroencephalogram arousal and/or a ≥3% decrease in oxygen desaturation from the pre-event baseline. The apnea hypopnea index (AHI) was defined as the number of apnea and hypopnea events occurring per hour. An AHI score of &lt; 5 was considered normal or simple snoring, score of 5 to 15 was considered mild OSA, score of 15 to 30 was considered moderate OSA, and score of &gt;30 was considered severe OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Hypertension was defined as SBP ≥ 140 mmHg, DBP ≥ 90 mmHg, self-reported history of hypertension, or use of antihypertensives.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Statistical Analyses</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The Kolmogorov–Smirnov test was performed to assess the normality of distribution. All continuous variables are presented as mean ± standard deviation (SD) or median with interquartile range (IQR), and the differences between the two groups for continuous variables were compared using Student’s </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-test or the Mann–Whitney </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">U</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">-test. All categorical variables are presented as number (percentage); differences between these variables were analyzed using the chi-square test. The variables with statistical significance in univariate analysis were considered as potential risk factors. Then, multivariate binary stepwise logistic regression analysis was performed to select independent risk factors for hypertension in patients with OSA. Binary logistic regression analysis was used to assess the role of each risk factor in hypertension after adjusting for covariates in three models: model 1 was adjusted for age; model 2 was adjusted for model 1 plus current smoking and current alcohol consumption; and model 3 was adjusted for model 2 plus BMI, gender, and family history of hypertension. Risk factors were also separately categorized into tertiles, and the lowest tertile was used as the reference group in the binary logistic regression. The results are shown as odds ratios (ORs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs); a two-tailed P-value &lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant. SPSS 25.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA) was used for statistical analysis, and GraphPad Prism 8.0 (GraphPad, San Diego, CA, USA) was used to construct figures.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Clinical and Polysomnographic Characteristics of the Study Population</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In this study, 416 OSA patients had hypertension and 392 did not. Compared with OSA patients without hypertension, those with hypertension were older (50.35 vs 43.90 years) and more obese (30.84 vs 29.07Kg/m</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">); had higher NC (42.40 vs 41.15 cm), WC (107.63 vs 101.70 cm), WHtR (0.63 vs 0.59), and ASBI score (0.084 vs 0.083 m</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>11/6</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Kg</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>−2/3</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">); and had a higher proportion of family history of hypertension (73.3% vs 49.0%) (all P &lt; 0.001). There was no significant difference in gender ratio, smoking habit, and current alcohol consumption between the groups (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). As shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, OSA patients with hypertension had higher ESS scores, AHI, AHI during rapid eye movement stage (REM AHI), AHI during non-rapid eye movement stage (NREM AHI), oxygen desaturation index (ODI), arousal index (ArI), apnea index (AI), hypopnea index (HI), mean hypopnea time (MHT), percentage of N1 sleep stage in total sleep time (N1%), proportion of cumulative sleep time with SpO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> below 90% in total sleep time (T90), and had lower mean oxygen saturation by finger pulse oximetry (MeanSpO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) and minimum oxygen saturation by finger pulse oximetry (MinSpO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) (all P &lt; 0.05). However, there was no significant difference in the total sleep time (TST), longest apnea time (LAT), mean apnea time (MAT), longest hypopnea time (LHT), percentage of rapid eye movement sleep stage in total sleep time (REM%), percentage of N2 sleep stage in total sleep time (N2%), and percentage of N3 sleep stage in total sleep time (N3%).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Clinical Characteristics of the Study Population</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSAHS without Hypertension</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSAHS with Hypertension</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Participants, n</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">392</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">416</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.90±2.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.35±13.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Men,%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">310(79.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">308(74.0)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.091</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Women,%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82(20.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108(26.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, Kg/m<sup>2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.07±6.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.84±5.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC, cm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.15±3.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.40±3.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WC, cm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101.70±13.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107.63±13.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHtR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59±0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63±0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABSI, m<sup>11/6</sup>Kg<sup>−2/3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.083±0.005</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.084±0.005</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current smoking,%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">178(45.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">201(48.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.408</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current drinking,%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">149(38.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">147(35.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.430</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family history of hypertension, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">189(49.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">305(73.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood pressure, mmHg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Systolic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">126.88±16.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">138.22±20.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Diastolic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.21±11.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.26±14.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: BMI, body mass index; NC, Neck circumference; WC, Waist circumference; WHtR, Waist-to-Height ration; ABSI, A Body Shape Index.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Polysomnographic Characteristics of the Study Population</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSAHS without Hypertension</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSAHS with Hypertension</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESS, score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.00(4.00,15.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10(4.00,16.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TST, min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">377.62±49.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">377.34±45.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.934</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI, events/h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.55(17.12,58.95)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.05(24.22,69.77)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mild,%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82(20.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48(11.5%)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Moderate,%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98(25.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83(20.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Severe,%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">212(54.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">285(68.5%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM AHI, events/h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.75(19.85,58.73)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.80(27.63,63.58)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NREM AHI, events/h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.45(15.10,58.48)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.15(22.05,69.55)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ODI, events/h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.25(13.40,56.43)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.6(21.03,66.40)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ArI, events/h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.25(10.18,37.57)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.35(11.93,39.80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AI, events/h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.00(2.20,34.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.25(3.00,40.53)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LAT, seconds</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.25(26.13,60.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.00(29.00,61.37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.139</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAT, seconds</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.20(15.60,26.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.90(16.50,26.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.408</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HI, events/h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.30(9.08,26.15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.85(10.93,33.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LHT, seconds</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.00(47.00,69.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.50(42.50,65.87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.137</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MHT, seconds</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.00(20.63,29.65)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.00(19.33,27.70)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM%,%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.50(6.54,16.83)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.77(6.11,14.97)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N1%,%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.68 (15.19,34.17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.48(18.00,40.12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N2%,%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.38(45.66,62.76)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.71(41.69,63.52)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.222</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N3%,%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.69 (0.90,11.77)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.67(0.45,10.45)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.103</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MeanSpO<sub>2</sub>,%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.85±3.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.95±3.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MinSpO<sub>2</sub>,%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.73±12.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.90±13.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T90,%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40 (0.20,13.07)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.40 (0.90,22.18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: ESS, Epworth sleepiness scale; TST, total sleep time; AHI, apnea-hypopnea index; REM AHI, apnea hypopnea index during rapid eye movement stage; NREM AHI, apnea hypopnea index during non-rapid eye movement stage; ODI, oxygen desaturation index; ArI, arousal index; AI, apnea index; LAT, longest apnea time; MAT, mean apnea time; HI, hypopnea index; LHT, longest hypopnea time; MHT, mean hypopnea time; REM%, percentage of rapid eye movement sleep stage in total sleep time; N1%, percentage of N1 sleep stage in total sleep time; N2%, percentage of N2 sleep stage in total sleep time; N3%, percentage of N3 sleep stage in total sleep time; MeanSpO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, mean oxygen saturation by finger pulse oximetry; MinSpO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, minimum oxygen saturation by finger pulse oximetry; T90, proportion of cumulative sleep time with SpO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> below 90% in total sleep time.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Risk Factors for Hypertension in Patients with OSA</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The indicators with statistical significance in univariate analysis, such as AHI, ODI, and NREM AHI (shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Tables 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">), were included in the multivariate binary stepwise logistic regression analysis. As shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, the multivariate binary stepwise logistic regression analysis showed that age (OR = 1.057; 95% confidence interval [CI] 1.043–1.070, P &lt; 0.001), WC (OR = 1.043; 95% CI 1.029–1.057, P &lt; 0.001), family history of hypertension (OR = 3.604; 95% CI 2.598–5.000; P &lt; 0.001), and REM AHI (OR = 1.007; 95% CI 1.000–1.014, P = 0.037) were positively associated with hypertension in patients with OSA. REM AHI was the only indicator in PSG related to hypertension in patients with OSA.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Multivariate Binary Stepwise Logistic Regression Analysis of Risk Factors for Hypertension in Patients with OSA</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">β</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">S <sub>x</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wald</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.055</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.396</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.057(1.043–1.070)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.594</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.043(1.029–1.057)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family history of hypertension</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.282</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.167</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.941</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.604(2.598–5.000)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM AHI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.343</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.007(1.000–1.014)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.010</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.842</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.439</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: WC, waist circumference; REM AHI, apnea hypopnea index in rapid eye movement stage.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Adjusted odds ratio and 95% confidence intervals (CI) for estimating the risk of hypertension in patients with OSA.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-1249-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: REM AHI, apnea hypopnea index during rapid eye movement stage; WC, waist circumference.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Association of REM AHI with the Risk of Hypertension in Patients with OSA</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> summarizes the results from binary logistic regression models estimating the risk of prevalent hypertension in patients with OSA based on REM AHI categories after adjusting for age, smoking, alcohol consumption, BMI, gender, and family history of hypertension. For the overall sample, after adjustment for potential confounders in model 3, the risk of hypertension increased with an increasing level of REM AHI (OR = 1.61 for tertile3 vs tertile1; 95% CI 1.07–2.42; P = 0.022 for trend). Consistent with this, when taken as a continuous variable, each SD increment of REM AHI was also significantly associated with the increased risk of hypertension in patients with OSA (OR = 1.007; 95% CI 1.001–1.014; P &lt; 0.05). REM AHI was also positively related to the risk of hypertension among women cohort in model 3 whether as a categorical or continuous variable (all P &lt; 0.05). However, in men cohort with OSA, no significant relationships were observed between increasing levels of REM AHI and the risk of hypertension in model 3 (all P &gt; 0.05). Higher REM AHI categories were significantly associated with a higher risk of prevalent hypertension in the total cohort (P = 0.022; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). In the subgroup with male cohort, higher REM AHI categories were associated with higher odds of hypertension but did not reach statistical significance (P = 0.181; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). In contrast, the association between higher REM AHI categories and higher odds of prevalent hypertension in the subgroup with women cohort was highly significant (P = 0.022; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2C</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Odds Ratio and 95% Confidence Intervals (CI) of Hypertension by Different Status of REM AHI in Patients with OSA</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Odds Ratios (95% CI)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 3</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Total</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Tertile1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Tertile2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39 (0.98,1.96)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38(0.97,1.94)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30 (0.90,1.88)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Tertile3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.27 (1.57,3.29)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.26 (1.56,3.27)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61 (1.07, 2.42)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P for trend</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Per SD increment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.013 (1.007,1.019)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.013 (1.007,1.019)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.007 (1.001,1.014)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Men</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Tertile1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Tertile2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 (0.74,1.65)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 (0.72,1.62)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 (0.67,1.5 9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Tertile3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.03(1.35,3.04)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.02(1.35,3.04)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47 (0.94,2.31)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P for trend</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.181</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Per SD increment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.011 (1.004,1.017)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.010 (1.004,1.017)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.005 (0.997,1.012)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Women</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Tertile1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Tertile2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.12 (1.01,4.49)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14 (1.01,4.52)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00 (0.90,4.44)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Tertile3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.69 (1.70,8.02)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.30 (1.90,9.69)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.79 (1.16,6.73)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> P for trend</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Per SD increment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.023 (1.010,1.036)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.025 (1.012,1.039)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.018 (1.003,1.033)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Model 1: adjusts for age. Model 2: adjusts for model 1 + current smoking and current drinking. Model 3: adjusts for model 2 + BMI, gender, and family history of hypertension in total cohort; adjusts for model 2 +BMI, and family history of hypertension in men/women cohort. In total cohort: Tertile1, REM AHI&lt;30.50 events/h; Tertile2, REM AHI 30.50-58.87 events/h; Tertile3 REM AHI≥58.87 events/h; In men cohort: Tertile1, REM AHI&lt;30.50 events/h; Tertile2, REM AHI 30.50-56.50 events/h; Tertile3 REM AHI≥56.50 events/h; In women cohort: Tertile1, REM AHI&lt;30.36 events/h; Tertile2, REM AHI 30.36-57.24 events/h; Tertile3 REM AHI≥57.24 events/h.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0005"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: REM AHI, apnea hypopnea index during rapid eye movement stage; CI, confidence intervals; BMI, body mass index.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Odds ratios and 95% confidence intervals (CI) for REM AHI severity categories and prevalent hypertension. Binary logistic regression models were fitted to examine the association between REM AHI categories and prevalent hypertension in patients with OSA. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative">) REM AHI categories were associated with increased risk of hypertension in total cohort and it reached statistical significance. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative">) REM AHI categories were associated with increased risk of hypertension in men cohort, but did not reach statistical significance. (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>C</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative">) Increasing REM AHI categories were statistically associated with increased risk of hypertension in women cohort.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-1249-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviation</bold>: REM AHI, apnea hypopnea index during rapid eye movement stage.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Prevalence of Hypertension by Tertiles of REM AHI in Patients with OSA</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The prevalence of hypertension by tertiles of REM AHI in the total cohort, male cohort, and female cohort are shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. The percentages of hypertension in the total cohort significantly increased in accordance with increasing tertiles of REM AHI (42.91% in tertile1, 52.35% in tertile2, and 59.92% in tertile3; P = 0.001). Moreover, the prevalence of hypertension increased in line with increasing tertiles of REM AHI in the male cohort, but did not achieve statistical significance (44.69% in tertile1, 48.65% in tertile2, and 56.67% in tertile3; P = 0.067). However, the prevalence of hypertension increased in line with increasing tertiles of REM AHI in the female cohort (40.00% in tertile1, 50.00% in tertile2, and 68.13% in tertile3; P = 0.007).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Prevalence of hypertension by tertiles of REM AHI in patients with OSA.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-1249-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: In total cohort: Tertile1, REM AHI &lt;30.50 events/h; Tertile2, REM AHI 30.50-58.87 events/h; Tertile3 REM AHI &gt;58.87 events/h; In men cohort: Tertile1, REM AHI &lt;30.50 events/h; Tertile2, REM AHI 30.50-56.50 events/h; Tertile3 REM AHI ≥56.50 events/h; In female cohort: Tertile1, REM AHI &lt;30.36 events/h; Tertile2, REM AHI 30.36-57.24 events/h; Tertile3 REM AHI ≥57.24 events/h.</attrib><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: REM AHI, apnea hypopnea index during rapid eye movement stage.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">It is generally acknowledged that hypertension is a multifactorial disease resulting from genetic and environmental factors.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In this study, we found that REM AHI was significantly and positively associated with hypertension in patients with OSA after adjusting for potential confounding factors. Importantly, we found a graded relationship between increasing REM AHI severity categories and prevalent hypertension in the women of our sample. In contrast, there was no significant relationship between REM AHI severity categories and the risk of hypertension in men.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">REM sleep, which was initially discovered in 1953, accounts for only 20% of total sleep time and is primarily concentrated in the latter half of the sleep period.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Various mechanisms are likely to be involved in the link between REM OSA and hypertension. It has been reported that there were significant changes in autonomic nervous system and cardiopulmonary function during REM sleep, which may lead to serious cardiovascular consequences.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Sympathetic activity was highest during REM sleep, resulting in a significant increase in blood pressure.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Somers et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> reported mean BP was 92 ± 4.5 mmHg when awake and reached peak levels of 116 ± 5 and 127 ± 7 mmHg during non-REM sleep and REM sleep in patients with OSA, respectively. Moreover, there was an increased tendency for upper airway collapse during REM sleep due to the decreased genioglossus muscle tone secondary to the inhibition of the hypoglossal nerve.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The ventilation drive for hypoxia and hypercapnia was reduced significantly during REM sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> These physiological phenomena could partly explain why obstructive apnea and hypopnea during REM sleep are longer in duration, are accompanied by greater oxygen desaturation, and lead to greater fluctuations in BP. These changes in hemodynamic and ventilation control during REM sleep could play a crucial role in the prevalence of hypertension.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The large, longitudinal, and community-based Wisconsin Sleep Cohort study involving 4385 sleep studies of 1451 individuals for 24 years established the significant and independent duration-association of REM AHI with prevalent hypertension and incident hypertension. The OR for REM AHI ≥15 relative to REM AHI &lt;1 was 1.26 (95% CI, 1.01–1.57; P = 0.04) and as high as 3.38 (95% CI, 1.70–6.72; P &lt; 0.001) in the subsample of subjects with non-REM AHI ≤5. A two-fold increase in REM AHI was associated with a 24% higher risk of hypertension (OR = 1.24; 95% CI, 1.08–1.41; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative">&lt;0.005) for patients with non-REM AHI ≤5. In addition, according to the longitudinal analysis, compared with patients with REM AHI ≤5, those with REM AHI ≥15 had a 77% higher risk of hypertension development.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Appleton et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> also conducted a longitudinal study based on community-dwelling men, known as the Men Androgens Inflammation Lifestyle Environment and Stress study, and found that REM AHI ≥20 was associated with prevalent and recent-onset hypertension, even among those with AHI &lt;10 and those with non-REM AHI &lt;10. According to another longitudinal study based on the Wisconsin Sleep Cohort, REM AHI was also shown to be independently associated with the incidence of non-dipping BP.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Consistent with this, in our hospital-based cross-sectional study, we found that high REM AHI levels were associated with prevalence of hypertension in patients with OSA. Compared with patients with REM AHI ≥58.87 events/h, those with REM AHI 30.50 events/h had an average 61% higher risk of hypertension. Every 10 additional apnea or hypopnea events per hour during REM sleep increased the risk of hypertension by an average of 7%. Additionally, we found that this effect was more pronounced in women patients, the OR for REM AHI ≥57.24 events/h relative to REM AHI &lt;30.36 events/h was 2.79 (95% CI, 1.16–6.73; P = 0.022); however, there was no significant difference in male patients. This may be related to the greater susceptibility of REM OSA in females.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Females may be protected from disordered breathing during much of sleep, which can be attributed to increased genioglossal muscle tension and ventilatory response induced by estrogen and progesterone. However, this protective mechanism could be greatly weakened by the disturbance of muscle tension associated with REM sleep. Moreover, compared with males, the upper airway of females may be more prone to collapse in REM sleep because of its smaller size. Furthermore, medullary chemosensitivity to hypoxia and hypercapnia is reduced during REM sleep, limiting the stimulatory effect of estrogen and progesterone on breathing.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Additionally, our findings may have important clinical implications for the duration of continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) use that is needed to reduce the risk of hypertension and control BP. It has been reported that 4-h use of nightly CPAP therapy during 70% of all nights, which translates to an average CPAP use of 2.8 h every night, is considered adequate adherence to therapy, while the effects of CPAP therapy on hypertension were modest, even negative.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Grimaldi et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> reported that 3-h to 4-h use of CPAP therapy overnight would result in 75% and 60% of obstructive events left untreated during REM sleep, respectively. Moreover, it was shown that 7-h use of CPAP therapy would overlap with most REM sleep. These results may partly explain the negative or modest effects of CPAP therapy on BP control. A randomized controlled trial of patients with OSA showed that the hours of CPAP use were significantly correlated with the reduction of 24-h mean BP.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> A large meta-analysis suggested that regular CPAP therapy for at least 5 h per night could result in a reduction in both systolic BP and diastolic BP.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Another randomized controlled trial based on patients with OSA demonstrated a significant reduction in incident hypertension in OSA patients adhering to an average of 6 h of regular CPAP therapy use per night.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Further studies are needed to determine the effective CPAP therapy time required to control BP. Additionally, one study showed that up to 70% of sleep studies involving REM AHI ≥15 would have clinically classified cases as no OSA or mild OSA based on the current diagnostic criteria; however, this degree of disordered breathing during REM sleep is associated with an increased risk of hypertension.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Additional research is needed to explore whether such patients need to be treated.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This study has several limitations. First, due to the cross-sectional nature of this study, we could not identify causality. In the future, we will conduct a prospective study about the development of hypertension in OSA patients.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Second, other potential confounding factors, such as dietary habits, labor intensity, economic status, and psychological conditions, were not included in our analysis because the data were extracted from the medical system. Finally, this was a single-center study based on the patients with OSA; therefore, it was restricted and could not be expanded to other groups.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Notwithstanding the limitations, this study presented REM AHI was significantly and positively associated with hypertension in patients with OSA. The effect was more pronounced in female patients. In contrast, no significant associations were observed between REM AHI and hypertension in men with OSA.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This work was supported by Grants from the Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 81970084). We would like to thank Editage (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="http://www.editage.cn" ext-link-type="uri">www.editage.cn</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) for English language editing.</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The data used during the current study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Ethics Statement</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The study protocol was approved by the Medical Ethics Committee of Tianjin Medical University General Hospital (IRB No.2020-WZ-091), and the procedures followed were in accordance with the principles of the Helsinki Declaration in 1995, as revised in 2013. The requirement for informed consent was waived because the patients’ information was extracted from electronic medical records at the sleep center, and the patients’ identities were maintained anonymous.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0008">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation, or in all these areas. All authors took part in drafting, writing, revising, and critically reviewing the article; reviewed and gave final approval for the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agreed to take responsibility and be accountable for all aspects of the manuscript.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0009">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Benjafield</surname>
<given-names>AV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ayas</surname>
<given-names>NT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eastwood</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Estimation of the global prevalence and burden of obstructive sleep apnoea: a literature-based analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Respir Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>687</fpage>–<lpage>698</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s2213-2600(19)30198-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31300334</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mashaqi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gozal</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea and systemic hypertension: gut dysbiosis as the mediator?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1517</fpage>–<lpage>1527</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.7990</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31596218</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Peppard</surname>
<given-names>PE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Young</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Palta</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Skatrud</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prospective study of the association between sleep-disordered breathing and hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>342</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>1378</fpage>–<lpage>1384</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/nejm200005113421901</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10805822</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Muxfeldt</surname>
<given-names>ES</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Margallo</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Costa</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of continuous positive airway pressure treatment on clinic and ambulatory blood pressures in patients with obstructive sleep apnea and resistant hypertension: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hypertension</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>736</fpage>–<lpage>742</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/hypertensionaha.114.04852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25601933</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Thunström</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Manhem</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosengren</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peker</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Blood pressure response to losartan and continuous positive airway pressure in hypertension and obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>193</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>310</fpage>–<lpage>320</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201505-0998OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26414380</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hou</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of obstructive sleep apnea with hypertension: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Glob Health</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>010405</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7189/jogh.08.010405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29497502</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kohler</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stradling</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>CrossTalk proposal: most of the cardiovascular consequences of OSA are due to increased sympathetic activity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>590</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<page-range>2813–2815;discussion 2823</page-range>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2012.229633</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pirzada</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>BaHammam</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Rapid eye movement predominant obstructive sleep apnoea: prognostic relevance and clinical approach</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Opin Pulm Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>514</fpage>–<lpage>522</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/mcp.0000000000000817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34620787</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mokhlesi</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Finn</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hagen</surname>
<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea during REM sleep and hypertension. results of the Wisconsin Sleep Cohort</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>190</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1158</fpage>–<lpage>1167</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201406-1136OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25295854</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mokhlesi</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hagen</surname>
<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Finn</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hla</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carter</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peppard</surname>
<given-names>PE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnoea during REM sleep and incident non-dipping of nocturnal blood pressure: a longitudinal analysis of the Wisconsin Sleep Cohort</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Thorax</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>70</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1062</fpage>–<lpage>1069</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2015-207231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26307037</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Appleton</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vakulin</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Hypertension is associated with undiagnosed OSA during rapid eye movement sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>150</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>495</fpage>–<lpage>505</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chest.2016.03.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27001264</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rishi</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rishi</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Rapid eye movement related obstructive sleep apnea: where do we stand?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Respir Investig</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>589</fpage>–<lpage>595</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resinv.2021.06.006</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Basoglu</surname>
<given-names>OK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tasbakan</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Gender differences in clinical and polysomnographic features of obstructive sleep apnea: a clinical study of 2827 patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>249</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-017-1482-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28197893</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Koo</surname>
<given-names>BB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dostal</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ioachimescu</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Budur</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effects of gender and age on REM-related sleep-disordered breathing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>264</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-007-0161-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18074161</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Krakauer</surname>
<given-names>NY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krakauer</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A new body shape index predicts mortality hazard independently of body mass index</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>e39504</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0039504</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22815707</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Berry</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Budhiraja</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gottlieb</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Rules for scoring respiratory events in sleep: update of the 2007 AASM manual for the scoring of sleep and associated events. Deliberations of the sleep apnea definitions task force of the American Academy of sleep medicine</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>597</fpage>–<lpage>619</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.2172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23066376</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Guide TJCoCHP</collab>. <article-title>Guidelines on Prevention and Treatment of Hypertension in China (2018 edition)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin J Cardiovasc</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>24</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Olack</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wabwire-Mangen</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smeeth</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Montgomery</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kiwanuka</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Breiman</surname>
<given-names>RF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Risk factors of hypertension among adults aged 35-64 years living in an urban slum Nairobi, Kenya</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1251</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-015-2610-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26679701</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aserinsky</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kleitman</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Regularly occurring periods of eye motility, and concomitant phenomena, during sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Science</italic></source>. <year>1953</year>;<volume>118</volume>(<issue>3062</issue>):<fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>274</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.118.3062.273</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13089671</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Alzoubaidi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mokhlesi</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea during rapid eye movement sleep: clinical relevance and therapeutic implications</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Opin Pulm Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>545</fpage>–<lpage>554</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/mcp.0000000000000319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27583667</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mokhlesi</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Punjabi</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>“REM-related” obstructive sleep apnea: an epiphenomenon or a clinically important entity?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.1570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22215911</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Somers</surname>
<given-names>VK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dyken</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clary</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abboud</surname>
<given-names>FM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sympathetic neural mechanisms in obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Invest</italic></source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>96</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1897</fpage>–<lpage>1904</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/jci118235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7560081</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mokhlesi</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carter</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Growing evidence linking OSA during rapid eye movement sleep to systemic hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>150</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>475</fpage>–<lpage>477</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chest.2016.03.047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27613971</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Peppard</surname>
<given-names>PE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ward</surname>
<given-names>NR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morrell</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The impact of obesity on oxygen desaturation during sleep-disordered breathing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>180</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>788</fpage>–<lpage>793</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.200905-0773OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19644043</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sawyer</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gooneratne</surname>
<given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marcus</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ofer</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Richards</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weaver</surname>
<given-names>TE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A systematic review of CPAP adherence across age groups: clinical and empiric insights for developing CPAP adherence interventions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>343</fpage>–<lpage>356</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2011.01.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21652236</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Grimaldi</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beccuti</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Touma</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Cauter</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mokhlesi</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association of obstructive sleep apnea in rapid eye movement sleep with reduced glycemic control in type 2 diabetes: therapeutic implications</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes Care</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>363</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc13-0933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24101701</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Martínez-García</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Capote</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Campos-Rodríguez</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of CPAP on blood pressure in patients with obstructive sleep apnea and resistant hypertension: the HIPARCO randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>310</volume>(<issue>22</issue>):<fpage>2407</fpage>–<lpage>2415</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2013.281250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24327037</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Haentjens</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Meerhaeghe</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moscariello</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The impact of continuous positive airway pressure on blood pressure in patients with obstructive sleep apnea syndrome: evidence from a meta-analysis of placebo-controlled randomized trials</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>167</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>757</fpage>–<lpage>764</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.167.8.757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17452537</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Barbé</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Durán-Cantolla</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sánchez-de-la-Torre</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of continuous positive airway pressure on the incidence of hypertension and cardiovascular events in nonsleepy patients with obstructive sleep apnea: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>307</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>2161</fpage>–<lpage>2168</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2012.4366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22618923</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
