<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35996417</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">9391942</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">359242</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S359242</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Cognitive Appraisal of Sleep and Brain Activation in Response to Sleep-Related Sounds in Healthy Adults</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Hwang et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Hwang et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7246-9316</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Hwang</surname>
            <given-names>Yunjee</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Kyung Hwa</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Nambeom</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Jooyoung</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7769-400X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Ha Young</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jeon</surname>
            <given-names>Jeong Eun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Yu Jin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2467-5451</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Seog Ju</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0002" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Brain and Cognitive Engineering, Korea University</institution>, <addr-line>Seoul</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Psychiatry and Center for Sleep and Chronobiology, Seoul National University, College of Medicine and Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Seoul</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Division of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, Department of Psychiatry, Seoul National University Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Seoul</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Biomedical Engineering Research Center, Gachon University</institution>, <addr-line>Incheon</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label><institution>Department of Psychiatry, Sungkyunkwan University College of Medicine, Samsung Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line>Seoul</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Yu Jin Lee, <institution>Department of Psychiatry and Center for Sleep and Chronobiology, Seoul National University, College of Medicine and Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Seoul</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country>, Email ewpsyche@snu.ac.kr</corresp>
        <corresp id="an0002">Seog Ju Kim, <institution>Department of Psychiatry, Sungkyunkwan University College of Medicine, Samsung Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line>Seoul</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country>, Email ksj7126@skku.edu</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <fpage>1407</fpage>
      <lpage>1416</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>03</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2022 Hwang et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Hwang et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Sounds play important roles in promoting and disrupting sleep. How our brain processes sleep-related sounds and individual differences in processing sleep-related sounds must be determined to understand the role of sound in sleep. We investigated neural responses to sleep-related sounds and their associations with cognitive appraisals of sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Participants and Methods</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Forty-four healthy adults heard sleep-related and neutral sounds during functional magnetic resonance imaging using a 3T scanner. They also completed the Dysfunctional Beliefs and Attitudes about Sleep (DBAS) questionnaire, which was used to assess cognitive appraisals of sleep. We conducted a voxel-wise whole-brain analysis to compare brain activation in response to sleep-related and neutral sounds. We also examined the association between the DBAS score and brain activity in response to sleep-related sounds (vs neutral sounds) using region of interest (ROI) and whole-brain correlation analyses. The ROIs included the anterior cingulate cortex (ACC), anterior insula (AI), and amygdala.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The whole-brain analysis revealed increased activation in the temporal regions and decreased activation in the ACC in response to sleep-related sounds compared to neutral sounds. The ROI and whole-brain correlation analyses showed that higher DBAS scores, indicating a negative appraisal of sleep, were significantly correlated with increased activation of the ACC, right medial prefrontal cortex, and brainstem in response to sleep-related sounds.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">These results indicate that the temporal cortex and ACC, which are implicated in affective sound processing, may play important roles in the processing of sleep-related sounds. The positive association between the neural responses to sleep-related sounds and DBAS scores suggest that negative and dysfunctional appraisals of sleep may be an important factor in individual differences in the processing of sleep-related sounds.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>anterior cingulate cortex</kwd>
        <kwd>appraisal</kwd>
        <kwd>functional magnetic resonance imaging</kwd>
        <kwd>sleep-related sounds</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="4"/>
        <table-count count="6"/>
        <ref-count count="47"/>
        <page-count count="10"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sounds can promote or disrupt sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Calming and soothing music helps people fall asleep, while short-duration, repetitive sounds (eg, clock-ticking) may prevent people from falling asleep. Sounds that disrupt sleep obviously affect sleep quality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Examining how the brain processes sleep-related sounds could help us understand how sounds promote or disrupt sleep. In addition, exploring the neural substrates of individual differences in the processing of sleep-related sounds may improve understanding of neurobiological vulnerability to sleep problems.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Neural activity differs among sound stimuli.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4–6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Sleep-related sounds may be associated with sleep hygiene. Sleep-related sounds are likely to elicit a neural response in brain regions involved in the affective processing of sound. The auditory cortex plays a key role in affective processing of sound.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7–9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The superior temporal cortex responds to sounds that elicit an automatic emotional response.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The neural network engaged in affective processing of sound extends to other brain areas as well as the auditory cortex.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Affective sounds enhance activity in the medial prefrontal cortex, which plays a role in emotional appraisal and evaluation.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12–14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The insula shows activity in response to all types of affective sounds, including human verbalizations,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15–17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and the amygdala is responsive to the sounds with negative valence.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Interindividual differences exist in affective and neurobiological sensitivity to sleep-related sounds. Some people appraise the sound of a ticking clock to be sufficiently bothersome to prevent sleep. These differences can be explained by cognitive appraisals of sleep, ie, subjective assessments of sleep-related cognitions.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Subjects with “dysfunctional” appraisals of sleep exhibit excessive worry and helplessness in relation to it.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> They are also more likely to perceive sleep-related sounds as unpleasant and stressful.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Although dysfunctional sleep-related cognition is associated with neural activity in response to sleep-related sound in insomnia patients,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> no studies have investigated the relationship between sleep-related cognition and brain activity in response to sleep-related sound in those without a sleep disorder.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Affective and neurobiological responses to sleep-related sounds can be changed by subjective reevaluation of sleep-related cognitions. Cognitive appraisal of sleep may be associated with neural activation in several brain areas involved in affective stimuli processing, including the anterior cingulate cortex (ACC; involved in the cognitive regulation of emotions and integration of cognitive-affective processes),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> anterior insula (AI; plays a role in detecting emotional salience),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and amygdala (preferentially processes the stimuli with a negative valence).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This study compared neural responses to sleep-related and neutral sounds. We examined whether individual differences in the neural processing of sleep-related sounds are associated with cognitive appraisals of sleep. Our first hypothesis was that brain activity in response to sleep-related sounds is different from that in response to neutral sounds. Specifically, we hypothesized that sleep-related sounds would induce greater activity in the auditory cortex and affective sound processing areas (eg, insula and amygdala) compared to neutral sounds. Our second hypothesis was that cognitive appraisals of sleep correlate with neural activity in response to sleep-related sounds in brain areas involved in the cognitive regulation of emotions and affective processing, such as the ACC, AI, and amygdala.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We recruited 47 healthy adults (23 females; age, 37.69 ± 12.03 years [range: 24–63 years]) via an advertisement placed on the notice board at Seoul National University Hospital. The exclusion criteria were a history of serious medical or neurological illness, current medical or neurological illness, any Axis I psychiatric disorder according to the Fourth Edition of the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, sleep disorders, shift work, borderline or antisocial personality disorder, pregnancy, and any contraindication for magnetic resonance imaging (MRI).</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The Structural and Clinical Interview for DSM disorders was administered to all participants by trained psychologists. Nocturnal polysomnography was conducted to screen out common sleep disorders, such as obstructive sleep apnea or periodic limb movement disorder (sleep apnea was defined as an Apnea-Hypopnea Index &gt; 15, and limb movement during sleep as a Periodic Limb Movement Index &gt; 15). All participants were provided with a description of the study and instructed to voluntarily provide written informed consent before the experiment. All participants received monetary compensation for participating in the experiment. This study was approved by the Institutional Review Board of Seoul National University Hospital and conducted in accordance with the declaration of Helsinki.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Self-Reported Questionnaires of Sleep-Related Variables</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">All participants completed the self-reported Dysfunctional Beliefs and Attitudes about Sleep (DBAS) questionnaire.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> The DBAS was used to evaluate dysfunctional appraisals of sleep (eg, unrealistic sleep expectations, perception of a lack of control regarding sleep, faulty beliefs, etc.). The DBAS is divided into five sub-scales: consequences of insomnia (1), control and predictability of sleep (2), sleep expectations (3), causal attributions of insomnia (4), and sleep-promoting practices (5).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> We used the Korean version of the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) to measure overall sleep quality and assess the severity of sleep problems.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Functional MRI (fMRI) Procedure</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The design of experimental procedure is presented in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. The experiment was based on a block design, and consisted of four sleep-related sound (SS) blocks and four neutral sound (NS) blocks. The blocks were randomized, but were presented in the same order across participants as follows: SS-NS-NS-SS-SS-NS-NS-SS. Each block lasted for 20s, followed by rest periods of 13–19s. The entire task lasted for approximately 5 min.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The design of experimental procedure.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-1407-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The SS consisted of two alarm sounds, one ticking clock sound, and one heartbeat sound were from online sources. Sounds commonly heard during bedtime were defined as SS based on discussions with two sleep medicine specialists. Alarm sounds are usually heard in bed before awakening, while heartbeat and ticking clock sounds are commonly perceived to be loud before falling asleep. The SS was validated in a previous study,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> in which &gt; 80% of the participants reported that the SS was associated with sleep. The NS consisted of white noise. The original SS and NS were electronically manipulated using Audacity software (ver. 3.0, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.audacityteam.org" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.audacityteam.org</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). The pitch of the NS was between 0 and 22,000 Hz, which was the same as for the SS. All stimuli have the same root mean square power, ie, normalized perceived amplitude intensity (−20 dBfs). Thus, SS and NS also had the same mean pitch (Hz) and amplitude.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All participants were instructed to listen to sound stimuli via MR-compatible headphones. The participants were asked to focus on the sounds while staring at the fixation cross on the screen with their eyes opened. All participants reported their level of sleepiness before the MRI scan, as assessed by the Stanford Sleepiness Scale.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> MRI examination was performed in participants who reported feeling wide awake. After the MRI scan, we asked the participants whether they fell asleep.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>fMRI Data Acquisition and Analyses</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">A 3T whole-body Tim Trio scanner (Siemens, Erlangen, Germany) with a 12-channel birdcage head coil was used to acquire the functional images, with an interleaved T2*-weighted echo-planar imaging gradient echo sequence (repetition time = 2000 ms, echo time = 30 ms, flip angle = 90°, slice thickness = 4.0 mm, in-plane resolution = 3.4×3.4 mm, 33 slices, field of view = 220 mm, matrix size = 64×64). We acquired 159 functional image volumes for each participant. The structural image was also acquired using a T1-weighted, three-dimensional gradient echo pulse sequence with magnetization-prepared rapid gradient echo (repetition time = 1670 ms, echo time = 1.89 ms, TI = 900 ms, flip angle = 9°, slice thickness = 1.0 mm, in-plane resolution = 1 mm × 1 mm, field of view = 250 mm, matrix size = 256×256).</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The fMRI data were preprocessed using SPM12 software (Wellcome Department of Cognitive Neurology, London, UK). The following preprocessing steps were applied to functional and structural images before statistical analyses. First, functional and structural images were visually inspected and reoriented to the anterior commissure. All functional volumes were corrected for slice timing and then realigned to the first image for motion correction. The realigned volumes were co-registered to an anatomical (T1) image. The volumes were spatially normalized to the Montreal Neurological Institute (MNI) template using a transformation matrix derived from T1 structural image segmentation (eg, gray and white matters and cerebrospinal fluid). The voxel sizes were resampled to 2 × 2 × 2 mm</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>3</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. Finally, the normalized images were smoothed using a Gaussian kernel with a full width at half maximum of 6 mm. We used the Artifact Detection Tool (ART, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="http://www.nitrc.org/projects/artifact_detect/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.nitrc.org/projects/artifact_detect/</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) to identify outlier volumes. Outliers with significant head motion in each participant were detected at &gt; 2 mm composite motion or a larger global mean intensity (ie, the difference in global mean intensity across functional volumes &gt; 3 SD). Participants were excluded if the outlier volumes exceeded 20% of the total volume; therefore, one participant was excluded from the final analyses.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">A general linear model was used to estimate neural activation of conditions of interest (SS and NS blocks). Two regressors pertaining to the presentation of sounds (one for SS and the other for NS) were entered into the model. Head motion parameters and outliers identified from the ART were also entered in the model to control for effects of motion and outliers. The design matrix was convolved temporally with a canonical hemodynamic response function to ensure a better fit. Two contrast images (SS vs implicit baseline [0] and NS vs implicit baseline [0]) for each participant were created to compare neural activation in response to SS or NS compared to implicit baseline.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The contrast images were compared using a whole brain paired </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">-test to explore neural activation differences between SS and NS. In addition, whole-brain correlation analysis was conducted to investigate the relationships between neural activity in response to SS (vs NS) and sleep-related variables, such as cognitive appraisal of sleep assessed by the DBAS. Sex and age were entered into the regression model to control for sex and age. A cluster-wise correction was performed using the 3dClustSim program, and smoothing was estimated using the 3dFWHMx function of the Analysis of Functional Neuroimages (v20.03.01, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://afni.nimh.nih.gov" ext-link-type="uri">https://afni.nimh.nih.gov</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) program, with the “acf” option selected. Cluster size was determined using Monte Carlo simulations, second nearest-neighbor clustering, and a two-sided threshold. Cluster-wise significance was evaluated based on a p-value of 0.001 and cluster sizes (k) to achieve a corrected significance threshold of p &lt; 0.05. Brain areas were labeled based on peak z values using the automated anatomical labeling atlas (AAL) 3. The MRIcroGL online tool (NITRC: MRIcroGL: Tool/Resource Info) was used to visualize the MRI results. To conduct ROI-based correlation analyses, ROI masks of the ACC, AI and amygdala were created using the human atlas in pickatlas (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.nitrc.org/projects/wfu_pickatlas/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nitrc.org/projects/wfu_pickatlas/</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">) from the SPM toolbox based on the AAL. The parameter estimates were extracted from each ROI mask using the marsbar toolbox (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://imaging.mrc-cbu.cam.ac.uk/imaging/CbuImaging" ext-link-type="uri">https://imaging.mrc-cbu.cam.ac.uk/imaging/CbuImaging</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) and exported to SPSS software (version 24.0; SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA) for statistical analysis</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Pearson’s correlation analysis was performed to investigate the association between the parameter estimates extracted from the ROIs (bilateral ACC, AI, and amygdala) and sleep-related variables (DBAS and PSQI scores). All analyses were two-tailed. A P-value &lt; 0.05 was considered significant.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Demographics and Questionnaire Scores</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Three participants were excluded because they failed to adhere to the experimental procedure due to a lack of understanding of the study protocol (n = 1), severe image distortion (n = 1), and excessive head motion (n = 1). Finally, 44 healthy adults (22 females; age, 37.5 ± 12.04 years) were included in the final analysis. No significant differences in age or sex were detected between the three excluded and 44 included participants.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">No significant sex differences were found in the DBAS or PSQI scores. Age was positively correlated with the PSQI score (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.42, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> &lt; 0.01) but not with the DBAS score. Older participants were more likely to report poor sleep quality. The DBAS score was correlated with the PSQI score (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.41, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> &lt; 0.01). Participants with poor sleep quality were more likely to show maladaptive appraisals of sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Comparison of Neural Responses to SS and NS</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Bilateral temporal regions exhibited greater activation in response to SS than NS (left MNI 64, −24, 6; k = 1554; z = 7.16, right MNI: −52, −38, 14; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">k</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 2163; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">z</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 7.06) (cluster-wise-corrected </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.05; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). The left ACC showed less activation following exposure to SS than to NS (MNI: 0, 40, −4; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">k</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 101; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">z</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 3.82) (cluster-wise-corrected </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.05; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Brain Areas Showing Different Activation Between Sleep-Related Sound and Neutral Sound</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Region</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Cluster Size</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Z-value</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">MNI Coordinates</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">SS &gt; NS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rt. STG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1554</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lt. STG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2163</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SS &lt; NS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lt. pACC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The statistical threshold was cluster-wise corrected </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.05 (97 voxels). Cluster size was calculated by 3dClusSim.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> SS, sleep-related sound; NS, neutral sound; MNI, Montreal Neurological Institute stereotactic standard brain template; Rt, right; Lt, left; STG, superior temporal gyrus; pACC, pregenual anterior cingulate cortex.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Brain areas showing different activation between sleep-related sound and neutral sound. There was significant greater activation in bilateral temporal regions (red and yellow color) and deactivation in pregenual anterior cingulate cortex (blue color) in response to SS compared to NS. The statistical threshold was cluster-wise corrected </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.05 (97 voxels). Cluster size was calculated by 3dClusSim.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-1407-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: SS, sleep-related sound; NS, neutral sound.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Associations Between Brain Activity and the DBAS Scores</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The ROI-based correlation analysis found that the higher DBAS score was correlated with increased ACC activation in response to SS compared with NS (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.37, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.017, Pearson’s correlation, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). However, no significant associations were detected between the DBAS score and the activity changes in response to SS (vs NS) among the other ROIs, such as the insula or amygdala. The correlation between PSQI and brain activity in response to SS (vs NS) was not associated with any brain area.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Brain areas where activation to sleep-related sound was associated with the Cognitive Appraisal of Sleep. Brain areas showing significant association between increased DBAS scores when exposed to SS compared to NS. The statistical threshold was cluster-wise corrected </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.05 (101 voxels). Cluster size was calculated by 3dClusSim.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-1407-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: DBAS, Dysfunctional Beliefs and Attitudes about sleep; SS, sleep-related sound.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The whole-brain regression analysis indicated that higher DBAS score was significantly associated with an increased neural response in the right medial superior frontal gyrus (MNI 14, 50, 26; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">k</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 154; z = 4.86), the medial raphe nucleus (MNI −4, −26, −28; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">k</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 145; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">z</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 4.58), the left precentral gyrus (MNI −48, 2, 38; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">k</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 105; z = 4.56), the left superior frontal gyrus (MNI −22, 52, 28; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">k</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 205; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">z</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 4.33), and the left middle frontal gyrus (MNI −32, 28, 28; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">k</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 314; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">z</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 4.28) in response to SS compared with NS (cluster-wise-corrected </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.05; </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Brain Areas Where Activation to Sleep-Related Sound Was Associated with the Cognitive Appraisal of Sleep</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Region</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Cluster Size</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Z-value</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">MNI Coordinates</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rt. SFGmedial</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">154</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RapheM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">145</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−28</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lt. precentral</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lt. SFG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">205</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lt. MFG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">314</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The statistical threshold cluster-wise corrected </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.05 (101 voxels). Cluster size was calculated by 3dClusSim.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations:</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> DBAS, Dysfunctional Beliefs and Attitudes about sleep; Rt, right; Lt, left; SFGmedial, medial superior frontal gyrus; RapheM, median raphe nucleus; SFG, superior frontal gyrus; MFG, middle frontal gyrus.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0004" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The association between activation to sleep-related sound in right anterior cingulate cortex and Cognitive Appraisal of Sleep. Relative BOLD response was calculated by subtracting BOLD response to NS from the one to SS.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-1407-g0004" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: SS, sleep-related sound; DBAS, Dysfunctional Beliefs and Attitudes about sleep; BOLD, Blood Oxygenation Level Dependent.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Additional Analyses</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Pearson’s correlation analysis was conducted to investigate the relationships between each sub-scales of the DBAS and ACC activity. DBAS scales are divided into 5 sub-scales: Consequences of insomnia (1), Control and predictability of sleep (2), Sleep requirement expectations (3), Causal attributions of insomnia (4), and Sleep-promoting practices (5). Among 5 sub-scales, ACC activity was positively correlated with “Consequences of insomnia (1)” and “Causal attributions of insomnia (4)” sub-scales (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.38, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.05, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">r</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0.32, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.05, respectively), but not with the other sub-scales.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In this study, stronger activation of the temporal cortex and deactivation of the ACC were observed in response to SS than NS. In addition, cognitive appraisals of sleep were associated with activation of the ACC, prefrontal cortex, and brainstem in response to SS compared to NS. To our knowledge, this is the first study to investigate neural responses to sleep-related sounds and their association with the cognitive appraisals of sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Consistent with our hypothesis, the temporal cortex activity was greater in response to SS compared to NS. The temporal cortex plays a role in interpretations of auditory information.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Previous studies reported that the temporal cortex is involved in affective sound processing.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In particular, the superior temporal cortex is more strongly activated in response to sounds with negative than neutral valence.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In addition, temporal cortex highly responds to arousing sounds that can induce automatic response from listener.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Thus, sleep-related sounds may also elicit temporal cortical activation; SS are often appraised as negative and arousing sounds before or during sleep. These properties of SS might be prominent compared to NS, which was white noise.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The finding that the ACC was deactivated in response to SS was unexpected. Deactivation, indicated by a negative value in BOLD response, represents decreased neural activity or increased neural inhibition.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Deactivation of the default mode network (DMN) has been suggested to imply efficient cognitive control, suppressing endogenous activity to facilitate exogenous task-relevant processes.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The ACC and medial prefrontal cortex are key DMN nodes</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> that play a critical role in the management of self-referential cognition. Therefore, deactivation of the ACC suggests inhibitory control of self-referential processing in response to sleep-related sounds.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Furthermore, individual variations in neurological sensitivity to sleep-related sounds may be detected depending on the cognitive appraisal of sleep, even in healthy people without a sleep disorder. Dysfunctional appraisals of sleep are associated with higher neural activity in the ACC and medial frontal cortex. These findings are consistent with those of a previous study reporting hyperactivity in the prefrontal cortex and DMN in response to sleep-related stimuli,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and with the finding that the ACC in insomnia patients has a lower gamma-aminobutyric acid level,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> which is usually related to dysfunctional sleep appraisals. Psychiatric disorders, such as bipolar disorder, major depressive disorder, and schizophrenia, commonly accompany insomnia, and are related to functional and structural abnormalities in the ACC.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42–44</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">In contrast to ACC hyperactivity in insomnia patients, ACC deactivation in response to SS suggests that those without insomnia successfully inhibit self-referential processing in response to SS. However, dysfunctional cognitive sleep appraisals were associated with sleep-elicited “reversed activity” in the ACC and medial frontal cortex, along with stronger cortical activity in insomnia patients. With consideration of previous results from insomnia studies, the current results suggest that ACC activity could be a biomarker for the risk of insomnia. Maladaptive appraisals of sleep may modulate activity in the ACC and medial prefrontal cortex in response to SS. Increased DMN activation in response to SS may reflect impaired inhibition of self-referential cognition by SS.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">More negative appraisals of sleep were associated with increased activity in the prefrontal cortex and raphe. Given that these are important brain structures in the ascending arousal system,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> dysfunctional appraisals of sleep may be related to hyperarousal of the ascending arousal system from the brainstem to the prefrontal cortex in response to SS. Thus, subjects with maladaptive appraisals of sleep are likely to show greater prefrontal activity in response to SS, as they may be more sensitive to sleep-related stimuli. The raphe nucleus, a key region in the serotonergic pathway, plays an important role in initiating and terminating sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Thus, hyperarousal related to serotonergic activity in response to SS may be associated with a negative appraisal of sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The current study provides novel data showing that dysfunctional cognitive sleep appraisals can alter neural signals in the ACC-mPFC and limbic system in response to SS. These findings suggest that even normal sleepers can exhibit cortical arousal or impaired inhibition in response to sleep-related sounds if they have maladaptive appraisals of sleep. Thus, cognitive appraisals of sleep could be a target for interventions aiming to address sleep problems. Moreover, failure to regulate ACC-mPFC activation to sleep-related stimuli could be a neurobiological risk factor for cortical hyperactivation and insomnia. In particular, the ACC response to sleep-related stimuli could be associated with scores on two DBAS sub-scales, indicating consequences of insomnia and casual attributions of insomnia. However, we could not compare the neurobiological pathway of negative sleep cognition in normal sleepers to that in clinical patients with a sleep disturbance. Thus, follow-up studies are needed to investigate whether healthy subjects with hyperactivity to SS develop sleep disorders. These findings will contribute to the identification of risk factors and neurobiological markers for sleep disorders.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In the current study, there was no correlation between neural response to SS and subjective sleep quality. This seems counterintuitive as neural response to SS would be implicated with sleep quality. The lack of correlation between neural response to SS and subjective sleep quality may be due to the fact that all participants of the current study did not have any clinically significant sleep disorders. Study participants reported lower PSQI scores (7.78±4.29) representing good sleep quality. Based on the best cut-off point of Korea version of the PSQI</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> distinguishing poor and good sleepers (8.5), 66% of study participants can be classified into those with good sleep quality. In addition, neural response was measured while listening to sleep-related sounds rather than during sleep. Therefore, neural response to SS would be more likely to be associated with cognitive appraisal of good sleeping people rather than sleep quality of sleep disorder patients.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This study had several limitations. First, we had a relatively small sample size. Second, we did not include patients with sleep disorders, such as chronic insomnia. Therefore, we cannot compare results between normal sleepers and insomnia sufferers. Future studies using larger sample sizes and clinical populations are needed to obtain a more detailed evaluation and clear neurobiological substrates for cognitive appraisals of sleep. Third, our study was cross-sectional; therefore, we could not determine whether brain activation in response to SS was associated with the subsequent development of clinically significant sleep disturbances. Fourth, SS was carefully selected by two sleep medicine specialists and validated as sleep-related sounds in participants with insomnia. Future research for validation of SS was needed in healthy population to confirm whether SS is an appropriate stimulation in healthy population. Fifth, although the white noise used as NS in the current study was matched for acoustic properties, using salient sounds unrelated to sleep or sleep-promoting sounds as NS would help us to specify the brain activation in response to SS, which interrupt sleep. However, given that sleep-unrelated salient sounds or sleep-promoting sounds may be meaningful, these sounds may cause other problems with interpreting results.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In conclusion, the current study revealed increased activation of the temporal cortex and decreased activation of the ACC in response to sleep-related sounds compared to neutral sounds. A dysfunctional appraisal of sleep was correlated with increased activation of the ACC, medial frontal cortex, prefrontal cortex, and brainstem in response to sleep-related sounds. These results suggest that negative and dysfunctional appraisals of sleep are associated with cortical hyperarousal and impaired inhibition in response to sleep-related sounds.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This research was supported by the Brain Research Program through the National Research Foundation of Korea, funded by the Ministry of Science, ICT and Future Planning (No. 2016M3C7A1904338; No. 2020M3E5D9080561, No.2022R1A2C2008417), and the grant of the Korea Health Technology R&amp;D Project through the Korea Health Industry Development Institute (KHIDI), funded by the Ministry of Health &amp; Welfare, Republic of Korea (No. HR21C0885).</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0005">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bion</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lowe</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Puthucheary</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Montgomery</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Reducing sound and light exposure to improve sleep on the adult intensive care unit: an inclusive narrative review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Intensive Care Soc</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>138</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1751143717740803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29796071</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aaron</surname>
<given-names>JN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carlisle</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carskadon</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meyer</surname>
<given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hill</surname>
<given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Millman</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Environmental noise as a cause of sleep disruption in an intermediate respiratory care unit</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>707</fpage>–<lpage>710</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/19.9.707</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9122557</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mills</surname>
<given-names>GH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Clinical review: the impact of noise on patients’ sleep and the effectiveness of noise reduction strategies in intensive care units</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Crit Care</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>208</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/cc7154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19344486</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Griffiths</surname>
<given-names>TD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The neural processing of complex sounds</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann N Y Acad Sci</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>930</volume>:<fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1749-6632.2001.tb05729.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11458824</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Theunissen</surname>
<given-names>FE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elie</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Neural processing of natural sounds</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>366</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn3731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24840800</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Seifritz</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Esposito</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hennel</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Spatiotemporal pattern of neural processing in the human auditory cortex</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Science</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>297</volume>(<issue>5587</issue>):<fpage>1706</fpage>–<lpage>1708</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1074355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12215648</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Frühholz</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trost</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kotz</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The sound of emotions-Towards a unifying neural network perspective of affective sound processing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurosci Biobehav Rev</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>68</volume>:<fpage>96</fpage>–<lpage>110</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2016.05.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27189782</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rauschecker</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scott</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Maps and streams in the auditory cortex: nonhuman primates illuminate human speech processing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>718</fpage>–<lpage>724</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.2331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19471271</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>von Kriegstein</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Friston</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Griffiths</surname>
<given-names>TD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Features versus feelings: dissociable representations of the acoustic features and valence of aversive sounds</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>41</issue>):<fpage>14184</fpage>–<lpage>14192</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1759-12.2012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23055488</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Frühholz</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grandjean</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Multiple subregions in superior temporal cortex are differentially sensitive to vocal expressions: a quantitative meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurosci Biobehav Rev</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>24</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2012.11.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23153796</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Szameitat</surname>
<given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kreifelts</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alter</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>It is not always tickling: distinct cerebral responses during perception of different laughter types</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroimage</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1264</fpage>–<lpage>1271</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2010.06.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20600991</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Amodio</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frith</surname>
<given-names>CD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Meeting of minds: the medial frontal cortex and social cognition</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>268</fpage>–<lpage>277</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn1884</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16552413</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bach</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grandjean</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sander</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Herdener</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Strik</surname>
<given-names>WK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seifritz</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effect of appraisal level on processing of emotional prosody in meaningless speech</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroimage</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>919</fpage>–<lpage>927</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2008.05.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18586524</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ethofer</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kreifelts</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wiethoff</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Differential influences of emotion, task, and novelty on brain regions underlying the processing of speech melody</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cogn Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1255</fpage>–<lpage>1268</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/jocn.2009.21099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18752404</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bamiou</surname>
<given-names>DE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Musiek</surname>
<given-names>FE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luxon</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The insula (Island of Reil) and its role in auditory processing. Literature review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Res Brain Res Rev</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>154</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0165-0173(03)00172-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12738055</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sander</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scheich</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Left auditory cortex and amygdala, but right insula dominance for human laughing and crying</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cogn Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1519</fpage>–<lpage>1531</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/089892905774597227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16269094</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martinez</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parsons</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Passive music listening spontaneously engages limbic and paralimbic systems</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroreport</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>2033</fpage>–<lpage>2037</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00001756-200409150-00008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15486477</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zald</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pardo</surname>
<given-names>JV</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The neural correlates of aversive auditory stimulation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroimage</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>3 Pt 1</issue>):<fpage>746</fpage>–<lpage>753</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/nimg.2002.1115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12169258</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Morin</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stone</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trinkle</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mercer</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Remsberg</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dysfunctional beliefs and attitudes about sleep among older adults with and without insomnia complaints</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Aging</italic></source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>463</fpage>–<lpage>467</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0882-7974.8.3.463</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8216967</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Espie</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Inglis</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harvey</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tessier</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomniacs’ attributions. psychometric properties of the dysfunctional beliefs and attitudes about sleep scale and the sleep disturbance questionnaire</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychosom Res</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>148</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-3999(99)00090-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10719130</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sandru</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Voinescu</surname>
<given-names>BI</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The relationship between emotion regulation, dysfunctional beliefs about sleep and sleep quality-an exploratory study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Evid Based Psychother</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>249</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kang</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>YJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Decreased regional brain activity in response to sleep-related sounds after cognitive behavioral therapy for psychophysiological insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>73</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>254</fpage>–<lpage>261</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pcn.12822</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30663182</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bush</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luu</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Posner</surname>
<given-names>MI</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cognitive and emotional influences in anterior cingulate cortex</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Trends Cogn Sci</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>222</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1364-6613(00)01483-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10827444</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stevens</surname>
<given-names>FL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hurley</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taber</surname>
<given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hurley</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hayman</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taber</surname>
<given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Anterior cingulate cortex: unique role in cognition and emotion</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neuropsychiatry Clin Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/jnp.23.2.jnp121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21677237</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Menon</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Uddin</surname>
<given-names>LQ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Saliency, switching, attention and control: a network model of insula function</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Struct Funct</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>214</volume>(<issue>5–6</issue>):<fpage>655</fpage>–<lpage>667</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00429-010-0262-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20512370</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Uddin</surname>
<given-names>LQ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Salience processing and insular cortical function and dysfunction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn3857</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25406711</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Davis</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whalen</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The amygdala: vigilance and emotion</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.mp.4000812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11244481</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>CF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monk</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berman</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kupfer</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Pittsburgh sleep quality index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0165-1781(89)90047-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2748771</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sohn</surname>
<given-names>SI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>MY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cho</surname>
<given-names>YW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The reliability and validity of the Korean version of the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>803</fpage>–<lpage>812</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-011-0579-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21901299</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>MacLean</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fekken</surname>
<given-names>GC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saskin</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knowles</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Psychometric evaluation of the Stanford sleepiness scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.1992.tb00006.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10607023</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Binder</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frost</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hammeke</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Human temporal lobe activation by speech and nonspeech sounds</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cereb Cortex</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>512</fpage>–<lpage>528</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/10.5.512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10847601</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ethofer</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Anders</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wiethoff</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of prosodic emotional intensity on activation of associative auditory cortex</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroreport</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>253</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.wnr.0000199466.32036.5d</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16462592</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wiethoff</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wildgruber</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kreifelts</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cerebral processing of emotional prosody–influence of acoustic parameters and arousal</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroimage</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>885</fpage>–<lpage>893</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2007.09.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17964813</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Concina</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Renna</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grosso</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sacchetti</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The auditory cortex and the emotional valence of sounds</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurosci Biobehav Rev</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>98</volume>:<fpage>256</fpage>–<lpage>264</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2019.01.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30664888</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mullinger</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mayhew</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bagshaw</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bowtell</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Francis</surname>
<given-names>ST</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Evidence that the negative BOLD response is neuronal in origin: a simultaneous EEG-BOLD-CBF study in humans</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroimage</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>94</volume>:<fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>274</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2014.02.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24632092</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Anticevic</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cole</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Murray</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Corlett</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>XJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krystal</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The role of default network deactivation in cognition and disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Trends Cogn Sci</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>584</fpage>–<lpage>592</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tics.2012.10.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23142417</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Raichle</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The brain’s default mode network</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Annu Rev Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>433</fpage>–<lpage>447</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-neuro-071013-014030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25938726</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gusnard</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raichle</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raichle</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Searching for a baseline: functional imaging and the resting human brain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>685</fpage>–<lpage>694</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35094500</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11584306</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fransson</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Spontaneous low-frequency BOLD signal fluctuations: an fMRI investigation of the resting-state default mode of brain function hypothesis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hum Brain Mapp</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.20113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15852468</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>YJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Exploration of changes in the brain response to sleep-related pictures after cognitive-behavioral therapy for psychophysiological insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>12528</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-13065-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28970534</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Plante</surname>
<given-names>DT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jensen</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schoerning</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Winkelman</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Reduced γ-aminobutyric acid in occipital and anterior cingulate cortices in primary insomnia: a link to major depressive disorder?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropsychopharmacology</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1548</fpage>–<lpage>1557</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/npp.2012.4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22318195</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fountoulakis</surname>
<given-names>KN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Giannakopoulos</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kövari</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bouras</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Assessing the role of cingulate cortex in bipolar disorder: neuropathological, structural and functional imaging data</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Res Rev</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainresrev.2008.04.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18539335</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>de Kwaasteniet</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruhe</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caan</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Relation between structural and functional connectivity in major depressive disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biol Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>74</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2012.12.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23399372</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dehaene</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Artiges</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Naccache</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Conscious and subliminal conflicts in normal subjects and patients with schizophrenia: the role of the anterior cingulate</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>100</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):<fpage>13722</fpage>–<lpage>13727</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2235214100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14597698</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fuller</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sherman</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pedersen</surname>
<given-names>NP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saper</surname>
<given-names>CB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Reassessment of the structural basis of the ascending arousal system</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Comp Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>519</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<fpage>3817</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.22781</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sakai</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crochet</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Differentiation of presumed serotonergic dorsal raphe neurons in relation to behavior and wake–sleep states</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroscience</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1141</fpage>–<lpage>1155</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0306-4522(01)00103-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11457597</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Monti</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The role of dorsal raphe nucleus serotonergic and non-serotonergic neurons, and of their receptors, in regulating waking and rapid eye movement (REM) sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>319</fpage>–<lpage>327</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2009.10.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20153670</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
