<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="brief-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36187325</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">9519124</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">372823</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S372823</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Short Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Emotional and Environmental Factors Aggravating Dream Enactment Behaviors in Patients with Isolated REM Sleep Behavior Disorder</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Jun et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Jun et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Jun</surname>
            <given-names>Jin-Sun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Sunwoo</surname>
            <given-names>Jun-Sang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Byun</surname>
            <given-names>Jung-Ick</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shin</surname>
            <given-names>Jung-Won</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Tae-Joon</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Schenck</surname>
            <given-names>Carlos H</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0006" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5528-9081</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Jung</surname>
            <given-names>Ki-Young</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0007" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Neurology, Kangnam Sacred Heart Hospital, Hallym University College of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Seoul</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Neurology, Kangbuk Samsung Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Seoul</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Neurology, Kyung Hee University Hospital at Gangdong</institution>, <addr-line>Seoul</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Neurology, CHA Bundang Medical Center, CHA University</institution>, <addr-line>Seongnam</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label><institution>Department of Neurology, Ajou University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Suwon</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0006"><label>6</label><institution>Minnesota Regional Sleep Disorders Center, and Department of Psychiatry, Hennepin County Medical Center and University of Minnesota Medical School</institution>, <addr-line>Minneapolis</addr-line>, <addr-line>MN</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0007"><label>7</label><institution>Department of Neurology, Seoul National University Hospital, Seoul National University College of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Seoul</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Ki-Young Jung, <institution>Department of Neurology, Seoul National University Hospital, Neuroscience Research Institute, Seoul National University College of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>101 Daehak-ro, Jongno-gu</addr-line>, <addr-line>Seoul</addr-line>, <addr-line>03080</addr-line>, <country>Korea</country>, <phone>Tel +82-2-2072-4988</phone>, <fax>Fax +82-2-3672-7553</fax>, Email jungky@snu.ac.kr</corresp>
        <fn id="ft0001">
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">*These authors contributed equally to this work</citation_analysis></p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>24</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <fpage>1713</fpage>
      <lpage>1720</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>29</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2022 Jun et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Jun et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Objective</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">To identify emotional and environmental factors that aggravate dream enactment behaviors (DEBs) in isolated rapid eye movement (REM) sleep behavior disorder (iRBD).</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In this cross-sectional study, a total of 96 polysomnography-confirmed iRBD patients (mean age, 68.5 years; men, 68%) and their caregivers completed questionnaires regarding potential aggravating factors related to DEBs, including emotion/feelings (stress, anger, anxiety, depressive mood, fatigue, pain), food (alcohol, caffeine, overeating in the evening, fasting/hunger), activities and sleep patterns (strenuous exercise, sex before bed, conflict/fighting, sleep deprivation, oversleeping, sleeping away from home, watching TV before bed), weather/environmental factors (cloudy or rainy weather, heat, cold, noise) and medication (skipping medication, taking hypnotics).</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The patients reported that stress (61%) was the most aggravating factor for DEBs, followed by anxiety (56%), anger (51%), fatigue (49%), and watching TV before bed (46%). Similarly, the caregivers reported that these factors were most relevant to the aggravation of DEBs in the patients, although some factors were ranked differently. In the subgroup analyses, aggravating factors for DEBs did not differ by RBD symptom severity. Interestingly, the proportion of patients experiencing DEB aggravation by stress, anxiety and depressive mood was significantly higher in women than in men. Furthermore, depressed patients reported that stress and cloudy or rainy weather made DEBs worse than nondepressed patients.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our results suggest that DEBs in iRBD patients may be mainly aggravated by emotional factors. These negative effects appeared to be more prominent in female and depressed patients.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>REM sleep behavior disorder</kwd>
        <kwd>dream enactment behavior</kwd>
        <kwd>precipitating factors</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Research Foundation</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="open-funder-registry">10.13039/100011512</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Research Foundation</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="open-funder-registry">10.13039/100011512</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Research Foundation</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="open-funder-registry">10.13039/100011512</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>This study was supported by a research grant of National Research Foundation funded by the Ministry of Science and ICT (MSIT) in Korea (NRF-2020R1C1C1013382), the Brain Research Program through the National Research Foundation of Korea funded by the Ministry of Science, ICT &amp; Future Planning (2017M3C7A1029688) and the National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF) grant funded by the Korean government (MSIP) (2017R1A2B2012280).</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="1"/>
        <table-count count="3"/>
        <ref-count count="33"/>
        <page-count count="8"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Rapid eye movement (REM) sleep behavior disorder (RBD) is a parasomnia characterized by dream enactment behaviors (DEBs) due to a loss of muscle atonia during REM sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> A growing body of evidence suggests that patients with isolated RBD (iRBD) eventually develop a neurodegenerative disease, including Parkinson’s disease (PD), dementia with Lewy bodies, and, less frequently, multiple system atrophy, with a conversion risk of over 80% in a decade or more.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">DEBs in patients with RBD range from simple motions such as limb jerking and sleep talking to complex and violent movements such as punching and kicking.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Previous studies have shown that DEBs can result in sleep disruption and life-threatening injuries for both patients and their bed partners.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Accordingly, appropriate treatment should be considered depending on the symptoms in patients with RBD. The current treatment guidelines for DEBs in RBD include pharmacological agents, mainly clonazepam and melatonin.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> However, definitive conclusions cannot be drawn from recent randomized controlled trials, in which both drugs failed to show effectiveness in patients with iRBD and PD patients with RBD.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8–10</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Bedroom environmental modifications are also recommended to prevent injurious behaviors for all patients with RBD. Recommended measures include removing dangerous objects from the bedroom, placing a mattress on the floor, and sleeping in separate bedrooms. However, these recommendations focus only on modifying the bedroom environment. In our experience, some patients with RBD complained of aggravation of DEBs after emotional stress or alcohol consumption. Furthermore, it has been reported that the worsening of DEBs was related to traumatic stress following a disturbing event</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> or chocolate ingestion.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> These observations suggest that it is necessary for patients with RBD to avoid DEB precipitating factors, but there have been no studies to comprehensively explore such factors. Therefore, in this study, we aimed to identify the emotional and environmental factors that potentially aggravate DEBs in iRBD patients.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Study Design and Participants</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We prospectively recruited consecutive patients with iRBD from the Department of Neurology at Seoul National University Hospital between 1 March 2020 and 31 August 2021. All participants underwent overnight video-polysomnography (PSG), and a diagnosis of RBD was confirmed based on the third edition of the International Classification of Sleep Disorders.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The participants were excluded if they had any sign suggestive of neurodegenerative disease, such as parkinsonism and dementia, confirmed by a neurologist. This study was approved by the Review Board of the Seoul National University Hospital and written informed consent for research was obtained from all individuals who participated in the study (IRB No. 2007-189-1144). The study followed the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Variables</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Twenty-three potential precipitating factors related to DEBs were selected by seven RBD experts based on their clinical experience, including emotion/feelings (stress, anger, anxiety, depressive mood, fatigue, pain), food (alcohol, caffeine, overeating in the evening, fasting/hunger), activities and sleep patterns (strenuous exercise, sex before bed, conflict/fighting, sleep deprivation, oversleeping, sleeping away from home, watching TV before bed), weather/environmental factors (cloudy or rainy weather, heat, cold, noise) and medication (skipping medication, taking hypnotics). Patients and their caregivers were independently asked to respond either “yes” or “no” to the questions about whether the above factors aggravated DEBs in the past.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In addition, the clinical severity of RBD was assessed using the Korean version of the RBD Questionnaire-Hong Kong (RBDQ-KR).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Depression was assessed using the Korean version of the Geriatric Depression Scale (GDS-K),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> and the cutoff value for the presence of depression was defined as ≥18. Cognitive function was assessed using the Korean version of the Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA-K).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">All data are presented as the mean±standard deviation. Data distribution and normality were assessed using the Shapiro–Wilk test. Demographic and clinical characteristics were compared using the chi-square test for categorical variables and Student’s </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-test or the Mann–Whitney </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">U</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">-test for continuous variables, as appropriate. We investigated the relationship between aggravation of DEBs by emotional and environmental factors and clinical variables, including age, RBD duration, and scores on the RBDQ-KR, GDS-K, and MoCA-K using point-biserial correlations for binary outcomes (aggravation yes/no). Furthermore, subgroup analyses were performed using the chi-square test or Fisher’s exact test to explore whether the association between DEB aggravation and emotional and environmental factors differs by sex, RBD symptom severity, the presence of depression, or severity of obstructive sleep apnea (OSA). Because this is an exploratory study, no adjustments were made to control type I error. All </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> values were two-sided, and a </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> value of less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant. Calculations were performed with SPSS (IBM) version 27.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">A total of 96 iRBD patients and 84 caregivers were included in this study. The demographic and clinical characteristics of all patients are shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. The mean age of the iRBD patients was 68.5±6.7 years, and 65 (67.7%) were men. The patients had a mean RBD symptom duration of 7.0±5.4 years. The male group had a higher education level than the female group (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=0.006). The scores on the GDS-K, MoCA-K and RBDQ-KR did not significantly differ between men and women. All patients were receiving clonazepam and/or melatonin for RBD at the time of the study.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Demographic and Clinical Characteristics</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (n=96)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men (n=65)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women (n=31)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.5 (6.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.3 (6.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.0 (6.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.610</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RBD duration, years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0 (5.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7 (6.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6 (3.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.086</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male sex, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (67.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Educational level, years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4 (4.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3 (3.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7 (4.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.006</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GDS-K</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7 (4.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2 (7.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7 (6.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.323</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MoCA-K score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.9 (2.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.7 (3.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.4 (2.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.657</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RBDQ-KR score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.3 (19.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.6 (20.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0 (18.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.222</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medication</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Clonazepam only, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (52.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (50.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (54.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Melatonin only, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (51.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (43.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (67.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Antidepressant, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (3.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Polysomnographic variables</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Time in bed, min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">450.9 (54.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">450.6 (60.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">451.7 (49.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.927</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Total sleep time, min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">345.9 (77.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">340.2 (85.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">354.2 (62.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.426</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Wake after sleep onset, min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.7 (61.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.3 (60.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.3 (68.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.665</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sleep efficiency, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.6 (13.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.6 (13.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.0 (14.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.425</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sleep latency, min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.0 (23.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0 (18.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.2 (28.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.276</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> REM sleep latency, min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">112.7 (60.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111.2 (58.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">127.6 (72.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.244</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> N1 sleep, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.0 (15.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.0 (15.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.2 (12.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> N2 sleep, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.8 (14.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.5 (12.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.4 (14.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> N3 sleep, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6 (7.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5 (6.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1 (9.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.390</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> REM sleep, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1 (6.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1 (6.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.0 (6.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.975</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> AHI, events/hour</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.6 (14.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8 (15.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1 (8.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.003</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Arousal index, events/hour</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.7 (18.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.7 (19.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.1 (16.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.263</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Notes</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Data are n (%) and the mean (standard deviation). Bold values denote statistical significance at the </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.05 level.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: AHI, apnea-hypopnea index; GDS-K, Korean version of the Geriatric depression scale; MoCA-K, Korean version of the Montreal Cognitive Assessment; N1, non-REM sleep stage 1; N2, non-REM sleep stage 2; N3, non-REM sleep stage 3; RBDQ-KR, Korean version of the REM Sleep Behavior Disorder Questionnaire-Hong Kong.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The results for potential DEB aggravating factors are shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. Fifty-five patients (61%) and 56 (67%) caregivers answered that stress was the primary factor that aggravated DEBs. The other top 5 precipitating factors for DEBs were anxiety (56%), anger (51%), fatigue (49%) and watching TV before going to bed (46%) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). According to caregivers, the top 5 precipitating factors for DEBs were fatigue (62%), watching TV before going to bed (57%), anxiety (56%), and anger (50%), which was roughly similar to the responses according to the patients (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). The results for potential DEB aggravating factors were not significantly different between the patients and their caregivers (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=372823.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). Next, we examined which clinical parameters were associated with the top 5 precipitating factors for DEBs, and these results are summarized in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=372823.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 2</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. We found that the aggravation of DEBs by stress was correlated with higher GDS-K scores (r=0.230, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">=0.024), whereas there were no significant correlations with the other clinical variables.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Dream enactment behavior aggravating factors, colored by category, according to isolated REM sleep behavior disorder patients (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>A</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) and their caregivers (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>B</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-1713-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In the subgroup analyses, the female group had a higher proportion of DEB aggravation by stress (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=0.026), anxiety (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=0.045), and depressive mood (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=0.022) than the male group (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). The proportion of DEB aggravation by alcohol was significantly higher in men than in women (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">=0.002). A comparison between depressed and nondepressed patients, depressed patients reported that stress (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=0.026) and cloudy or rainy weather (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">=0.05) made DEBs worse than nondepressed patients (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">). Aggravating factors did not differ by RBD symptom severity or OSA severity (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=372823.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Tables 3</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=372823.docx" ext-link-type="uri">4</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Comparison of Precipitating Factors on Dream Enactment Behaviors Between Men and Women</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men (n=65)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women (n=31)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Emotion and feelings</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Stress</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (53.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (77.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.026</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Anger</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (44.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (64.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.068</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Anxiety</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (49.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (71.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.045</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Depressive mood</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (27.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (51.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.022</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Fatigue</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (44.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (58.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.218</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Pain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (23.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (38.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.111</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Food</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Alcohol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (32.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (3.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.002</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Caffeine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (26.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (25.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.971</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Overeating in the evening</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (21.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (16.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.534</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Fasting/Hunger</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (15.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (19.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.625</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Activities and sleep patterns</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Strenuous exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (20.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (16.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.650</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sex before bed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (12.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (3.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.153</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Conflict/fight</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (30.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (45.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.168</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sleep deprivation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (26.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (35.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.347</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Oversleeping</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (12.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (12.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.934</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sleeping away from home</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (29.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (32.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.763</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Watching TV before bed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (44.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (48.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.729</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Weather or environmental factors</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Cloudy or rainy weather</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (18.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (16.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.780</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Heat</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (16.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (12.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.612</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Cold</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (15.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (25.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.221</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Noise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (20.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (9.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.204</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Medication</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Skipping medication</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (18.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (22.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.636</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Taking hypnotics</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (9.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (16.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.321</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Note</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Bold values denote statistical significance at the </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.05 level.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Comparison of Precipitating Factors on Dream Enactment Behaviors Between Depressed and Nondepressed Groups</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depressed Group (n=13)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nondepressed Group (n=83)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Emotion and feelings</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Stress</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (92.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (56.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.026</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Anger</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (76.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (47.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.071</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Anxiety</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (76.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (53.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.138</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Depressive mood</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (53.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (32.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.211</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Fatigue</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (61.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (47.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.382</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Pain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (30.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (27.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Food</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Alcohol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (15.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (24.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.726</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Caffeine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (38.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (24.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.313</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Overeating in the evening</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (38.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (16.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.126</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Fasting/Hunger</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (23.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (15.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.450</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Activities and sleep patterns</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Strenuous exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (15.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (19.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sex before bed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (7.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (9.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Conflict/fight</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (61.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (31.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.058</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sleep deprivation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (38.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (27.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.514</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Oversleeping</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (15.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (12.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.664</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sleeping away from home</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (30.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (30.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Watching TV before bed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (46.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (45.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Weather or environmental factor</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Cloudy or rainy weather</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (38.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (14.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.050</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Heat</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (30.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (13.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.117</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Cold</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (30.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (16.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.257</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Noise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (15.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (16.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Medication</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Skipping medication</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (7.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (21.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.454</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Taking hypnotics</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (23.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (9.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.168</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Note</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: Bold values denote statistical significance at the </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.05 level.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In this study, we investigated which emotional and environmental factors aggravate DEBs in iRBD patients. Our results showed that iRBD patients reported that emotional factors such as stress, anxiety, and anger were the factors that aggravated DEBs most frequently, which is roughly consistent with the results reported by their caregivers. In the subgroup analyses, the proportion of patients experiencing DEB aggravation by stress, anxiety and depressive mood was significantly higher in women than in men. Furthermore, depressed patients reported that stress and cloudy or rainy weather made DEBs worse than nondepressed patients. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study to systematically investigate precipitating factors for DEBs in iRBD patients.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Previous studies found that post-traumatic stress disease (PTSD) is related to DEBs in patients with RBD as well as those with non-REM parasomnias,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> which is in line with our findings. While the precise mechanism of RBD in patients with PTSD remains largely unknown, it is suggested that the increased turnover of noradrenaline by PTSD results in its depletion in the peri-locus coeruleus, which causes dysfunction in the regulation of REM sleep atonia.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Furthermore, there is also evidence showing that psychological stress itself, regardless of PTSD, provokes disturbances of noradrenergic function in various brain regions.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Given the potential role of noradrenaline in the occurrence of RBD,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> one can postulate that noradrenergic pathway alterations due to emotional stress contribute to the aggravation of DEBs in iRBD patients. Although stress has also been reported to increase serotonin turnover in the brain,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> it remains debatable whether the serotonergic system is directly involved in RBD pathogenesis.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Alternatively, a recent animal study revealed that chronic stress provokes enhanced REM sleep,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> which may partially explain our findings.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">On the other hand, stressful events can result in highly traumatic or violent dreams.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Considering the fact that verbal or motor components of dreaming are enacted behaviorally in iRBD patients,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> changes in dream contents by stressful events may not only increase the occurrence of DEBs per se but also provoke more aggressive DEBs. In support of this hypothesis, a recent study showed that aggressiveness was more frequent in dreams related to DEBs in iRBD patients, although the frequency of aggressive dream contents did not differ between the patients and healthy controls.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our results showed that the proportion of patients experiencing DEB aggravation by emotional factors was significantly higher in females than males, indicating sex-specific effects of precipitating factors for DEBs in iRBD patients. In general, females tend to have a higher prevalence and greater severity of mental disorders, including PTSD, panic disorder, and major depressive disorder.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Accordingly, it is plausible that the absolute proportion of patients experiencing emotional factors is higher in females, which may contribute to disparities between the sexes in factors aggravating DEBs. However, this possibility cannot be explained by our finding that there was no significant difference in depressive symptoms between men and women. On the other hand, sex differences in responses to the stress neuropeptide, which is a corticotropin-releasing factor, are thought to increase female vulnerability to stress in mental disorders.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In this context, increased stress sensitivity in females may be linked to sex differences in the emotional factors aggravating DEBs in iRBD patients.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Similarly, the impact of stress on DEB aggravation was more prominent in depressed patients than in nondepressed patients, which may be associated with emotion dysregulation.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Emotion regulation is a complex process that involves adjusting emotional responses to cope with difficult situations, and its impairment is regarded as a potential mechanism in the development of depression.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Accordingly, we speculate that depressed patients have more severe emotion dysregulation, increasing vulnerability to stress.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In addition to emotional factors, “watching TV before bed” was one of the major factors aggravating DEBs in iRBD patients. It is well known that watching TV at night is associated with sleep problems, mainly due to exposure to bright light.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, considering the current finding of a potential association between emotional factors and DEBs, TV content may be more important than the act of watching TV itself in determining the extent of aggravation by watching TV. One patient had repetitively experienced DEBs more frequently and violently when he watched action movies or martial sports before going to bed. Unfortunately, our study did not include an analysis of the contents or duration of watching TV before bed, which needs to be performed in future studies.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">A recent review suggests that patients with RBD should avoid alcohol consumption, as this factor can aggravate RBD-related symptoms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Based on our experience, we also hypothesized that alcohol intake would be associated with the worsening of DEBs in iRBD patients. However, only approximately one-quarter of our patients answered that alcohol intake aggravated DEBs, and alcohol intake was ranked 12th among 23 potential precipitating factors. This weak relationship may be due to the low frequency of alcohol consumption in this study sample. In the current study, the proportion of patients who consumed alcohol more than 2 times per week was just less than 10%. Consistent with this assumption, our results showed that the negative impact of alcohol intake on DEBs seemed prominent only in men, and not surprisingly, men (68%) were more likely to drink alcohol than women (10%).</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The present study has several limitations. First, the assessment of DEBs or its aggravating factors was based on self-report and therefore may have the risk of introducing recall bias. However, given the night-to-night variability in DEBs, patient-reported outcome measures may be more reliable than objective outcome measures using PSG. Moreover, to minimize bias, we also included each caregiver’s assessment, and the results were similar to those of patients. Second, because this study focused on the frequency of DEBs as an outcome measure, it still remains unclear whether exposure to emotional and environmental factors affect the severity of DEBs. Third, the sample size in subgroup analyses was modest in some cases, which may hamper the detection of significant associations. Additionally, our sample size was limited to the power to determine differences according to sex or the presence of depression in precipitating factors for DEBs. Fourth, the proportion of patients consuming alcohol in our dataset was relatively small. Furthermore, we did not obtain data on the quantity of alcohol consumption. For these reasons, a reliable conclusion about the association between alcohol intake and DEBs cannot be drawn from our results. Further studies with a larger sample size of regular alcohol-drinkers and detailed information on alcohol consumption, such as the frequency and intensity of alcohol consumption and the type of alcohol consumed, should be considered to clarify this issue. Fifth, although dream content changes may be one of the plausible mechanisms by which emotional factors were associated with DEB aggravation in our findings, we could not perform a dream content analysis due to lack of data. Last, the cross-sectional design of the current study prevented us from drawing conclusions about causality.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In summary, our results suggest that DEBs in iRBD patients may be mainly aggravated by emotional factors such as stress, anxiety, and anger. These effects were more prominent in females and depressed patients. Our results may emphasize the potential importance of emotional control as well as lifestyle modification to manage DEBs in iRBD patients. However, because this study design has potential biases from self-reported subjective data, further studies using objective measures of emotional factors and DEBs should be performed to clarify this issue.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0005">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Dr Carlos H Schenck reports personal fees from Eisai, Inc., outside the submitted work. The authors report no other conflicts of interest in this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schenck</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mahowald</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>REM sleep behavior disorder: clinical, developmental, and neuroscience perspectives 16 years after its formal identification in SLEEP</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>120</fpage>–<lpage>138</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/25.2.120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11902423</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cesari</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heidbreder</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>St Louis</surname>
<given-names>EK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Video-polysomnography procedures for diagnosis of rapid eye movement sleep behavior disorder (RBD) and the identification of its prodromal stages: guidelines from the International RBD Study Group</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>zsab257</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsab257</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34694408</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Iranzo</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Santamaria</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tolosa</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Idiopathic rapid eye movement sleep behaviour disorder: diagnosis, management, and the need for neuroprotective interventions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>405</fpage>–<lpage>419</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(16)00057-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26971662</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Olson</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boeve</surname>
<given-names>BF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Silber</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Rapid eye movement sleep behaviour disorder: demographic, clinical and laboratory findings in 93 cases</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>123</volume>(<issue>Pt 2</issue>):<fpage>331</fpage>–<lpage>339</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/123.2.331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10648440</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McCarter</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>St Louis</surname>
<given-names>EK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boswell</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Factors associated with injury in REM sleep behavior disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1332</fpage>–<lpage>1338</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2014.06.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25194585</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aurora</surname>
<given-names>RN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zak</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maganti</surname>
<given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Best practice guide for the treatment of REM sleep behavior disorder (RBD)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.27717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20191945</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gilat</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marshall</surname>
<given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Testelmans</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buyse</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lewis</surname>
<given-names>SJG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A critical review of the pharmacological treatment of REM sleep behavior disorder in adults: time for more and larger randomized placebo-controlled trials</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>269</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>148</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00415-020-10353-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33410930</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shin</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>WW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jeon</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Clonazepam for probable REM sleep behavior disorder in Parkinson’s disease: a randomized placebo-controlled trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>401</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jns.2019.04.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31035190</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jun</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Byun</surname>
<given-names>JI</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prolonged-release melatonin in patients with idiopathic REM sleep behavior disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Clin Transl Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>716</fpage>–<lpage>722</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/acn3.753</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31019996</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gilat</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coeytaux jackson</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marshall</surname>
<given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Melatonin for rapid eye movement sleep behavior disorder in Parkinson’s disease: a randomised controlled trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mov Disord</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>344</fpage>–<lpage>349</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mds.27886</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31674060</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jeevan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Clinical correlates of dream enactment behaviors in previously deployed OEF/OIF/OND Veterans: an exploratory analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neuropsychiatry Clin Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>147</fpage>–<lpage>153</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.neuropsych.19010009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31587626</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Elliott</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Opel</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pleshakov</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Posttraumatic stress disorder increases the odds of REM sleep behavior disorder and other parasomnias in Veterans with and without comorbid traumatic brain injury</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>3</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsz237</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vorona</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ware</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Exacerbation of REM sleep behavior disorder by chocolate ingestion: a case report</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>365</fpage>–<lpage>367</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1389-9457(02)00008-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14592201</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sateia</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>International classification of sleep disorders-third edition: highlights and modifications</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>146</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1387</fpage>–<lpage>1394</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.14-0970</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25367475</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>SX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wing</surname>
<given-names>YK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lam</surname>
<given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Validation of a new REM sleep behavior disorder questionnaire (RBDQ-HK)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2009.06.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19945912</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>You</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moon</surname>
<given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Do</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The REM sleep behavior disorder screening questionnaire: validation study of the Korean version (RBDQ-KR)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1429</fpage>–<lpage>1433</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.6840</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29117888</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bae</surname>
<given-names>JN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cho</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Development of the Korean version of the Geriatric Depression Scale and its short form among elderly psychiatric patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychosom Res</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>305</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychores.2004.01.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15507257</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dong Woo</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cho</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Brief screening for mild cognitive impairment in elderly outpatient clinic: validation of the Korean version of the Montreal Cognitive Assessment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Geriatr Psychiatry Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>104</fpage>–<lpage>110</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0891988708316855</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18474719</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Husain</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>PP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carwile</surname>
<given-names>ST</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Rem sleep behavior disorder: potential relationship to post-traumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Neurophysiol</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>148</fpage>–<lpage>157</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004691-200103000-00005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11435805</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pacák</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Palkovits</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Stressor specificity of central neuroendocrine responses: implications for stress-related disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Endocr Rev</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>502</fpage>–<lpage>548</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/edrv.22.4.0436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11493581</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jiménez-Jiménez</surname>
<given-names>FJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alonso-Navarro</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>García-Martín</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Agúndez</surname>
<given-names>JAG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Neurochemical features of rem sleep behaviour disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Pers Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>880</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jpm11090880</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34575657</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chaouloff</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berton</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mormède</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Serotonin and stress</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropsychopharmacology</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>2 Suppl</issue>):<fpage>28s</fpage>–<lpage>32s</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0893-133X(99)00008-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10432486</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Arnaldi</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fama</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Carli</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The role of the serotonergic system in REM sleep behavior disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1505</fpage>–<lpage>1509</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.5000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25845692</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nollet</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hicks</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCarthy</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>REM sleep’s unique associations with corticosterone regulation, apoptotic pathways, and behavior in chronic stress in mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>116</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>2733</fpage>–<lpage>2742</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1816456116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30683720</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pillar</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malhotra</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lavie</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Post-traumatic stress disorder and sleep—what a nightmare</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>183</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/smrv.1999.0095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12531165</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nielsen</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Levin</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Nightmares: a new neurocognitive model</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>295</fpage>–<lpage>310</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2007.03.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17498981</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cavallotti</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stein</surname>
<given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Savarese</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Terzaghi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>D’Agostino</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Aggressiveness in the dreams of drug-naïve and clonazepam-treated patients with isolated REM sleep behavior disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2022.02.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35325765</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Breslau</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davis</surname>
<given-names>GC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peterson</surname>
<given-names>EL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schultz</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Psychiatric sequelae of posttraumatic stress disorder in women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Gen Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archpsyc.1997.01830130087016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9006404</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bangasser</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Curtis</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reyes</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sex differences in corticotropin-releasing factor receptor signaling and trafficking: potential role in female vulnerability to stress-related psychopathology</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>896</fpage>–<lpage>904</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2010.66</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jun</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jung</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Emotion dysregulation in idiopathic rapid eye movement sleep behavior disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>zsz224</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsz224</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31553439</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gross</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Emotion regulation: current status and future prospects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Inq</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1047840X.2014.940781</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gradisar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wolfson</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harvey</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hale</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosenberg</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Czeisler</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The sleep and technology use of Americans: findings from the National Sleep Foundation’s 2011 Sleep in America poll</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1291</fpage>–<lpage>1299</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.3272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24340291</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dauvilliers</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schenck</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Postuma</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>REM sleep behaviour disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Dis Primers</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>19</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41572-018-0016-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30166532</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
