<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36284857</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">9588286</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">381020</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S381020</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>The Association of Tonsil Hypertrophy with Pediatric Dentofacial Development: Evidence from a Cross-Sectional Study of Young Children in Shanghai, China</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Tong et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Tong et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Tong</surname>
            <given-names>Xianqin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Yuanyuan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Gang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Hao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jiang</surname>
            <given-names>Yiwei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>Jin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Da</surname>
            <given-names>Dongxin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zeng</surname>
            <given-names>Xiaoli</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3033-8873</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Yuehua</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0002" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Orthodontics, Shanghai Stomatological Hospital &amp; School of Stomatology, Fudan University</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Shanghai Key Laboratory of Craniomaxillofacial Development and Diseases, Fudan University</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Pediatric Dentistry, Shanghai Stomatological Hospital &amp; School of Stomatology, Fudan University</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Preventive Dentistry, Shanghai Stomatological Hospital &amp; School of Stomatology, Fudan University</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Xiaoli Zeng, <institution>Department of Preventive Dentistry, Shanghai Stomatological Hospital &amp; School of Stomatology, Fudan University</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, Email lylyz97@163.com</corresp>
        <corresp id="an0002">Yuehua Liu, <institution>Department of Orthodontics, Shanghai Stomatological Hospital &amp; School of Stomatology, Fudan University</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, Email liuyuehua@fudan.edu.cn</corresp>
        <fn id="ft0001">
          <label>*</label>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">These authors contributed equally to this work</citation_analysis></p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>19</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <fpage>1867</fpage>
      <lpage>1875</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>03</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2022 Tong et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Tong et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The prevalence of dentofacial deformity was reportedly higher than decades ago, to which upper airway (UA) obstruction-induced sleep-disordered breathing (SDB) might contribute a lot. Tonsil hypertrophy appears relatively common in the population of young children. Given that the association between tonsil hypertrophy and pediatric dentofacial deformity remained controversial, this cross-sectional research was designed to explore the internal relationship of those among young children in Shanghai, China.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Patients and Methods</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">A stratified cluster sampling procedure was adopted, and a representative sample of 715 young children (8–10 years old) was recruited. The OSA-18 quality-of-life questionnaires (OSA-18) were finished by their guardians, and well-trained orthodontists performed the oral examinations. After collecting the valuable information, the descriptions and analyses were run by statistical software (SPSS, version 26.0).</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">715 participants (334 boys and 381 girls) were involved in the analyses. As calculated, the current prevalence of malocclusion identified by Angle’s classification was 45.6% in this sample. No evident relation between OSA-18 scores and dentofacial abnormalities (P &gt; 0.05) was found. With the enlargement of tonsil size, the proportion of children with triangular dental arch form (P &lt; 0.05) and high vault palate (P &lt; 0.001) was increasingly higher. More children with protruding profiles and fewer upright profiles were observed as the tonsil size increased, although it did not show a statistical difference (P = 0.103).</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Dental and craniofacial growth deficiency has become more prevalent among children, demanding more concerns from health authorities. Tonsil hypertrophy plays an essential role in the direction of dentofacial development. More efforts from local health authorities should be made to enhance public propaganda and education on the prevention and interruption of tonsil hypertrophy and related dentofacial abnormalities.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>dentofacial growth</kwd>
        <kwd>malocclusion</kwd>
        <kwd>tonsil enlargement</kwd>
        <kwd>sleep-disordered breathing</kwd>
        <kwd>OSA-18</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="0"/>
        <table-count count="5"/>
        <ref-count count="30"/>
        <page-count count="9"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The prevalence of dentofacial deformity among the Chinese population of children and adolescents, as is reported, has increased by 27% from the 1960s to the 21st century, which not only deteriorates oral function but also compromises psychological state.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Among multiple complex factors, upper airway (UA) obstruction is one of the most common pathologies threatening pediatric dentofacial growth,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> attributed to anatomical factors like tonsil enlargement, adenoid hypertrophy, and nasal obstruction.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Chronic airway obstruction possibly induces long-term sleep-disordered breathing (SDB) behaviors like mouth-breathing, snoring, and the most severe form of obstructive sleep apnea (OSA). If left ignored, long-term SDB might cause morbid behavioral disturbances, neurocognitive dysfunction, and even higher expression of inflammatory mediators throughout the whole system.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Also, alterations in the tongue’s position and posture of the head and neck may break the balance of oral and peri-oral muscles during mouth-breathing, consequently negatively impacting the pattern of morphological growth according to Moss’s theory.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> These children tend to develop a more retrusive mandible, less pronounced nose, integrated with occlusion and dental arch abnormalities.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Almost 65% of children with habitual mouth-breathing suffered from tonsil and adenoid enlargement, as reported by a cross-sectional study on 114 children.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The role that tonsil enlargement plays in the process of dentofacial growth has been previously discussed within the orthodontic field and yet remained controversial. In 1987, Behlfelt et al conducted research on a sample of 73 children with enlarged tonsils in Sweden. It was figured out later that these children might tend to be afflicted with functional or morphological disorders such as short dental arches and crossbite, statistically correlated with narrow nasopharyngeal airways.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The positive relationship between sagittal cephalometric abnormalities and tonsil grades was also confirmed.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> A majority of scholars and researchers obtained similar conclusions that tonsil hypertrophy might be one of the risk factors for dentofacial abnormalities.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Different voices, however, also emerged. Deana and his coworkers carried out an observable cross-sectional study among children from 6 to 12 years old and found no correlation between the grades of palatal tonsil and dental arch-related parameters.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">To our best knowledge, related literature on the Chinese population of children was rare. Our cross-sectional study aimed to estimate the prevalence of dentofacial abnormalities and clarify the association of tonsil grades with dentofacial growth characteristics based on a sample of Chinese children aged about 9 years old in Shanghai. Given the frequent occurrence of pediatric dentofacial abnormalities these years, we tried to explore the connection between tonsil hypertrophy and dentofacial abnormalities among Chinese children in Shanghai, hoping to adopt intervention in the earlier stage.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Design and Participants</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This cross-sectional study was conducted from March to June 2019 in Shanghai, China. A stratified-cluster sampling procedure was adopted, and a representative sample of the primary students of the fourth grade was enrolled. Briefly, two districts in the urban and rural areas in Shanghai were randomly selected. Three primary schools in every district were subsequently obtained, and two classes from the fourth grade were randomly selected. Students (mean age: 9.3 ± 0.4 years) in these classes were identified as participants in the survey. Students with tooth agenesis, any congenital disorders or diseases, and lower behavior management abilities were excluded from the study. Informed consents were obtained from all participants and their guardians, which has been approved by the Ethical Committee of the Shanghai Stomatological Hospital (2016-0007). We conducted this research in compliance with the Declaration of Helsinki.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Methods</title>
        <sec id="s0002-s2002-s3001">
          <title>OSA-18 Survey</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">OSA-18 is a specific questionnaire to classify the life quality of children with OSA risk. Compared to polysomnography (PSG), OSA-18 is more comfortable and affordable for families, concise, and suitable for large-scale epidemiological investigations. This questionnaire was chosen in our work to help the orthodontists to evaluate the OSA risk and help guardians to realize the OSA impact more comprehensively. In our research, the OSA-18 questionnaire was modified, consisting of 5 parts and 20 items (sleep disturbance, physical suffering, emotional distress, daytime problems, and caregiver concerns).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The response categories were set from 1 (rare) to 7 (always) to reflect the frequency and severity of OSA-related symptoms like snoring. The total scores were calculated to be 140. OSA-18 applied in this study was the Mandarin version,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and all guardians of the children were asked to finish the questionnaires.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2002-s3002">
          <title>Oral Examination</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Oral examinations were conducted by three trained and certified orthodontists. Meanwhile, the data was collected and recorded by assistants according to a standard form. The inter-examiner reliability was ensured by Cohen’s kappa coefficient (value &gt; 0.8). The examination generally required lateral profile, intra-oral, and occlusion parts. As follows, some essential items were described in detail.</citation_analysis></p>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">According to the literature, tonsil size was graded from I to IV,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> implying tonsils were hidden within pillars, extending to pillars, beyond pillars but not to the midline, and extending to the midline.</citation_analysis></p>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The dentofacial abnormalities in the present study were qualitatively evaluated, including lateral profile, molar occlusion, dental arch, and palatal depth. The lateral profile was divided into upright, protruding, and concave types. Molar occlusions were collected considering the relationship between the upper and lower first permanent molars; Angle’s classes I (neutral), II (distoclusion), and III (mesioclusion) were recorded. Dental arch forms were recorded as triangular form, U-shape, and square shape. Palatal depth was assessed as a normal or high vault. Within our dentistry examination, overjet, overbite, and crossbite of anterior teeth, maxillary/mandibular crowding, and space were also carefully recorded.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2002-s3003">
          <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The analyses were performed by commercially available statistical software (SPSS, version 26.0). The significant difference was statistically assumed as both-sided P &lt; 0.05.</citation_analysis></p>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Homogeneity and the normality of variances were analyzed by Levene’s test and Shapiro–Wilk test. The distributions of continuous variables were summarized as mean ± standard deviation (M ± SD). The analyses of continuous variables according to gender were carried out by Student’s </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">-test or Mann–Whitney </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">U</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">-test, including age, height, weight, and scores of OSA-18. Categorical variables were described by absolute frequencies and percentages. The chi-squared test was applied to determine the statistical associations among the dentofacial development variables according to gender, tonsil size, and total OSA-18 scores. Further analyses of the various items in the OSA-18 questionnaire according to tonsil size were performed using the Spearman rank correlation test to determine the strength of association.</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Among the 863 students from the 24 classes, 776 families agreed to participate in the survey, and 734 completed the oral examination after the exclusion of samples based on the criteria. After excluding data with apparent errors, 715 participants were involved in the result analyses, including 334 boys and 381 girls aged 8–10 years old (mean age: 9.3 ± 0.4 years). The general physiological features are presented in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. Males were significantly different from females in height and weight (P &lt; 0.05). Body mass index (BMI) was similar regardless of gender (P = 0.118). Besides, males got higher OSA-18 total scores (40.8 ± 11.9) than females (38.8 ± 11.7, P &lt; 0.05).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Distributions of General Physical Characterizations Between Genders</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Total (N = 715)</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Gender</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">P</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boys (N = 334)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Girls (N = 381)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3 ± 0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4 ± 0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3 ± 0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.235</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">138.4 ± 8.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">139.8 ± 8.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">137.1 ± 7.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body weight</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.9 ± 8.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.5 ± 8.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.5 ± 8.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.5 ± 5.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.9 ± 5.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.2 ± 5.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.118</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Score of OSA-18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.8 ± 11.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.8 ± 11.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.8 ± 11.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018*</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Note</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: *Statistically significant at P &lt; 0.05; **Statistically significant at P &lt; 0.01.</citation_analysis></p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">: BMI, Body mass index; OSA-18, obstructive sleep apnea-18.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The associations between the scores of the OSA-18 and tonsil status are displayed in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">. Tonsil grades were found significantly different in the items of sleep disturbance (P &lt; 0.001), physical suffering (P = 0.003) and total scores (P = 0.002). The children with normal tonsil sizes obtained scores of 38.5 ± 11.8, while children with obstructive tonsil sizes (grade III and IV) got average scores of 41.4 and 42.4, respectively (P = 0.002).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Spearman’s Rank Correlation Coefficient Between Tonsil Size and OSA-18 Questionnaire</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">Total</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Tonsil Size</th><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">Rho</th><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">P</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(N = 341, 47.8%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(N = 197, 27.6%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(N = 146, 20.5%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(N = 29, 4.1%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep disturbance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5 ± 2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2 ± 2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7 ± 2.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9 ± 2.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4 ± 2.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical suffering</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3 ± 3.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0 ± 2.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4 ± 2.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6 ± 3.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5 ± 3.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emotional distress</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0 ± 3.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8 ± 3.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1 ± 3.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5 ± 3.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1 ± 3.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.059</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daytime problems</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1 ± 3.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8 ± 3.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2 ± 3.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6 ± 4.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8 ± 4.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.083</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caregiver concerns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9 ± 3.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7 ± 3.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1 ± 4.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8 ± 3.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6 ± 3.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.158</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total OSA-18 score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.8 ± 11.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.5 ± 11.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.5 ± 11.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.4 ± 11.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.4 ± 10.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002**</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Note</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: **Statistically significant at P &lt; 0.01.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The distributions of different dentofacial growth variables were described and analyzed in detail in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. Of those comparisons, mandibular crowding (P = 0.019) and maxillary dentition space (P = 0.045) presented a statistical difference between genders. In the analysis of OSA-18 scores, the average of this sample was calculated to be 39.8 (95% CI, 28.0–51.6). Thus, we roughly classify them into three ranks (&lt;30, 30–45, &gt;45) and explored the associations between OSA-18 scores and dentofacial abnormalities using the chi-square tests (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">) and Spearman correlation analyses (data not shown), but no correlations were found.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Distributions of Various Dentofacial Growth Variables Between Genders</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="2"/><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Total</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Gender</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">P</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boys</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Girls</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Profile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upright</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">453 (63.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">224 (31.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">229 (32.0%)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.156</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Concave</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (3.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (1.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (2.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protruding</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">238 (33.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 (14.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">138 (19.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Molar occlusion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutral</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">391 (54.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">185 (25.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">206 (28.8%)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.924</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distoclusion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">286 (40.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">131 (18.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">115 (21.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesioclusion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (5.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (2.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (2.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Anterior overjet</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0–3 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">344 (48.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">152 (21.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">192 (27.1%)</td><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">0.114</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–5 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">266 (37.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125 (17.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">141 (19.9%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5–8 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 (11.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (5.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (5.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;8 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (2.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (1.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (0.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Anterior overbite</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 1/3 crown</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">269 (38.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">113 (16.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">156 (22.1%)</td><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">0.211</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/3–2/3 crown</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">277 (39.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">133 (18.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">144 (20.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/3–1 crown</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">121 (17.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (8.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (8.2%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; full crown</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (5.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (3.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (2.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Anterior openbite</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">687 (97.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">325 (46.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">362 (51.3%)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.453</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;3 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (2.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (0.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (1.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–5 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (0.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (0.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Anterior crossbite</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">601 (84.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">284 (40.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">317 (44.7%)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.590</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108 (15.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (6.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (8.5%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">Maxillary crowding</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (8.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (4.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (3.6%)</td><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">0.252</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0–2 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">367 (51.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">176 (24.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">191 (26.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2–4 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">177 (24.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81 (11.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96 (13.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–8 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (12.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (5.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (7.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;8 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (3.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (0.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (2.2%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">Mandibular crowding</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96 (13.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (8.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (5%)</td><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">0.019 *</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0–2 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">338 (47.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">149 (20.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">189 (26.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2–4 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">181 (25.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 (11.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98 (13.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–8 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (12.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (5.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (6.9%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;8 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (2.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (0.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (1.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Maxillary dentition space</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">298 (41.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">124 (17.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">174 (24.3%)</td><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">0.045*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0–2 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">333 (46.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">161 (22.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">172 (24.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2–4 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (9.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (5.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (3.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;4 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (2.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (15%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (1.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Mandibular dentition space</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">333 (46.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">141 (19.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">192 (26.9%)</td><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">0.077</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0–2 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">348 (48.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">173 (24.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">175 (24.5%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2–4 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (3.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (2.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (1.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;4 mm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (1.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (0.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (0.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Arch form</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triangular shape</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">165 (23.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (10.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93 (13.2%)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.604</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U-shape</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">440 (62.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">210 (29.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">230 (32.5%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Square shape</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102 (14.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (7.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (7.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Plate form</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">576 (81.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">274 (38.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">302 (42.9%)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.433</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High arch</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128 (18.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (8.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (10.2%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Note</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: *Statistically significant at P &lt; 0.05.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Chi-Square Test Between Dentofacial Growth Variables and OSA-18 Grades</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">Total</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Total OSA-18 Scores</th><th rowspan="3" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">χ</italic><sup>2</sup></th><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">P</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 31</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">31–45</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; 45</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(N = 160, 22.2%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(N = 361, 50.1%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(N = 199, 27.6%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lateral facial profile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upright</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">455 (63.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110 (68.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">215 (59.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">130 (65.3%)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">6.03</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.197</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Concave</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (3.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (3.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (4.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (2.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protruding</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">240 (33.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (28.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">130 (36%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (32.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Molar occlusion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutral</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">393 (54.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90 (56.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">195 (54%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108 (54.3%)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">2.65</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.619</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distoclusion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">289 (40.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 (36.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">151 (41.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79 (39.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesioclusion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (5.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (6.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (4.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (6.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arch form</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triangular shape</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">165 (23.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (26.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (24.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (18.6%)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">4.22</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.377</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U-shape</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">445 (62.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91 (58%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">221 (62.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">133 (66.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Square shape</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102 (14.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (15.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (13.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (14.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Palate form</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">581(81.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">129 (82.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">289 (81.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">163 (83.6%)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.60</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.741</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High arch</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128 (18.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (17.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (19.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (16.4%)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">We explored the associations between tonsil status and dentofacial abnormalities (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). With the increase in tonsil size, the proportion of children with triangular dental arch form (P &lt; 0.05) and high vault palate (P &lt; 0.001) was increasingly higher. An increasing number of children with protruding profiles and fewer upright profiles were observed as tonsil size increased, although it did not show a statistical difference (P = 0.103). As for the molar relationship identified by Angle’s classification, no correlations to the tonsil size were discovered. We also explored the associations between tonsil size and anterior overbite, overjet and crossbite, and maxillary/mandibular crowding and spacing using Spearman correlation analyses, but no statistical correlation was detected (data not shown).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0005"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Chi-Square Test Between Dentofacial Growth Variables and Tonsil Size</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">Total</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Tonsil Size</th><th rowspan="3" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">χ</italic><sup>2</sup></th><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">P</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(N = 342, 47.6%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(N = 199, 27.7%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(N = 148, 20.6%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(N = 29, 4%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lateral facial profile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upright</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">454 (63.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">232 (67.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">124 (62.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (57.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (44.8%)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">10.56</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.103</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Concave</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (3.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (3.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (2.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (4.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (6.9%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protruding</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">240 (33.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99 (28.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70 (35.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (38.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (48.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Molar occlusion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutral</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">391 (54.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">195 (57.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 (50.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 (56.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (44.8%)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">8.42</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.209</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distoclusion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">289 (40.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">130 (38.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (46.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (36.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (44.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesioclusion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (5.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (5.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (3.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (7.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (10.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arch form</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triangular shape</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">165 (23.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (21.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (24.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (21.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (48.3%)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">15.12</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.019*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U-shape</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">445 (62.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">212 (62.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120 (61.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 (68.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (44.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Square shape</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 (14.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (16.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (13.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (10.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (6.9%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Palate form</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">579 (81.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">295 (87.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">158 (81.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">112 (76.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (50.0%)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">28.56</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High arch</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128 (18.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (12.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (19.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (23.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (50.0%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Note</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">: *Statistically significant at P &lt; 0.05; **Statistically significant at P &lt; 0.01.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Dentofacial development is a complex biological process that could be affected and remodeled by various risk factors breaking the balance. Our team adopted a stringent sampling design and standard protocols for the Chinese version of the OSA-18 questionnaire and oral examination. The cross-sectional research provided an accurate prevalence of dentofacial abnormalities in the young children population of Shanghai and compared several risk factors, including tonsil hypertrophy and SDB issues.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">The current prevalence of malocclusion in mixed dentition (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, 45.3%) appeared higher in comparison with the comprehensive investigation of Chinese children (35.42%) in 2002,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> but matched with the estimated overall prevalence of malocclusion in Chinese school children from 1991 to 2018 (47.92%).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> A higher prevalence of overjet, overbite, and crossbite could be observed compared to the literature.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Occlusion in mixed dentition was not stable due to incomplete eruption, and this malocclusion would be spontaneously corrected with the growth of the mandible.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Also, it might be attributed to the discrepancy of age, geography, race, time among selected samples, methodological diversity, and publication bias. It has been universally acknowledged that the prevalence of dentofacial deformity increased over the years in children, requiring comprehensive epidemiological researches and proactive interventions.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">PSG is a golden standard decisive in the diagnosis of OSA. Speaking of the OSA-18, it was disputable whether OSA-18 could be regarded as one of the reliable predictors for OSA apart from PSG evaluation. Some supported the idea</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> but others raised their doubts as well.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> As far as it goes, OSA-18 could be an abbreviated method of predicting pediatric OSA though further evidence was still required. It has been proved that the mandarin version of the OSA-18 was a reliable and valid instrument in an investigation of Chinese children aged 6–12.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In our study, no evident relationship between dentofacial growth information and OSA-18 scores was observed by our analysis (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). It suggested that OSA-18, reported as an OSA-specific questionnaire, might not be applicable and practicable for predicting dentofacial abnormalities. Most orthodontics believe breathing patterns play an essential role in the process of children’s growth and behaviors.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The craniofacial disharmony seen in the clinic could be linked to SDB or OSA among children.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> However, the results of OSA-18 relied on subjective guardians’ reports on their children. Compared with the oral quantitative examination, personal bias has been mentioned, such as parental overreporting or ignorance of some symptoms,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> thus possibly leading to a deviated outcome.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Whether pediatric dentofacial development was associated with enlarged tonsils has been contradicted by contemporary evidence. In a cross-sectional investigation, little significant connection between malocclusion and obstructive size of tonsils was observed through analyzing the collected data of 401 children.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Adenotonsillar surgery, statistically at least, appeared to have no benefits for dentofacial development.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Mouth-breathing could add an environmental weight to the development of malocclusions. Other possible factors should also be taken into consideration when dentofacial growth was mentioned, like negative maxilla development, narrow airway and heredity. It indicated that elimination of tonsil obstruction would not necessarily lead to normal breathing patterns.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> The mainstream viewpoint generally supported that tonsil status was closely linked with dental and craniofacial growth. Chinese experts have reached a consensus that tonsil hypertrophy was defined as one of the risk factors for malocclusion.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In the assessment of dentofacial parameters (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">), participants with grade IV hypertrophy of tonsils were inclined to show triangular dental arch type (P &lt; 0.05) and high vault palates (P &lt; 0.001). In contrast, non-obstructive tonsil enlargement would not affect the dental arch morphology and palatal depth. In addition, we could clearly figure out that the lateral profile intended to be protruding (P = 0.103). The proportion of malocclusion of both II and III types (P = 0.209) went up if tonsil size was added, although it did not show any statistical difference. Among ones with class III malocclusion in this study, children with tonsil grades III and IV (17.7%) were more likely to develop class III malocclusion than those with grades I and II (8.5%). Some researchers believed that independent tonsil hypertrophy correlated with class III malocclusion, while a higher rate of class II would be detected if combined with nasal or adenoid obstruction.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The others shared the opinion that patients with tonsil grade III and IV were more likely to develop class II malocclusion than those with I and II.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The mixed dentition of young children could naturally result in class II malocclusion in some cases.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Combining our results with current literature, we believed the severity of obstructive tonsil enlargement could be a crucial indication for SDB and dentofacial growth, requiring preventive and interceptive treatments in the early stage.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="negative">Honestly, there were some deficiencies in our research. The first limitation was the absence of cephalometric data like BNS and ANB. The lateral profile, selected as a qualitative representative of facial disharmonies, might not satisfy a more detailed quantified analysis if further studies on tonsil grades were required. Similarly, dental arch morphology was divided into three types, and it would be better if inter-canine width, inter-molar width, arch length, and perimeter were added to the research. Also, it would be better if palatal classification and tonsil grades were combined and considered in our oral examination. Furthermore, there were many other predictive methods for assessing pediatric SDB or OSA when PSG was unavailable.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> We would like to know better whether these convenient tools could help predict the direction of dentofacial growth in the future.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Dentofacial deficiency not only impairs multiple functions but also directly connects with the quality of a child’s whole life. Issues on dentofacial abnormalities induced by adenoid hypertrophy have raised more concerns than decades ago among parents and doctors in communities. However, the tonsil enlargement has not been sufficiently focused. We call for more efforts from local government and health authorities to enhance public propaganda and education on preventive and interceptive measurements for related dentofacial abnormalities. Meanwhile, further studies on tonsil-related dentofacial growth should necessarily be attached with great importance. More resources of versatile and multidisciplinary combinations could be introduced into the clinics mutually. Local joint departments of otorhinolaryngology and orthodontics in communities could be cultured and incubated.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Dental and craniofacial growth deficiency has become more prevalent among Chinese children than before, demanding more concerns from health authorities. The tonsil hypertrophy was significantly related to SDB issues and dentofacial development. More efforts from local health authorities should be made to enhance public propaganda and education on preventing and interrupting of tonsil hypertrophy and related dentofacial abnormalities.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We are grateful to the participants for their contributions to the research. This work was supported by Clinical Research Plan of Shanghai Shenkang Hospital Development Center (No. SHDC2020CR2043B) and Shanghai Municipal Health Commission (No. 2019SY041 and No. GWV-10.2-YQ16).</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0006">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>X-B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ye</surname>
<given-names>Q-F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>China experts’ consensus on preventive and interceptive orthodontic treatments of malocclusions of children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">West Chin J Stomatol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>369</fpage>–<lpage>376</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7518/hxkq.2021.04.001</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The prevalence of malocclusion in China – an investigation of 25,392 children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin J Stomatol</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>371</fpage>–<lpage>373</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Clark</surname>
<given-names>WD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Preventing dentofacial abnormalities with the proper correction of pediatric upper airway obstruction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Otolaryngol</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>131</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>916</fpage>–<lpage>918</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archotol.131.10.916</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Montgomery-Downs</surname>
<given-names>HE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gozal</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep habits and risk factors for sleep-disordered breathing in infants and young toddlers in Louisville, Kentucky</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>219</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2005.11.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16564742</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ryan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>CT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McNicholas</surname>
<given-names>WT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Selective activation of inflammatory pathways by intermittent hypoxia in obstructive sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circulation</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>112</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>2660</fpage>–<lpage>2667</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/circulationaha.105.556746</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16246965</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jen</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mazzotti</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Symptom subtypes and risk of incident cardiovascular and cerebrovascular disease in a clinic-based obstructive sleep apnea cohort</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>2093</fpage>–<lpage>2102</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.9986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35459444</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Moss</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salentijn</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The primary role of functional matrices in facial growth</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J of Orthod</italic></source>. <year>1969</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>566</fpage>–<lpage>577</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0002-9416(69)90034-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5253955</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Markkanen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rautiainen</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Niemi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Is securing normal dentofacial development an indication for tonsil surgery in children? A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Pediatr Otorhi</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>133</volume>:<fpage>110006</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijporl.2020.110006</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nunes</surname>
<given-names>WR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Di Francesco</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Variation of patterns of malocclusion by site of pharyngeal obstruction in children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Otolaryngol</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>136</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1116</fpage>–<lpage>1120</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archoto.2010.187</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Behlfelt</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Linder-Aronson</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mcwilliam</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Dentition in children with enlarged tonsils compared to control children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Orthod</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>416</fpage>–<lpage>429</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.ejo.a036014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2591488</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Diouf</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ngom</surname>
<given-names>PI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fadiga</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Influence of tonsil size on sagittal cephalometric measurements</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int Orthod</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>163</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ortho.2015.03.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25986708</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Diouf</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ngom</surname>
<given-names>PI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sonko</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Influence of tonsillar grade on the dental arch measurements</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>147</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>214</fpage>–<lpage>220</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajodo.2014.10.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25636555</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>D-K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rhee</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yun</surname>
<given-names>P-Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Adenotonsillar hypertrophy as a risk factor of dentofacial abnormality in Korean children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Arch Oto-Rhino-L</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>272</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>3311</fpage>–<lpage>3316</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00405-014-3407-6</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Diouf</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Diallo</surname>
<given-names>BK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Diop-Ba</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Relationships between the obstructive character of the tonsils and the type of ventilation and lip posture</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int Orthod</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>349</fpage>–<lpage>360</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ortho.2018.03.007</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Perez</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alves</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lizana</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Influence of the palatine tonsil grade on the morphology of the maxillary and mandibular dental arches</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Morphol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1201</fpage>–<lpage>1207</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4067/S0717-95022020000501201</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The efficacy of different treatment approaches for pediatric OSAHS patients with mandibular retrognathia: study protocol for a multicenter randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Trials</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>595</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13063-020-04398-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32605655</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kang</surname>
<given-names>K-T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weng</surname>
<given-names>W-C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yeh</surname>
<given-names>T-H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Validation of the Chinese version OSA-18 quality of life questionnaire in Taiwanese children with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Formos Med Assoc</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>113</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>454</fpage>–<lpage>462</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jfma.2012.10.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24961188</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Friedman</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ibrahim</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bass</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Clinical staging for sleep-disordered breathing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Otolaryng Head Neck</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>127</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/mhn.2002.126477</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence of malocclusion in Chinese schoolchildren from 1991 to 2018: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Paediatr Dent</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>144</fpage>–<lpage>155</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ipd.12591</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31677307</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Birgit</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lucia</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clementina</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence of malocclusion and orthodontic treatment need in children and adolescents in Bogota, Colombia. An epidemiological study related to different stages of dental development</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Orthod</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ejo/23.2.153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11398553</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Y-S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hwang</surname>
<given-names>F-M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>C-H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Clinical manifestations of pediatric obstructive sleep apnea syndrome: clinical utility of the Chinese-version Obstructive Sleep Apnea Questionnaire-18</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiat Clin Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>752</fpage>–<lpage>762</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pcn.12331</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ishman</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>C-J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Is the OSA-18 predictive of obstructive sleep apnea: comparison to polysomnography</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Laryngoscope</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>125</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1491</fpage>–<lpage>1495</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lary.25098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25545468</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Festa</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mansi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Varricchio</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association between upper airway obstruction and malocclusion in mouth-breathing children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Otorhinolaryngo</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>436</fpage>–<lpage>442</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14639/0392-100x-n1225</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Katyal</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pamula</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Craniofacial and upper airway morphology in pediatric sleep-disordered breathing: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Orthod Dentofac</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>143</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>20</fpage>–<lpage>U204</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajodo.2012.08.021</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huynh</surname>
<given-names>NT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morton</surname>
<given-names>PD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rompre</surname>
<given-names>PH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Associations between sleep-disordered breathing symptoms and facial and dental morphometry, assessed with screening examinations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Orthod Dentofac</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>140</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>762</fpage>–<lpage>770</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajodo.2011.03.023</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Souki</surname>
<given-names>BQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pimenta</surname>
<given-names>GB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Souki</surname>
<given-names>MQ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence of malocclusion among mouth breathing children: do expectations meet reality?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Pediatr Otorhi</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>73</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>767</fpage>–<lpage>773</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijporl.2009.02.006</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lofstrand-Tidestrom</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hultcrantz</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Development of craniofacial and dental arch morphology in relation to sleep disordered breathing from 4 to 12 years. Effects of adenotonsillar surgery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Pediatr Otorhi</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>74</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>143</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijporl.2009.10.025</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Iwasaki</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sato</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suga</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Relationships among nasal resistance, adenoids, tonsils, and tongue posture and maxillofacial form in Class II and Class III children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Orthod Dentofac</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>151</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>929</fpage>–<lpage>940</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajodo.2016.10.027</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tinano</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Godinho</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Becker</surname>
<given-names>HMG</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence of malocclusion in children with upper airway obstruction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Rev Port Estomatol M</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>204</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24873/j.rpemd.2017.12.209</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>C-R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tu</surname>
<given-names>Y-K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chuang</surname>
<given-names>L-P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Diagnostic meta-analysis of the Pediatric Sleep Questionnaire, OSA-18, and pulse oximetry in detecting pediatric obstructive sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>101355</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2020.101355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32750654</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
