<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36540196</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">9760070</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">388863</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S388863</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Review</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Different Intensities of Evening Exercise on Sleep in Healthy Adults: A Systematic Review and Network Meta-Analysis</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Yue et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Yue et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4537-8395</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Yue</surname>
            <given-names>Tian</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
          <xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Xuefang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
          <xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gao</surname>
            <given-names>Qi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4499-5954</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Yan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>School of Sports Medicine and Rehabilitation, Beijing Sport University</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Yan Wang, <institution>School of Sports Medicine and Rehabilitation, Beijing Sport University</institution>, <addr-line>No. 48 Xinxi Road, Haidian District</addr-line>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, <phone>Tel +86 15201061266</phone>, Email wyweiwei@126.com</corresp>
        <fn id="ft0001">
          <label>*</label>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">These authors contributed equally to this work</citation_analysis></p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>14</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <fpage>2157</fpage>
      <lpage>2177</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>06</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2022 Yue et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Yue et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The effects of different intensities of evening exercise on subsequent sleep remain contradictory. Thus, this systematic review and network meta-analysis aimed to compare and rank the effects of different intensities of acute evening exercise on sleep in healthy adults with good sleep. Articles were systematically searched journals indexed in the PubMed, Web of Science, Cochrane Library, Embase, and Scopus databases from inception to the 5th of May, 2022. The basic search terms included exercise, sleep and timing, which were combined with AND. Of the 12,203 retrieved, twenty-eight studies with 325 participants met the inclusion criteria. Results revealed that there were no significant differences in terms of impacts on sleep caused by different intensities of acute evening exercise, except that when compared to no exercise, acute evening high-intensity exercise decreased rapid eye movement sleep (mean difference [MD] = −1.95%, 95% credible interval [CI] = −3.58 to −0.35). Compared to no exercise, acute evening moderate-intensity exercise was ranked as the most potential method to improve sleep, displaying a trend to improve wake time after sleep onset (MD = −2.50 min, 95% CI = −8.17 to 1.62), sleep efficiency (MD = +0.41%, 95% CI = −0.71 to 1.66), the proportion of stage N1 (MD = −0.72%, 95% CI = −2.08 to 0.71) and N3 sleep (slow-wave sleep) (MD = +0.84%, 95% CI = −1.17 to 2.78). Acute evening low-intensity exercise displayed the greatest tendency to shorten sleep onset latency (MD = −1.02 min, 95% CI = −4.39 to 2.50) compared to no exercise. Overall, regardless of intensity, acute evening exercise completed before bedtime does not disrupt subsequent sleep in healthy young and middle-aged adults.</citation_analysis></p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>evening exercise</kwd>
        <kwd>sleep quality</kwd>
        <kwd>exercise intensity</kwd>
        <kwd>systematic review</kwd>
        <kwd>network meta-analysis</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="5"/>
        <table-count count="2"/>
        <ref-count count="76"/>
        <page-count count="21"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sleep and exercise play the vital role in maintaining human health. The prevalence of insomnia ranges from 10% to 30% in the general population,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> increasing the risk of variable diseases and affecting life expectancy.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2–5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Exercise has been proven to be a low-cost and effective way to improve sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> A previous systematic review and meta-analysis showed regular exercise and daytime acute exercise had beneficial effects on sleep quality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Time-use epidemiology showed that exercising and sleeping time competed with each other in daily life.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Lack of time has become an obstacle hindering people’s exercise.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Exercise in the evening progressively becomes a good option for people burdened with day-to-day work. The appearance of 24-hour gym also provides the environment for evening exercise.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Nonetheless, the American Academy of Sleep Medicine (AASM) does not recommend exercising in the evening as it would cause arousal and disrupt subsequent sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> A cross-sectional study found that most people reported that evening exercise did not disrupt their sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Some studies also showed that exercise in the evening did not disrupt sleep but rather had small to moderate beneficial effects on sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Dworak et al found that compared to no exercise, only acute evening high-intensity exercise (HIE) made the positive modification to sleep efficiency (SE), sleep onset latency (SOL) and slow-wave sleep (SWS) while evening moderate-intensity exercise (MIE) had no significant effects on sleep in children.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Not inconsistent with Dworak et al, Oda and Shirakawa suggested acute evening HIE delayed sleep onset (+ 14 min), shortened total sleep time (TST) and decreased SE in active young adults, whereas evening MIE did not disrupt sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The level of delayed sleep onset found by Oda and Shirakawa was greater than that previously reported in the study of Browman and Tepas (+6.5min).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Ramos-Campo et al recruited recreational ultra-endurance male runners to conduct acute morning MIE, morning HIE, evening MIE and evening HIE in a random sequence. A significantly higher average time of each awakening was observed in acute evening HIE than in the other three interventions.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The result of Ramos-Campo et al study suggested that exercise intensity was as important as training time in the evening or the morning.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Actually, the effects of different evening exercise intensities on sleep are still a hot spot, leading to debates. Vlahoyiannis et al found that acute evening sprint interval training increased TST compared to MIE and no exercise. Moreover, compared to no exercise, sprint interval training also improved SE and shortened wake time after sleep onset (WASO).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> A recent study by Thomas et al of endurance-trained runners showed that compared to no exercise, both acute evening HIE and low-intensity exercise (LIE) increased TST and shortened WASO despite the increase in cardiac autonomic activity.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Myllymäki et al also found that acute evening LIE, MIE and HIE did not disrupt sleep quality in young adults.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Conversely, Browman and Tepas found that even evening LIE ended 2 h before bedtime delayed sleep onset compared to no exercise in undergraduates.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> It remains unclear whether acute evening exercise with different intensities disrupts sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The controversies of previous studies might be attributed to the different times of evening exercise, the hours from the cessation of exercise to bedtime, the exercise modality, the physical activity level of participants, and the duration of evening exercise.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Furthermore, there might be an intensity threshold for the effects of evening exercise on sleep. Previous pairwise meta-analyses only focused on comparing high-intensity or moderate-intensity exercise with no-exercise controls, lacking comprehensive comparisons of different intensities of acute evening exercise.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> It was necessary to conduct a comprehensive analysis of currently available data regarding acute evening exercise on sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The current systematic review and network meta-analysis (NMA), which would combine direct and indirect evidence to potentially improve the precision of the effect estimates,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> aimed to compare and rank different intensities of acute evening exercise on sleep in healthy adults. Owing to the larger magnitude of physiologic excitement that might be induced by HIE, we hypothesized that performing HIE before bedtime would disrupt sleep compared to no exercise, whereas performing MIE and LIE would not.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Search Strategy</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The search was performed in the PubMed, Web of Science, Cochrane Library, Embase and Scopus databases from inception to the 5th of May, 2022. The basic search strategy consisted of the keywords and MeSH terms related to the intervention (exercise), the outcomes (sleep) and the timing (evening), which was combined with “AND”. The detailed search strategy for Pubmed was: (exercise [mesh] OR sports [mesh] OR physical exertion [mesh] OR “interval training” [tiab] OR aerob* [tiab] OR endurance [tiab] OR strength* [tiab] OR sprint* [tiab] OR anaerob* [tiab] OR exercise [tiab] OR “physical activity” [tiab] OR “high intensity training” [tiab] OR run* [tiab] OR cycling [tiab] OR walk* [tiab] OR swim* [tiab] OR row* [tiab] OR “physical exertion” [tiab] or sport [tiab]) AND (sleep [mesh] OR sleep [tiab] OR “sleep architecture” [tiab] OR “sleep quality” [tiab] OR “sleep efficiency” [tiab] OR polysomnography [tiab] OR actigraphy [tiab]) AND (timing [tiab] OR evening [tiab] OR late-night [tiab] OR bedtime [tiab] OR afternoon [tiab] OR late [tiab] OR “time of day” [tiab] OR time-of-day [tiab] OR “pre sleep” [tiab] OR “before sleep”[tiab] OR pre-sleep [tiab] OR “going to sleep” [tiab] OR “going to bed” [tiab] OR “before bed”[tiab] OR nighttime [tiab] OR night-time [tiab] OR night [tiab]). In addition, we also searched the literature from references cited in the included articles and previous systematic reviews.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Eligibility Criteria</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The population, intervention, comparison, outcome and study design (PICOS) framework was used to measure the eligibility criteria. Inclusion criteria for this systematic review and network meta-analysis included: 1) Population: healthy adults (18–65 years) with normal sleep. 2) Intervention: acute exercises in the evening (less than 4h before bedtime or if stated to be conducted in the evening) (high intensity: ≥77% maximal heart rate (HRmax), ≥60% heart rate reserve (HRR) or VO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> reserve (VO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">R), ≥64% maximal oxygen consumption (VO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">max) or rating of perceived exertion (RPE) ≥14; moderate intensity: 64–76% HRmax, 40–59% HRR or VO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">R, 46–63% VO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">max or RPE 12–13; low intensity: ≤63% HRmax, ≤39% HRR or VO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">R, ≤45% VO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">max or RPE ≤11).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> 3) Comparison: no exercise, LIE, MIE or HIE compared with each other 4) Outcomes: sleep quality and sleep quantity were objectively measured by polysomnography (PSG) and actigraphic sleep parameters and subjectively measured by questionnaires. 5) Study design: randomized controlled trials, randomized crossover trials and within-subject designs written in English were included.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Data Extractions and Risk of Bias Assessment</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Two of the authors independently read the full text of included literature and extracted outcomes in an unblinded manner. Any disagreements were resolved by discussion with a third author to achieve consensus. The extracted information included (1) authorship and study design; (2) participant characteristics (sample size, age, gender, physical activity level); (3) intervention characteristics (exercise intervention type, duration, intensity and timing of exercise before bedtimes); (4) bedtimes; (5) sleep measurements; (6) sleep outcomes. The primary outcomes were: TST, SE, SOL, WASO, and sleep architecture including the proportion of stages N1, N2, N3, SWS, and rapid eye movement (REM) sleep. If a study reported the primary outcomes measured by actigraphy and PSG, the PSG data would be extracted for our network meta-analysis. Actigraphy is one-dimensional, while polysomnography includes at least three different types of data (electroencephalogram, electrooculogram, electromyogram) that together determine whether a person is asleep or awake.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Therefore, PSG is the “gold standard” for the sleep study.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The secondary outcome was subjective sleep quality (SSQ).</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Risk of bias was measured by using the revised Cochrane risk of bias tool for crossover trials (RoB 2.0), which considered the crossover designs. ROB 2.0 consisted of 5 domains: (1) bias arising from the randomization process; (2) bias due to deviations from the intended intervention; (3) bias due to the missing outcome data; (4) bias in the measurement of the outcome; (5) bias in the selection of the reported result. Each domain had signaling questions, requiring the assessors to respond “probably yes”, “yes”, “probably no”, “no” or “no information”. According to an algorithm to the judgment of each domain, the included studies were rated as “low risk of bias”, “some concerns” or “high risk bias”. The assessment was conducted by two authors independently in an unblinded manner.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Means and standard deviations (SDs) were extracted from included studies. If the study only reported standard errors (SEs), SDs were calculated by the following formula: </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><inline-formula id="ilm0001"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-2157-e0001.jpg"/><tex-math id="Tex001">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$${\rm{SD}}\,{\rm{ = }}\,{\rm{SE*}}\sqrt {\rm{N}} $$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Mean differences (MDs) and 95% credible intervals (CIs) were calculated for measuring the effect sizes of each objective sleep outcome, whereas standardized mean differences (SMDs) and 95% CIs were calculated for measuring the effect sizes of subjective sleep quality because of different evaluation methods in included studies. For this NMA, heterogeneity was assessed by I</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> static. Values of I</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> ≤25%, 25% &lt; I</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> ≤50%, 50% &lt; I</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> ≤75%, and I</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> &gt; 75% indicated no significant heterogeneity, low heterogeneity, medium heterogeneity, and high heterogeneity, respectively.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Bayesian effects network meta-analysis (NMA) was performed by using the “gemtc” package in R (version 4.2.0). Four Markov chain Monte Carlo chains were used to assess convergence with 20,000 iterations. Posterior summaries were then obtained from 50,000 iterations in each of the four chains. Convergence was assessed by using potential scale reduction factors (PSRF). The value of PSRF approached 1, indicating the convergence of the model was satisfactory.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Network plots were created to describe different intensities of acute evening exercise on outcomes. Nodes in the geometry represented different intensities of acute evening exercise and no-exercise control and the lines represented direct comparisons for interventions. The size of each node and the thickness of each line were proportional to the number of participants.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Global inconsistency was assessed by comparing the difference values of differences in conditions (DIC) between the consistency and inconsistency models. A difference value of DIC &gt;5 indicated an inconsistent model.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Local inconsistency was evaluated by using the node splitting method. In addition, probability ranking for each intervention was conducted by the surface under the cumulative ranking curve (SUCRA) values ranging from 0% to 100%, where 100% indicated the best intervention.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">To test the robustness of the results and examine the effects of potential modifiers on primary outcomes, subgroup analyses were performed according to the following variables: time of evening exercise (early evening: 16:00 to 20:00, late evening: after 20:00), hours from cessation of exercise to bedtime (0.5–1.5 h, 2 or &gt;2–4 h), exercise modality (cycling, running), physical activity level of participants (sedentary, physically fit), exercise duration (25–30 min, &gt;30–60 min). Publication bias was subjectively assessed with comparison-adjusted funnel plots. In all the analyses, a statistical significance was set at </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> &lt; 0.05.</citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This systematic review and network meta-analysis was carried out in conformance with the PRISMA Extension for Network Meta-analyses (PRISMA-NMA) checklist.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The protocol for this systematic review and NMA has been registered on PROSPERO (CRD42022327787).</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Study Selection</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">A PRISMA diagram of literature search and selection is presented in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. A total of 12,203 studies were initially identified from PubMed, Web of Science, Cochrane Library, Embase, and Scopus databases. After removing duplicates (n = 4131) and reading titles and abstracts (n = 8072), the remaining studies (n = 48) progressed to full-text review and 24 studies met the inclusion criteria. Twenty-four studies were excluded for the following reasons: (1) daytime exercise (n = 10), (2) poor sleep participants (n = 2), (3) adolescents (n = 1), (4) observational or cross-sectional designs (n = 5), (5) review (n = 2), (6) no sleep data (n = 3), (7) interrupted sleep (n = 1). In addition, four additional studies were found from the references of eligible studies. Overall, 28 studies were finally included in this systematic review and network meta-analysis.
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">PRISMA flow diagram of systematic search and included trials.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-2157-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Notes:</bold> PRISMA figure adapted from Liberati A, Altman D, Tetzlaff J, et al. The PRISMA statement for reporting systematic reviews and meta-analyses of studies that evaluate health care interventions: explanation and elaboration. Journal of clinical epidemiology. 2009;62(10). Creative Commons.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Study Characteristics</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The characteristics of the included studies are presented in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. The SUCRA values were shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. The network plot of eligible comparisons on objective and subjective sleep quality are shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. Four nodes were included in the NMA. Each node denoted different interventions: no-exercise control, evening low-intensity exercise (LIE), evening moderate-intensity exercise (MIE), and evening high-intensity exercise (HIE). Among the 28 crossover trials from 1976 to 2021 included in the analyses, 19 studies had two arms,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30–45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> 6 had three arms</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46–48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and 3 had four arms.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> There were 325 participants (mean age: 25 years old, range: 18–49 years), of which 290 participants were male, and 35 participants were female. Twenty-three studies were men only,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15–20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40–48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> one was women only</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> and the remaining four included both men and women.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In addition, most of the participants were physically active or trained populations, and the others were sedentary participants.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0001" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Descriptive Characteristics of the Included Studies</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Participants</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Design</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arms</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outcomes</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Timing of Exercise interventions (Start – end Time)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Time</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arias et al 2016<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 9 young non-professional sportsmen (performing exercise about 3 times per week) <bold>M</bold> = all males <bold>Age</bold> = 18–38 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HIE</bold>: 5 sets of 20m-SRT interspersed with 6 min breaks <bold>CON</bold>: no exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Actigraphy</bold>: SE, SOL, Movement and fragmentation index <bold>Subjective sleep quality</bold>: NSFSD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17:00 - NR / 21:00 - NR ended &gt; 4 h before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Usual bedtime/ad libitum</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aloulou et al 2020<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 11 well-trained male runners <bold>M</bold>: all males <bold>Age</bold> (mean ± SD) = 32.3 ± 5.2 years<break/><bold>Chronotype</bold>: neither-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial 1 week washout period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HIE</bold>: 45 min running at uphill (+10%) at 65% MAS; downhill (−12.5%) at 80% MAS &amp; level treadmill (0%) at 60% MAS to maximal speed. Average HR was 83% HRmax <bold>CON</bold>: no exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSG</bold>: TIB, TST, WASO, SE, SOL, REM-L, %N1, %N2, %N3, %REM <bold>Actigraphy</bold>: TST, WASO, SOL, SE <bold>Subjective sleep quality</bold>: SSI score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21:00–22:00 ended 2 h before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">00:46–9:00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Browman &amp; Tepas 1976<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 9 male undergraduates, average physical fitness <bold>M</bold>: all males <bold>Mean age</bold> = 18.89 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>LIE</bold>: 45 min cycling alternating 5 min of cycling with a load of 0.5 kg and 3-min breaks <bold>CON</bold>: no exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSG</bold>: TST, %N1, %N2, %SWS, % REM, REM-L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Started 2.5 h prior to bedtime; ended 2 h before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Usual bedtime/ad libitum, 7.5 h sleep duration</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bulckaert et al 2011<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 9 young adults with good physical health <bold>M</bold>: 4 males <bold>Age</bold> (mean ± SD) = 23 ± 3.4 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MIE</bold>: 60 min cycling at 65–75% HRmax <bold>CON</bold>: reference night</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSG</bold>: SOL, %N2, %SWS, %REM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Started 2 h before bedtime ended 1h before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22:30–23:00 to 7:00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Driver et al 1988<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 9 young sedentary women <bold>M</bold>: 0 male <bold>Age</bold> (mean ± SD) = 24 ± 3 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial 1 day washout period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HIE</bold>: 60 min cycling at 70% VO<sub>2peak</sub>
<bold>CON</bold>: no exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSG</bold>: SOL, REM-L, N2, SWS <bold>Subjective sleep quality</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16:00–19:00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flausino et al 2012<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 17 healthy young good sleepers with no regular exercise habits <bold>M</bold> = all males <bold>Age</bold> (mean ± SD) = 27.2 ± 3.6 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial ≥ 1 week washout period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HIE</bold>: 30 and 60min running at Delta 50 (50% above VT1) <bold>MIE</bold>: 30 and 60 min running at VT1 <bold>CON</bold>: no exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSG</bold>: TST, WASO, SOL, SE, % N1, %N2, %SWS, % REM, REM-L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20:00–20:30 ended 2 h before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22:30–23:00 to 06:00–07:00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hayashi et al 2014<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 9 sedentary college students <bold>M</bold> = all males <bold>Age</bold> (mean ± SD) = 22.8 ± 2.0 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial ≥ 3 days washout period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HIE</bold>: 60 min cycling at 80% HRmax <bold>MIE</bold>: 60 min cycling at 65% HRmax <bold>LIE</bold>: 60 min at 50% HRmax <bold>CON</bold>: no exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSG</bold>: TIB, TST, SE, SOL, REM-L, WASO, %N1, %N2, %N3, %REM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ended 2 h before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Go to bed 2 h after exercise</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kern et al 1995<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 10 healthy non-professional male triathletes <bold>M</bold> = all males <bold>Age</bold> = 20–26 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial ≥1 week washout period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MIE</bold>: 120–150 km cycling at moderate intensity <bold>LIE</bold>: 40 km cycling at low intensity <bold>CON</bold>: no exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSG</bold>: TST, SOL, %N1, %N2, SWS, %REM, REM-L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16:00–20:30 (LIE) 18:00–20:30 (MIE) ended 2.5 before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23:00–7:00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Larsen et al 2019<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 11 inactive men <bold>M</bold> = all males <bold>Age</bold> (mean ± SD) = 49 ± 5 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial ≥5 days washout period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HIE</bold>: 30 min HIIT (60s cycling at 100% VO<sub>2peak</sub>, interspersed with 240s active recovery at 50% VO<sub>2peak</sub>) <bold>CON</bold>: baseline or no exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSG</bold>: TIB, TST, SE, SOL, REM-L, WASO, %N1, %N2, %N3, %REM <bold>Actigraphy</bold>: TIB, TST, SE, SOL, WASO, number of awakenings</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19:00–20:00 3 h before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ad libitum bedtimes and wake time</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Miura et al 2016<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 10 young sedentary adults <bold>M</bold> = all males <bold>Age</bold> = 18–25 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial 1 week washout period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MIE</bold>: 60-min upright cycling at 60 rpm at an intensity of 50% HRR <bold>CON</bold>: no exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Actigraphy</bold>: TST, WASO, SE, SOL, REM, stage 1and2 sleep, stage 3 and 4 sleep</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17:00–18:00 ended &gt; 4 h before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23:00–00:00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myllymäki et al 2011<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 11 physically fit young adults <bold>M</bold> = 7 males <bold>Age</bold> (mean ± SD) = 26 ± 3 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial 1 week washout period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HIE</bold>: 30 min incremental cycling until exhaustion at 100 W for men and 25 W for women <bold>CON</bold>: no exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSG</bold>: TST, SOL, %N1, %N2, %N3, %REM <bold>Actigraphy</bold>: TST, SE, FI, total activity <bold>Subjective sleep quality</bold>: questionnaire</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21:00 - ended 2 h before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myllymäki et al 2012<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 14 physically healthy young adults <bold>M</bold> = all males <bold>Age</bold> (mean ± SD) = 35.9 ± 4.3 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trail ≥ 48h washout period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HIE</bold>: 30 min running at 75% VO<sub>2max</sub>
<bold>MIE</bold>: 30 min running at 60% VO<sub>2max</sub>
<bold>LIE</bold>: 30 min running at 45% VO<sub>2max</sub>
<bold>CON</bold>: no exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Actigraphy</bold>: TST, SE, FI, activity counts <bold>Subjective sleep quality</bold>: VAS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18:00–19:00, ended 4 h before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23:28–07:04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Miller et al 2020<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 12 healthy young males with regular exercise at least 3 times per week <bold>M</bold> = all males <bold>Age</bold> (mean ± SD) = 21.9 ± 2.7 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trail 1 day washout period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MIE</bold>: 30 min cycling at 75% HRmax <bold>CON</bold>: no exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSG</bold>: TST, SOL, N1, N2, N3, REM, SE <bold>Subjective sleep quality</bold>: Karolinska Sleep Scale</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20:45–21:30 ended 1.5 h before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23:00–8:00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">O’Connor et al 1998<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 8 physically active college students <bold>M</bold> = all males <bold>Age</bold> (mean ± SD) = 20.8 ± 2 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MIE</bold>: 60 min cycling at 60% VO<sub>2peak</sub>
<bold>LIE</bold>: 60 min cycling at 20% VO<sub>2peak</sub>
<bold>CON</bold>: no exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep Assessment Device</bold>: SOL, TST, SE, awakenings</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Late evening ended 1.5 h before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23:00–8:00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oda &amp; Shirakawa 2014<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 12 active young adults <bold>M</bold> = all males <bold>Age</bold> (mean ± SD) = 19.8 ± 0.9 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial 4–7 days washout period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HIE</bold>: 30 min running at 80% HRR <bold>MIE</bold>: 30 min running at 60% HRR <bold>CON</bold>: no exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSG</bold>: TST, WASO, SOL, SE, N1, N2, SWS and REM, REM-L <bold>Subjective sleep quality</bold>: Sleep Inventory of Oguri-Shirakawa-Azumi</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21:20–22:00 ended 1 h before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23:00–7:00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Park et al 2021<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 9 healthy young men with regular exercise no more than twice a week <bold>M</bold> = all males <bold>Age</bold> (mean ± SD) = 23.8 ± 2.7 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial 1 week washout period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MIE</bold>: 60 min running at 60% VO2max <bold>CON</bold>: no exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSG</bold>: TIB, TST, SOL, SE, N1, N2, SWS, REM-L<bold>Subjective sleep quality</bold>: Sleep Inventory of Oguri-Shirakawa-Azumi</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17:00–18:00 ended 6 h before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23:30–24:30 to 8:00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Robey et al 2013<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 11 athletes <bold>M</bold> = all males <bold>Age</bold> (mean ± SD) = 26 ± 4.4 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial<break/>1 week washout period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HIE</bold>: 30 min cycling at 75% peak power + maximal time trial <bold>CON</bold>: no exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSG</bold>: TIB, TST, SE, SOL, %WASO, %N1, %N2, %N3, %REM, REM-L, %NERM <bold>Actigraphy</bold>: TST, SOL, WASO, SE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19:00–20:00 ended 2.5 h before bed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22:30–6:00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ramos-Campo et al 2019<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 14 recreational ultra-endurance male runners <bold>M</bold> = all males <bold>Age</bold> (mean ± SD) = 27.6 ± 7.4 years<break/><bold>Chronotype</bold>: neither-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial ≥ 72h washout period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HIE</bold>: 7 x 3 min running at 100% VO<sub>2max</sub>, interspersed with 3 min passive rest <bold>MIE</bold>: 60 min running at 60% VO<sub>2max</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Actigraphy</bold>: TIB, TST, SE, wake of time, number of awakenings, average time of each awakening <bold>Subjective sleep quality</bold>: Karolinska Sleep Diary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20:00–21:00 ended 2–4 h before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saidi et al 2020<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 16 healthy college students <bold>M</bold>: 8 males <bold>Age</bold> (mean ± SD) = 22.31 ± 1.44 years<break/><bold>Chronotype</bold>: neither-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MIE</bold>: 50 min running at 60% HRmax <bold>CON</bold>: no exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Actigraphy</bold>: TIB, TST, SE, WASO, SOL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18:30–19: 30 ended 4h before bedtime 20:30–21:30 ended 2h before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22:00–8:00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thomas et al 2020<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 8 endurance trained runners <bold>M</bold> = all males <bold>Age</bold> (mean ± SD) = 27.8 ± 6.9 years<break/><bold>Chronotype</bold>: neither-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial ≥ 4 days washout period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HIE</bold>: 6×5 min running at 90% VO<sub>2peak</sub>, interspersed with 5 min at 60% VO<sub>2peak</sub>
<bold>LIE</bold>: 60 min running at 45% VO<sub>2peak</sub>
<bold>CON</bold>: no exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSG</bold>: TIB, TST, SOL, REM latency, WASO, %N1, %N2, SWS, %REM<bold>Actigraphy</bold>: TST, SOL, activity counts, FI<bold>Subjective sleep quality</bold>: Likert scale from the Consensus sleep diary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17:50 - ended 3.5h before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22:30–7:00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ucar et al 2017<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 20 healthy male college students <bold>M</bold> = all males <bold>Age</bold> = 20–24 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HIE</bold>: 90 min hard football match <bold>CON</bold>: no exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Subjective sleep quality</bold>: Karolinska Sleep Diary, PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21:30–23:00 ended 2.5 h before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:39–8:08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vitale et al 2017<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 23 college soccer players <bold>M</bold> = all males <bold>Age</bold> (mean ± SD) = 21.7 ± 2.72 years<break/><bold>Chronotype</bold>: both morning-type and evening-type</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial 1 week washout period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HIE</bold>: 4×4 min running at 90–95% HRmax, interspersed with 3 min recovery at 70% HRmax <bold>CON</bold>: pre exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Actigraphy</bold>: SE, SOL, activity counts, MFI, moving time, immobility time</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20:00 - NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vincent et al 2020<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 12 healthy males with regular exercise at least 3 times per week <bold>M</bold> = all males <bold>Age</bold> (mean ± SD) = 27.3 ± 3.4 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial 4 days washout period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MIE</bold>: 30 min cycling at 75% HRmax <bold>CON</bold>: no exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSG</bold>: TST <bold>Subjective sleep quality</bold>: Karolinska Sleep Diary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20:45–21:30 ended 1.5h before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23:00–8:00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vlahoyiannis et al 2021<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 10 recreationally trained young males <bold>M</bold> = all males <bold>Age</bold> (mean ± SD) = 23.9 ± 3.3 years<break/><bold>Chronotype</bold>: neither-types</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial 1 week washout period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HIE</bold>: 10×1 min cycling at 90% Wmax interspersed with 1 min recovery at 20% Wmax / 6×20 s cycling at 140% Wmax, interspersed with 140s active recovery at 20% Wmax <bold>MIE</bold>: 45 min cycling at 70% Wmax <bold>CON</bold>: no exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSG</bold>: TIB, TST, SE, SOL, WASO, METs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19:00–20:00 ended 3 h before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ad libitum sleep duration</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wong et al 2013<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 12 healthy sedentary young adults <bold>M</bold> = 3 males <bold>Age</bold> (mean ± SD) = 25.2 ± 4.0 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial ≥ 2 days washout period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HIE</bold>: 40 min running at 65% VO2max / 75% VO2max <bold>MIE</bold>: 40 min running at 55% VO<sub>2max</sub>
<bold>LIE</bold>: 40 min running at 45% VO<sub>2max</sub>
<bold>CON</bold>: no exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSG</bold>: TST, SOL, WASO, REM-L, SE, %SWS, %REM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Started 6 h prior to bedtime; ended 4–5 h before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bedtime 22:30–01:30 (majority 23:30), ad libitum wake time</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yoshida et al 1998<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 5 healthy university male students with no exercise habits <bold>M</bold> = all males <bold>Age</bold> (mean ± SD) = 21.0 ± 0.7 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial 1–3 weeks washout period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MIE</bold>: 50 min aerobic exercise at AT <bold>CON</bold>: no exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSG</bold>: SWS <bold>Subjective sleep quality</bold>: Sleep Inventory of Oguri-Shirakawa-Azumi</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16:30–17:30 ended &gt; 4 h before bedtime 20:30–21:30 ended 2 h before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23:30–7:30</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Youngstedt et al 1999<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 16 highly fit cyclists <bold>M</bold> = all males <bold>Age</bold> (mean ± SD) = 27.3 ± 4.3 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial 2–4 weeks washout period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HIE</bold>: 3 h cycling at 65–75% of HRR under bright light (3000 lux) in a laboratory <bold>CON</bold>: no exercise or bright light alone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Actigraphy</bold>: TST, SOL, WASO <bold>Subjective sleep quality</bold>: SOL, WASO, subjective rating of insomnia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ended 30 min before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 min after exercise and were awakened at their usual time</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yamanaka et al 2015<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold> = 8 healthy young males, paid volunteers, with a habit of light exercise once or twice a week <bold>M</bold>: all males</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossover trial</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MIE</bold>: 90 min cycling at 65–75% HRmax (2 x 45 min interspersed with a 10-min recovery) <bold>CON</bold>: no exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PSG</bold>: TST, SOL, SE, WASO</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18:00–20:00 ended 4h before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24:00–8:00</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative">: M, male; LIE, low-intensity exercise; MIE, moderate-intensity exercise; HIE, high-intensity exercise; TIB, time in bed; TST, total sleep time; SOL, sleep onset latency; WASO, wake time after sleep onset; SE, sleep efficiency; REM, rapid eye movement; REM-L, rapid eye movement latency; SWS, slow-wave sleep; NERM, non-rapid eye movement; N1, stage N1 sleep; N2, stage N2 sleep; N3, stage N3 sleep; SQ, sleep quality; SSQ, subjective sleep quality; PSG, polysomnography; SRT, Shuttle-Run-Test; NSFSD, National Sleep Foundation-Sleep Diary; SSI, Spiegel Sleep Inventory; KSS, Karolinska Sleep Scale; HR, heart rate; MAS, maximal aerobic speed; VT1, ventilatory threshold 1; PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index; VO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sub>2peak</sub></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">, peak oxygen uptake; FI, fragmentation index; NR, not reported; METs, metabolic equivalent of tasks; Wmax, maximal power output; MAS, Maximal Aerobic Speed.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Network plots for comparisons of outcomes.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-2157-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: LIE, low-intensity exercise; MIE, moderate-intensity exercise; HIE, high-intensity exercise; TST, total sleep time; SOL, sleep onset latency; WASO, wake time after sleep onset; SE, sleep efficiency; REM, rapid eye movement; REM-L, rapid eye movement latency; N1, stage N1 sleep; N2, stage N2 sleep; N3, stage N3 sleep; SSQ, subjective sleep quality.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">SUCRA Values of Different Intensities of Acute Evening Exercise for Sleep Outcomes</citation_analysis></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TST</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOL</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">WASO</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM-L</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">N1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">N2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">N3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSQ</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.8%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LIE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.9%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MIE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.1%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><bold>Abbreviations</bold></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative">: LIE, low-intensity exercise; MIE, moderate-intensity exercise; HIE, high-intensity exercise; TST, total sleep time; SOL, sleep onset latency; WASO, wake time after sleep onset; SE, sleep efficiency; REM, rapid eye movement; REM-L, rapid eye movement latency; N1, stage N1 sleep; N2, stage N2 sleep; N3, stage N3 sleep; SSQ, subjective sleep quality.</citation_analysis></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In terms of sleep outcomes, 22 of 28 studies reported on the results of the TST</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15–20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34–39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44–50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and SOL.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30–39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44–50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> 18 of 28 studies reported on the results of the SE.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37–39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48–50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Two studies did not report SE and calculations were conducted by TST and TIB.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Half of the studies (n = 14) reported on the results of the WASO</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44–46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and SSQ (n = 14).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Less than half of the studies reported the latency of rapid eye movement (REM-L) (n = 12),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> the proportion of REM sleep (n = 11),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> the proportion of stage N3 sleep (SWS) (n = 11),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> the proportion of stage N1 sleep (n = 9),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and the proportion of N2 sleep (n = 10).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis></p>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The evening exercises ranged from 25 min to 3 h and comprised cycling or running. Eleven of the included studies used early evening protocol (16:00–20:00),</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18–20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33–35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and thirteen of the studies used late-evening protocol (after 20:00).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15–17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40–42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Three of the remaining studies used both early evening and late-evening protocols,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> while one study did not mention the time to exercise in the evening.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Evening exercise ended 0.5 to 4 h before bedtime.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Quality Assessment</title>
        <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Details of RoB 2.0 in each included study were shown in </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=388863.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">. The majority of included studies showed low risk bias, while eight studies had “some concerns” regarding the randomization process, wash-out period or missing outcome data.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Both “low risk bias” studies and “some concerns” studies were included in this network meta-analysis.</citation_analysis></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Network Meta-Analysis</title>
        <sec id="s0003-s2004-s3001">
          <title>TST</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">No significant difference was observed in regard to TST among these groups. In comparison with no exercise, the ranking probability based on the SUCRA values indicated that acute evening MIE had the lowest impact on TST (MD = −1.62 min, 95% CI = −9.17 to 6.00, SUCRA = 47.3%), followed by HIE (MD = −2.11 min, 95% CI = −10.01 to 6.24, SUCRA = 44.2%) and LIE (MD = −3.04 min, 95% CI = −10.19 to 7.34, SUCRA = 37.0%). Compared with LIE, acute evening MIE and HIE were comparable to each other in terms of the effects of increased TST, and no significant difference was found. Compared to MIE, though acute evening HIE reduced TST, no significant difference was observed (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Forest plots of network meta-analysis of all comparisons for TST, SOL, WASO, REM-L, and SE.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-2157-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: TST, total sleep time; SOL, sleep onset latency; WASO, wake time after sleep onset; REM-L, rapid eye movement latency; SE, sleep efficiency.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2004-s3002">
          <title>SOL</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">No significant difference was observed in regard to SOL among these groups. In comparison with no exercise, according to the SUCRA values, acute evening LIE was ranked to be better for the shortening of SOL (MD = −1.02 min, 95% CI = −4.39 to 2.50, SUCRA = 61.7%), followed by MIE (MD = −0.76 min, 95% CI = −2.87 to 1.28, SUCRA = 60.3%) and HIE (MD = −0.54 min, 95% CI = −2.31 to 1.31, SUCRA = 50.4%). Compared with LIE, acute evening MIE and HIE were comparable to each other in terms of the effects of increased SOL, and no significant difference was found. Compared to MIE, no significant difference was observed while acute evening HIE increased SOL (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2004-s3003">
          <title>WASO</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Regarding WASO, no statistically significant difference was observed among these groups. In comparison with no exercise, the SUCRA revealed that acute evening MIE was ranked the best method to shorten WASO (MD = −2.50 min, 95% CI = −8.17 to 1.62, SUCRA = 74.8%), followed by LIE (MD = −1.87 min, 95% CI = −9.51 to 4.78, SUCRA = 59.4%) and HIE (MD = −0.64 min, 95% CI = −5.85 to 2.91, SUCRA = 39.4%). Compared with LIE, acute evening MIE shortened WASO and HIE increased WASO, respectively, and no significant difference was found. Compared to MIE, no significant difference was observed while acute evening HIE increased WASO (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2004-s3004">
          <title>SE</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Acute evening LIE, MIE and HIE yielded no significant effects on SE compared with no exercise. The MDs and 95% CIs of SE in the acute evening LIE, MIE, and HIE were +0.29% (95% CI = −1.27 to 1.91), +0.41% (95% CI = −0.71 to 1.66), and −0.17% (95% CI = −1.25 to 0.94), respectively. Acute evening MIE had the highest probability of being the best option to improve SE, based on the SUCRA values (72.1%). Compared with LIE, acute evening MIE improved SE, while HIE decreased SE, and no significant difference was found. Compared to MIE, no significant difference was observed while acute evening HIE decreased SE (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2004-s3005">
          <title>REM-L</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In comparison with no exercise, although there were no significant effects, acute evening HIE was ranked the best intervention to increase REM-L (MD = +8.57 min, 95% CI = −1.80 to 18.58, SUCRA = 71.0%), followed by LIE (MD = +8.99 min, 95% CI = −6.10 to 24.14, SUCRA = 69.3%) and MIE (MD = +4.84 min, 95% CI = −7.57 to 17.74, SUCRA = 46.9%). Compared with LIE, acute evening MIE and HIE resulted in similar results, and no significant difference was found. Compared to MIE, no significant difference was observed while acute evening HIE increased REM-L (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2004-s3006">
          <title>The Proportion of Stage N1 Sleep</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In comparison with no exercise, acute evening LIE, MIE, and HIE did not show significant reductions in the proportion of stage N1 sleep, showing MDs of −0.39% (95% CI = −2.49 to 1.59), −0.72% (95% CI = −2.08 to 0.71), and −0.66% (95% CI = −1.69 to 0.44), respectively. The ranking probability based on the SUCRA values indicated that acute evening MIE had the highest probability of being the best option to reduce the proportion of stage N1 sleep (SUCRA = 67.2%). Compared with LIE, both acute evening MIE and HIE resulted in a reduction of the proportion of stage N1 sleep, and no significant difference was found. Compared to MIE, no significant difference was observed while acute evening HIE increased stage N1 sleep (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0004" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Forest plots of network meta-analysis of all comparisons for N1, N2, N3, and REM sleep.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-2157-g0004" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: N1, stage N1 sleep; N2, stage N2 sleep; N3, stage N3 sleep (slow-wave sleep); REM, rapid eye movement.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2004-s3007">
          <title>The Proportion of Stage N2 Sleep</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In comparison with no exercise, although there were no significant effects, acute evening HIE was regarded as the best method to increase the proportion of stage N2 sleep (MD = +2.09%, 95% CI = −0.12 to 4.34, SUCRA = 68.9%), followed by MIE (MD = +2.13%, 95% CI = −1.19 to 5.30, SUCRA = 66.6%) and LIE (MD = +1.62%, 95% CI = −1.45 to 4.68, SUCRA = 55.2%). Compared with LIE, both acute evening MIE and HIE resulted in increasing the proportion of N2 sleep, and no significant difference was found. Compared to MIE, no significant difference was observed while acute evening HIE decreased stage N2 sleep (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2004-s3008">
          <title>The Proportion of Stage N3 Sleep (SWS)</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">There was no significant difference observed in regard to the proportion of N3 sleep among these groups. In comparison with no exercise, the SUCRA revealed that acute evening MIE ranked the highest in terms of improving the proportion of N3 sleep (MD = +0.84%, 95% CI = −1.17 to 2.78, SUCRA = 86.2%), followed by HIE (MD = −0.41%, 95% CI = −2.04 to 1.24, SUCRA = 33.9%) and LIE (MD = −0.64%, 95% CI = −2.55 to 1.27, SUCRA = 25.0%). Compared with LIE, both acute evening MIE and HIE resulted in increasing the proportion of N3 sleep, and no significant difference was found. Compared to MIE, no significant difference was observed while acute evening HIE shortened stage N3 sleep (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2004-s3009">
          <title>The Proportion of REM Sleep</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The NMA suggested that, in comparison with no exercise, acute evening HIE was ranked to be significantly better for the shortening of REM (MD = −1.95%, 95% CI = −3.58 to −0.35, SUCRA = 85.4%), followed by MIE (MD = −1.56%, 95% CI = −3.54 to 0.48, SUCRA = 73.6%) and LIE (MD = −0.10%, 95% CI = −2.14 to 1.75, SUCRA = 23.1%). Compared with LIE, both acute evening MIE and HIE resulted in shortening REM, and no significant difference was found. Compared to MIE, no significant difference was observed while acute evening HIE shortened REM (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2004-s3010">
          <title>SSQ</title>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In comparison with no exercise, although there were no significant effects, the ranking probability based on the SUCRA values indicated that acute evening MIE had the lowest impact on SSQ (SMD = −0.01, 95% CI = −0.44 to 0.42, SUCRA = 73.1%), followed by LIE (SMD = −0.16, 95% CI = −0.67 to 0.37, SUCRA = 43.9%) and HIE (SMD = −0.34, −0.67 to 0.00, SUCRA = 11.2%). Compared with LIE, acute evening MIE improved SSQ, while HIE decreased SSQ, and no significant difference was found. Compared to MIE, no significant difference was observed while acute evening HIE decreased SSQ (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).
</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><fig position="float" id="f0005" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">A forest plot of network meta-analysis of all comparisons for SSQ.</citation_analysis></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-2157-g0005" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviation</bold>: SSQ, subjective sleep quality.</attrib></fig></citation_analysis></p>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The test of global inconsistency did not show any significant difference between the consistency and inconsistency models for all outcomes (all difference values of DIC were &lt;5). Similarly, the node splitting method, which tested local inconsistency, showed that all comparisons among direct and indirect estimates were consistent for all outcomes (all p values &gt;0.5, </citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=388863.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table S12</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). In addition, no significant global heterogeneity of the NMA was found (I</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> = 0%). There was no significant local heterogeneity in most of the comparisons in this NMA (I</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 0% or 5.2%) except that only three comparisons showed low local heterogeneity (I</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> = 15.6%, 24.7% and 29.1%) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=388863.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Tables S2</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">–</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=388863.docx" ext-link-type="uri">S11</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive">). The comparison-adjusted funnel plots for the outcomes suggested publication bias was not evident (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=388863.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figures S1</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">–</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=388863.docx" ext-link-type="uri">S10</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p>
          <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The subgroup NMA explored the effects of time of evening exercise, hours from cessation of exercise to bedtime, exercise modality, physical activity level, and exercise duration of acute evening exercise on objective sleep quality. The results of NMA of all outcomes were not modified in most of the comparisons. Different intensities of exercise performed in early- and late-evening had no negatively impact on objective sleep quality. The timeslot between the end of exercise and bedtime (0.5–1.5 h, 2 h, &gt;2–4 h) had no effects on objective sleep quality. In addition, regardless of sedentary or physically fit participants, different intensities of evening exercise had no effects on objective sleep quality. However, compared with no exercise, MIE with cycling significantly increased REM-L (MD = 38.78 min, 95% CI = 3.99 to 73.80) and a longer (&gt;30–60 min) HIE decreased REM sleep (MD = −2.50%, 95% CI = −4.74 to −0.35) (</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=388863.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table S13</ext-link></underline></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">).</citation_analysis></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">This systematic review and network meta-analysis explored the effects of acute evening exercise with different intensities on sleep in healthy adults. In contrast to our hypothesis, no significant differences were observed in both objective and subjective sleep quality with different evening exercise intensities. The present findings were in line with a study showing that different intensities of acute evening exercises did not disrupt sleep in healthy young and middle-aged adults.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, in line with our hypothesis and Frimpong et al's pairwise meta-analysis, 30–60 min duration with acute evening HIE resulted in a decrease in the REM sleep, which might worsen sleep quality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In addition, acute MIE with cycling in the evening resulted in an improvement on REM-L.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Sufficient sleep plays an important role in restoring the consumption of the nervous system and metabolization in the waking stage,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> and daytime exercise has been proven to be positive for sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> TST was associated with daytime sleepiness.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Furthermore, a previous study from the Asia Cohort Consortium suggested that TST was a behavioral risk factor in mortality in both men and women and TST of seven hours was recommended.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Oda and Shirakawa found a reduction in TST after acute HIE was completed one hour before bedtime compared with no exercise while TST in MIE did not change in twelve young males.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Not in line with Oda and Shirakawa, a recent study reported, compared with no exercise, acute evening HIE did not disrupt TST in 12 healthy males.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Thomas et al also found that acute evening HIE and LIE resulted in similar improvements in TST.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The crossover trial of Miller et al suggested that 30 min cycling at 75% HRmax ended 1.5 h before bedtime did not affect TST in 12 young males.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The results of the present NMA also supported the notion that acute evening exercise did not disrupt TST regardless of exercise intensities in healthy young and middle-aged adults. The results of Frimpong et al's pairwise meta-analysis were consistent with the current study that evening HIE did not significantly disrupt TST (+ 2.34 min).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In addition to TST, knowledge about SOL, WASO, and SE was also important, because SOL, WASO, and SE could predict the perceived sleep quality in healthy subjects.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> SOL could be recalled easily in the morning, which might result in increment in the perception of daytime dysfunction as well as perceived poor sleep quality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The current study found there was a trend of shortening SOL after acute evening exercise compared to no exercise, and LIE might be the best method for the improvement of SOL (- 1.02 min). Oda and Shirakawa found a delay in SOL (+ 14 min) after HIE in the evening,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> which was contrary to the current study that acute evening HIE did not delay sleep onset (−0.54 min). In line with our findings, Hayashi et al suggested relative to no exercise, acute evening HIE and MIE could significantly shorten SOL in nine sedentary college students.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In Myllymäki et al study, some indications of shortened SOL were also observed after acute evening HIE.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In addition, Ramos-Campo et al found average time of each awakening was significantly higher when 14 recreational male runners conducted acute evening HIE compared to MIE.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Conversely, a previous meta-analysis found that exercise conducted at any time of the day had a significantly positive result for WASO.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The current NMA revealed a decreased trend of WASO after acute evening exercise and the largest decrease in WASO was observed after acute evening MIE compared to no exercise (−2.50 min). In consistent with our findings, a recent crossover trial also found acute evening MIE did not affect WASO compared with no exercise in 16 healthy college students.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In regard to SE, although our study found acute evening exercise did not disrupt SE, different trends of SE after different intensities of acute evening exercise were observed. The current NMA resulted in improved trends of SE after acute evening LIE (+ 0.29%) and MIE (+ 0.41%), while the worsening trend of SE was observed after HIE (- 0.17%) compared with no exercise. This was supported by a study conducted in eight physically active college students, which revealed that SE was not worsened after acute evening MIE and LIE.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> In regard to acute evening HIE, compared to no exercise, a recent pairwise meta-analysis revealed similar trends of SE (−0.22%) with the findings in our study.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Disturbances of SOL and SE were associated with an increased risk of mortality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The non-disruptive findings of SOL, WASO, and SE in the current NMA were of potential clinical significance.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In regard to sleep architecture, compared to no exercise, the current NMA did not find significant changes in the proportion of stages N1, N2, N3 sleep as well as REM-L after different intensities of acute evening exercise, while the proportion of REM sleep was significantly decreased after acute evening HIE. There was an indication of increased stage N1 sleep during the whole night in Aloulou et al study, and they also observed the proportion of stage N1 sleep was higher during the first 180 min of the night after acute evening HIE compared with no exercise.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Not inconsistent with the findings of Aloulou et al, Flausino et al found that the stage N1 sleep significantly decreased after acute evening HIE and MIE compared with no exercise.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The results of the current study showed a declining trend in stage N1 sleep after acute evening exercise compared to no exercise. As stage N1 sleep represented light sleep, acute evening MIE might be the best method to shorten the proportion of stage N1 sleep in our findings (−0.72%). A previous pairwise meta-analysis also supported our results that stage N1 sleep was not significantly changed after evening HIE compared to no exercise.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> SWS, a component of non-rapid eye movement (NERM) sleep, was associated with increased growth hormone and decreased cortisol secretion.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Therefore, it has been proved to be the most restorative sleep stage. There were different trends in SWS after different intensities of acute evening exercise observed in the current findings. The positive modification of SWS was observed after acute evening MIE (+ 0.84%) while shortened SWS was observed after acute evening LIE (−0.64%) and HIE (−0.41%) compared to no exercise. In contrast to our findings, the randomized crossover trial of Dworak et al found that acute evening HIE completed 3–4 h before bedtime resulted in a significantly increased proportion of SWS, and this change was not found in acute evening MIE.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The discrepancy might be attributed to the population. The current study focused on young and middle-aged adults, whereas children (mean: 12.6 years old) were recruited in the study of Dworak et al. However, Hayashi et al study echoed the current results. Although Hayashi et al did not find significant difference, they found a tendency for an increase in the proportion of SWS after acute evening MIE compared to no exercise in nine sedentary college students (mean: 22.8 years old).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Considering that the sample size of included studies was small, the effects of evening MIE on SWS needed to be further researched.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Our study found REM sleep was significantly shortened after acute evening HIE compared to no exercise (−1.95%), which was consistent with Frimpong et al pairwise meta-analysis (−2.34%).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Previous studies found the similar effects of evening exercise on REM sleep. The meta-analysis of Stutz et al revealed that, after sensitivity analysis, the decrease of REM sleep became a trend or significant after acute evening exercise compared to no exercise (−0.69%).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Both Larsen et al and Aloulou et al observed a tendency for decreased REM sleep during the whole night after acute evening HIE compared to no exercise in healthy young adults.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Moreover, there was also a tendency for decreased REM sleep after acute evening LIE (−0.10%) and MIE (−1.56%) in the present study, which conformed to the result of Wong et al study.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Wong et al showed that there was a trend of a reduced proportion of REM sleep with increased evening exercise intensity.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The results of our study showed that acute evening HIE decreased REM sleep, whereas LIE and MIE did not. What is more, previous analyses found even if exercise during the day, REM sleep still decreased.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> However, decreased REM sleep was not necessarily harmful. A previous study found that decreased REM sleep could reflect the consolidation of REM sleep and could also be the result of enhanced SWS.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The PSG data from Larsen et al showed decreased REM sleep predominantly within the initial 180 min of sleep after acute evening HIE, in keeping with the findings of Netzer et al and Robey et al</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Furthermore, Netzer found that an increase in norepinephrine after intense exercise was associated with decreased REM sleep and increased REM-L.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Indeed, the results of the current NMA revealed a tendency for increased REM-L after acute evening exercise compared to no exercise, and acute evening HIE was regarded as the best intervention to increase REM-L (+ 8.57 min). After HIE, the release of norepinephrine was 14.5 higher than MIE,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> which might result in delayed REM sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">In addition, most of the included studies assessed SSQ. There were disagreements about whether evening exercise was beneficial to SSQ among previous studies. Both Aloulou et al and Arias et al reported SSQ was impaired after acute evening HIE while good SSQ was observed without evening exercise.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Delayed onset muscle soreness after HIE might be the reason for poor SSQ the next morning.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> In contrast to Aloulou et al and Arias et al, some studies revealed that SSQ was not affected after acute evening LIE, MIE and HIE compared to no exercise.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Compared with no exercise, acute evening MIE and HIE did not negatively affect subjective TST and WASO.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Oda &amp; Shirakawa found that compared with no exercise, subjective SOL was negatively affected by acute evening HIE but not by acute evening MIE.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> Conversely, some studies also supported the notion that neither acute evening MIE nor HIE would negatively affect subjective SOL compared to no exercise.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> As we mentioned above, the SOL would be easily recalled in the next morning, which might affect the perceived SSQ of participants. The present NMA did not find distorted SOL after evening exercise, and the results supported the notion that evening exercise regardless of low-, moderate- and high intensity did not disrupt SSQ in young and middle-aged adults.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Previous pairwise meta-analyses suggested that the time of evening exercise, the hours from cessation of exercise to bedtime, the exercise modality, the physical activity level of participants, and the duration of evening exercise should be considered when analyzing the effects of acute evening exercise on objective sleep quality.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Subgroup analyses in the current study revealed a long duration (&gt;30–60 min) of acute evening HIE significantly decreased the proportion of REM sleep compared to no exercise (−2.50%). Considering increased norepinephrine levels after HIE,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> long duration might be a potential factor to facilitate this process. The results of Youngstedt et al study also showed acute evening HIE with 3 hours did not disrupt subsequent sleep in 16 cyclists.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Given that active participants might recover in a short period of time after exercise, the physical activity level of participants was considered in subgroup analysis. The present NMA subgroup analysis of physical activity level did not show any significant effects of acute evening exercise on objective sleep quality. In addition, cycling with acute evening MIE had significantly positive effects on REM-L compared to no exercise (+ 38.78 min), while there were no effects observed after running. Meanwhile, although a study had proven that running was more likely to induce higher levels of muscle damage and inflammation compared to cycling,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> no sufficient evidence showed that muscle damage and inflammation affect sleep negatively.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Given that an acute psychophysiological response was induced by an acute exercise, exercise in the early evening might have sufficient recovery for a psychophysiological response that might not disrupt subsequent sleep, whereas exercise in the late evening might negatively affect sleep. However, the subgroup analysis of time of evening exercise in the present study found exercise in the early and late evening did not disrupt sleep regardless of exercise intensity. A previous meta-analysis found early evening HIE shortened SOL (−4.6 min), and late-evening exercise had no negative effects on sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> When considering the hours from cessation of exercise to bedtime, exercise performed close to bedtime might disrupt sleep especially HIE.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Oda and Shirakawa found that compared with no exercise, evening HIE end 1 h before bedtime delayed sleep onset (+14 min) and decreased TST and SE.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Conversely, the study of Youngstedt et al suggested that even acute evening HIE ended 0.5 h before bedtime did not disturb sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Thus, the subgroup analysis was conducted to explore the effects of the hours from cessation of exercise to bedtime. The results of the present study showed that evening exercise regardless of intensity ended 0.5–1.5 h, 2 h and &gt;2–4 h before bedtime did not disrupt sleep. In line with the present results, evening MIE ended 1h or 0.5 h before bedtime had no effects on sleep in previous studies.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The meta-analysis of Frimpong et al also showed that evening HIE ended 2 h before bedtime significantly decreased SOL and increased TST.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Although some studies found that compared with no exercise, evening HIE and MIE ended 2–4 h before bedtime decreased REM sleep,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> the decreases in REM sleep were also found in daytime exercise</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6–8</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> and, as we discussed above, the decreases in REM sleep did not necessarily indicate a negative effect on sleep. These results of subgroup analyses consolidated the main finding that evening exercise regardless of intensity did not disrupt subsequent sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The chronotypes of participants might be a potential factor modulating the effects of evening exercise on sleep. Six of included studies reported the chronotypes of participants.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17–19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The study of Aloulou et al found that, compared with no exercise, late-evening HIE ended 2 h before bedtime had negative impacts on sleep in neither-type participants.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Not consistent with Aloulou et al, Thomas et al and Vlahoyiannis et al reported that evening HIE ended 3–3.5 h before bedtime improved sleep quality in neither-type participants.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Moreover, the positive changes of sleep quality induced by evening LIE ended 3.5 h before bedtime were comparable to those induced by evening HIE in neither-type participants.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Saidi et al also showed that early evening MIE ended 4 h before bedtime had positive effects on sleep quality in neither-type participants.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The study of Vitale et al, which involved both morning-type and evening-type participants, demonstrated that the sleep quality of morning-type participants was negatively affected by late evening HIE while that of evening-type participants was not affected.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, morning HIE did not negatively affect the sleep quality of both morning-type and evening-type participants.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> A recent cross-sectional study investigated 909 college students, and showed chronotype moderated the relationship between exercise timing and bedtime.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> For every minute of delay in exercise timing, bedtime was delayed by 6.1 minutes for morning-type participants and only 3.6 minutes for evening-type participants.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Existing studies mainly focus on neither-type participants, while only one of included studies considered morning-type and evening-type participants. Few studies had taken chronotype into consideration when exploring the effects of evening exercise on sleep quality. Therefore, how chronotype modulates the relationship between different intensities of evening exercise and subsequent sleep needs to be further researched.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The potential complicated mechanisms between acute evening exercise and sleep were still unclear and were roughly clarified as the thermoregulation hypothesis, body recovery hypothesis, and energy storage hypothesis.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67–69</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Some previous studies reported the rising body temperature induced by exercise made a positive effect on the proportion of SWS.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The study of Horne and Moore, who used extra clothes (hot) to elevate body temperature, found only exercise in hot conditions increased SWS.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Actually, during the period of high core body temperature (CBT), the human body was awake and active while during the period of low CBT, the body was inactive and asleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Based on this view and in consideration of previously mentioned studies which showed rising body temperature associated with the improvement of SWS were not conducted in the evening,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> it seemed that high CBT close to bedtime was detrimental to subsequent sleep. However, some studies were in contrast with this notion. Youngstedt et al recruited 16 healthy cyclists, and the results showed that rising CBT caused by acute evening HIE with 3 hours completed 30 min before bedtime did not disrupt sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The study of Aloulou et al showed that, although CBT significantly increased at the end of acute evening HIE (+1.40 ± 0.43°C) and remained high during the first 3 hours of sleep compared with no exercise, the objective sleep quality was not distorted by the elevated temperature.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Another notion that the decrease of CBT after exercise rather than absolute CBT was the inducement of sleep onset was worth mentioning to illustrate the influence of evening exercise on sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Nevertheless, Miller et al found that CBT elevated during acute evening MIE and CBT returned to its pre-exercise level when going to bed, but no positive modification of SOL was observed.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Flausino et al did not find peripheral body temperature would increase with the increment of exercise intensity, nor did they find that the peripheral body temperature played a vital role in the delay of sleep latency and TST reduction.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> CBT also declined rapidly after acute evening exercise, yet it did not make an improvement on SOL in Flausino et al study.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The present NMA subgroup analysis of hours from the cessation of exercise to bedtime (0.5–2 h, 2h, &gt;2–4 h) did not show any significant difference between acute evening exercise on subsequent objective sleep quality regardless of exercise intensity, which disproved the thermoregulation hypothesis indirectly. However, complete clinical trials are also needed to directly verify whether the thermoregulation hypothesis can explain the effects of acute evening exercise with different intensities on sleep.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The body recovery and energy storage hypothesis suggested the quantity of TST and SWS would increase with the increased energy consumption.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> High catabolic activity during awake was beneficial to anabolic activity during sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> As a previous study found, the growth hormone released during the SWS phase was beneficial to physical and mental health.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> However, as existing studies did not measure energy consumption during different intensities of evening exercise, future studies could focus on this area. Moreover, hormone secretion after evening exercise might also affect subsequent sleep. As was mentioned in the study of Netzer et al, more norepinephrine released after HIE compared to MIE was associated with induced delayed REM sleep and the shortened proportion of REM sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Buxton et al and Miyazaki et al found both the onset and peak phase of plasma melatonin were earlier after an acute exercise compared to no exercise.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> How hormone secretion after different intensities of acute evening exercise affected subsequent sleep needed to be further researched.</citation_analysis></p>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">To the best of our knowledge, this NMA represented the most comprehensive analysis of currently available data regarding different effects of intensities of acute evening exercise on subsequent sleep. The convergence of the current NMA was good (PSRF = 1 or 1.01) and the global heterogeneity was low (I</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><sup>2</sup></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> = 0%). However, some limitations should be noted in this study. The sample size of included studies was small (ranged 5 to 23) and most of the participants were males, which might cause bias in the results. In addition, this systematic review and network meta-analysis focused on acute evening exercise. Thus, the effects of different intensities of chronic evening exercise on sleep needed to be further researched. Our study did not find positive effects of acute evening exercise on subsequent sleep due to ceiling and floor effects, which meant that it would be more effective for participants who were already presented impaired sleep to exercise before sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Also, only good sleepers were explored in our study, limiting the application of the findings to a broad population.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">This systematic review and network meta-analysis found that acute evening exercise regardless of intensity completed before bedtime did not disrupt subsequent sleep in healthy young and middle-aged adults without sleep disorders. The modality and duration of evening exercise should be considered when developing sleep hygiene recommendations.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors thank Ruicong Liu for advice during research writing.</citation_analysis></p>
    </ack>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0006">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ohayon</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Epidemiology of insomnia: what we know and what we still need to learn</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>111</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/smrv.2002.0186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12531146</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lovato</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lack</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia and mortality: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2018.10.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30529432</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bertisch</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pollock</surname>
<given-names>BD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mittleman</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia with objective short sleep duration and risk of incident cardiovascular disease and all-cause mortality: sleep Heart Health Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>6</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsy047</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ogilvie</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The epidemiology of sleep and diabetes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Diab Rep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>82</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11892-018-1055-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30120578</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jarrin</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alvaro</surname>
<given-names>PK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bouchard</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jarrin</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drake</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morin</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia and hypertension: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2018.02.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29576408</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kubitz</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Landers</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petruzzello</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effects of acute and chronic exercise on sleep. A meta-analytic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sports Med</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>277</fpage>–<lpage>291</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/00007256-199621040-00004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8726346</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Youngstedt</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Connor</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dishman</surname>
<given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effects of acute exercise on sleep: a quantitative synthesis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>214</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/20.3.203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9178916</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kredlow</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Capozzoli</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hearon</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Calkins</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Otto</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effects of physical activity on sleep: a meta-analytic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Behav Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>449</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10865-015-9617-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25596964</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pedišić</surname>
<given-names>Ž</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dumuid</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olds</surname>
<given-names>TS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Integrating sleep, sedentary behaviour, and physical activity research in the emerging field of time-use epidemiology definitions, concepts, statistical methods, theoretical framework, and future directions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Kinesiology</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>252</fpage>–<lpage>269</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cerin</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leslie</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sugiyama</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Owen</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Perceived barriers to leisure-time physical activity in adults: an ecological perspective</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Phys Act Health</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>451</fpage>–<lpage>459</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/jpah.7.4.451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20683086</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sargent</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roach</surname>
<given-names>GD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scanlan</surname>
<given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vincent</surname>
<given-names>GE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lastella</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Moderate-intensity exercise performed in the evening does not impair sleep in healthy males</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Sport Sci</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>80</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17461391.2019.1611934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31072217</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</collab>. <article-title>International classification of sleep disorders, revised: diagnostic and coding manual</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</publisher-name>; <year>2001</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xlink:href="https://cir.nii.ac.jp/crid/1571135650687048576" ext-link-type="uri">https://cir.nii.ac.jp/crid/1571135650687048576</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>June</month>
<day>13</day>, 2022</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buman</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Phillips</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Youngstedt</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kline</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hirshkowitz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Does nighttime exercise really disturb sleep? Results from the 2013 national sleep foundation sleep in America Poll</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>755</fpage>–<lpage>761</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2014.01.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24933083</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dworak</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wiater</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alfer</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stephan</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hollmann</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Strüder</surname>
<given-names>HK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Increased slow wave sleep and reduced stage 2 sleep in children depending on exercise intensity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>266</fpage>–<lpage>272</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2007.04.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17644426</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Oda</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shirakawa</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep onset is disrupted following pre-sleep exercise that causes large physiological excitement at bedtime</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Appl Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>114</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1789</fpage>–<lpage>1799</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00421-014-2873-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24859750</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Browman</surname>
<given-names>CP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tepas</surname>
<given-names>DI</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effects of presleep activity on all-night sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychophysiology</italic></source>. <year>1976</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>536</fpage>–<lpage>540</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8986.1976.tb00876.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">186836</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ramos-Campo</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ávila-Gandía</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luque</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rubio-Arias</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of hour of training and exercise intensity on nocturnal autonomic modulation and sleep quality of amateur ultra-endurance runners</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiol Behav</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>198</volume>:<fpage>134</fpage>–<lpage>139</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.physbeh.2018.10.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30389476</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vlahoyiannis</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aphamis</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eddin</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Giannaki</surname>
<given-names>CD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effect of evening cycling at different intensities on sleep in healthy young adults with intermediate chronobiological phenotype: a randomized, cross-over trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sports Sci</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>192</fpage>–<lpage>199</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02640414.2020.1812194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32844703</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Thomas</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whitworth-Turner</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Louis</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>High-intensity exercise in the evening does not disrupt sleep in endurance runners</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Appl Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>120</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>359</fpage>–<lpage>368</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00421-019-04280-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31813044</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Myllymäki</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rusko</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Syväoja</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Juuti</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kinnunen</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kyröläinen</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of exercise intensity and duration on nocturnal heart rate variability and sleep quality</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Appl Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>112</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>801</fpage>–<lpage>809</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00421-011-2034-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21667290</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Frimpong</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mograss</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zvionow</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dang-Vu</surname>
<given-names>TT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effects of evening high-intensity exercise on sleep in healthy adults: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>101535</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2021.101535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34416428</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stutz</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eiholzer</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spengler</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of evening exercise on sleep in healthy participants: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sports Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>269</fpage>–<lpage>287</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40279-018-1015-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30374942</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mills</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thorlund</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ioannidis</surname>
<given-names>JPA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Demystifying trial networks and network meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>346</volume>:<fpage>f2914</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.f2914</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23674332</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ades</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Combination of direct and indirect evidence in mixed treatment comparisons</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Stat Med</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>3105</fpage>–<lpage>3124</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/sim.1875</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15449338</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Garber</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blissmer</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deschenes</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Quantity and quality of exercise for developing and maintaining cardiorespiratory, musculoskeletal, and neuromotor fitness in apparently healthy adults: guidance for prescribing exercise</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Med Sci Sports Exerc</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1334</fpage>–<lpage>1359</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/MSS.0b013e318213fefb</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21694556</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ancoli-Israel</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cole</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alessi</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chambers</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moorcroft</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pollak</surname>
<given-names>CP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The role of actigraphy in the study of sleep and circadian rhythms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>342</fpage>–<lpage>392</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/26.3.342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12749557</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liang</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pan</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhong</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zeng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>ASK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of aerobic, resistance, and combined exercise on metabolic syndrome parameters and cardiovascular risk factors: a systematic review and network meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Rev Cardiovasc Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1523</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.31083/j.rcm2204156</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34957791</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hutton</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salanti</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caldwell</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The PRISMA extension statement for reporting of systematic reviews incorporating network meta-analyses of health care interventions: checklist and explanations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>162</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>777</fpage>–<lpage>784</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M14-2385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26030634</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liberati</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Altman</surname>
<given-names>DG</given-names></string-name> and <string-name><surname>Tetzlaff</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The PRISMA statement for reporting systematic reviews and meta-analyses of studies that evaluate healthcare interventions: explanation and elaboration</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic></source>, <volume>339</volume>(<issue>jul21 1</issue>), <fpage>b2700</fpage>–<lpage>b2700</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.b2700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19622552</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Arias</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Madinabeitia-Mancebo</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Santiago</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Corral-Bergantinos</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Robles-Garcia</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of early or late-evening fatiguing physical activity on sleep quality in non-professional sportsmen</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sports Med Phys Fitness</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>597</fpage>–<lpage>605</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27285348</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aloulou</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duforez</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bieuzen</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nedelec</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effect of night‐time exercise on sleep architecture among well‐trained male endurance runners</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>6</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12964</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bulckaert</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Exadaktylos</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haex</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Valck</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Verbraecken</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berckmans</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Elevated variance in heart rate during slow-wave sleep after late-night physical activity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chronobiol Int</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>282</fpage>–<lpage>284</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/07420528.2011.552820</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21452924</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Driver</surname>
<given-names>HS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meintjes</surname>
<given-names>AF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rogers</surname>
<given-names>GG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shapiro</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Submaximal exercise effects on sleep patterns in young women before and after an aerobic training programme</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Physiol Scand Suppl</italic></source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>574</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3245468</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Larsen</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marino</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Melehan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guelfi</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duffield</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Skein</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Evening high‐intensity interval exercise does not disrupt sleep or alter energy intake despite changes in acylated ghrelin in middle‐aged men</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Exp Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>826</fpage>–<lpage>836</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/EP087455</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30801859</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Miura</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Myouken</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yamada</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of aerobic exercise in early evening on the following nocturnal sleep and its haemodynamic response</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Res Sport Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>16</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15438627.2015.1076415</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Myllymäki</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kyröläinen</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Savolainen</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of vigorous late-night exercise on sleep quality and cardiac autonomic activity: late-night exercise and sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1pt2</issue>):<fpage>146</fpage>–<lpage>153</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.2010.00874.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20673290</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Díaz</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matsumoto</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Exercise improves the quality of slow-wave sleep by increasing slow-wave stability</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>4410</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-83817-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33627708</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Robey</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dawson</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Halson</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of evening postexercise cold water immersion on subsequent sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Med Sci Sports Exerc</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1394</fpage>–<lpage>1402</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/MSS.0b013e318287f321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23377833</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Saidi</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davenne</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lehorgne</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duche</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of timing of moderate exercise in the evening on sleep and subsequent dietary intake in lean, young, healthy adults: randomized crossover study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Appl Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>120</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1551</fpage>–<lpage>1562</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00421-020-04386-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32372217</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Uçar</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Özgöçer</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yildiz</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Late-night exercise affects the autonomic nervous system activity but not the hypothalamo-pituitary-adrenal axis in the next morning</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sports Med Phys Fitness</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>1–2</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.23736/S0022-4707.16.06766-9</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vincent</surname>
<given-names>GE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sargent</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roach</surname>
<given-names>GD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Exercise before bed does not impact sleep inertia in young healthy males</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e12903</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12903</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31621995</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vitale</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bonato</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Galasso</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep quality and high intensity interval training at two different times of day: a crossover study on the influence of the chronotype in male collegiate soccer players</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chronobiol Int</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>260</fpage>–<lpage>268</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07420528.2016.1256301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27906554</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yoshida</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ishikawa</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shiraishi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kobayashi</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of the timing of exercise on the night sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>140</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1819.1998.tb00994.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9628115</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Youngstedt</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kripke</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elliott</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Is sleep disturbed by vigorous late-night exercise?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Med Sci Sports Exerc</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>864</fpage>–<lpage>869</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005768-199906000-00015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10378914</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yamanaka</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hashimoto</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Takasu</surname>
<given-names>NN</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Morning and evening physical exercise differentially regulate the autonomic nervous system during nocturnal sleep in humans</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>309</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>R1112</fpage>–<lpage>R1121</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpregu.00127.2015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26333783</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Flausino</surname>
<given-names>NH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Da Silva Prado</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Queiroz</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tufik</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mello</surname>
<given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Physical exercise performed before bedtime improves the sleep pattern of healthy young good sleepers: exercising before bedtime and sleep pattern</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychophysiol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>186</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8986.2011.01300.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kern</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perras</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wodick</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fehm</surname>
<given-names>HL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Born</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Hormonal secretion during nighttime sleep indicating stress of daytime exercise</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Appl Physiol</italic></source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>79</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1461</fpage>–<lpage>1468</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jappl.1995.79.5.1461</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8594001</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>O’Connor</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Breus</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Youngstedt</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Exercise-induced increase in core temperature does not disrupt a behavioral measure of sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiol Behav</italic></source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>217</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0031-9384(98)00049-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9748085</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Halaki</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chow</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effects of moderate to vigorous aerobic exercise on the sleep need of sedentary young adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sports Sci</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>386</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02640414.2012.733823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23075031</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hayashi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nishihira</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Higashiura</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Usui</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effects of different intensities of exercise on night sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Adv Exerc Sport Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Assefa</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Diaz-Abad</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wickwire</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scharf</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Functions of Sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">neuroscience</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>171</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3934/Neuroscience.2015.3.155</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Carskadon</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dement</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>, <collab>Carskadon MA, Dement WC</collab>. <article-title>Nocturnal determinants of daytime sleepiness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1982</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>suppl_2</issue>):<fpage>S73</fpage>–<lpage>S81</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/5.S2.S73</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7156657</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Svensson</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saito</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Svensson</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of sleep duration with all- and major-cause mortality among adults in Japan, China, Singapore, and Korea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Netw Open</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e2122837</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.22837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34477853</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Goelema</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Regis</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haakma</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van den Heuvel</surname>
<given-names>ER</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Markopoulos</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Overeem</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Determinants of perceived sleep quality in normal sleepers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>388</fpage>–<lpage>397</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15402002.2017.1376205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28929803</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0055">
        <label>55.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Halson</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnston</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Appaneal</surname>
<given-names>RN</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep quality in elite athletes: normative values, reliability and understanding contributors to poor sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sports Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>426</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40279-021-01555-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34554425</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0056">
        <label>56.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dew</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoch</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Healthy older adults’ sleep predicts all-cause mortality at 4 to 19 years of follow-up: psychosomatic medicine</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Cell Proteomics</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.PSY.0000039756.23250.7C</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0057">
        <label>57.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Obal</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krueger</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>GHRH and sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>367</fpage>–<lpage>377</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2004.03.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15336237</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0058">
        <label>58.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Driver</surname>
<given-names>HS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Exercise and sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>387</fpage>–<lpage>402</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/smrv.2000.0110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12531177</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0059">
        <label>59.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lucidi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Devoto</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Violani</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Gennaro</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mastracci</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bertini</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Rapid eye movements density as a measure of sleep need: REM density decreases linearly with the reduction of prior sleep duration</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Electroencephalogr Clin Neurophysiol</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>556</fpage>–<lpage>561</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0013-4694(96)95671-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9020815</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0060">
        <label>60.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Netzer</surname>
<given-names>NC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kristo</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Steinle</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lehmann</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Strohl</surname>
<given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>REM sleep and catecholamine excretion: a study in elite athletes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Appl Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>84</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>521</fpage>–<lpage>526</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004210100383</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11482546</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0061">
        <label>61.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Boutcher</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>High-intensity intermittent exercise and fat loss</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Obes</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>2011</volume>:<fpage>868305</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2011/868305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21113312</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0062">
        <label>62.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lewis</surname>
<given-names>PB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruby</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bush-Joseph</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Muscle soreness and delayed-onset muscle soreness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Sports Med</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.csm.2011.09.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22341015</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0063">
        <label>63.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>MacIntyre</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reid</surname>
<given-names>WD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McKenzie</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Delayed muscle soreness: the inflammatory response to muscle injury and its clinical implications</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sports Med</italic></source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>24</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/00007256-199520010-00003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7481277</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0064">
        <label>64.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nieman</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dréau</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Immune and inflammation responses to a 3-day period of intensified running versus cycling</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Behav Immun</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>180</fpage>–<lpage>185</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2013.09.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24055861</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0065">
        <label>65.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fullagar</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Skorski</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duffield</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meyer</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effect of an acute sleep hygiene strategy following a late-night soccer match on recovery of players</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chronobiol Int</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>490</fpage>–<lpage>505</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/07420528.2016.1149190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27031035</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0066">
        <label>66.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Glavin</surname>
<given-names>EE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ceneus</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chanowitz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Relationships between sleep, exercise timing, and chronotype in young adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Health Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>2636</fpage>–<lpage>2647</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1359105320926530</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32498631</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0067">
        <label>67.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McGinty</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Szymusiak</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Keeping cool: a hypothesis about the mechanisms and functions of slow-wave sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Trends Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>480</fpage>–<lpage>487</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0166-2236(90)90081-K</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1703678</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0068">
        <label>68.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Adam</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oswald</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Protein synthesis, bodily renewal and the sleep-wake cycle</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Sci</italic></source>. <year>1983</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>561</fpage>–<lpage>567</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/cs0650561</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0069">
        <label>69.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Berger</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Phillips</surname>
<given-names>NH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Comparative aspects of energy metabolism, body temperature and sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Physiol Scand Suppl</italic></source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>574</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3072836</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0070">
        <label>70.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Horne</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moore</surname>
<given-names>VJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep EEG effects of exercise with and without additional body cooling</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Electroencephalogr Clin Neurophysiol</italic></source>. <year>1985</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0013-4694(85)90948-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2578352</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0071">
        <label>71.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Horne</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Staff</surname>
<given-names>LH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Exercise and sleep: body-heating effects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1983</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/6.1.36</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6844796</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0072">
        <label>72.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Van Dongen</surname>
<given-names>HPA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dinges</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Circadian rhythms in fatigue, alertness and performance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Principle Pract Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>391</fpage>–<lpage>399</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0073">
        <label>73.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Murphy</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Nighttime drop in body temperature: a physiological trigger for sleep onset?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>505</fpage>–<lpage>511</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/20.7.505</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9322266</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0074">
        <label>74.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buxton</surname>
<given-names>OM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>L’Hermite-Baleriaux</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Turek</surname>
<given-names>FW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Cauter</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Exercise elicits phase shifts and acute alterations of melatonin that vary with circadian phase</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>284</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>R714</fpage>–<lpage>R724</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpregu.00355.2002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12571075</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0075">
        <label>75.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Miyazaki</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hashimoto</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Masubuchi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Honma</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Honma</surname>
<given-names>KI</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Phase-advance shifts of human circadian pacemaker are accelerated by daytime physical exercise</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>281</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>R197</fpage>–<lpage>R205</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpregu.2001.281.1.R197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11404294</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0076">
        <label>76.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Youngstedt</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Ceiling and floor effects in sleep research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>351</fpage>–<lpage>365</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/smrv.2001.0239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14505601</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
