<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="editorial">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36713639</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">9875581</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">402694</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S402694</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Editorial</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>The Tale of Orthosomnia: I Am so Good at Sleeping that I Can Do It with My Eyes Closed and My Fitness Tracker on Me</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Jahrami et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Jahrami et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8990-1320</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Jahrami</surname>
            <given-names>Haitham</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Trabelsi</surname>
            <given-names>Khaled</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9776-0473</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Vitiello</surname>
            <given-names>Michael V</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1706-6167</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>BaHammam</surname>
            <given-names>Ahmed S</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0006" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0007" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Psychiatry, Ministry of Health</institution>, <addr-line>Manama</addr-line>, <country>Kingdom of Bahrain</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Psychiatry, College of Medicine and Medical Sciences, Arabian Gulf University</institution>, <addr-line>Manama</addr-line>, <country>Kingdom of Bahrain</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>High Institute of Sport and Physical Education of Sfax, University of Sfax</institution>, <addr-line>Sfax</addr-line>, <addr-line>3000</addr-line>, <country>Tunisia</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Research Laboratory: Education, Motricity, Sport and Health, EM2S, LR19JS01, University of Sfax</institution>, <addr-line>Sfax</addr-line>, <addr-line>3000</addr-line>, <country>Tunisia</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label><institution>Department of Psychiatry &amp; Behavioral Sciences, University of Washington</institution>, <addr-line>Seattle</addr-line>, <addr-line>WA</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0006"><label>6</label><institution>Department of Medicine, College of Medicine, University Sleep Disorders Center, King Saud University</institution>, <addr-line>Riyadh</addr-line>, <country>Saudi Arabia</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0007"><label>7</label><institution>The Strategic Technologies Program of the National Plan for Sciences and Technology and Innovation in the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia</institution>, <addr-line>Riyadh</addr-line>, <country>Saudi Arabia</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Haitham Jahrami, <institution>Department of Psychiatry, College of Medicine and Medical Sciences, Arabian Gulf University</institution>, <addr-line>P.O. Box 26671</addr-line>, <addr-line>Manama</addr-line>, <country>Kingdom of Bahrain</country>, <phone>Tel +973 17286334</phone>, <fax>Fax +973 17270637</fax>, Email HJahrami@health.gov.bh</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>21</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2023</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>15</volume>
      <fpage>13</fpage>
      <lpage>15</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2023 Jahrami et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Jahrami et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="0"/>
        <ref-count count="15"/>
        <page-count count="3"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">While the use of wearable commercial fitness trackers or mobile phone technologies to learn about an individual’s sleep quality grows more and more popular, some sleep experts worry that a preoccupation with such data may lead to poor sleep quality and the possible development of insomnia.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The obsessive pursuit of optimal sleep metrics based on fitness tracker or mobile phone app data is termed “orthosomnia”,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> coined by combining “ortho” referring to straight, right or proper, and “somnia” referring to sleep.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> While insomnia and orthosomnia are both related to sleep, they are not at all synonymous. Insomnia is a diagnosable sleep disorder, whereas orthosomnia is a societal phenomenon, similar to “social jet lag”, another societal phenomenon that is gaining considerable notoriety. The current understanding of orthosomnia and its components is quite limited, although several behaviors are typically associated with it. These behaviors include preoccupation with sleep tracker data, frequently checking the sleep tracker, and anxiety about disassociation from the technology. In short, orthosomnia can be viewed as the obsessive pursuit of ideal sleep, free from disturbances, with regular sleep cycles and a focus on the body’s healing process.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis></p>
    <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">Nomophobia is defined as the fear of no access to mobile a phone is an emerging psychological condition (and a societal phenomenon).</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Our research group has documented a strong association between nomophobia and insomnia.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4–7</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> The link between nomophobia and insomnia may provide some insight into orthosomnia. The first and most important behavior associated with orthosomnia is that individuals suffering from it often and incorrectly assume that their sleep trackers are “perfect”, so they spend an unusual amount of time in bed striving to enhance that data. It is important to recognize that consumer sleep technology (CST) trackers are only data recorders and not standalone technology. A mobile phone is necessary to read and report the sleep data from the tracker; therefore, it is valid to assume that the orthosomnia obsession is likely to include mobile phones and with their use experience nomophobia.</citation_analysis></p>
    <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Individuals with orthosomnia may manifest insomnia-like symptoms while obsessing about “perfect sleep” because they are concerned with improving the CST’s sleep statistics. As a result, those with orthosomnia are likely to exhibit the following symptoms: difficulty falling asleep at night, waking up throughout the night, waking up too early, not feeling well-rested after a night’s sleep, tiredness or drowsiness during the day, anger, despair, or anxiety, difficulties paying attention, focusing on activities, or remembering, as well as an increase in mistakes or accidents, that is the typical symptom profile of insomnia.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither">,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8–10</xref></citation_analysis></p>
    <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Although some studies demonstrated no observed adverse effects of CST on sleep,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> those studies did not assess the potential negative effects of using sleep trackers, such as orthosomnia, resulting in measurement bias and selective reporting of sleep results only reporting benefits. This stresses the importance of developing a validated measurement for potential negative effects and consequences on sleep while using CST devices.</citation_analysis></p>
    <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">In their case series report, Baron et al discussed three orthosomnia cases;</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> The authors noted that these cases present unique challenges in Cognitive Behavioral Therapy for Insomnia (CBT-I) and exacerbate sleep-related anxiety or perfectionism in some patients.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="negative"> There was a perception of insufficient sleep by each patient as well as periods of restlessness or light sleeping.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Despite several validation studies having shown that CST tracking devices fail to discriminate sleep stages accurately and have poor accuracy in detecting wakefulness,</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Baron et al found their patients’ perceptions difficult to alter.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Another study had two groups; group 1 included 30 individuals whose sleep was monitored via a sleep-tracking device for a week, and group 2 were 45 participants who had been using a sleep-tracking device for a month to two years.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="neither"> Assessment of participants of both groups underscored trends of anxiety related to aiming for perfect sleep with a resultant extension of bedtime to increase sleep scores and attempts to remove any in-bed activity that might decrease sleep scores.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></citation_analysis></p>
    <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">An important consideration here is that monitoring any biological body signal may create in some individuals a “mental health concern” of targeting perfection; this is supported by data from studies on patients with diabetes mellitus who use continuous glucose monitors. Constant glucose data availability may result in greater concern about glucose levels, worry, psychological distress, and poorer communication regarding blood glucose levels.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12–14</xref></citation_analysis></p>
    <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">Therefore, could the widespread practice of self-monitoring of sleep using CST leads to a sleep paradox, in which preoccupation with perfect sleep induces stress, anxiety and arousal, compromising rather than improving sleep?</citation_analysis></p>
    <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">As sleep specialists, we are concerned orthosomnia may harm an individuals sleep quality in the long term. This may occur for several reasons. First, individuals may overestimate the accuracy and reliability of their sleep tracker or mobile phone app data, which can lead them to misunderstand how well they sleep. Second, efforts to maximize CST measured sleep may result in anxiety and arousal based worsening of sleep. Third, reliance on CST may delay their seeking appropriate professional services before the problems become deep-rooted. Individuals may disregard the need for sleep studies if they become accustomed to relying solely on their sleep tracker instead of formal sleep studies (polysomnography or actigraphy), which are widely regarded as the most accurate source of detailed sleep data. These poorly conceived and poorly guided attempts to improve or maximize sleep are likely to make it worse. Even worse is the possibility of recommending similar tactics to friends and family members of persons who suffer from orthosomnia.</citation_analysis></p>
    <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">The development of a validated scale to measure unhealthy sleep obsessions is a work in progress.</citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"><xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></citation_analysis><citation_analysis attribute="positive"> Developing a scientifically validated scale is particularly important in studying this new emerging condition. Such a scale could also provide useful therapeutic information to sleep medicine practitioners who might find themselves attempting to treat such individuals.</citation_analysis></p>
    <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">We suspect that many of our patients were experiencing an orthosomnia-like condition in the sense that they did not always fit the traditional definition of insomnia or hypersomnia but were nonetheless experiencing disturbed sleep because of worries about the information provided by their sleep-tracking devices and their efforts to improve their sleep accordingly.</citation_analysis></p>
    <p><citation_analysis attribute="positive">To conclude, taking care of one’s sleep health is never a negative, but doing so with inadequate knowledge may be potentially harmful. It has been estimated that 90% of adults own a smart phone of some type, and about 20% own a fitness tracker. CST is rapidly evolving and will likely increase in use. Although CST technologies have the potential to offer crucial information about irregular circadian rhythms and long-term sleep habits, relying solely on algorithms from modern technology with inexperienced interpretation might lead to poor management of sleep issues that results in disturbed sleep or exacerbates undiagnosed conditions. Therefore, considerable research about CST utility and disutility needs to be done. Sleep tracking using CST can be viewed in a manner similar to how positive airway pressure device downloads are already utilized in clinical sleep medicine, with a significant positive impact on adherence to therapy. Therefore, long-term CST validation studies are essential, taking into consideration the evaluation of all potential adverse effects of this technology on sleep in healthy subjects and patients with insomnia and other sleep disorders, using validated assessment measures. Additionally, during CBT-I, the therapist should review the benefits and downsides of tracking sleep when interviewing patients interested in utilizing a sleep tracker to monitor their sleep. Moreover, assessing if CST-generated reports affects treatment adherence or generates debilitating anxiety should be reviewed with each patient as an essential part of their treatment.</citation_analysis></p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0002">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p><citation_analysis attribute="neither">The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</citation_analysis></p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baron</surname>
<given-names>KG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abbott</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jao</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Manalo</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mullen</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Orthosomnia: are some patients taking the quantified self too far?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>351</fpage>–<lpage>354</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.6472</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27855740</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Baron</surname>
<given-names>KG</given-names></string-name>. <part-title>CBT-I for patients with orthosomnia</part-title>. In: <source><italic toggle="yes">Adapting Cognitive Behavioral Therapy for Insomnia</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>; <year>2022</year>:<fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Aupetit</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dubroca</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Escaich</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cabon</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <part-title>A qualitative study of sleep trackers usage: evidence of orthosomnia</part-title>. In: <string-name><surname>Charles</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Golightly</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, editors. <source><italic toggle="yes">Contemporary Ergonomics and Human Factors</italic></source>. <publisher-name>CIEHF</publisher-name>; <year>2019</year>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jahrami</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abdelaziz</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Binsanad</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The association between symptoms of nomophobia, insomnia and food addiction among young adults: findings of an exploratory cross-sectional survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph18020711</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jahrami</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fekih-Romdhane</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saif</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A social media outage was associated with a surge in nomophobia, and the magnitude of change in nomophobia during the outage was associated with baseline insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clocks Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>508</fpage>–<lpage>519</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/clockssleep4040040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36278533</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jahrami</surname>
<given-names>HA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fekih-Romdhane</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saif</surname>
<given-names>ZQ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep dissatisfaction is a potential marker for nomophobia in adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>98</volume>:<fpage>152</fpage>–<lpage>157</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2022.07.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35868112</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jahrami</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rashed</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>AlRasheed</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Nomophobia is associated with insomnia but not with age, sex, BMI, or mobile phone screen size in young adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Sci Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1931</fpage>–<lpage>1941</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/nss.S335462</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34737661</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Gaunt</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nacsa</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Penz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <part-title>Baby lucent: pitfalls of applying quantified self to baby products</part-title>. In: <source><italic toggle="yes">CHI’14 Extended Abstracts on Human Factors in Computing Systems</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>; <year>2014</year>:<fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>268</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Kane</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Newhouse</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sethu-Jones</surname>
<given-names>GR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Barbaro</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Quantified baby: parenting and the use of a baby wearable in the wild</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc ACM Hum-Comput Interact</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Glazer Baron</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Culnan</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duffecy</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>How are consumer sleep technology data being used to deliver behavioral sleep medicine interventions? A systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>187</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15402002.2021.1898397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33757392</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Arroyo</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zawadzki</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The implementation of behavior change techniques in mHealth apps for sleep: systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JMIR Mhealth Uhealth</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e33527</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/33527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35377327</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Albanese-O’Neill</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macieira</surname>
<given-names>TGR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Human factors associated with continuous glucose monitor use in patients with diabetes: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes Technol Ther</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>589</fpage>–<lpage>601</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/dia.2019.0136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31335196</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Murata</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuroda</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matsuhisa</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Predictive factors of the adherence to real-time continuous glucose monitoring sensors: a prospective observational study (PARCS STUDY)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Diabetes Sci Technol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1084</fpage>–<lpage>1092</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1932296820939204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32762345</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tanenbaum</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Messer</surname>
<given-names>LH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Help when you need it: perspectives of adults with T1D on the support and training they would have wanted when starting CGM</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes Res Clin Pract</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>180</volume>:<fpage>109048</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.diabres.2021.109048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34534592</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Van den Bulck</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Chronorexia and Orthosomnia: towards the development of scales to measure unhealthy obsessions with sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>100</volume>:<fpage>S29</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2022.05.091</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
