<?xml-model href="deep_markup.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<full_article>
<!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
<title> 
 Which Sleep Health Characteristics Predict All-Cause Mortality in Older Men?
 An Application of Flexible Multivariable Approaches
</title>
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 
 
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
<authors>
 Meredith L. Wallace, PhD1
 , Katie Stone, PhD2,3
 , Stephen F. Smagula, PhD1
 , Martica H. Hall, PhD1
 , Burcin Simsek, PhD1
 , Deborah M. Kado, MD, MS4
 , Susan
 Redline, MD, MPH5
 , Tien N. Vo, MS6
 ,
 Daniel J. Buysse, MD1
 , for the Osteoporotic Fractures in Men (MrOS) Study Research Group
</authors>
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 

 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
<schools>
 1
 Department of Psychiatry, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA; 2
 California Pacific Medical Center, Research Institute, San Francisco, CA; 3
 Department of Epidemiology and
 Biostatistics, University of California, San Francisco, CA; 4
 Department of Family Medicine &amp; Public Health, University of California, La Jolla, San Diego, CA; 5
 Departments of
 Medicine, Brigham and Women’s Hospital and Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA; 6
 Division of Epidemiology and Community Health,
 University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN
</schools>
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 
 
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
<summary>
  
  <subtitle>
   Study Objectives:
  </subtitle>
   Sleep is multidimensional, with domains including duration, timing, continuity, regularity, rhythmicity, quality, and sleepiness/alertness.
  Individual sleep characteristics representing these domains are known to predict health outcomes. However, most studies consider sleep characteristics in
  isolation, resulting in an incomplete understanding of which sleep characteristics are the strongest predictors of health outcomes. We applied three multivariable
  approaches to robustly determine which sleep characteristics increase mortality risk in the osteoporotic fractures in men sleep study.
  
  <subtitle>
  Methods: 
  </subtitle>
  In total, 2,887 men (mean 76.3 years) completed relevant assessments and were followed for up to 11 years. One actigraphy or self-reported sleep
  characteristic was selected to represent each of seven sleep domains. Multivariable Cox models, survival trees, and random survival forests were applied to
  determine which sleep characteristics increase mortality risk.
  
  <subtitle> 
  Results: 
  </subtitle>
  Rhythmicity (actigraphy pseudo-F statistic) and continuity (actigraphy minutes awake after sleep onset) were the most robust sleep predictors across
  models. In a multivariable Cox model, lower rhythmicity (hazard ratio, HR [95%CI] =1.12 [1.04, 1.22]) and lower continuity (1.16 [1.08, 1.24]) were the strongest
  sleep predictors. In the random survival forest, rhythmicity and continuity were the most important individual sleep characteristics (ranked as the sixth and eighth
  most important among 43 possible sleep and non-sleep predictors); moreover, the predictive importance of all sleep information considered simultaneously
  followed only age, cognition, and cardiovascular disease.
  
  <subtitle>
   Conclusions:
  </subtitle>
   Research within a multidimensional sleep health framework can jumpstart future research on causal pathways linking sleep and health, new
  interventions that target specific sleep health profiles, and improved sleep screening for adverse health outcomes.
  
</summary>
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 

 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->

 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <kw>
     Keywords: sleep health, circadian rhythm, multivariable analyses, mortality, men, late-life, survival tree, random survival forest.
 </kw>
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 
 
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <subsection>
  
   <subtitle>
    INTRODUCTION
   </subtitle>
  
    Measures of sleep duration,1–11 quality,5,12,13 timing,14,15 continuity,16–19 circadian rhythmicity,20,21 regularity,22–24 and daytime sleepiness25–27 have been shown to predict important health outcomes.
    Many of these findings are based on models that consider only one
    of these sleep characteristics at a time,7–9,12–14,16–18,21,22 or at most
    two or three of them simultaneously.3,4,20,23–27 The clinical reality,
    however, is that sleep is a multidimensional construct that can be
    characterized across several domains.28,29 Ignoring the multidimensional nature of sleep makes it difficult to organize findings
    across the literature to determine which aspects of sleep are most
    important for predicting health outcomes. Moreover, a combination of characteristics is more likely to be associated with health
    and behavioral outcomes than any individual characteristic. Thus,
    studies that consider multidimensional sleep health are warranted.
    We recently developed a working definition of “sleep health”
    as a “multidimensional pattern of sleep-wakefulness…that
    promotes physical well-being.”29 Although the exact number
    of relevant sleep health dimensions is open to debate, we here
    emphasize seven potential domains: (1) Duration: the total
    amount of sleep obtained per 24 hours; (2) Continuity: the ease of
    falling asleep and returning to sleep; (3) Timing: the placement
    of sleep within the 24-hour day; (4) Sleepiness/Alertness: the
    ability to maintain attentive wakefulness; (5) Quality: the subjective assessment of “good” or “poor” sleep; (6) Regularity: the
    consistency of sleep timing; and (7) Rhythmicity: the strength
    of the overall sleep–wake pattern in a 24-hour cycle. Although
    other potential domains could be considered (e.g., sleep depth or
    adaptability), these seven were selected based on prior literature
    indicating their independence from one another as well as their
    potential roles in important health outcomes.29
    Because sleep health is relevant for everyone, not just those
    with sleep disorders, research within a multidimensional sleep
    health framework has the potential to inform large-scale public health initiatives by improving screening and clinical recommendations.29–31 It could also inform which specific sleep
    characteristics should be considered in mechanistic studies and
    ultimately lead to the development of targeted sleep treatments
    that may reduce mortality and morbidity. But despite its potential
    impact, few previous studies have utilized a multidimensional
    One possible reason is that complex,
    nonlinear relationships are likely to exist among sleep characteristics, nonsleep risk factors, and health outcomes. Traditional
    multivariable regression has numerous advantages, including
    the ability to quantify the added risk of having a more extreme
    level of one sleep characteristic while adjusting for other sleep
    and nonsleep risk factors. However, a weakness of multivariable
    regression is that it is not conducive to modeling complex, nonlinear associations such as those that may be observed within a
    multidimensional sleep health framework.
    Two flexible, nonlinear multivariable modeling approaches
    that could facilitate research within a multidimensional sleep
    health framework are conditional inference tree-structured analyses32 and random forests.33,34 Conditional inference tree-structured analysis is a data-driven approach that recursively divides
    the sample into covariate-defined subsamples with similar outcomes. Given a set of potential predictors, the algorithm first
    identifies the single predictor with the strongest association
    with the outcome and then identifies the binary split-point on
    the selected predictor that best divides the sample into two subsamples with different outcomes. This splitting procedure continues iteratively on each successive subsample until there are
    no remaining significant predictors or the subsample size is too
    small. A random forest is comprised of hundreds of trees fit to
    bootstrap samples. The trees in the “forest” are averaged to get
    predictions for new individuals. A variable importance (VIMP)
    index34 can be extracted from the random forest and used to
    rank each variable (or a set of variables) based on its relative
    predictive importance. Multivariable regression, tree-structured analysis, and random forests are three complementary
    approaches that can provide a comprehensive assessment of the
    associations between multivariable sleep and health outcomes.
    The primary goal of this manuscript is to use data from the
    Outcome of Sleep Disorders in Older Men (MrOS) Sleep study,35
    a large multisite cohort study of older men, to robustly determine
    which sleep characteristics predict time to all-cause mortality in
    older men. Given the potentially complex associations among sleep
    risk factors, nonsleep risk factors, and health outcomes, we accomplish this goal by comparing findings from three complimentary
    multivariable modeling approaches for survival endpoints: Cox regression, tree-structured survival analysis, and a random survival
    forest. Moreover, we expect that the demonstration of these three
    multivariable approaches will promote the study of multidimensional sleep health with other samples and outcomes.
    
 </subsection>
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 
 
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <subsection>
  
  <subtitle>
   Statement of Significance
  </subtitle>
  
  Most studies use individual sleep characteristics to predict health outcomes. However, sleep can be characterized along multiple dimensions such
  as duration, continuity, and rhythmicity. We applied three multivariable modeling approaches in a large sample of older men to examine which sleep
  characteristics are most important for predicting mortality. Across approaches, lower sleep-wake rhythmicity and lower sleep continuity were the sleep
  characteristics that conferred the strongest risk for mortality among older men. These findings can help us to clarify how sleep affects health, how sleep
  problems should be evaluated, and how sleep treatments might improve health. Ultimately, studying multidimensional sleep could improve public health by
  promoting healthy sleep for the entire population, rather than only those with sleep disorders.
 </subsection>
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 
 
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
<subsection>
 
 <subtitle>
  METHODS
 </subtitle>
 
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
   <subsubsection>
       <subsubtitle>
        Participants
       </subsubtitle>
    
       The full MrOS cohort consists of 5,994 community dwelling,
       ambulatory men aged 65 years and older, recruited at six clinical centers across the United States between March 2000 and
       April 2002. Inclusion criteria were as follows: (1) ability to
       walk unassisted, (2) absence of bilateral hip replacements, (3)
       ability to provide self-reported data, (4) absence of a medical
       condition resulting in imminent death, and (5) ability to understand and provide informed consent. All participants provided
       written informed consent. The initial wave of the MrOS Sleep
       study was completed between December 2003 and March 2005.
       It recruited 3,125 participants from the full MrOS cohort for
       a comprehensive sleep assessment. Men were screened and
       Figure 1—Derivation of analytic sample.
       Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/41/1/zsx189/4642232 by Falk Library user on 22 October 2024
       SLEEP, Vol. 41, No. 1, 2018 3 An Application of Flexible Multivariable Approaches—Wallace et al.
       generally excluded for nightly use of mechanical devices during sleep, mouthpiece for snoring or sleep apnea, or oxygen
       therapy. Full details of the sample are published elsewhere.35–37
       Our analytic sample consists of 2,887 men who took part in
       the sleep study and for whom all relevant sleep and covariate
       data were observed (Figure 1). The mean (SD) age of the analytic sample at the baseline sleep visit was 76.3 (5.5) years, ranging from 67 to 96. The sample primarily consists of Caucasian
       men (89.9%, N = 2,595) and most have at least some college
       education (78.9%, N = 2,277)
   </subsubsection>
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
   <subsubsection>  
       <subsubtitle>
        MrOS Sleep Study
       </subsubtitle>
    
       In the MrOS Sleep study, sleep characteristics were captured
       through retrospective self-report, actigraphy, daily sleep diary,
       and one night of in-home polysomnography. Our primary
       focus herein is on sleep as captured through retrospective selfreport and actigraphy. Briefly, the Sleepwatch-O (Ambulatory
       Monitoring, Inc., Ardsley, NY) was used to capture actigraphy
       data. Actigraphs are wristwatch-like devices that provide an
       estimate of the sleep-wake cycle via rest-activity patterns. They
       summarize the frequency of motions into epochs of specified
       time duration and store the summary in memory. These data
       are then downloaded and scored to generate various sleep
       characteristics. The actigraphy data used herein were analyzed
       using Action W-2 software with Proportional Integration Mode
       and the University of California, San Diego scoring algorithm.38
       Circadian rhythm variables (e.g., Pseudo-F statistic [PsF])
       were scored using an extended cosine model.39 Full details of
       these actigraphy methods have been published previously.37,40
       Men wore the actigraphs for a minimum of four consecutive
       24-hour periods. In our analytic sample, each participant had a
       mean (SD) of 5.3 (0.8) nights of sleep data. Additional details
       regarding the inter- and intra-subject variability of the relevant
       actigraphy measures are provided in Supplementary Material.
   </subsubsection>
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
   <subsubsection>  
       <subsubtitle>
        Outcome
       </subsubtitle>
       
       
        Although numerous health outcomes could be studied, we
        selected time to all-cause mortality (confirmed by centralized
        review of death certificates) as an unequivocal “hard” outcome
        of importance to patients and society. In our analytic sample,
        36.7% (N = 1,060) of participants died during follow-up, 3.9%
        (N = 112) terminated the study, and 59.4% (N = 1,715) were still
        alive and being followed. As fewer than 50% of individuals died
        during follow-up, the median (50th percentile) years to all-cause
        mortality was not observed. The 25th percentile (95% CI) years
        to all-cause mortality was 8.0 (7.7, 8.3), with a maximum of
        11.2 years of follow-up.
   </subsubsection>
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
   <subsubsection>
       <subsubtitle>
        Sleep Characteristics and Domains
       </subsubtitle>
       
        Our primary aim was to robustly determine which sleep health
        characteristics predict time to all-cause mortality by comparing
        findings across three complementary multivariable approaches:
        Cox regression, tree-structured survival analysis, and random
        survival forest. In Cox regression, inclusion of variables that
        are too highly correlated (i.e., multicollinearity) can lead to
        unstable estimates. Therefore, we used clinical and scientific
        justification to select one sleep characteristic to represent each
        of the seven proposed domains (duration, continuity, timing, sleepiness/alertness, quality, regularity, and rhythmicity)
        and then examined correlations to ensure that the selected
        characteristics were not too highly correlated. Although random survival forests and tree-structured survival analysis can
        accommodate highly correlated variables, our strategy was to
        use the same clinically meaningful subset of variables across all
        three approaches. This strategy facilitates a direct comparison
        of findings across approaches and enhances our ability to obtain
        meaningful results. Finally, when making our selections, we
        prioritized measures that were objective, stable, representative
        of an individual’s usual sleep pattern, and clinically relevant.
        To this end, we gave preference to estimates from actigraphy
        (based on multiple nights of sleep in an individual’s usual environment) over polysomnography (based on a single night of
        sleep in a lab) or self-report measures when possible.
        We selected actigraphy-assessed average total sleep time
        (TST; minutes of actual asleep at night) to represent duration,
        actigraphy-assessed wake after sleep onset (WASO; the number of minutes an individual is awake after falling asleep) to
        represent continuity, and actigraphy-assessed mean sleep midpoint (midpoint of bed and wake time) to represent timing. We
        selected the Epworth Sleepiness Scale41 (ESS) to represent
        sleepiness/alertness. The ESS is a self-report scale including
        eight questions, with total scores ranging from 0 (no sleepiness) to 24 (severe sleepiness). We selected the Pittsburgh Sleep
        Quality Index (PSQI) sleep quality item to represent the quality
        domain.42 The PSQI sleep quality item asks “During the past
        month, how would you rate your sleep quality overall?” with
        possible responses: “Very Good” (0), “Fairly Good” (1), “Fairly
        Bad” (2), and “Very Bad” (3). This single item was selected
        over the total PSQI score because the total PSQI score also
        incorporates information about other domains of sleep (e.g.,
        sleep timing and continuity).
        We selected the standard deviation of wake time (SD wake)
        to represent regularity. This measure was selected over other
        possible measures of regularity, such as the standard deviation
        of sleep midpoint, because it is less resistant to change and specifically relates to the time that people are exposed to morning light, which is a strong circadian zeitgeber. The PsF was
        selected to represent circadian rhythmicity. PsF captures the
        extent to which an individual’s sleep-wake activity conforms
        to an extended cosine model,39 with higher values indicating
        greater conformity to the cosine shape. An individual could
        have a strong rhythm that takes a different shape; however, a
        uniphasic circadian rhythm such as that captured by the PsF
        is the dominant rhythm in most adults. Furthermore, PsF has
        previously been shown to be related to important health outcomes.21,43,44 Although SD wake and PsF are similar in some
        regards, they do address conceptually different entities. That
        is, SD wake reflects the regularity surrounding wake timing
        specifically, whereas PsF captures the strength of the overall
        rhythmicity of the rest–activity (or sleep–wake) cycle. The relatively small correlation among these two measures (Spearman
        r = −0.21) further solidified our consideration of regularity and
        rhythmicity as separate domains.
        Motivated by prior sleep health research,45 we were also interested in the predictive ability of a clinically meaningful composite
        measure defined as the number of “extreme” sleep characteristics. To compute this composite measure, we used existing clinical and scientific guidelines to identify values of “extreme” sleep
        Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/41/1/zsx189/4642232 by Falk Library user on 22 October 2024
        SLEEP, Vol. 41, No. 1, 2018 4 An Application of Flexible Multivariable Approaches—Wallace et al.
        characteristics wherever possible. In the absence of such guidelines, we empirically identified the most extreme third of the distribution. We defined early sleep midpoint as ≤2:00 am, medium
        sleep midpoint as 2:01 am–4:00 am, and late sleep midpoint as
        &gt;4:00 am. Extreme sleep midpoint was defined as either early or
        late sleep midpoint.46 Based on the published recommendations,41
        extreme ESS was defined as a total score of &gt;10. Extreme sleep
        quality was indicated as “Very Bad” or “Fairly Bad” responses on
        the PSQI sleep quality item. Extreme WASO, PsF, and SD wake
        were defined as the most extreme third of the distribution (high
        WASO, low PsF, and high SD wake). Because both short and long
        durations may be related to poor health outcomes,47 extreme TST
        was defined as either the lowest sixth or highest sixth of the distribution, resulting in one-third of the distribution having extreme
        TST. Further details of selected sleep characteristics and specific
        cut points are provided in Table 1.
        Hereafter, we refer to the selected characteristics by their
        respective domain names to enhance readability. We provide
        sleep characteristic names in parentheses when useful for clarification or interpretation of model results.
   </subsubsection>
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
   <subsubsection>  
        <subsubtitle>
         Nonsleep Risk Factors
        </subsubtitle>
        
         Numerous nonsleep risk factors for mortality were captured in
         the MrOS study and considered in our analyses. Demographic
         characteristics were age, clinic site, and years of education.
         Health characteristics were self-reported health status (good or
         poor), physical activity (Physical Activity Scale for the Elderly;
         PASE48), depressed mood (Geriatric Depression Scale49), smoking
         status (current, past, or never), caffeine intake (mg per day), alcohol use (&gt;1 drink per week), cognitive function (Teng Modified
         Mini-Mental State (3MS) Exam50), and body mass index (BMI;
         kg/m2
         ). Self-reported histories of the following medical conditions were considered: arthritis (osteoarthritis or rheumatoid
         arthritis), cardiovascular disease (CVD), stroke, diabetes mellitus, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), and hypertension (HTN). Finally, use of the following medications in the
         past 30 days was considered: antidepressants, benzodiazepines,
         and other sedatives or hypnotics, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory
         drugs (NSAIDs), and corticosteroids. All medications recorded
         by the clinics were entered into an electronic medications inventory (San Francisco Coordinating Center, San Francisco, CA).
         Each medication was matched to its ingredient(s) based on the
         Iowa Drug Information Service (IDIS) Drug Vocabulary (College
         of Pharmacy, University of Iowa, Iowa City, IA) and coded based
         on the published recommendations.51 Further descriptions of
         these nonsleep predictors and their associations with all-cause
         mortality in MrOS are provided in Supplementary Material.
   </subsubsection>
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
   <subsubsection>
   
     <subsubtitle>
      Data Analysis
     </subsubtitle>

     <algo>
        <algotitle>
         Cox Proportional Hazards Regression
        </algotitle>
        We fit Cox models with time to all-cause mortality as the
        outcome, utilizing univariable, multivariable, and composite
        approaches to modeling sleep characteristics. In univariable
        approaches (fit primarily for comparison purposes), we modeled
        Table 1—Descriptive Statistics for Continuous and Categorical Sleep Characteristics.
        Sleep domain Representative sleep characteristic Median (1st quartile, 3rd
        quartile) for continuous
        sleep characteristic
        Categorical sleep
        characteristic definition
        % (N) for Categorical
        Sleep Characteristic
        Duration Actigraphy average mean total sleep time
        (TST) in minutes
        391.00 (345.20, 432.20) ≤ 319.6 (short)
        319.6–450.3 (medium)
        &gt; 450.3a
        (long)
        16.70 (482)
        66.68 (1925)
        16.63 (480)
        Continuity Actigraphy average mean wake after sleep
        onset (WASO) in minutes
        68.67 (45.60, 101.40) &lt; 88
        ≥ 88a
        66.47 (1919)
        33.52 (968)
        Timing Actigraphy average mean sleep midpoint 03:01 am (02:27 am, 03:38 am) ≤ 02:00a
        (early)
        02:01–04:00 (middle)
        &gt;04:00a
        (late)
        12.23 (353)
        71.87 (2075)
        15.90 (459)
        Sleepiness/
        alertness
        Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS) 6 (3, 8) ≤10
        &gt;10a
        87.18 (2517)
        12.82 (370)
        Quality Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PQSI)
        sleep quality itemb
        1 (0, 1) ≤ 1
        &gt; 1a
        84.21 (2431)
        15.79 (456)
        Rhythmicity Actigraphy pseudo-F statistics (PsF) 967.44 (700.45, 1319.43) ≤ 785.60a
        &gt; 785.60
        66.68 (1925)
        33.32 (962)
        Regularity Standard deviation of actigraphy wake time
        in hours (SD wake)
        0.57 (0.37, 0.87) &lt; 0.75
        ≥0.75a
        65.74 (1898)
        34.26 (989)
        Composite Number of extreme sleep characteristics 2 (1, 3) 0
        1
        2
        3
        ≥4
        15.48 (447)
        28.65 (827)
        25.46 (735)
        16.56 (478)
        13.86 (400)
        a
        “Extreme” sleep category.
        b
        PSQI Sleep quality Index sleep quality item coding: 0 = “Very Good,” 1 = “Somewhat Good,” 2 = “Somewhat Bad,” 3 = “Very Bad.”
        Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/41/1/zsx189/4642232 by Falk Library user on 22 October 2024
        SLEEP, Vol. 41, No. 1, 2018 5 An Application of Flexible Multivariable Approaches—Wallace et al.
        each sleep characteristic in a separate model. In multivariable
        approaches, we included all seven sleep characteristics simultaneously in the same model. In composite approaches, we
        included the number of extreme sleep characteristics, considered continuously in one model and categorically (0, 1, 2, 3, ≥4
        extreme characteristics) in another. For univariable, multivariable, and composite approaches, we first fit base models adjusted
        for only age and clinic site, and then fit full models that were
        adjusted for all nonsleep risk factors (demographics, clinical
        measures, lifestyle factors, medications, and medical history).
        Given previous reports of U-shaped or nonlinear associations
        for timing and duration, quadratic forms of these variables were
        considered; however, quadratic effects that were nonsignificant
        in a model were removed. To enhance interpretability of HRs,
        continuous sleep and nonsleep measures were standardized.52
     </algo>
<!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
    
<!-- ============================================================================================================== -->   
     <algo>
   
      <algotitle>
       Tree-Structured Survival Models
      </algotitle>
      A conditional inference tree model empirically identifies the
      variable and cut-point that best divide the sample into two subsamples with different mortality risks. This splitting process
      continues iteratively on each successive subsample, resulting in
      a final set of covariate-defined subsamples with different risks
      for mortality. We first fit a base tree model that considered only
      the seven continuous sleep characteristics and the number of
      extreme sleep characteristics. We then fit a second tree model
      that considered the full set of sleep and nonsleep risk factors. To
      maximize stability and interpretability, we required a minimum
      of N = 289 (10% of the sample) in each subsample, allowed a
      maximum of three successive splits, and required a significance
      of p &lt; .05 after a Bonferroni correction for multiple comparisons.
     </algo>
<!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
    
<!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
    <algo>
     
     <algotitle>
      Random Survival Forest
     </algotitle>
     A random survival forest is comprised of a series of survival trees
     models fit to bootstrap samples. VIMP statistics can be extracted
     and used to rank the variables (or sets of variables) from most to
     least predictive in context of one another. We fit a random survival forest including the seven continuous sleep characteristics,
     the number of extreme sleep characteristics, and all nonsleep
     risk factors. After fitting this model, we calculated the VIMP for
     each individual sleep and nonsleep predictor, the joint VIMP for
     the seven sleep characteristics considered simultaneously (“7
     Sleep”), and the joint VIMP for the seven sleep characteristics
     plus the number of extreme sleep characteristics considered
     simultaneously (“7 Sleep + # Extreme”). To provide a clinically
     meaningful frame of reference for the VIMP, we calculated the
     percentage of each predictor’s VIMP relative to that of the strongest and most clinically meaningful predictor, age [i.e., (VIMP of
     predictor)/(VIMP of age) × 100]. Finally, we assessed the direction and magnitude of the effects of the most highly ranked
     predictors in the forest (those with VIMPs that were at least 5%
     of the VIMP of age) by using them to predict time to all-cause
     mortality in a multivariable Cox regression model.
    </algo>
<!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
   
<!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
    <algo>
     <algotitle>
      Sensitivity Analyses
     </algotitle>
     To assess the importance of the sleep characteristics above and
     beyond sleep apnea, a prevalent sleep disorder with established
     health risks,53,54 we refit the fully adjusted models controlling
     for the apnea–hypopnea index (AHI) determined by overnight
     in-home polysomnography conducted at the same exam cycle
     as actigraphy.40 This measure was not included in the primary
     analyses because it was missing in 173 (6%) men in our sample.
     To rule out confounding by possible ongoing and unmeasured
     disease processes, we also refit the fully adjusted models after
     excluding 29 (1%) individuals who died during the year immediately following the sleep assessment.
    </algo>
<!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
   </subsubsection>
</subsection>
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 

 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
<subsection>
  
  <subtitle>
   RESULTS
  </subtitle>

  Table 1 describes the distributions of the seven selected sleep
  characteristics and the frequencies of individuals with 0, 1, 2,
  3, and ≥4 extreme sleep characteristics. The sleep characteristics had a median Spearman correlation magnitude of 0.12 (1st
  quartile = 0.09, 3rd quartile = 0.18). The largest correlations
  were observed between continuity and duration (r = −0.45),
  rhythmicity and duration (r = 0.23), and rhythmicity and regularity (r = −0.21). All other correlation magnitudes among
  the sleep characteristics were &lt;0.20. The full set of sleep and
  nonsleep variables had a median Spearman correlation magnitude of only 0.04 (1st quartile &lt; 0.001, 3rd quartile = 0.08). See
  Supplementary Material for additional descriptions, including
  (1) the full correlation matrix among sleep characteristics, (2)
  a detailed characterization of the sample based on nonsleep
  demographic, health, and behavioral risk factors, including
  their associations with time to mortality, and (3) types and combinations of extreme sleep characteristics in the sample.
  
  <algo>
   <algotitle>
    Cox Proportional Hazards Regression
   </algotitle>
   Table 2 provides results from Cox models with sleep characteristics considered continuously. Across all models, lower sleep–
   wake rhythmicity (lower PsF) and lower continuity (higher
   WASO) were significantly associated with increased mortality
   risk and had the largest HRs. In the full multivariable model
   (i.e., adjusting for all other sleep and nonsleep risk factors), we
   observed HRs (95% CIs) of 1.12 (1.04, 1.22) per one SD decrease in rhythmicity and 1.16 (1.08, 1.24) per one SD decrease
   in continuity. Quadratic effects for timing were also significant
   across all models, indicating that earlier and later timing were
   associated with greater mortality risk.
   Linear or quadratic effects for duration were significant in the
   univariable models and the base multivariable model, but not in
   the full multivariable model. Lower regularity (higher SD wake)
   was significantly associated with increased mortality risk in the
   base univariable models but not in any full or multivariable
   model. Sleepiness/alertness was not associated with mortality
   in any of the models. Sleep quality results were unexpected.
   Quality was not significantly associated with mortality in the
   base models. However, in the multivariable models, having
   better sleep quality was significantly associated with increased
   mortality risk (1.08 [1.02, 1.16] in the full multivariable model).
   In general, similar inferences were made when sleep characteristics were considered categorically based on cutoffs in Table 1.
   In the full multivariable model, having extreme rhythmicity
   (1.27 [1.10, 1.46]), extreme continuity (1.33 [1.16, 1.53]), and
   (unexpectedly) nonextreme sleep quality (i.e., “Very Good” or
   “Somewhat Good”) (1.28 [1.08, 1.54]) were each significantly
   associated with increased risk for mortality. Full details of these
   categorical models are provided in Supplementary Material.
   Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/41/1/zsx189/4642232 by Falk Library user on 22 October 2024
   SLEEP, Vol. 41, No. 1, 2018 6 An Application of Flexible Multivariable Approaches—Wallace et al.
   Table 3 provides results from the Cox models for the number of
   extreme sleep characteristics. Treated continuously, having additional extreme sleep characteristics was significantly associated
   with increased mortality (1.10 [1.05, 1.15] in the full model).
   This measure was also significantly associated with time to mortality when treated categorically. Having 3 (1.40 [1.11, 1.77]) or
   ≥4 (1.57 [1.23, 2.00]) versus zero extreme sleep characteristics
   were each associated with increased mortality risk.
  </algo>
 
  <algo>
    <algotitle>
     Tree-Structured Model
    </algotitle>
    The base survival tree model considering age, site, the seven
    sleep characteristics, and the number of extreme sleep characteristics is shown in Figure 2. Only age, sleep continuity, and
    the number of extreme sleep characteristics were empirically
    selected to enter the model. For those aged ≤72, having &gt;1
    extreme sleep characteristic was associated with increased mortality risk (1.68 [1.21, 2.33]). For those aged &gt;72 and ≤79, lower
    continuity (i.e., WASO &gt; 98.6) was associated with increased
    mortality risk (1.74 [1.41, 2.14]). For those aged &gt;79, age
    again splits the tree such that those aged &gt;83 had an even further increased risk of mortality (1.79 [1.51, 2.14]). In the full
    survival tree model considering all sleep and nonsleep predictors, only age, physical activity, and cognition were empirically
    selected to enter the model (see Supplementary Material).
  </algo>
 
  <algo>
    <algotitle>
     Random Survival Forest
    </algotitle>
    Figure 3 shows the VIMP for each predictor as a percent of the
    VIMP for age (0.036) in the random survival forest. Cognition
    Table 2—Cox Proportional Hazards Regression Models for (Standardized) Continuous Sleep Domains Predicting Time to All-Cause Mortality.
    Univariable models: each sleep characteristic in a
    separate model
    Multivariable models: all sleep characteristics in
    the same model
    HR (95% CI) X2 statistic (p-value) HR (95% CI) X2 statistic (p-value)
    Base models: Sleep characteristic(s), age, and site
    Quality (PSQI quality itema
    ) 1.01 (0.95, 1.07) 0.11 (.738) 0.96 (0.90, 1.02) 1.91 (.167)
    Sleepiness/alertness (ESS) 1.04 (0.98, 1.11) 1.79 (.181) 1.01 (0.95, 1.08) 0.14 (.705)
    Timing (sleep midpoint) — 12.67 (.002) — 8.13 (.017)b
    Linear term 1.04 (0.97, 1.11) 1.18 (.277) 0.99 (0.93, 1.05) 0.14 (.707)
    Quadratic termc 1.02 (1.01, 1.04) 11.67 (&lt;.001) 1.03 (1.01, 1.04) 11.75 (&lt;.001)
    Duration (TST) — 11.50 (.003) — NA
    Linear term 0.95 (0.89, 1.01) 2.68 (.102) 1.10 (1.02, 1.18) 6.47 (.011)
    Quadratic termc 1.03 (1.00, 1.07) 4.46 (.035) NA NA
    Continuity (WASO) 1.23 (1.16, 1.30) 55.93 (&lt;.001) 1.25 (1.17, 1.34) 44.83 (&lt;.001)
    Rhythmicity(PsFd
    ) 0.80 (0.75, 0.86) 36.53 (&lt;.001) 0.83 (0.77, 0.90) 22.21 (&lt;.001)
    Regularity (SD wake) 1.12 (1.06, 1.19) 14.12 (&lt;.001) 1.04 (0.97, 1.11) 1.30 (.255)
    Full models: Sleep characteristic(s) and all nonsleep characteristicse
    Quality (PSQI quality itema
    ) 0.94 (0.88, 1.00) 3.88 (.049) 0.92 (0.86, 0.98) 7.35 (.007)
    Sleepiness/Alertness (ESS) 0.99 (0.93, 1.06) 0.08 (.775) 0.98 (0.91, 1.04) 0.60 (.440)
    Timing (sleep midpoint) — 7.28 (.026) — 6.81 (.033)b
    Linear term 0.99 (0.93, 1.06) 0.04 (.841) 0.97 (0.91, 1.03) 0.96 (.328)
    Quadratic Termc 1.02 (1.01, 1.04) 9.90 (.002) 1.02 (1.01, 1.04) 9.86 (.002)
    Duration (TST) 0.93 (0.87, 0.98) 6.37 (.012) 1.02 (0.94, 1.10) 0.177 (.674)
    Continuity (WASO) 1.15 (1.08, 1.22) 22.42 (&lt;.001) 1.16 (1.08, 1.24) 17.83 (&lt;.001)
    Rhythmicity(PsFd
    ) 0.88 (0.82, 0.95) 11.29 (&lt;.001) 0.89 (0.82, 0.96) 8.54 (.004)
    Regularity (SD wake) 1.05 (0.99, 1.12) 2.63 (.105) 1.01 (0.95, 1.08) 0.13 (.719)
    HR = hazard ratio; CI = confidence interval; PSQI = Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index; ESS = Epworth Sleepiness Scale; WASO = minutes awake after sleep
    onset; PsF = pseudo-F statistic; SD wake = within-subject standard deviation of wake time; ACT = actigraphy-assessed; TST = total sleep time. a
    Lower values indicate worse quality.
    b
    Likelihood ratio test for inclusion of both linear and quadratic terms.
    c
    HRs associated with the quadratic term &gt; 1 indicate a convex (i.e., “U”-shaped) associations, with larger values suggesting a steeper curve. d
    Lower values indicate more irregularity of overall sleep–wake rhythm.
    e
    Adjusted for age, site, race, education, self-reported health status, physical activity, depressed mood, smoking, caffeine intake, daily alcohol use, cognitive
    function, body mass index, self-reported histories of medical conditions (arthritis, cardiovascular disease, stroke, diabetes, chronic obstructive pulmonary
    disease, and hypertension), and uses of medications (antidepressants, benzodiazepines, and other sedatives/hyponotics, NSAIDS, corticosteroids).
    Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/41/1/zsx189/4642232 by Falk Library user on 22 October 2024
    SLEEP, Vol. 41, No. 1, 2018 7 An Application of Flexible Multivariable Approaches—Wallace et al.
    and CVD had VIMPs that were approximately 20% of the VIMP
    of age. The joint VIMP for all sleep information (“7 Sleep + #
    Extreme”) was 14.4% of the VIMP for age. VIMPs for physical
    activity (PASE), rhythmicity, and the seven sleep characteristics
    considered jointly (“7 Sleep”) were 11.5%, 9.2%, and 8.8% of
    the VIMP for age, respectively. Following these were depression at 8.0%, continuity at 7.7%, and the number of extreme
    sleep characteristics (“# Extreme”) at 5.5%. Timing, duration,
    quality, and sleepiness/alertness each had VIMPs &lt; 1%.
    Finally, the Cox model including age and the variables with a
    VIMP at least 5% of the VIMP of age (cognition CVD, physical
    activity, rhythmicity, depression, continuity, and the number of
    extreme sleep characteristics) is shown in Table 4. Older age
    (1.70 [1.60, 1.81]), CVD (1.49 [1.32, 1.69]), lower cognition
    (1.19 [1.14, 1.25]), and lower physical activity (1.14 [1.05,
    1.22]) conferred the strongest risk for mortality. Closely following was lower sleep continuity (1.13 [1.06, 1.20]), lower
    rhythmicity (1.09 [1.01, 1.18]), and higher depressive symptoms (1.08 [1.02, 1.15]). After adjusting for these risk factors,
    the number of extreme sleep characteristics was no longer significantly associated with mortality (1.03 [0.98, 1.09]).
  </algo>
 
  <algo>
    <algotitle>
     Sensitivity Analyses
    </algotitle>
    Models Adjusted for AHI (N = 2,714)
    We obtained very similar results across approaches when AHI
    was included among potential covariates. In the full multivariable Cox model, rhythmicity (1.11 [1.03, 1.20]) and continuity (1.15 [1.07, 1.23]) remained the strongest predictors of time
    to all-cause mortality, whereas no significant association was
    observed for AHI (1.00 [0.93, 1.07]). In a fully adjusted Cox
    model, the number of extreme sleep characteristics treated continuously was associated with mortality (1.09 [1.04, 1.15]),
    whereas AHI was not (1.01 [0.94, 1.08]). Similarly, the number of extreme sleep characteristics treated categorially was
    associated with mortality (X2
    = 17.06, p = .0002; HR [95%CI]
    for 3 vs. 0 = 1.37 [1.08, 1.74]; HR [95%CI] for ≥4 versus
    0 = 1.56 [1.21, 2.00]), whereas AHI was not (1.00 [0.94, 1.07]).
    In the survival tree model considering AHI, the identical variables (age, cognition, and physical activity) and cut-points were
    empirically selected as in the tree model that did not consider
    AHI (see Supplementary Material). Finally, in the random survival forest including AHI, the top 10 predictors were identical
    to those in the random survival forest that did not include AHI,
    with only slight changes in order. AHI was ranked as the 21st
    most important predictor in the random survival forest, with
    a VIMP that was 1.03% of that of age. Additional details are
    provided in Supplementary Material.
    Models Addressing Reverse Causality (N = 2,858)
    We obtained very similar results excluding those who died in
    the year following the Sleep Visit (addressing “reverse causality”). In the full multivariable Cox model, rhythmicity (1.11
    [1.03, 1.20]) and continuity (1.16 [1.08, 1.24]) remained the
    strongest predictors of time to all-cause mortality. In a full Cox
    model, the number of extreme sleep characteristics treated continuously was associated with mortality (1.09 [1.04, 1.14]).
    Similarly, the number of extreme characteristics treated categorically was associated with mortality [X2
    = 17.06, p = .0002]
    Table 3—Cox Proportional Hazards Regression Models for the Number of Extreme Sleep Characteristics and All-Cause Mortality.
    HR (95% CI) X2 statistic (p-value)
    Base model: number of extreme sleep characteristics, age, and site
    Continuous 1.17 (1.12, 1.22) 56.89 (&lt;.001)
    Categorical — 59.84 (&lt;.001)a
    1 vs 0 1.23 (1.00, 1.53) 3.66 (.056)
    2 vs 0 1.35 (1.09, 1.68) 7.45 (.006)
    3 vs 0
    4+ vs 0
    1.76 (1.40, 2.20) 24.17 (&lt;.001)
    2.13 (1.70, 2.68) 42.94 (&lt;.001)
    Full model: number of extreme sleep characteristics and all nonsleep characteristicsb
    Continuous 1.10 (1.05, 1.15) 16.74 (&lt;.001)
    Categorical — 20.71 (&lt;.001)a
    1 vs 0 1.09 (0.88, 1.36) 0.60 (.438)
    2 vs 0 1.17 (0.94, 1.46) 1.97 (.161)
    3 vs 0 1.40 (1.11, 1.77) 8.17 (.004)
    4+ vs 0 1.57 (1.23, 2.00) 13.31 (&lt;.001)
    HR = hazard ratio; CI = confidence interval.
    a
    Likelihood ratio test for categorical variable with &gt;2 categories.
    b
    Adjusted for age, site, race, education, self-reported health status, physical activity, depressed mood, smoking, caffeine intake, daily alcohol use, cognitive
    function, body mass index, self-reported histories of medical conditions (arthritis, cardiovascular disease, stroke, diabetes, chronic obstructive pulmonary
    disease, and hypertension), and uses of medications (antidepressants, benzodiazepines, and other sedatives/hypnotics, NSAIDS, corticosteroids).
    Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/41/1/zsx189/4642232 by Falk Library user on 22 October 2024
    SLEEP, Vol. 41, No. 1, 2018 8 An Application of Flexible Multivariable Approaches—Wallace et al.
    Figure 3—Variable importance (VIMP) from a random survival forest, expressed as the percentage relative to age. The model included the
    seven individual sleep characteristics, the number of extreme characteristics (# Extreme), and all nonsleep predictors. Joint VIMPs for the
    seven sleep characteristics (“7 Sleep”) and the seven sleep characteristics plus the number of extreme sleep characteristics (“7 sleep + #
    Extreme”) were also calculated. CVD = cardiovascular disease; PASE = Physical Activity Scale for the elderly; HTN = hypertension; SR
    Health = Self-Reported Health Status; COPD = chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; BMI = body mass index; NSAIDS = nonsteroidal
    anti-inflammatory drugs.
    Figure  2—Conditional inference tree model. Characteristics considered for inclusion were the seven individual sleep characteristics, the
    number of extreme sleep characteristics, age, and site. Terminal nodes show time in years to 25% mortality (95% CI). NA indicates that the
    estimate cannot be obtained because either the 25% mortality rate or its upper or lower confidence limit was not observed. HR = hazard ratio;
    CI = confidence interval; #Extreme = number of extreme sleep characteristics; PASE = Physical Activity Scale for the elderly.
    Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/41/1/zsx189/4642232 by Falk Library user on 22 October 2024
    SLEEP, Vol. 41, No. 1, 2018 9 An Application of Flexible Multivariable Approaches—Wallace et al.
    such that having 3 versus 0 (1.37 [1.08, 1.73]) or ≥4 versus 0
    (1.50 [1.17, 1.91]), extreme sleep characteristics were significantly associated with mortality. In the survival tree model, only
    age and CVD were empirically selected (see Supplementary
    Material). This is different from the results based on the full
    sample, where age, cognition, and physical activity were empirically selected to enter the tree model. Finally, in the random
    survival forest, the top 10 predictors were identical to those in
    the full sample, with only slight changes in order. Additional
    details are provided in Supplementary Material.
  </algo>
   
</subsection>
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 
 
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
<subsection>
  <subtitle>
   DISCUSSION
  </subtitle>
  This study used a multivariable sleep health framework29 to
  simultaneously examine seven sleep characteristics as predictors of time to all-cause mortality in older men. Across multivariable approaches, lower sleep-wake rhythmicity and lower
  sleep continuity increased risk for all-cause mortality even
  after considering other important sleep, demographic, health,
  and behavioral risk factors. Similar findings regarding the
  importance of measures of continuity (here, measured by actigraphy-assessed minutes awake after sleep onset) and rhythmicity (here, measured by actigraphy-derived PsF) for predicting
  mortality in older adults have been observed previously by at
  least one other study.20 
  
  <contradiction>
  <!-- negative citation!! -->
  However, current sleep recommendations from the National Sleep Foundation55,56 and the American
  Academy of Sleep Medicine57 are primarily focused on sleep
  duration, which has been most widely studied. 
  
  In our Cox models that focused on duration as the only sleep characteristic
  (with or without other nonsleep risk factors), duration was a
  significant predictor. However, in the full multivariable models including all sleep and nonsleep predictors, duration was no
  longer significant. This highlights the importance of studying
  sleep within a multidimensional sleep health framework and
  considering multiple sleep characteristics simultaneously.
  </contradiction>
  
  Our findings also emphasize how the simultaneous consideration of multiple sleep characteristics can enhance predictive power. In the random survival forest, only age, cognition,
  and history of CVD were more important than all of the sleep
  variables considered simultaneously (i.e., the seven sleep
  characteristics and the number of extreme characteristics). This
  finding, combined with the fact that sleep is modifiable through
  behavioral techniques, suggests that multidimensional sleep
  measures could play an important role in future prognostic
  models, and that it may also be an important target for largescale population interventions.
  The number of extreme sleep characteristics was a significant
  predictor of mortality even after adjusting for numerous nonsleep risk factors in a Cox regression model. It was also empirically selected as the best predictor of mortality among men
  aged &lt;72 in the base tree-structured survival model. However,
  the random survival forest indicated that rhythmicity and continuity were more important for predicting mortality than the
  number of extreme sleep characteristics, and the number of
  extreme sleep characteristics was not significant in a multivariable Cox model that also included rhythmicity and continuity.
  As such, it is probably that rhythmicity and continuity are the
  primary contributors to the “number of extreme sleep characteristics” variable. To explore this further, we recalculated the
  number of extreme sleep characteristics variable in two ways:
  (1) counting only rhythmicity and continuity (ranging from 0
  to 2), and (2) counting only duration, continuity, rhythmicity,
  regularity, and quality (i.e., excluding rhythmicity and continuity, ranging from 0 to 5). The continuous measure counting only
  rhythmicity and continuity was significantly associated with
  mortality (HR [95% CI] = 1.31 [1.19, 1.43]). However, the continuous measure excluding rhythmicity and continuity was not
  significantly associated with mortality (HR [95%CI] = 1.05
  [0.99, 1.11]). These findings provide further support for the
  importance of both rhythmicity and continuity in predicting
  mortality among older men.
  Our strategy of using both traditional Cox models and flexible, nonlinear tree-modeling approaches allowed us to establish which findings are most robust amidst potentially complex
  associations. In general, our findings from the Cox model
  regarding rhythmicity, continuity, and the number of extreme
  sleep characteristics were replicated using flexible tree-structured analysis and/or the random forests. However, the finding
  from the fully adjusted Cox models showing that better quality
  Table 4.—Multivariable Cox Model Including Age and Variables With Variable Importance Statistics (VIMPs) at Least 5% as Large as Age (Identified From
  Random Forest).
  Predictor HR (95% CI) X2 statistic (p-value)
  Age 1.70 (1.60, 1.81) 292.37 (&lt;.001)
  Cognition (MMSE) 0.84 (0.80, 0.88) 45.25 (&lt;.001)
  History of cardiovascular disease 1.49 (1.32, 1.69) 39.80 (&lt;.001)
  Physical activity (PASE) 0.88 (0.82, 0.95) 11.80 (&lt;.001)
  Rhythmicity (PsF) 0.92 (0.85, 0.99) 5.25 (.022)
  Depression (GDS) 1.08 (1.02, 1.15) 7.12 (.008)
  Continuity (WASO) 1.13 (1.06, 1.20) 14.47 (&lt;.001)
  Number of extreme sleep characteristics 1.03 (0.98, 1.09) 1.58 (.209)
  MMSE = Mini-Mental State Exam; CVD = History of cardiovascular disease; PASE = Physical Activity Scale for the elderly; GDS = Geriatric Depression
  Scale; WASO = minutes awake after sleep onset.
  Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/41/1/zsx189/4642232 by Falk Library user on 22 October 2024
  SLEEP, Vol. 41, No. 1, 2018 10 An Application of Flexible Multivariable Approaches—Wallace et al.
  (captured by the PSQI sleep quality item) was significantly
  associated with increased mortality risk was not replicated in
  the tree-structured model or the random forest. This discrepancy
  suggests that it is unlikely that better sleep quality increases
  mortality risk. It also highlights the importance of considering
  flexible, nonlinear alternatives such as tree-structured models
  and random forests when studying multivariable sleep health.
  Our variable selection strategy was to preselect one sleep characteristic for each domain, prioritizing measures that are clinically relevant, stable, representative of daily life, and based on
  prior scientific evidence. This strategy is likely to yield clinically meaningful model interpretations and reduces the risk of
  spurious findings because of the scientific evidence behind our
  selections. However, it does not necessarily result in the greatest
  predictive power, nor does it provide a comprehensive assessment of exactly which characteristics within each sleep domain
  are most representative or predictive. In future research, it may be
  useful to apply factor analysis and develop representative domain
  scores (e.g., through item response theory) for use in subsequent
  models. Alternatively, the tree-structured models and random
  forests used herein, as well as regularized regression approaches
  (e.g., the elastic net58), allow for many potentially correlated variables to be considered simultaneously. Using these multivariable
  approaches to explore which sleep characteristics (out of a much
  larger, exploratory pool of potential sleep characteristics) are the
  strongest predictors of health outcomes could yield important
  findings that differ from the results presented here.
  
  Our findings should be interpreted in the context of some limitations. First, we explored multiple models and analytic strategies, and as such, our findings are hypothesis-generating and
  need to be validated in future studies. 
  
  <takeaway>
  However, the fact that rhythmicity and continuity consistently emerged as important
  across a variety of modeling strategies and sensitivity analyses suggests that these findings are robust within our sample.
  </takeaway>
  
  Second, although conditional inference tree-structured models and random forests have numerous strengths as discussed
  above, they also have weaknesses. Conditional inference tree
  models can be unstable in their structure, are less efficient than
  regression when associations between predictors and the outcome are truly linear, and are not necessarily optimal predictors
  (i.e., each split is selected to optimally predict the outcome at
  each node; however, this does not necessarily result in an entire tree that optimally predicts the outcome). Although random
  forests mitigate these limitations of the single tree model, a disadvantage is that they do not facilitate a nuanced interpretation
  of the direction and magnitude of the associations. Third, our
  results are specific to older men enrolled in the MrOS study and
  an all-cause mortality outcome. Similar analyses should be conducted with other outcomes (e.g., cause-specific mortality or
  specific disease states) and populations (e.g., women) to assess
  generalizability.
  A final limitation is that we did not investigate mechanisms
  through which sleep characteristics (namely, sleep-wake rhythmicity and sleep continuity) may relate to mortality. Thus, we
  cannot discern whether these sleep characteristics are directly
  related to mortality or whether they are indirectly related to mortality through other factors. Prior studies investigating mechanistic links between sleep and mortality have primarily (but not
  exclusively59,60) focused on long or short sleep duration.47,61–63
  Our study suggests that shifting the focus of these mechanistic
  studies from sleep duration to measures of sleep-wake rhythmicity and sleep continuity may be a promising direction of
  future research, especially given their associations with potential mortality-related mechanisms including immunity,60,64
  inflammation,22,59 depression,65 cognitive deficits,66,67 high blood
  pressure,68 and obesity.69 Notably, a previously published study59
  using a subset of our MrOS sample investigated inflammation
  and morbidity or lifestyle factors (measured concurrently with
  sleep) as mechanisms through which actigraphy-measured
  WASO (i.e., sleep continuity) predicted mortality. However, the
  WASO-mortality association was found to be independent of
  these potential mechanisms.
  In conclusion, we found that the simultaneous consideration
  of multiple sleep characteristics can enhance predictive power
  for mortality among older men, and that rhythmicity and continuity in particular confer the strongest risk for mortality.
  Critical next steps in the study of multivariable sleep health will
  be to conduct studies to elucidate the physiological, psychological, and behavioral mechanisms through which rhythmicity
  and continuity (individually and in combination with one another) relate to all-cause mortality; to develop new treatments
  that target the specific sleep profiles that cause morbidity and
  mortality; and to create enhanced health screening tools that
  incorporate multivariable sleep measures.
</subsection>
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 
 
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
<subsection>
  <subtitle>
   REFERENCES
  </subtitle>
  1. Cappuccio FP, Cooper D, D’Elia L, Strazzullo P, Miller MA. Sleep
  duration predicts cardiovascular outcomes: a systematic review and
  meta-analysis of prospective studies. Eur Heart J. 2011; 32(12):
  1484–1492.
  2. da Silva AA, de Mello RG, Schaan CW, Fuchs FD, Redline S, Fuchs
  SC. Sleep duration and mortality in the elderly: a systematic review with
  meta-analysis. BMJ Open. 2016; 6(2): e008119.
  3. Smagula SF, Stone KL, Redline S, et al.; Osteoporotic Fractures in Men
  (MrOS) Research Group. Actigraphy- and polysomnography-measured
  sleep disturbances, inflammation, and mortality among older men.
  Psychosom Med. 2016; 78(6): 686–696.
  4. Hoevenaar-Blom MP, Spijkerman AM, Kromhout D, van den Berg JF,
  Verschuren WM. Sleep duration and sleep quality in relation to 12-year
  cardiovascular disease incidence: the MORGEN study. Sleep. 2011;
  34(11): 1487–1492.
  5. Lou P, Chen P, Zhang L, et al. Relation of sleep quality and sleep duration to type 2 diabetes: a population-based cross-sectional survey. BMJ
  Open. 2012;2(4). pii: e000956.
  6. Engeda J, Mezuk B, Ratliff S, Ning Y. Association between duration and
  quality of sleep and the risk of pre-diabetes: evidence from NHANES.
  Diabet Med. 2013; 30(6): 676–680.
  7. Yaggi HK, Araujo AB, McKinlay JB. Sleep duration as a risk factor
  for the development of type 2 diabetes. Diabetes Care. 2006; 29(3):
  657–661.
  8. Soreca I, Wallace ML, Frank E, Hasler BP, Levenson JC, Kupfer DJ.
  Sleep duration is associated with dyslipidemia in patients with bipolar
  disorder in clinical remission. J Affect Disord. 2012; 141(2-3): 484–487.
  9. Kowall B, Lehnich AT, Strucksberg KH, et al. Associations among sleep
  disturbances, nocturnal sleep duration, daytime napping, and incident
  prediabetes and type 2 diabetes: the Heinz Nixdorf Recall Study. Sleep
  Med. 2016; 21: 35–41.
  10. Gallicchio L, Kalesan B. Sleep duration and mortality: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Sleep Res. 2009; 18(2): 148–158.
  11. Cappuccio FP, D’Elia L, Strazzullo P, Miller MA. Sleep duration and
  all-cause mortality: a systematic review and meta-analysis of prospective studies. Sleep. 2010; 33(5): 585–592.
  12. Haseli-Mashhadi N, Dadd T, Pan A, Yu Z, Lin X, Franco OH. Sleep
  quality in middle-aged and elderly Chinese: distribution, associated
  Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/41/1/zsx189/4642232 by Falk Library user on 22 October 2024
  SLEEP, Vol. 41, No. 1, 2018 11 An Application of Flexible Multivariable Approaches—Wallace et al.
  factors and associations with cardio-metabolic risk factors. BMC Public
  Health. 2009; 9: 130.
  13. Elder SJ, Pisoni RL, Akizawa T, et al. Sleep quality predicts quality
  of life and mortality risk in haemodialysis patients: results from the
  Dialysis Outcomes and Practice Patterns Study (DOPPS). Nephrol Dial
  Transplant. 2008; 23(3): 998–1004.
  14. Akerstedt T, Kecklund G, Johansson SE. Shift work and mortality.
  Chronobiol Int. 2004; 21(6): 1055–1061.
  15. Frost P, Kolstad HA, Bonde JP. Shift work and the risk of ischemic heart
  disease - a systematic review of the epidemiologic evidence. Scand J
  Work Environ Health. 2009; 35(3): 163–179.
  16. Dew MA, Hoch CC, Buysse DJ, et al. Healthy older adults’ sleep predicts all-cause mortality at 4 to 19 years of follow-up. Psychosom Med.
  2003; 65(1): 63–73.
  17. Grandner MA, Jackson NJ, Pak VM, Gehrman PR. Sleep disturbance
  is associated with cardiovascular and metabolic disorders. J Sleep Res.
  2012; 21(4): 427–433.
  18. Troxel WM, Buysse DJ, Matthews KA, et al. Sleep symptoms predict the development of the metabolic syndrome. Sleep. 2010; 33(12):
  1633–1640.
  19. Laugsand LE, Vatten LJ, Platou C, Janszky I. Insomnia and the risk
  of acute myocardial infarction: a population study. Circulation. 2011;
  124(19): 2073–2081.
  20. Zuurbier LA, Luik AI, Hofman A, Franco OH, Van Someren EJ, Tiemeier
  H. Fragmentation and stability of circadian activity rhythms predict mortality: the Rotterdam study. Am J Epidemiol. 2015; 181(1): 54–63.
  21. Paudel ML, Taylor BC, Ancoli-Israel S, et al.; Osteoporotic Fractures in
  Men (MrOS) Study. Rest/activity rhythms and mortality rates in older
  men: MrOS Sleep Study. Chronobiol Int. 2010; 27(2): 363–377.
  22. Okun ML, Reynolds CF 3rd, Buysse DJ, et al. Sleep variability, health-related practices, and inflammatory markers in a community dwelling
  sample of older adults. Psychosom Med. 2011; 73(2): 142–150.
  23. Ogilvie RP, Redline S, Bertoni AG, et al. Actigraphy measured sleep
  indices and adiposity: the Multi-Ethnic Study of Atherosclerosis
  (MESA). Sleep. 2016; 39(9): 1701–1708.
  24. Chontong S, Saetung S, Reutrakul S. Higher sleep variability is associated with poorer glycaemic control in patients with type 1 diabetes. J
  Sleep Res. 2016; 25(4): 438–444.
  25. Hays JC, Blazer DG, Foley DJ. Risk of napping: excessive daytime
  sleepiness and mortality in an older community population. J Am
  Geriatr Soc. 1996; 44(6): 693–698.
  26. Newman AB, Spiekerman CF, Enright P, et al. Daytime sleepiness
  predicts mortality and cardiovascular disease in older adults. The
  Cardiovascular Health Study Research Group. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2000;
  48(2): 115–123.
  27. Sabanayagam C, Shankar A, Buchwald D, Goins RT. Insomnia symptoms and cardiovascular disease among older American Indians: the
  Native Elder Care Study. J Environ Public Health. 2011; 2011: 964617.
  28. Short MA, Gradisar M, Lack LC, Wright HR. The impact of sleep on
  adolescent depressed mood, alertness and academic performance. J
  Adolesc. 2013; 36(6): 1025–1033.
  29. Buysse DJ. Sleep health: can we define it? Does it matter? Sleep. 2014;
  37(1): 9–17.
  30. Stine NW, Chokshi DA, Gourevitch MN. Improving population health in
  US cities. JAMA. 2013; 309(5): 449–450.
  31. Institute of Medicine (US) Committee on Sleep Medicine and Research.
  Sleep Disorders and Sleep Deprivation: An Unmet Public Health
  Problem. In: Colten HR, Altevogt BM, eds. Washington, DC: National
  Academies Press (US); 2006.
  32. Hothorn T, Hornik K, Zeileis A. Unbiased recursive partitioning: a conditional inference framework. J Comp Graph Stat. 2006; 15(3): 651–674.
  33. Ishrawan H, Kogalur UB, Blackston EH, Lauer MS. Random Survival
  Forests. Ann Appl Stat. 2008; 2: 841–860.
  34. Heagerty PJ, Zheng Y. Survival model predictive accuracy and ROC
  curves. Biometrics. 2005; 61(1): 92–105.
  35. Orwoll E, Blank JB, Barrett-Connor E, et al. Design and baseline
  characteristics of the osteoporotic fractures in men (MrOS) study–a
  large observational study of the determinants of fracture in older men.
  Contemp Clin Trials. 2005; 26(5): 569–585.
  36. Blank JB, Cawthon PM, Carrion-Petersen ML, et al. Overview of recruitment for the osteoporotic fractures in men study (MrOS). Contemp
  Clin Trials. 2005; 26(5): 557–568.
  37. Blackwell T, Ancoli-Israel S, Redline S, Stone KL; Osteoporotic
  Fractures in Men (MrOS) Study Group. Factors that may influence the
  classification of sleep-wake by wrist actigraphy: the MrOS sleep study. J
  Clin Sleep Med. 2011; 7(4): 357–367.
  38. Girardin JL, Kripke DF, Mason WJ, Elliott JA, Youngstedt SD. Sleep
  estimation from wrist movement quantified by different modalities. J
  Neurosci Methods 2001; 105(2): 185–191.
  39. Marler MR, Gehrman P, Martin JL, Ancoli-Israel S. The sigmoidally
  transformed cosine curve: a mathematical model for circadian rhythms
  with symmetric non-sinusoidal shapes. Stat Med. 2006; 25(22):
  3893–3904.
  40. Mehra R, Stone KL, Blackwell T, et al.; Osteoporotic Fractures in Men
  Study. Prevalence and correlates of sleep-disordered breathing in older
  men: osteoporotic fractures in men sleep study. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2007;
  55(9): 1356–1364.
  41. Johns MW. A new method for measuring daytime sleepiness: the
  Epworth Sleepiness Scale. Sleep. 1991; 14(6): 540–545.
  42. Buysse DJ, Reynolds CF 3rd, Monk TH, Berman SR, Kupfer DJ. The
  Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research. Psychiatry Res. 1989; 28(2): 193–213.
  43. Smagula SF, Ancoli-Israel S, Blackwell T, et al.; Osteoporotic Fractures
  in Men (MrOS) Research Group. Circadian rest-activity rhythms predict
  future increases in depressive symptoms among community-dwelling
  older men. Am J Geriatr Psychiatry. 2015; 23(5): 495–505.
  44. Rogers TS, Blackwell TL, Lane NE, et al. Rest-activity patterns and falls
  and fractures in older men. Osteoporos Int. 2017; 28(4): 1313–1322.
  45. Furihata R, Hall MH, Stone KL, et al. An aggregate measure of sleep
  health is associated with prevalent and incident depression among community-dwelling older women. Sleep. 2017;40(3).
  46. Walch OJ, Cochran A, Forger DB. A global quantification of “normal”
  sleep schedules using smartphone data. Sci Adv. 2016; 2(5): e1501705.
  47. Kurina LM, McClintock MK, Chen JH, Waite LJ, Thisted RA,
  Lauderdale DS. Sleep duration and all-cause mortality: a critical
  review of measurement and associations. Ann Epidemiol. 2013; 23(6):
  361–370.
  48. Washburn RA, Smith KW, Jette AM, Janney CA. The Physical Activity
  Scale for the Elderly (PASE): development and evaluation. J Clin
  Epidemiol. 1993; 46(2): 153–162.
  49. Aikman GG, Oehlert ME. Geriatric Depression Scale: long form versus
  short form. Clin Gerontol. 2000;22(3/4):63–70.
  50. Teng EL, Chui HC. The Modified Mini-Mental State (3MS) examination. J Clin Psychiatry. 1987; 48(8): 314–318.
  51. Pahor M, Chrischilles EA, Guralnik JM, Brown SL, Wallace RB,
  Carbonin P. Drug data coding and analysis in epidemiologic studies. Eur
  J Epidemiol. 1994; 10(4): 405–411.
  52. Kraemer HC, Blasey CM. Centring in regression analyses: a strategy to
  prevent errors in statistical inference. Int J Methods Psychiatr Res. 2004;
  13(3): 141–151.
  53. Ram S, Seirawan H, Kumar SK, Clark GT. Prevalence and impact of
  sleep disorders and sleep habits in the United States. Sleep Breath. 2010;
  14(1): 63–70.
  54. Kendzerska T, Mollayeva T, Gershon AS, Leung RS, Hawker G,
  Tomlinson G. Untreated obstructive sleep apnea and the risk for serious
  long-term adverse outcomes: a systematic review. Sleep Med Rev. 2014;
  18(1): 49–59.
  55. Foley D, Ancoli-Israel S, Britz P, Walsh J. Sleep disturbances and
  chronic disease in older adults: results of the 2003 National Sleep
  Foundation Sleep in America Survey. J Psychosom Res. 2004; 56(5):
  497–502.
  56. Hirshkowitz M, Whiton K, Albert SM, et al. National Sleep Foundation’s
  sleep time duration recommendations: methodology and results summary. Sleep Health. 2015; 1(1): 40–43.
  57. Watson NF, Badr MS, Belenky G, et al. Joint consensus statement of the
  American Academy of Sleep Medicine and Sleep Research Society on
  the recommended amount of sleep for a healthy adult: methodology and
  discussion. J Clin Sleep Med. 2015;11(8):931–952.
  Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/41/1/zsx189/4642232 by Falk Library user on 22 October 2024
  SLEEP, Vol. 41, No. 1, 2018 12 An Application of Flexible Multivariable Approaches—Wallace et al.
  58. Zou H, Hastie T. Regularization and variable selection via the elastic net.
  R Stat Soc Series B Stat Methodol. 2005;67(2):301–320.
  59. Smagula SF, Stone KL, Redline S, et al.; Osteoporotic Fractures in Men
  (MrOS) Research Group. Actigraphy- and polysomnography-measured
  sleep disturbances, inflammation, and mortality among older men.
  Psychosom Med. 2016; 78(6): 686–696.
  60. Haus EL, Smolensky MH. Shift work and cancer risk: potential mechanistic roles of circadian disruption, light at night, and sleep deprivation.
  Sleep Med Rev. 2013; 17(4): 273–284.
  61. Grandner MA, Hale L, Moore M, Patel NP. Mortality associated with
  short sleep duration: The evidence, the possible mechanisms, and the
  future. Sleep Med Rev. 2010; 14(3): 191–203.
  62. Grandner MA, Drummond SP. Who are the long sleepers? Towards an
  understanding of the mortality relationship. Sleep Med Rev. 2007; 11(5):
  341–360.
  63. Hall MH, Smagula SF, Boudreau RM, et al. Association between sleep
  duration and mortality is mediated by markers of inflammation and
  health in older adults: the Health, Aging and Body Composition Study.
  Sleep. 2015; 38(2): 189–195.
  64. Logan RW, Sarkar DK. Circadian nature of immune function. Mol Cell
  Endocrinol. 2012; 349(1): 82–90.
  65. Luik AI, Zuurbier LA, Hofman A, Van Someren EJ, Tiemeier H.
  Stability and fragmentation of the activity rhythm across the sleep-wake
  cycle: the importance of age, lifestyle, and mental health. Chronobiol
  Int. 2013; 30(10): 1223–1230.
  66. Oosterman JM, van Someren EJ, Vogels RL, Van Harten B, Scherder
  EJ. Fragmentation of the rest-activity rhythm correlates with age-related
  cognitive deficits. J Sleep Res. 2009; 18(1): 129–135.
  67. Maaskant M, van de Wouw E, van Wijck R, Evenhuis HM, Echteld MA.
  Circadian sleep-wake rhythm of older adults with intellectual disabilities. Res Dev Disabil. 2013; 34(4): 1144–1151.
  68. Matthews KA, Kamarck TW, H Hall M, et al. Blood pressure dipping
  and sleep disturbance in African-American and Caucasian men and
  women. Am J Hypertens. 2008; 21(7): 826–831.
  69. van den Berg JF, Knvistingh Neven A, Tulen JH, et al. Actigraphic sleep
  duration and fragmentation are related to obesity in the elderly: the
  Rotterdam Study. Int J Obes (Lond). 2008; 32(7): 1083–1090.
</subsection>
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 
 
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
 <!-- ============================================================================================================== -->
<subsection>
  <subtitle>
   SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL
  </subtitle>
  Supplementary material is available at SLEEP online.
</subsection>

<subsection>
  <subtitle>
   FUNDING
  </subtitle>
  The National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI) provides funding for
  the MrOS Sleep ancillary study “Outcomes of Sleep Disorders in Older Men”
  under the following grant numbers: R01 HL071194, R01 HL070848, R01
  HL070847, R01 HL070842, R01 HL070841, R01 HL070837, R01 HL070838,
  and R01 HL070839. The Osteoporotic Fractures in Men (MrOS) Study is
  supported by National Institutes of Health funding. The following institutes
  provided their support: the National Institute on Aging (NIA), the National
  Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS), the
  National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences (NCATS), and National
  Institutes of Health Roadmap for Medical Research under the following grant
  numbers: U01 AG027810, U01 AG042124, U01 AG042139, U01 AG042140,
  U01 AG042143, U01 AG042145, U01 AG042168, U01 AR066160, and UL1
  TR000128. MLW has been supported by National Institutes of Health grants
  K01 MH096944 and R01 AG056331. SFS has been supported by National
  Institutes of Health grants T32 MH019986 and T32 HL082610.
</subsection>
 
<subsection>
  <subtitle>
   SUBMISSION &amp; CORRESPONDENCE INFORMATION
  </subtitle>
  Submitted for publication April, 2017
  Submitted in final revised form October, 2017
  Accepted for publication October, 2017
  Address correspondence to: Meredith Wallace, 3811 O’Hara Street,
  Pittsburgh, PA 15132, USA. Telephone: (412) 648-5938; Fax: (412) 383-5412;
  Email: lotzmj@upmc.edu
 
</subsection>

<subsection>
  <subtitle>
   DISCLOSURE STATEMENT
  </subtitle>
  SR reports receiving a research contract from Jazz Pharmaceuticals. DJB
  reports receiving consultation fees from Bayer HealthCare, BeHealth Solutions,
  Ebb Therapuetics/Cereve, Inc., CME Insitute, CME Outfitters, Emmi Solutions,
  Medscape, and Merck; and grants from NIH, outside the submitted work.
  In addition, DJB receives licensing fees (royalties) for the Pittsburgh Sleep
  Quality Index (PSQI), which is copyrighted by the University of Pittsburgh.
  Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/41/1/zsx189/4642232 by Falk Library user on 22 October 2024
</subsection>

</full_article>