<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<paper>
    
    <LICENSE>
        PMCID
    </LICENSE>
    <link>
        https://doi.org/10.1093/sleep/zsad060
    </link>

    <title>
        Pediatric sleep: current knowledge, gaps, and opportunities for the future
    </title>
    
    <authors>
        Alexandria M. Reynolds1,*, , Andrea M. Spaeth2, , Lauren Hale3, Ariel A. Williamson4,5, , Monique K. LeBourgeois6, Sachi D. Wong6, Lauren E. Hartstein6, , Jessica C. Levenson7,8, Misol Kwon9, , Chantelle N. Hart10,11, Ashley Greer10, Cele E. Richardson12, Michael Gradisar13, Michelle A. Clementi14, , Stacey L. Simon14, Lilith M. Reuter-Yuill15, Daniel L. Picchietti16, Salome Wild17,18,
        Leila Tarokh17,18, Kathy Sexton-Radek19, Beth A. Malow20,21, Kristina P. Lenker22, Susan L. Calhoun22, Dayna A. Johnson23, and Mary A. Carskadon25
        , Daniel Lewin24
    </authors>
    
    <labs> 
        1Department of Psychology, University of South Carolina, Columbia, SC, USA,
        2Department of Kinesiology and Health, Rutgers University, New Brunswick, NJ, USA,
        3Department of Family, Population and Preventive Medicine, Stony Brook University, Stony Brook, NY, USA,
        4Department of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia, PA, USA,
        5Department of Psychiatry, Perelman School of Medicine, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA, USA,
        6Department of Integrative Physiology, University of Colorado Boulder, Boulder, CO, USA,
        7Department of Psychiatry, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, Pittsburgh, PA, USA,
        8Department of Pediatrics, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, Pittsburgh, PA, USA,
        9Division of Sleep Medicine, University of Pennsylvania Perelman School of Medicine, PA, USA,
        10The Center for Obesity Research and Education, College of Public Health, Temple University, Philadelphia, PA, USA,
        11The Department of Social and Behavioral Sciences, College of Public Health, Temple University, Philadelphia, PA, USA,
        12School of Psychological Science, University of Western Australia, Perth, WA, Australia,
        13Sleep Cycle AB, Gothenburg, Sweden,
        14Clinical Sciences, School of Medicine, University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, CO, USA,
        15Comprehensive Speech and Therapy Center, Western Michigan University, Kalamazoo, MI, USA,
        16University of Illinois School of Medicine, Carle Illinois College of Medicine, Carle Foundation Hospital, and University of Illinois School of Medicine, Urbana, IL, USA, 17Translational Research Center, University Hospital of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy, University of Bern, Bern, Switzerland,
        18University Hospital of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry and Psychotherapy, University of Bern, Bern, Switzerland,
        19Division of the Social Sciences, Elmhurst University, Elmhurst, IL, USA,
        20Departments of Neurology and Pediatrics, Burry Chair in Cognitive Childhood Development, Vanderbilt University Medical Center, Nashville, TN, USA,
        21Sleep Disorders Division, Vanderbilt University Medical Center, Nashville, TN, USA,
        22Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Health, Penn State Health Milton S. Hershey Medical Center, Penn State College of Medicine, Hershey, PA, USA, 23Department of Epidemiology, Rollins School of Public Health, Emory University, Atlanta, GA, USA,
        24Department of Pulmonary and Sleep Medicine, Children’s National Hospital, Washington, DC, USA, and
        25Bradley Hospital Sleep Lab, Warren Alpert Medical School, Brown University, Providence, RI, USA
    </labs>
    
    <date>
        Submitted for publication: January 10, 2023; Revised: February 19, 2023
    </date>
    
    <Abstract> 
    This White Paper addresses the current gaps in knowledge, as well as opportunities for future studies in pediatric sleep. The Sleep Research Society’s Pipeline Development Committee assembled a panel of experts tasked to provide information to those interested in learning more about the field of pediatric sleep, including trainees. We cover the scope of pediatric sleep, including epidemio- logical studies and the development of sleep and circadian rhythms in early childhood and adolescence. Additionally, we discuss current knowledge of insufficient sleep and circadian disruption, addressing the neuropsychological impact (affective functioning) and cardiometabolic consequences. A significant portion of this White Paper explores pediatric sleep disorders (including circadian rhythm disorders, insomnia, restless leg and periodic limb movement disorder, narcolepsy, and sleep apnea), as well as sleep and neurodevelopment disorders (e.g. autism and attention deficit hyperactivity disorder). Finally, we end with a discussion on sleep and public health policy. Although we have made strides in our knowledge of pediatric sleep, it is imperative that we address the gaps to the best of our knowledge and the pitfalls of our methodologies. For example, more work needs to be done to assess pediatric sleep using objective methodologies (i.e. actigraphy and polysomnography), to explore sleep disparities, to improve accessibility to evi- dence-based treatments, and to identify potential risks and protective markers of disorders in children. Expanding trainee exposure to pediatric sleep and elucidating future directions for study will significantly improve the future of the field.
    </Abstract>
    
    <Key_words>
        Key words: adolescent sleep; attention deficit hyperactivity disorder; autism; cardiometabolic health; circadian rhythm disorders; insomnia; insufficient sleep; narcolepsy; pediatric sleep; sleep apnea
    </Key_words>
     
    <Executive_Summary> 
        This White Paper is a collaborative effort of pediatric sleep experts initiated by the Sleep Research Society’s Pipeline Development Committee. The committee identified key areas of pediatric sleep that would serve as a launching point for trainees interested in studying and practicing in the field, including (1) current knowl- edge, (2) future directions, (3) critical gaps in the knowledge, and (3) a road map for trainees to further their knowledge in each niche subject.
        First, we explore the epidemiological studies among pediat- ric populations. There is discussion on how to improve pediat- ric sleep health measurement and better understand the social and contextual determinants of pediatric sleep. Next, we cover the development of sleep and circadian rhythms in both early childhood and adolescence, providing thoughtful guidance on the future directions of sleep disparities, sleep as an early pre- dictor of health and development, digital medias, methodologies, brain maturation and development, school involvement, and access to evidence-based treatments. The consequences of insuf- ficient sleep and impact on mood, emotion, and cardiometabolic health are discussed, including a spotlight specifically on delayed sleep phase and puberty’s impact on affective functioning. There is considerable dialogue regarding clinical sleep disorders (cir- cadian rhythm disorders, insomnia, restless leg syndrome and periodic limb movement disorder [PLMD], narcolepsy, and sleep apnea), as well as neurodevelopmental disorders (autism spec- trum disorder [ASD] and attention deficit hyperactivity disorder [ADHD]). Finally, we end with public health policy and the impor- tance of sleep.
        We begin the White Paper with a Foreword by Mary A. Carskadon, who provides a brief introduction to the broad field of pediatric sleep, as well as encouraging words for new trainees exploring this area.
    </Executive_Summary>
    
    <Foreword> 
        Section author: Mary A. Carskadon
        In my career, I have engaged in sleep research and later in cir-
        cadian rhythms research in many ways and not just with chil- dren/adolescents, though not babies. (I was terrified when asked by Christian Guilleminault, MD, to watch over preemies in the NICU making sure they kept breathing . . . and one stopped. I learned quickly that infants were not for me, but the research need remains, as you’ll see in this document below.)
        With encouragement from my primary mentor, William C. Dement, MD, PhD, I got involved in developing methods for study- ing sleep that resulted most notably in the multiple sleep latency test. This measure arose from a clinical need, yet it played an important role in my research to explore daytime sleepiness in the elderly, adults, emerging adults (college students), adoles- cents, and children under conditions of extended and restricted sleep and sleep loss, and of course narcolepsy. So, I wasn’t always
        a just child person, and you, too, may be moving into pediatrics from another area . . . don’t be shy.
        Measurement tools are critical to our research and need to be evaluated for reliability and validity, so beware of shiny new tools that may not be suitable for your needs. Thus, as you spread your wings into sleep/circadian research, you also need to identify the best measures and variables for your work . . . with luck, you may be the person to fill measurement gaps useful to the field. You may also find yourself, as have I, needing to stick to your guns to perform the study or studies you feel are needed. When I wanted to run forced desynchrony studies in kids, for example, I was told it couldn’t be done . . . I did it. Don’t give up.
        Because of sleep’s central role in emotional, cognitive, behav- ioral, and physical health, you’ll be advised to keep your train- ing focused, but I urge you to keep your interests broad. For me, working across many ages provided a deeper perspective on ado- lescent research. Don’t ignore basic science literature or findings from allied fields either.
        Remember, too that among the most important components of successful science are curiosity, creativity, and good writing! I give my graduate students, postdoctoral fellows, and junior fac- ulty mentees my favorite book on writing well—the same book Dr Dement gifted me a half-century ago and that I refer to even today—Strunk and White, The Elements of Style.
        My hope for the future of sleep and circadian science in chil- dren and adolescents is that coming generations of scientists will expand our knowledge in unpredicted and unanticipated ways. Yet I urge trainees to ground yourselves in the current knowl- edge and then start your exploration in the gap areas identified by these authors or other gaps as you see them.
    </Foreword>
    
    <Epidemiological_studies>
        Pediatric Sleep—Health Epidemiology
        Section authors: Lauren Hale and Ariel A. Williamson.
        The multidimensional concept of sleep health often includes measures such as sleep duration, regularity, satisfaction, quality, and timing [1]. Among pediatric populations, most epidemiologic studies rely on caregiver- or self-reported data primarily limited to sleep duration [2], with occasional measures of snoring, sleep quality, and napping. Population-based research shows several broad trends, including a shift from biphasic sleep to mono- phasic sleep around ages 3–5, decreasing sleep duration across development, and later timing starting in puberty through ado- lescence. Two consensus panels provide recommended sleep duration starting at 14–17 hours per 24 hours (including naps) for infants and moving to 8–10 hours per night for adolescents [3, 4] for optimal health and well-being. Across epidemiologic studies, there are notable sleep disparities, with children of racial/ethnic minority backgrounds or those of lower socioeconomic status
        (SES) more likely to evidence poor sleep health [5, 6].
          Statement of Significance
        This paper’s intent is to explore the current knowledge of the field of pediatric sleep. The Sleep Research Society’s Pipeline Develop- ment Committee assembled a group of experts to provide information across the scope of pediatric sleep, exploring epidemiolog- ical studies, development of sleep and circadian rhythms, insufficient sleep, clinical sleep disorders, neurodevelopment disorders and sleep, and public policy. Gaps in knowledge, road maps for trainees, and suggested readings provide more direction for those individuals interested in pursuing pediatric sleep as a field of study. This work is significant to the field of pediatric sleep because it serves as a launching point for those interested in not only learning the scope of the field, but how to improve moving forward.
           Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/46/7/zsad060/7070629 by guest on 22 September 2024
        
        Epidemiologic studies of sleep health in early childhood (0–5 years) suggest considerable variability in total (24 hours) sleep duration and timing, particularly between birth and 36 months [7–9]. In a large, cross-cultural sample of families from 17 countries/regions, infants, and toddlers from predominantly Asian (e.g. China, Korea, and Vietnam) contexts had significantly later caregiver-reported bedtimes and shorter total sleep dura- tion than those from predominantly Caucasian (e.g. Australia, Canada, and United States) contexts [9]. Bedtimes ranged from 19:27 (New Zealand) to 22:17 (Hong Kong), while total sleep dura- tion ranged from 11.6 hours (Japan) to 13.3 hours (New Zealand) [9]. In a US study of primarily lower-SES and racial/ethnic minor- ity preschoolers, over 20% of caregivers reported insufficient child sleep duration ((less than) 10 hours) [10]. Another US study of car- egiver-rated child sleep duration from birth to age 7 found that children of Black, Hispanic/Latinx, and Asian backgrounds were more likely than non-Latinx White children to exhibit chronic sleep curtailment (below recommended sleep duration thresh- olds) although adjustment for SES attenuated some of these racial differences [11].
        Cross-sectional, population-based research on school-aged children (6–11 years) in the US indicates a high prevalence of insufficient sleep [12]. On school nights, an estimated 55% of chil- dren get less than the recommended 9 hours of sleep [13]. In the one of the few studies to longitudinally assess actigraphy-derived sleep in school-aged children, Black children exhibited shorter actigraphic sleep duration and endorse more sleep problems compared to White youth [14, 15]. Children of lower-SES back- grounds also showed shorter sleep duration compared to those of higher SES [14, 15].
        National and community-based studies show that more than half of US teens obtain less than the recommended 8 hours of sleep per night [16, 17]. However, overall absolute estimates for insufficient sleep vary according to measurement strategy (self-report and actigraphy) and sample characteristics [16–19]. Actigraphic studies of teens have identified differential sleep duration by race/ethnicity and sex [17–19]. In particular, com- pared to White teens, Black teens sleep approximately 20–30 min- utes less per night, and male teens sleep about 20 minutes less than female teens [17–19]. Furthermore, there has been a slight increase in inadequate sleep among adolescents during the past decade, which has been attributed to an increase in smartphone use in the bedroom environment [20].
    </Epidemiological_studies>
    
    <Future_directions_critical_gaps_in_knowledge> 
        Improve pediatric sleep health measurement.
        Pediatric sleep health research is often limited to survey ques- tions on a small number of sleep variables. Future epidemiologic research should incorporate measures of sleep regularity and timing, with information about both inter- and intra-individual variation in sleep [21]. The use of videosomnography, actigraphy, and other wearables should also be incorporated into data col- lection efforts to reduce measurement error from self-reported or caregiver-reported data, particularly in early childhood and school-aged samples.
        Estimate the continuity of childhood sleep health to short- term and longer-term outcomes, including adulthood.
        Most research examining sleep and child outcomes has focused on sleep duration in short-term or cross-sectional studies [2]. Evidence of continuity in a broad range of sleep health param- eters from early childhood on short and longer-term outcomes
        Reynolds et al. | 3 is critical for justifying and supporting future population-based
        sleep health promotion efforts.
        Identify the role of social and contextual determinants of pediatric sleep.
        Elucidating the role of social and contextual factors, including neighborhood and household environments, is necessary for developing effective and culturally tailored sleep health pro- motion interventions. Examples of modifiable sleep health fac- tors include bedtime routines, light, noise, physical activity, and screen time.
    </Future_directions_critical_gaps_in_knowledge>
    
    <Road_map_for_trainees>
        Trainees interested in pediatric sleep epidemiology should seek multidisciplinary training in areas such as sleep, psychology, public health, and the social sciences. Mentorship with hands-on data collection and analytic experience in pediatric sleep epi- demiology is also necessary. Trainees will benefit from attend- ing pediatric and general sleep meetings and acquiring skills in translating research findings into actionable sleep health promo- tion strategies.
    </Road_map_for_trainees>
    
    <Development_of_Sleep_and_Circadian_Rhythms>
        Early development of sleep and circadian rhythms
        Section authors: Monique K. LeBourgeois, Sachi D. Wong, and Lauren E. Hartstein.
        Brief summary of the field.
        Developmental changes in sleep behavior during the first decade of life are remarkable [22]. On average, newborns sleep for 15–17 hours, displaying a polyphasic sleep–wakefulness pattern across the 24-hour day. Around 5 months of age, sleep becomes more con- solidated, with the longest nighttime sleep episode of ~6 hours. By 12 months, infants sleep ~14 hours, where ~11 hours of these occur at night. By 22 months, most infants have dropped their morning nap [23]. Afternoon naps gradually decline in number and duration across the preschool years, and as a result, sleep becomes consol- idated into one nighttime period of 11–13 hours. By 8 years of age, sleep duration declines to ~10 hours, which on average remains consistent through the end of the first decade of life.
        Newborns do not produce overt rhythms as evidenced by the absence of significant circadian rhythmicity in their sleep/wake cycle, body temperature, melatonin, and cortisol [24]. Infants receive time-of-day cues from their environment through light, as well as maternal signals via diurnal variation in breast milk hormones [25, 26]. Measurable outputs appear throughout the first 2–6 months of life, including sleep and wakefulness, as well as rhythms in body temperature, melatonin, and cortisol [24]. The timing of the circadian clock delays throughout childhood: melatonin onset occurs at ~19:30 in toddlers and at ~20:40 in 9 to 10-year-olds [27, 28]. There is wide individual variability in the timing of circadian development, and factors that influence the emergence of a stable circadian clock remain understudied.
        Across infancy and childhood, behavioral changes in sleep are due to increased maturation of the sleep homeostatic and circa- dian systems in their interaction with individual difference fac- tors (e.g. sex, chronotype, and temperament) within the context of social and familial environments (i.e. opportunities, demands, and stressors) [29].
         Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/46/7/zsad060/7070629 by guest on 22 September 2024
        
        4 | SLEEP, 2023, Vol. 46, No. 7 Future directions and road map.
        The following represent current gaps in the literature with regard to sleep, circadian rhythms, and infant and child development. These areas offer rich opportunities for trainees to create their own road map toward a rich independent research career.
        • Brain maturation: further research is needed to deter- mine the association between changes in sleep throughout development and brain maturation and whether it is bidi- rectional [30, 31].
        • Digital media: the increase in digital media use, even in young children, is associated with later bedtimes and shorter sleep durations [32]. Additional experimental stud- ies are critical to understanding the underlying mecha- nisms and whether interventions to limit children’s screen time lead to improvements in sleep health.
        • Sleep disparities: white, non-Hispanic children are more likely to have earlier and more regular bedtimes, longer nighttime sleep durations, and take fewer naps than children of racial/ethnic minorities [6]. More research is crucial to understanding predictors and consequences of sleep disparities and resulting disparities in health outcomes.
        • Sleep as early predictor of health and development: data from longitudinal studies suggest insufficient sleep in early childhood can have lasting impacts on physical health, emotion regulation, and academic performance [33, 34]. The underlying mechanisms and effectiveness of early sleep interventions remain largely unknown.
        • Premature birth: current understanding of whether pre- mature birth has long-term implications for children’s sleep and the development of circadian rhythms is limited [35].
        • Pre- and peri-natal melatonin: little is known about whether a pregnant woman’s melatonin levels influence rest/activity patterns in the fetus [36]. Additionally, future work should examine how a mother’s light exposure and sleep cycles influence the melatonin received by a breast-feeding baby, and whether that in turn impacts the child’s sleep and circadian rhythms [26].
        • Methodology: estimating circadian phase and period cur- rently involves challenging procedures that are difficult to perform with young children. Future research should explore whether circadian timing can be estimated through simpler procedures (e.g. a single blood draw) [37], or math- ematical modeling from noninvasive measures (e.g. actig- raphy, light history) [38].
        • Impact of light: evening bright light suppresses children’s melatonin production [39, 40]. How light-induced mela- tonin suppression affects children’s sleep, however, is cur- rently unknown. Additionally, the impact of light timing, spectrum, and duration on children’s sleep and circadian rhythms remain unexplored areas of research.
        • Stability of chronotype: chronotype shifts throughout the lifespan and can differ between individuals [41]. However, research on the variability of chronotypes through- out childhood and how well individual chronotypes are reflected in parent-selected bedtimes is sparse.
        Adolescent sleep
        Section author: Jessica C. Levenson.
        Many adolescents experience short, poorly timed, and inade- quate sleep [42, 43], with only 25% obtaining the recommended duration of 8 hours or greater [44]. Insufficient sleep has serious consequences for adolescents across various domains, such as emotion dysregulation, increased likelihood of depression, suici- dality and risky behavior, poorer physical health, and poor school performance [45, 46]. Insufficient adolescent sleep results from a “perfect storm” of biological and psychosocial factors that char- acterize this developmental period, including delayed circadian phase and slowed accumulation of sleep pressure, increased bedtime autonomy, and social networking, among others [42, 47]. Yet, the biological processes underlying the circadian phase delay and slower accumulation of sleep pressure that characterize ado- lescence are not fully understood, despite recent advances [48]. Early school start times are a modifiable contributor to insuffi- cient and poorly timed sleep; when start times are delayed, teens demonstrate improvements in weekday sleep duration, sleep- iness, weekend oversleep, and school attendance [49–51]. Yet, logistical and financial challenges, among other factors, have contributed to the maintenance of early start times in many dis- tricts [52]. Several universal sleep education programs addressing other modifiable contributors to poor sleep among adolescents have been developed and tested, primarily in schools [53]. While these programs have good accessibility and reach, and are suc- cessful in improving sleep knowledge, they have limited impact on improving sleep behavior [54–56].
        Sleep disorders frequently emerge during adolescence. Insomnia is the most common at ~11% lifetime prevalence [57, 58]. Though cognitive behavioral interventions for insomnia are efficacious among youth in general, relatively few studies have been conducted among adolescents, with even fewer focused on adolescents with medical or psychiatric comorbidities [59–61]. Recently, an intervention to address adolescent sleep and circa- dian rhythms transdiagnostically has been developed and tested (TranS-C), and growing evidence supports its efficacy [62–65]. Adolescent sleep concerns are frequently reported in primary care visits [66–68], where youth are likely to first discuss sleep issues [69]. Yet, behavioral treatment for sleep rarely occurs in primary care [67, 70, 71], likely due to lack of clinician training and comfort in addressing sleep, and limited time during adoles- cent visits [67, 70, 72]. Furthermore, given the shortage of trained pediatric sleep providers in our country [73, 74], there is an urgent need to increase access to evidence-based behavioral treatment for adolescents.
    </Development_of_Sleep_and_Circadian_Rhythms>
    
    <Critical_gaps_and_future_directions.> 
        1. Sleep regulation: build on recent research to further elu- cidate the biological processes underlying changes to the homeostatic sleep and circadian systems that characterize adolescence.
        2. School start times: partner with school districts and com- munity stakeholders to address barriers to delaying school start times and advocate for policy change.
        3. School-based sleep programs: increase the impact of school-based sleep programs on sleep behavior by tar- geting mechanisms that translate sleep knowledge into behavior change (e.g. family involvement, tailoring of strat- egies, and creating a culture change). Applying frameworks such as knowledge to action can support this work [53].
        4. Access to evidence-based treatments: increase screen- ing for and treatment of sleep disturbances, especially
    
        
        insomnia, in primary care, and among youth with comor- bid conditions. Increase access to evidence-based treat- ments for sleep disorders by enhancing sleep education at various stages of provider training, across clinicians (e.g. school and outpatient nurses, physicians, and behavioral health clinicians) and settings (e.g. schools, primary care, adolescent medicine, and specialty behavioral health).
    </Critical_gaps_and_future_directions.>
    
    <Road_map_for_trainees>
        Those interested in adolescent sleep should seek general training in sleep and behavioral sleep medicine, public health, adolescent development, and particularly the role of sleep changes during this period. Specific to the future directions identified here, train- ees should seek training and mentorship in: community-based participatory research, especially with stakeholders in schools and primary care; intervention development and adaptation; rel- evant theories of adolescent behavior change; and dissemination and implementation science.
        Acknowledgment.
        The author thanks Dr Daniel Buysse and Dr Ariel Williamson for their feedback on earlier versions of this work.
    </Road_map_for_trainees>
    
    <Consequences_of_Insufficient_Sleep_and_Circadian_Disruption>
        Neuropsychological (affective functioning)
        Section author: Misol Kwon.
        Brief summary of what is known.
        During pubertal onset (between ages 9 and 14), rapid physical growth occurs, with significant changes in neuropsychological functioning and brain maturation [75]. The adolescent brain goes through a period of heightened affective reactivity characterized by greater sensitivity to rewards and negative stimuli [76, 77]. These include greater sensitivity to social evaluation and emo- tional reactions, such as sensation-seeking, risk-taking behaviors, intensified focus on social relationships, and desire for inde- pendence [75, 78–80]. Simultaneously, dramatic changes in sleep timing, architecture, and homeostasis occur during adolescence [81]. Across puberty, the sleep slow-wave activity sharply declines [82, 83] alongside significant maturation of sleep spindles, which facilitates synaptic elimination and brain reorganization [84]. A few brain regions especially susceptible to sleep loss include prefrontal cortex and amygdala; these regions are also areas crit- ical for advancements in emotional reactivity, evaluation, and expression [85, 86]. Insufficient sleep and circadian disruption may pose greater susceptibility and heightened risk in children and adolescents for affective dysfunction and onset of related psychological disorders and affect their life trajectory.
    </Consequences_of_Insufficient_Sleep_and_Circadian_Disruption>
    
    <Sleep_and_its_association_with_affective_functioning.>
        Burgeoning evidence indicates that sleep influences affective functioning such as mood, emotion, and emotion regulation among adolescents. Under sleep deprivation (characterized by ≤ 6.5 hours the first night, ≤2 hours the second night), adoles- cents reported less positive affect and more anxiety as a result of catastrophizing compared to rest, than adults [87]. Another experimentally induced sleep deprivation (characterized as ≤ 6.5 hours for 5 nights) found that both parents and adolescents under the sleep-restricted condition experienced significantly more
        negative emotion and poorer emotional regulation than those rested [88]. A similar finding was found where positive moods (i.e. happy, energetic) significantly decreased among adolescents' sleep restricted to ≤ 5 hours for 5 nights than those with more sleep opportunity [89]. Bidirectional and temporal associations between sleep and affective functions have also been reported [90]. For instance, in a naturalistic environment, longer self-re- ported sleep duration was associated with lower negative affect among adolescents, though this association differed on sleep measurement and affect dimensions [91].
        Delayed sleep phase and sleep loss experienced during adoles- cence may further enhance developmental tendencies towards increased sensitivity, impulsivity, and lack of control [92–94]. Significant bidirectional associations between sleep problems and increased difficulties with impulse control were found among adolescents [95], and reciprocal associations between sleep prob- lems and self-control during childhood [96]. In a similar context, adolescents are at an increased likelihood of engaging in risk-tak- ing behaviors, including consuming highly caffeinated drinks and/ use of substance use to perceive positive effects on their mood, performance, and alertness or energy level [97] thereby, perpetuating and worsening existing sleep deprivation problems [93].
    </Sleep_and_its_association_with_affective_functioning.>
    
    <Critical_gaps_and_future_directions.>
        Future studies are recommended to integrate multimodal sleep assessment methods measured both objectively and subjectively. For instance, incorporating chronotype and sleep health assess- ments [98], especially sleep timing and regularity, including fre- quencies of unintentional and intentional naps, intra-individual variability of sleep health using ecological momentary measures will allow researchers to better understand and refine temporal- ity as well as interrelationships between sleep and affect.
        The aggregated research suggests a complex, bidirectional interplay between sleep and affective functioning; however, the focus often lies on sleep and single dimensions of affective func- tion such as mood, and is limited in the areas of emotion and emotion regulation [99]. Firstly, future studies can benefit and build upon existing research by utilizing standardized meas- ures of affect such as the Positive and Negative Affect Schedule [100], and using consistent terminology when describing different affective functioning constructs (i.e. mood, positive and negative emotions, and emotional regulation) [99]. Additional work could also address the bidirectionality between sleep and affective function among clinical and nonclinical samples of adolescents, particularly those with history/ diagnosis of neurological, devel- opmental, mood, and substance use disorders.
        Identifying potential risks and protective markers, the distal and proximal social determinant factors that take the family con- text into consideration related to sleep and affective functioning may represent an important future direction for research and translational benefits.
    </Critical_gaps_and_future_directions.>
    
    <Sleep_Circadian_Disruption_and_Cardiometabolic_Health>
        Section authors: Chantelle N. Hart and Ashley Greer.
        Brief summary of what is known
        There is increasing recognition of the importance of sleep duration, and more recently the potential role of sleep tim- ing, in the promotion of cardiometabolic health. Meta-analyses
        Reynolds et al. | 5
         Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/46/7/zsad060/7070629 by guest on 22 September 2024
        
        6 | SLEEP, 2023, Vol. 46, No. 7
        of observational studies demonstrate prospective associations between shorter sleep duration and increased risk of obesity in children and adults [101, 102]. Short sleep in adults (e.g. 6 hours or less) has also been associated with increased risk of type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM), hypertension, and cardiovascular and coronary heart diseases [103] while shorter sleep duration in children has been associated with disturbances in insulin sensitivity and elevations in blood pressure [104]. Experimental studies with adults lend further support to disturbances in glu- cose regulation and insulin sensitivity that result from short sleep [105, 106], and also demonstrate that sleep restriction leads to increased caloric intake that predisposes to weight gain [107]—a finding also observed in pediatric samples [108, 109]. Taken together, extant findings provide compelling evidence for the important role of achieving sufficient sleep for cardiometa- bolic risk reduction.
        Beyond sleep duration, emerging work is demonstrating the potentially important role of the circadian timing system for car- diometabolic health as well. Ample evidence has demonstrated the negative impact of night shift work on obesity, diabetes, and cardiovascular disease [106]. Experimental studies in rodents and adults underscore the negative impact of misaligned sleep on weight regulation and impaired glucose metabolism [106, 110]. Although less work has been conducted with children, obser- vational studies have shown that both the timing of sleep, par- ticularly bedtimes, as well as, greater variability in sleep–wake times are associated with less healthy eating and activity behav- iors and increased risk for obesity [111]. It is also of note that both of the above-noted pediatric experimental studies observed changes in eating behaviors when sleep was restricted by delay- ing bedtimes [108, 109], thus calling into question the relative impact of the circadian timing system versus sleep duration on study outcomes. In sum, although less attention has been paid to the role of the circadian timing system in cardiometabolic risk, emerging work is underscoring the importance of future work in this area.
        Critical gaps and future directions
        There are a number of important future directions for this work, some of which are highlighted below.
        • Most evidence to date that has supported the importance of optimal sleep duration for cardiometabolic health has relied on cross-sectional and prospective observational studies or experimental studies that have assessed how large changes in sleep duration acutely effect cardiomet- abolic outcomes within tightly controlled laboratory set- tings. As such, an important next step is determining the clinical utility of enhancing sleep within real-world con- texts for reducing cardiometabolic risk.
        • It will also be important to determine the importance of enhancing sleep duration and timing for disease risk reduc- tion relative to other health behaviors. For example, how interventions to enhance sleep can independently con- tribute to disease risk reduction relative to those focused on eating and activity behaviors—or together with such approaches—could inform extant treatment approaches.
        • Overall, fewer studies have focused on the importance of circadian rhythms on cardiometabolic outcomes, yet a number of lines of research point to the potentially impor- tant role of sleep timing and consistency for optimizing cardiometabolic health. It will therefore be important to further explore the role of the circadian timing system
        (both within well-controlled laboratory settings as well as in real-world settings, and that focuses on work across the lifespan) for cardiometabolic risk reduction.
        • Given observed sleep-related health disparities, it will also be important to understand the potential role of enhancing sleep in decreasing observed disparities in obesity, type 2 diabetes, and cardiovascular disease.
        Roadmap for trainees.
        Trainees interested in the role of sleep and circadian influences on cardiometabolic health should consider not only seeking founda- tional training in sleep and circadian science, but also additional training in cardiometabolic health, including risk and protective factors for development of obesity, T2DM, and cardiovascular disease, as well as effective approaches for prevention and treat- ment. Hands-on training with an experienced mentor in the field can provide a well-rounded skillset grounded in scientific rigor and that offers the opportunity for exposure to the day-to-day management of research in this area. Gaining hands-on experi- ence not only in the conduct of research, but also in presentation of findings will provide a strong foundation for continued work in this area.
    </Sleep_Circadian_Disruption_and_Cardiometabolic_Health> 
        
    <Pediatric_Clinical_Sleep_Disorders> 
     Circadian rhythm disorders
     Section authors: Cele E. Richardson and Michael Gradisar.
     Brief summary of what we know.
     The ability of our endogenous circadian rhythm to adjust to a new timezone is a wonderful example of our body’s ability to adapt. Unfortunately, one’s circadian rhythm can travel to a different timezone, even though the physical body remains steadfast. This decoupling mainly strikes those living in their second decade—adolescents. The adolescent phenotype is one of falling asleep late, an inability to obtain sufficient sleep on school nights, and difficulty waking up for morning commit- ments [47].
     Whilst delayed sleep timing is common amongst adolescents, the prevalence of delayed sleep–wake phase disorder (DSWPD) likely ranges between 1.1% and 4.0% [33, 112, 113]. Compared to their “better”-sleeping peers, teenagers with DSWPD are at greater risk of substance use (alcohol, caffeine), being more sedentary, school nonattendance, and higher anxiety levels [33, 112, 113]. Fortunately, these ill effects can be reversed using interventions such as bright light therapy, exogenous melatonin, and chrono- therapy [114, 115].
     Gaps and future directions.
     Here, we posit the 3 Ms (see also Figure 1):
     (1) Motivation. Anyone who has worked with a sleepy teenager knows how much harder it is for them to muster motiva- tion. Yet motivation is essential to behavior change, par- ticularly in the morning (e.g. getting up earlier, exposure to bright light). Whilst there have been a burst of new stud- ies investigating teens’ motivation in the context of treat- ment [64, 116–119], it is not yet clear whether Motivational Interviewing enhances treatment outcomes.
     (2) Melatonin. An expert panel review concluded that the recom- mended treatment for DSWPD in children and adolescents
      Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/46/7/zsad060/7070629 by guest on 22 September 2024
     
     Figure 1. The 3 Ms for circadian rhythm sleep disorders future directions. The 3 Ms for future research directions: motivating teens to change sleep behaviors; evaluating the efficacy of strategically timed melatonin for delayed circadian rhythms; mechanisms linking delayed circadian rhythm disorders and mental health.
     is “strategically-timed melatonin.” [120] However, the state of the evidence was considered weak. Whilst many studies demonstrate the efficacy of immediate-release melatonin for children with delayed sleep [121], more well-designed clinical trials are needed to understand the efficacy of var- ious formulations of melatonin for DSWPD in adolescents. For instance, more evidence is needed to address concerns about the efficacy and safety of over-the-counter versions of melatonin. Finally, whilst some pharmacologic formu- lations are not to be prescribed for those under 18 years (e.g. Ramelteon), this may change if suitable evidence from clinical trials demonstrates their efficacy in adolescents of all ages with DSWPD.
     (3) Mental Health. There is a close association between cir- cadian rhythm disorders and mental health issues in young people, especially depression [122]. Science inves- tigating the etiology and natural course of delayed circa- dian rhythms in youth, the mechanisms linking circadian mistiming/poor sleep with emotional symptoms, and the effects of chronobiological treatments on sleep, circadian and mental health is needed. Such research could inform of whether chronobiological treatments (e.g. bright light therapy, melatonin) should be considered before psycho- logical treatments (e.g. cognitive-behavior therapy) for mental health disorders.
     A road map for trainees
     A trainee may become aware and interested in adolescent cir- cadian rhythm disorders at the undergraduate, graduate, or postgraduate level. Undertaking one’s PhD in this area will cer- tainly lay an excellent foundation. Seeking supervision from an
     experienced and knowledgeable mentor in this area is essential. We also encourage mentees to publish their work throughout their studies. Optimally, combining research with clinical train- ing to diagnose and treat circadian rhythm disorders in teenagers will accelerate one’s knowledge, skills, and career satisfaction.
    </Pediatric_Clinical_Sleep_Disorders>
    
    <Pediatric_Insomnia> 
        Section authors: Michelle A. Clementi and Stacey L. Simon. Pediatric insomnia, characterized by difficulty initiating and/ or maintaining sleep despite age-appropriate time and opportu- nity, is common and associated with numerous consequences for children and their families, including poor physical health and psychological dysfunction [57, 70, 123, 124]. Etiology is varied and pediatric insomnia often cooccurs with neurodevelopmental disorders, chronic medical conditions, and psychiatric disorders [125–127]. In young children, insomnia may present as depend- ency on specific sleep conditions (e.g. stimulation, objects, and settings) and/or bedtime resistance resulting in prolonged sleep onset. Substantial caregiver intervention is often necessary for initiating or returning to sleep. In adolescents, insomnia is often characterized by heightened physiological and/or cognitive
        arousal interfering with sleep onset.
        Strong empirical evidence exists for the efficacy of cognitive
        and behavioral interventions for treating pediatric insomnia [59, 128, 129]. These interventions typically focus on training and modifying parental behaviors (e.g. withdrawing reinforcement/ excessive parental involvement) to promote the child’s ability to self-soothe for sleep onset and reduce unwanted behaviors such as bedtime resistance [129, 130]. In adolescents, cognitive behavioral therapy for insomnia (CBT-I) has demonstrated ini- tial efficacy in improving a range of sleep indices and daytime
        Reynolds et al. | 7
          Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/46/7/zsad060/7070629 by guest on 22 September 2024
        
        8 | SLEEP, 2023, Vol. 46, No. 7
        consequences [128]. CBT-I techniques include sleep restriction, stimulus control, relaxation, and cognitive interventions to reduce sleep-interfering cognitions (bedtime worry, rumination) [131].
        Currently, no medications are approved by the US Food and Drug Administration for the treatment of pediatric insomnia, though medications are frequently prescribed off-label or avail- able over-the-counter [132]. Insufficient data and lack of con- trolled studies are available to demonstrate efficacy and safety of many of these substances [133, 134]. However, recent evidence does support the efficacy and safety of melatonin for sleep-onset insomnia in youth [135].
        Future directions
        Future research on treatment for pediatric insomnia should focus on understanding mechanisms of change, dose–response, and evaluation of individual treatment components through dismantling studies. Exploration of clinically meaningful bio- markers may help inform treatment outcomes and evaluation. Our understanding of treatment for adolescent insomnia is less robust than that of behavioral interventions for younger children. Examination of appropriate adaptations of CBT-I and considera- tions of motivation and treatment adherence for adolescents is necessary for the context of significant developmental changes during this period. Adaptation and study of insomnia interven- tions in youth with neurodevelopmental, medical, and psychi- atric comorbidities are also imperative, as controlled studies in these populations are generally lacking [129] despite exceedingly high rates of comorbidity [127]. Moreover, addressing health disparities in treatment development and implementation is important to address recent findings implicating socioeconomic status, race, ethnicity, and sex in persistence of insomnia symp- toms across childhood [136]. Consideration of alternative forms of behavioral intervention delivery (e.g. internet-delivered CBT-I) is important to study from a dissemination, implementation, and cost-effectiveness perspective. Finally, more rigorous study of the safety and efficacy of pharmacologic intervention for pediatric insomnia (including in combination with behavioral intervention) is important for standardizing practice parameters and ensuring long-term safety.
        Road map for trainees
        Trainees interested in pediatric insomnia are encouraged to gain clinical experience in behavioral sleep interventions across the developmental spectrum. Providers that possess this skillset may include psychologists working in pediatric specialty clinics such as sleep centers and primary care settings. Interested trainees may also consider pursuing the Diplomate in Behavioral Sleep Medicine credential granted by the Board of Behavioral Sleep Medicine. Eligibility for the DSBM credential requires a graduate degree in a health-related field and documentation of specialized training experiences. Additional information may be found at www.bsmcredential.org/.
    </Pediatric_Insomnia>
    
    <Pediatric_Restless_Legs_Syndrome_and_PLMD_Common_Disorders_Commonly_Misunderstood> 
        Section authors: Lilith M. Reuter-Yuill and Daniel L. Picchietti. Pediatric restless legs syndrome (RLS) and PLMD are com- mon, complex, and neurologic disorders that negatively impact sleep and daytime function [137, 138]. RLS is characterized by
        an uncontrollable urge to move the legs, usually accompanied by uncomfortable and unpleasant sensations, which are worse at night and alleviated by movement [137, 138]. Although new research suggests that the underlying pathophysiological mech- anisms may be similar, PLMD is diagnosed by polysomnographic findings associated with adverse clinical consequences, while RLS is a clinical diagnosis elicited by careful history [137, 138]. It is estimated that ~85% of children with RLS experience sleep disturbance [139]. RLS and PLMD are treatable [138]. However, it is common for RLS to be disregarded as “growing pains” by pedi- atricians, and PLMD may not be considered, even if polysomno- graphic findings are present. In addition, many aspects of these disorders are yet to be discerned. Consequently, greater attention to RLS and PLMD from the medical and research communities is needed to better understand these disorders.
        Epidemiology
        Population-based studies estimate a high prevalence of 2%–4% for pediatric RLS, which exceeds other common childhood disorders such as pediatric diabetes ((less than) 1%) and seizure disorders (~0.5%) [138, 139]. Approximately one-third of children are affected by moderate-to-severe RLS symptoms, impacting sleep and daytime function. However, very little is known about the incidence or natural course over time, including ameliorating or exacerbat- ing factors [140]. Further work assessing the quality of life and comorbidities with standardized instruments, and the inclusion in prospective cohort studies would be worthwhile. Although very little is known about the epidemiology of PLMD, periodic limb movements, and PLMD are commonly reported at pediatric sleep centers [141, 142].
        Diagnosis.
        Expert consensus on the pediatric diagnostic criteria for RLS was formalized in the medical literature in 2002 and updated in 2013 [137]. The 2013 update integrated unique inductive and qualita- tive research methods to access useful diagnostic information directly from pediatric RLS patients [143]. In addition, pediatric and adult diagnostic criteria were harmonized, and subsequently accepted by the International Classification of Sleep Disorders (ICSD-3) and the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-5). Recommendations for diagnostic interviews with pediatric patients include semistructured approaches with straightforward diagnostic prompts that allow the child to describe the symptoms in their own words or through drawings (see Figure 2) [137, 138]. Furthermore, diagnostic criteria for PLMD were updated [137].
        Based on these diagnostic criteria, development of validated diagnostic and severity tools are needed for pediatric RLS [144] Such instruments will help substantially to standardize clinical care and research. The Clinical Global Impression Scales are not specific to RLS but have been used in some pediatric RLS stud- ies, lacking other measures. In addition, new tools for the diag- nosis and longitudinal assessment of PLMD are needed, such as portable accelerometers, video devices, or innovative wearable technology for limb movements, to compliment polysomnogra- phy. Children who are less than 6 years of age or developmen- tally delayed are particularly challenging to diagnose, although further work on PLMD evolving to RLS [145] and the newly defined restless sleep disorder [146], will likely be productive.
        Pathophysiology.
        Genetics, brain iron deficiency, and neurotransmitter dysfunction are all probably involved in the pathophysiology of RLS and PLMD
         Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/46/7/zsad060/7070629 by guest on 22 September 2024
        
        Figure 2. Drawing and description from a pediatric sleep patient. A 15-year-old female: “‘My bed, and my pillow, and (inaudible). My head is usually somewhere around here. Sometimes at night, I just have to flip my whole body around or else it just bugs me. So then, I just sleep at the bottom of the bed for like a week, and then I can go back to sleeping like I’m supposed to. Feeling tired; (inaudible) blue eyes, and they’re bloodshot because I didn’t get any sleep; (inaudible) all over them. And my legs, they’re like tingly, (inaudible) wavy. And my arms kind of do the same thing. So I just have to keep moving them, or else it just bugs me all night long, and then I definitely don’t get any sleep.’” From J Child Neurol. 2011;26:1365-76. Reproduced with permission from SAGE Publications.
        based on work in adults [147]. The highly familial nature of RLS [141] provides a unique opportunity to explore these aspects in pediatric populations, particularly genetic, and epigenetic factors.
        Clinical treatment.
        Oral iron therapy and alpha-2-delta ligands have shown prom- ising results in the treatment of pediatric RLS and PLMD [138, 148, 149]. However, these data are predominated by limited ret- rospective case reports and series rather than prospective con- trolled trials, and no therapies have been approved by the US or European regulatory agencies for children. Additional case series are needed for these and other potential treatments, including behavioral interventions, intravenous iron [150], and vitamin D, which could then provide a sound basis for large randomized clinical trials. Also, therapeutic approaches need to be investi- gated for pediatric RLS that is comorbid commonly with ADHD, anxiety, or depression [145, 151]. The clinical response to iron therapy of the sleep movement disorders RLS, PLMD, and restless sleep disorder merits further investigation, as well [152, 153].
        Future directions and roadmap for trainees
        In addition to the topics mentioned above, comorbidity of RLS and PLMD with other conditions, such as ASDs [154], paras- omnias [155], chronic kidney disease [156], nocturnal enuresis, and migraine headaches, merits further research. Basic science aspects of RLS and PLMD could be unlocked using recently
        developed animal models [157]. New imaging techniques for brain iron deficiency, like transcranial ultrasound, could provide valuable information in both adults and children.
        Trainees should seek intra- and interprofessional collabora- tion to address complex clinical problems (e.g. cross-discipline practitioner–practitioner, practitioner-basic researcher, and patient-practitioner collaborations). Expand what you know and who you know! Seeking mentorship is crucial to developing skills and perspective in a new area. In addition, affiliation with groups dedicated to research in RLS and PLMD, may prove invaluable as a way to network with like-minded individuals and find career support. The International RLS Study Group (young investigator awards), the RLS Foundation (seed grants), the Sleep Research Society, and the American Academy of Sleep Medicine (mentor- ship grants) are all dedicated to advancing sleep science.
    </Pediatric_Restless_Legs_Syndrome_and_PLMD_Common_Disorders_Commonly_Misunderstood>
    
    <Pediatric_Narcolepsy> 
        Section authors: Salome Wild and Leila Tarokh.
        Narcolepsy is a rare neurological disorder characterized by
        disruption to the sleep–wake cycle and excessive daytime sleep- iness. Narcolepsy is often overlooked and underdiagnosed in youth given its rarity, developmentally changing manifestation, and symptoms resembling psychiatric conditions [158, 159]. A first peak in emergence is seen during puberty with more than half of patients reporting symptoms before the age of 18 [160, 161]. However, often the interval between first onset of symp- toms and correct diagnosis is a decade or more later [162, 163]. Although the precise etiology is unknown, narcolepsy is currently conceptualized as an autoimmune condition marked by a dys- function or loss of orexin neurons in the hypothalamus, leading to a disrupted sleep–wake cycle [160]. Both genetic and envi- ronmental influences are involved in its initial manifestation; a genetic predisposition coupled with environmental factors, such as psychological stressors, head injury, or infection with a sea- sonal influenza virus, may cause the disease to unfold [164, 165].
        Typical symptoms of narcolepsy include excessive daytime sleepiness, fragmented sleep, hallucinations, sleep paralysis, as well as cataplexy [163, 166]. More specifically, in children and ado- lescents, narcolepsy might manifest in an increased duration of nighttime sleep, a need for daytime naps, sleep attacks during the day, as well as hyperactivity and irritability [167]. Correct diagno- sis in children and adolescents is challenging because symptoms might be misattributed to mental health problems, parasomnias (e.g. nightmare disorder), or even considered normal in the course of development [167, 168]. Moreover, cataplexy, the most specific symptom of narcolepsy, presents differently in pediatric as com- pared to adult patients, further complicating the correct detec- tion of the disease in adolescence.
        Being a chronic, nonprogressive disorder, narcolepsy most often necessitates continuous treatment [169]. Symptoms of nar- colepsy impact the daily lives of children and teens by negatively affecting cognitive performance and mood regulation as well as peer and family relationships [163]. Therefore, treatment options generally aim at improving quality of life and include behavioral interventions, education, and medication. However, evidence on safety and efficacy of different treatment approaches in children is limited. For instance, the beneficial effects of behavioral inter- ventions such as scheduled naps or exercise have not sufficiently been subject to scientific study. Furthermore, medications are fre- quently used “off-label” due to a lack of randomized controlled trials in child and adolescent samples [169, 170]. Preliminary
        Reynolds et al. | 9
          Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/46/7/zsad060/7070629 by guest on 22 September 2024
        
        10 | SLEEP, 2023, Vol. 46, No. 7
        evidence on hypocretin receptor antagonists as well as treat- ments considering the immune-mediated nature of the disease is encouraging [171]. Yet, future research is required to deter- mine the appropriateness, efficacy, and risk-to-benefit ratio of both pharmacological and behavioral treatments in youth [169] at different developmental stages (e.g. pre- vs. post-pubertal). Moreover, accurate diagnosis and treatment of comorbid physical (e.g. metabolic upset) and mental conditions (e.g. mood disorders) is paramount to lessen the burden of disease and to enable opti- mal development for affected youth [172, 173].
    </Pediatric_Narcolepsy>
    
    <Sleep-Disordered_Breathing_in_Children>
        Section author: Kathy Sexton-Radek.
        The International Classification of Diseases manual recognizes
        Pediatric Sleep-disordered breathing as an array of ventilator dis- orders from multi-organ involvement [174, 175]. Sleep apnea in a pediatric population is included in this diagnostic grouping. Specifically, obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) within this category is associated with neurocognitive disorders, medical conditions of obesity, elevated blood pressure, diabetes, cardiovascular dis- orders, and increased mortality [176–178]. Sleep apnea is experi- enced qualitatively distinctly in children as compared to adults. The daytime sleepiness and fatigue are absent in children with OSA [175]. Children with OSA display behavioral issues of hyper- activity and poor concentration due to the compromise in sleep quality. OSA is a disorder of breathing where tissue in the upper larynx/pharynx areas has become flaccid and stents the airway. A disruption in ventilation and oxygen/hemoglobin becomes sub- stantially disturbed [175].
        OSA in a pediatric population is common [179]. The prevalence of OS is increased in populations of children diagnosed with med- ical conditions that compromise breathing such as intellectual disability, cerebral palsy, prematurity, craniofacial abnormalities, and obesity. The scope of OSA diagnoses in a pediatric population is further intensified by empirically measured clinical findings in both short and long-term medical complications. Thus, diagno- sis and preventative treatment are essential for a child with OSA health [180]. Specifically, Duman et al. [181] identified short-term medical complications of OSA in the pediatric population as the following: perioperative edema and need for mechanical ventila- tion and/or intubation [182]. Medical long-term complications of OSA further intensify for the child with OSA; they are cognitive deficits of attention, concentration, excessive daytime sleepiness, hyperactivity, cardiovascular complications (i.e. cor pulmonade, elevated blood pressure, autonomic instability), and metabolic syndromes (i.e. serum insulin-like growth factor decreases [183, 184]. Some genetic evidence of pediatric OSA suggests a famil- ial tendency [183, 184]. Additional studies have examined the probability of inflammation factors such as CRP, dL-6, IFN-γ, and TNF- and anti-inflammatory cytokine dL-10 decreases [185]. In some genetic conditions, OSA is at higher risk. The Pierre Robin syndrome 22q11 deletion (DeGeorge syndrome) both have been studied with increased risk for OSA due to craniofacial changes that result from these conditions (e.g. micrognathia) [186].
        Secondhand smoke was identified by studies as the high- est in China, Bangladesh, Indonesia, India, and the Philippines. Children’s respiratory conditions of asthma, allergies, and res- piratory infections are at substantial risk from secondhand smoke as well as OSA [177, 187, 188].
        A nocturnal polysomnograph (PSG) is used to study and diag- nose OSA. Per Association for Sleep Medicine guidelines, a posi- tive airway pressure therapy titration may be conducted during
        the all-night PSG [179]. Also, the assessment may continue with a daytime nap study/multiple sleep latency test to further assess sleep and daytime sleepiness level. Kothare et al. [189] suggest using electronic medical records to ensure quality treatment with a thorough review of medical examination data. A snoring assess- ment is to be conducted for all screenings as a screening measure as well as physical exam measures of obesity and adenotonsillar hypertrophy [174].
        Gozal et al. [190] presented treatment approaches for the removal of enlarged upper airway lymphadenitis tissues, use of anti-inflammatory therapy, orthodontic intervention, rapid max- illary expansion, myofunctional therapy, and continuous pos- itive airway pressure [174, 185, 191]. The treatment approaches are decided on a case-by-case basis depending on the symptom severity [176, 179, 191]. Some children with OSA may receive con- tinued positive airway treatment (CPAP) as part of their assess- ment and as a treatment. In other cases, surgical consultation and treatments such as tonsillectomy/adenoidectomy maybe considered [174, 189, 190].
        For the neonate, sleep has been measured to be 55% to 65% active sleep that transforms into rapid eye movement (REM) by 2–3 months of age [192]. Apnea of prematurity occurs when- ever the birth weight is below 1500 g or less than 28 weeks old and breathing is expressed with prolonged apnea of 20 or more seconds or brief response accompanied by reduction in oxyhe- moglobin saturation or bradycardia [192]. In children under 18 years, Upper Airway Resistance Syndrome presents as an arousal preceded by an episode lasting two breaths of one of the following factors: increased respiratory effort, flattening of the inspiratory pressure signal, snoring, or elevated tidal PaCO2 [193]. An analy- sis of all-night polysomnogram findings particular to respiratory events and nasal pressure transducers is sometimes consid- ered an additional factor. In Obesity Hypoventilation Syndrome, patients living with morbid obesity present with hypercapnia during wakefulness due to excess carbon dioxide produced from inefficient ventilation.
        Central, obstructive, and mixed apnea is considered to possi- bly be present in cases of apnea in prematurity [192]. In situations where the infant is under one year, Sudden Infant Death syndrome is diagnosed. An attenuation of central arousal mechanism lead- ing to overheating, prime position, and environmental maternal and prenatal factors are considered for etiology components of the diagnosis. Research has been focused on the serotonergic net- work in the control of breathing [192]. Some cases of central apnea in childhood are caused by Congenital Central Hypoventilation Syndrome, a rare genetic condition determined by the homeobox gene PHOX2b mutation on chromosome 4p12. A secondary form may occur from developmental malformations such as in Arnold- Chiari type II, Zellweger syndrome, and Leigh Syndrome [192].
        The diagnosis and treatment of Childhood OSA and sleep-re- lated breathing disorders in childhood are to be evaluated by the Physician using a history, examination, and PSG sleep study if needed. Additional testing of laboratory tests, nap study, and repeat nights of a PSG sleep study can be determined from preliminary findings. The examination is to include oro- pharyngeal exam findings. The following are to be considered in the evaluation: nocturnal or day symptoms, oropharyn- geal exam findings, body mass index, growth level, medication usage, sleep environment, and association with other disorders (e.g. Craniofacial disorders, Down Syndrome, Cerebral palsy, Neuromuscular disorders, Chronic Lung Disease, Sickle Cell dis- ease, Central Hypoventriculation Syndrome, Genetic Diseases, and Cardiorespiratory Failure).
         Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/46/7/zsad060/7070629 by guest on 22 September 2024
        
        The Physician/Sleep Fellow in the conduction of the history, exam, and oropharyngeal examination may want to consider a referral for an all-night PSG. Several studies and clinical recom- mendations suggest in the case of moderate/severe OSA in chil- dren suggest management with an adenotonsillectomy surgery. In mild cases of OSA, position therapy and weight reduction with sleep log follow-up are to be conducted. With persistent sleep-re- lated breathing disorders, a positive airway pressure device is recommended. In some cases, pharmacological intervention with nasal steroids and leukotrienes antagonists may be medically successful. Currently, the small amount of literature that focuses on dental appliances and procedures for children with OSA sug- gests deferment to a more empirically validated procedure.
    </Sleep-Disordered_Breathing_in_Children>
    
    <Partial_Arousal_Disorders_of_Sleep_in_a_Pediatric_Population> 
        Section author: Kathy Sexton-Radek.
        Partial arousals disorders of sleep are a group of behaviors
        that occur alongside sleep. There is an abrupt departure from slow-wave sleep or REM sleep that results in transitional states of sleep and wake, which the sleeper is usually amnestic to [194]. Furthermore, the partial arousals are positioned at the beginning of the night in terms of slow-wave sleep incomplete arousals and, during the last or second to last cycle of REM, during the second half of the sleep interval. In general, the factors influencing par- tial arousals are thought to be both internal physiological factors of immature sleep homeostat, dysregulation of circadian rhythm from sleep disorder/disorder, and behavioral factors that reduce overall inhibition such as high stress, anxiety conditions, some medications, substance use, and, commonly, sleep deprivation [195]. Sleep deprivation from sleep loss and fragmentation of sleep schedules pressures the sleep homeostat. Additionally, the pediatric population has higher prevalence due to the maturity of their sleep cycle; also, OSA in children increases their risk for partial arousal from sleep [196, 197].
        The following partial arousals of sleep in the non-rapid eye movement (nREM) sleep cycle occur in slow-wave stages 3 and 4 sleep: sleep terrors, somnambulism, confusional arousals, and sleep-related eating. Sleep Terrors are characterized by a shrill, loud cry and a behavior of marked upset. There is no responsiveness from the sleeper and they are amnestic for the episode(s). Mason et al. [195] described PSG results of a Sleep Terror episode as high-amplitude slow-waves of stage 4 nREM sleep, then a sudden arousal with an admixture of electroen- cephalographic frequencies and muscle movement. Treatments include safety of the environment and the provision of gentle guidance back to bed without waking the sleeper. The preva- lence drops to less than 1% of the adult population for Sleep Terrors; a maturity of the sleep cycle is presumed to facilitate this recovery [195, 198].
        With Confusional Arousals, the pediatric sleeper may experience nighttime and or daytime napping bouts of confusion character- ized by vocalizations, sitting up in bed, decreased responsiveness on awakening, amnestic for the episode, and normal autonomic activity [196]. Mason et al. [195] reported a 4.2% prevalence for Confusional Arousals, which are more common in childhood than adolescence (1%–17% prevalence), Somnambulism with a peak between 8 and 12 years, and 2.2% Sleep Terrors in child- hood. Sleep disorders such as restless legs/periodic limb disor- der or OSA can precipitate confusional partial arousals and other parasomnias [196, 199].
        In Somnambulism, the sleeper is partially awakened in usually the first third of the night, they have vocalizations, move in famil- iar motor movements with decreased responsive, and amnesia for the event(s). The parasomnias typically have a positive family his- tory of parasomnia [195]. Rhythmic Movement Disorder is expressed as a burst from slow-wave sleep with repetitive large muscle movements. Jactatio capitis nocturna (head banging), head roll- ing, and body rocking represent some of the rhythmic movements [197, 200, 201]. The treatment is a thorough clinical study of med- ical history and clinical study of PSG findings. Pharmacological agents that lower arousal threshold, such as selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors, must be considered [194].
        In Sleep-Related Eating partial arousal, the sleeper consumes peculiar food(s) and is amnestic for the event. Fleetham and Flemming [196] report all parts of the sleep cycle and stages 2-3-4 departures with vocalizations. Treatments are behavioral to establish a safety plan to reduce self-injury. Sleep Eating Disorder co-occurs with Somnambulism, Restless legs/Periodic Limb dis- order, and Sleep-Related Breathing Disorder. Prevalence is higher in females than males and in eating disorders versus no eating disorder population [195, 200].
        The REM Behavior Disorder (RBD) emerges from REM sleep, mainly the last third of the night interval. There is no autonomic activ- ity, and the person is responsive to awakening. The prevalence of RBD is estimated at 0.38% of general population. Fleetham and Fleming [196] reported RBD as more common in men. Treatment for RBD is thorough assessment and clinical study, treatment of coexisting condition of Parkinson's disease if evident, and pallia- tive care to reduce factors that may be contributing to the loss of inhibition. Behavioral sleep medicine interventions are effective in treating sleep hygiene, sleep deprivation, and inadequate sleep schedules of RBD patients.
        In Nightmare disorder, the pediatric patient’s partial arousal is from REM sleep of the last third of the night, sometimes occurs with vocalizing. Psychiatric issues must be discerned; Watson et al [202]. identified the use of the Anomalous Sleep Experiences scale to distinguish Nightmare Disorder experiences with and from psychopathology. Treatment considerations included thor- ough medical history, clinical study of PSG, and medication eval- uation to consider threshold-elevating medications (e.g. Lithium, SSRIs, and Antihistamines) that alter REM. Behavioral treatment using Imagery Rehearsal has been successful, as well as CBT [175, 194, 202].
        In the disorder of Sleep Paralysis, the partial arousal from REM sleep occurs from any of the REM episodes. A slight groaning vocalization may occur, and there is no autonomic activity or post-event confusion. There are no movement or injury risk con- cerns [196]. Prevalence figures of 15%–40% among students have been reported [196].
        In summary, REM partial arousals most often occur in the last third of the night. As in nREM partial arousals, REM partial arousals are to be distinguished from other sleep and medical disorders such as seizures with a thorough history, examina- tion, and PSG. Parasomnias are not stereotyped, do not have an automatic component, and have distinguished times of the burst from slow wave or REM sleep by comparison to seizures. General treatment guidelines for the Practitioner with Partial Arousals from sleep (Parasomnias) in a pediatric population is thorough evaluation with history, clinical study of PSG findings, evaluation of current medications and medical conditions of patient, reas- surance, and in some cases such as severe nightmare disorder or RBD, prescribed medications (e.g. Prazosin, Clonidine). Medical
        Reynolds et al. | 11
         Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/46/7/zsad060/7070629 by guest on 22 September 2024
        
        12 | SLEEP, 2023, Vol. 46, No. 7
        treatment and diagnostic issues are comprehensively addressed in Fleetham and Fleming [196], Ferber et al. [203], and Mason et al. [195]. Reviews of Behavioral treatments for pediatric parasomnias can be found in Mindell et al. [198], Sexton-Radek et al. [175], and Galbiati et al. [199].
    </Partial_Arousal_Disorders_of_Sleep_in_a_Pediatric_Population>
    
    <Pediatric_Sleep_and_Neurodevelopmental_Disorders>
        ASD and sleep
        Section author: Beth A. Malow.
        ASD and sleep.
        Current estimates are that 1 in 68 children has an ASD with prevalence rates continuing to rise yearly. In children with ASD, 50%–80% have sleep problems, which, when treated, often have a profoundly positive impact on daytime behaviors in the child and parent functioning. Those with ASD and other neurodevelop- mental conditions have been identified as a high-priority group for sleep research. Others have identified sleep disturbance as a valuable phenotype for defining those with ASD. Therefore, the study of sleep in ASD provides an unprecedented opportunity to work in a rapidly developing field while contributing to the health and well-being of affected individuals and their families.
        Mechanisms are multifactorial; see Figure 3 for a representa- tion of the biological, medical, and behavioral factors involved with ASD and sleep. Basic mechanisms that tie autism and brain chemistry together include differences in circadian regulation patterns, genetic contributors, or arousal patterns. For example, mutations in circadian-relevant genes (such as TIMELESS and CLOCK) affecting gene function are more frequent in patients with ASD than in controls [204]. Individuals with ASD have also been shown to have higher heart rates, including during sleep, than typically developing controls [205].
        • Areas for future research into these mechanisms may include work in genetics (identification of polymorphisms predictive of sleep disturbance in individuals with ASD),
        imaging of brain circuits common to sleep and ASD, com- parison of indicators of arousal (such as heart rate varia- bility, cortisol, and catecholamine levels), or measurement of biomarkers implicated in sleep and ASD (evening or overnight levels of blood, saliva, or urine melatonin or mel- atonin metabolites). Behavioral or medication trials [206] focused on improving sleep may include these measure- ments as biomarkers of treatment success.
        Family systems are also strongly impacted by the birth of a child with significant developmental delays. The dynamics between parents and siblings can be significantly burdened and contrib- ute to sleep disturbance [207]. Emergence of anxiety at bedtime, and the process of implementing rituals and routines all require study to guide intervention and to identify the pathophysiology of sleep disturbance in ASD. See Figure 4 for a sample visual schedule that may be used during an intervention to implement healthy routines.
        • Areas for future research into these mechanisms may include cross-sectional, longitudinal, or interventional studies focused on the relationship between parenting stress and sleep in children with ASD, including behavioral approaches to improve sleep [208].
        Road map for training
        If an MD. . ..
        • As part of your sleep fellowship, seek out rotations where you can get exposure to children, teens, and/or adults with ASD. For children and teens, seek out a developmental medicine clinic in pediatrics, or clinics in child neurology or child psychiatry. For adults, neurology or psychiatry clin- ics may have subspecialty clinics for ASD, or for individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities.
        • Work with a psychologist or another faculty member with expertise in behavioral therapies—including applied
        Figure 3. Biological, medical, and behavioral overlap in ASD and sleep. Visual representation of the biological, medical, and behavioral overlap and the multifactorial nature of ASD and its impact on sleep.
          Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/46/7/zsad060/7070629 by guest on 22 September 2024
        
        behavioral analysis, developing visual schedules, or other routines. This will be helpful in working with individuals with ASD and their family members.
        • Some institutions have LEND (Leadership Education in Neurodevelopmental and Related Disabilities) or UCEDD (University Centers of Excellence in Developmental Disabilities) programs that you can participate in as a postdoctoral fellow (2nd year after sleep fellowship). You can look up participating institutions on these websites.
        LEND website: https://www.aucd.org/template/page. cfm?id=473
        UCEDD website: https://www.aucd.org/directory/directory. cfm?program
        If planning a PhD or in a postdoctoral program. . ..
        • Seek out institutions for graduate or postdoctoral training with IDDRCs - (Intellectual and Developmental Disabilities Research Centers) or neuroscience departments or institutes.
        • Talk with your sleep mentor about getting exposure to training within the IDDRC in neuroscience department/ institute.
        • Getting clinical exposure to patients with ASD (see resources above under MD) will also benefit you in a simi- lar way to getting exposure to sleep patients.
    </Pediatric_Sleep_and_Neurodevelopmental_Disorders>
    
    <ADHD_and_Sleep>
        Section authors: Kristina P. Lenker and Susan Calhoun.
        The prevalence of sleep disturbances and disorders in youth with ADHD is high, ranging from 25% to 70% [209]. Insomnia symptoms are the most frequently parent/self-reported sleep problems, while sleep-disordered breathing, RLS, PLMD, or cir- cadian rhythm sleep disorders are the most common sleep dis- orders. Both ADHD and sleep problems negatively impact many aspects of youths’ lives including risk for psychiatric morbidities
        [210].
        Emerging evidence suggests that there is symptom overlap (e.g.
        inattention, hypoarousal) of sleep problems and ADHD, which may indicate shared underlying neurobiological mechanisms. Indeed, the cortical and brainstem regions most involved in the regulation of sleep/arousal are also the major sites implicated in
        Figure 4. Visual schedule for healthy routines. Sample visual schedule that could be used in an intervention setting to promote healthy implementation of rituals and routines for children.
        Reynolds et al. | 13
          Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/46/7/zsad060/7070629 by guest on 22 September 2024
        
        14 | SLEEP, 2023, Vol. 46, No. 7
        the pathophysiology of ADHD, given their role in the regulation of attentional processes [211]. There is an overlap in the neuro- transmitter systems involved in the regulation of sleep, arousal, and attention; both dopamine and norepinephrine are involved in maintaining activation of the prefrontal cortex during wake- fulness as well as the impact of deficient sleep associated with specific sleep disorders on the prefrontal cortex. The identifica- tion of physiological and behavioral sleep disorders, regulation, and differences early in life may help in the development of phe- notyping of children with ADHD based on the presence of specific sleep disorders [212] that may lead to identification of predictors of ADHD, description of developmental trajectories of ADHD or prediction of the prognosis of ADHD. The development of phe- notype-based treatments will also improve the care of youth with ADHD through the application of specific sleep interven- tions such as cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT-I), chronother- apy, and/or pharmacotherapy. Recent cutting-edge research has proposed that a disruption in normal circadian regulation may be a core mechanism in some youth with ADHD [213] and that the presence of PLMD may be associated with specific behavioral/ neurocognitive phenotypic presentations [214]. Other research is underway to confirm these physiological-behavioral relationships by identifying biomarkers such as heart rate variability or corti- sol levels in ADHD [215]. Recent evidence also suggests that sleep disorders may be related to genetic differences linked to ADHD. Common genetic substrates leading to widespread dopaminergic dysfunction are a possible shared etiopathogenic mechanism for both ADHD and sleep disorders [216]. Moreover, an innate cat- echolaminergic dysregulation or specific alterations in “clock” genes may be common in both ADHD and sleep disorders [217]. Epigenetic studies will be critical in answering whether sleep dis- turbances and disorders play a role in the etiology of ADHD in children.
        The bidirectional relationship between ADHD and sleep dis- turbances poses challenges for clinicians and researchers in the evaluation and development of treatment strategies [218]. From an etiological perspective, the distinction between sleep dis- orders and disturbances in ADHD is blurred given the ongoing debate of whether sleep problems are intrinsic to ADHD, a result due to a comorbid sleep disorder, or cause ADHD-like symptoms that may result in a misdiagnosis. Advances in sleep and ADHD pathophysiology and assessment measures in both fields may impact clinical practice if early identification and treatment of sleep disorders prove to decrease symptom severity and/or need for stimulant medication in children with ADHD. Longitudinal studies are needed to establish whether sleep disturbances in early childhood are a pre-morbid neurophysiological or behavio- ral sign of ADHD [219] while randomized clinical trials addressing ADHD and behavioral sleep disorder overlap should compare the effectiveness of behavioral therapies, use of off-label medications (e.g. sedating antidepressant) and supplements (e.g. melatonin), and examine the PLMD and ADHD overlap and treatment options (iron supplements, gabapentin).
        Future studies including youth with and without ADHD, as well as subclinical ADHD symptoms, are necessary to examine the psychosocial, biologic, epigenetic, contextual factors, and bio- markers that intersect with sleep functioning. It is unclear how sleep problems contribute to clinical, neurocognitive, and psy- chosocial presentations in ADHD, and impacts the persistence of ADHD symptoms over the lifespan. An enhanced understanding of the proposed underlying neurophysiologic systems and rela- tionships between the regulation of sleep, attention, arousal,
        genetic vulnerabilities, and environmental influences on both areas may shed light on shared mechanistic pathways and in turn influence the development of patient-centered, novel ther- apeutic approaches that are translatable to daily clinical practice.
        Special consideration for trainees
        • Gain clinical exposure through working in various spe- cialty clinics (e.g. behavioral health, sleep, developmental pediatrics, and psychiatry) and with psychologists/other faculty members whose expertise is in behavioral thera- pies for sleep problems and ADHD such as behavioral par- ent training or CBT.
        • Seek out working with faculty members in training pro- grams including clinical, school, health, and pediatric psychology.
        • Participate in conferences special interest groups within research institutions.
        • Seek funding from NIMH, NICHD, NINR, NINDS, and PCORI.
    </ADHD_and_Sleep>
    
    <Sleep_and_Public_Health_Policy>
        Pediatric public sleep health research and priorities
        Section authors: Dayna A. Johnson and Daniel Lewin.
        Overview.
        Public health research (PHR) may be considered the final step of translational research. There have been many adults and a few pediatric sleep and circadian health initiatives that have advanced into national and public policy. In pediatric research, there have been some notable advances based on established and emerging science over the past decade, but as with all research in pediatrics, there tends to be a time lag behind adult research. This brief article provides definitions, summarizes some recent pediatric sleep PHR initiatives, poses questions about translation of basic and clinical science to the public health sector, and poses some key priority or gap areas that exist in pediatric sleep and circadian public health.
        Public health research.
        PHR encompasses several methodologies that aim to improve effi- cacy, effectiveness, and efficiency of public health interventions to improve population health. Another important aspect of PHR is to identify the multilevel determinants of health (i.e. social, envi- ronmental, and genetic) which shape population health. PHR can estimate the impact of interventions or guidelines on the health of large communities and populations and guide implementa- tion and tracking of public health initiatives. There are models, frameworks, and theories that can aid in the understanding of sociological, diversity, and economic risks and benefits of health indicators and initiatives. Surveillance and epidemiologic data collection and economic models are some of the key methods to conducting PHR, always an interdisciplinary effort that may include epidemiology, health behavior/education, environmen- tal health, sociology, psychology, implementation specialists, as well as other domain-specific specialists who understand meas- urement of key underlying variables and methodology. Examples of public health initiatives related to sleep and circadian health include: healthy People, 2020 and 2030, the Back-to-Sleep cam- paign for healthy infant sleep [220]; guidelines for sleep duration
         Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/46/7/zsad060/7070629 by guest on 22 September 2024
        
        [221] and healthy school start times [222]. These initiatives are often developed based on epidemiologic surveillance datasets that include pediatric sleep and circadian health data.
        Public health importance of sleep.
        Healthy sleep is a public health priority. Pediatric sleep health was first included in Healthy People 2020 and was expanded in Healthy People 2030 with objectives to (1) increase the proportion of children and high school students who get sufficient sleep, (2) reduce drowsy driving, (3) increase the proportion of infants who are put to sleep on their backs and in a safe sleep environment, and (4) increase the proportion of secondary schools with a start time of 8:30 am or later. Inclusion of sleep was a major advance- ment for the field of sleep and circadian medicine made possible by large surveillance data sets that facilitate longitudinal track- ing and demonstrated a high prevalence of short sleep duration ((less than) 9 hours for children aged 6–12 years and (less than) 8 hours for teens aged 13–18 years) [16]. The preponderance of evidence identified dire consequences of deficient sleep including unhealthy diet and metabolic dysregulation, poorer academic performance, mood disturbance, sleepiness, injury, risky behavioral, and other health consequences [111, 223, 224], aided in the immediate need to make sleep a public health priority.
        Healthy sleep initiatives.
        Championing a public health initiative requires understanding of when a body of scientific evidence is sufficient for large-scale implementation (e.g. safe infant sleep practices). In some cases, public health initiatives may be based on a weaker evidence base and common sense recommendations intended to educate and change behavior (e.g. the food pyramid), which then has the ben- efit of spawning decades of PHR. There is undoubtedly strong evi- dence from clinical and epidemiologic studies that greater screen time, inconsistent bedtimes, physical inactivity, secondhand smoke exposure, minority race, early school start times, lower socioeconomic status, and adverse neighborhood environments are associated with increased risk and disparities in sleep dura- tion, circadian misalignment, and sleep disorders such as OSA [225–231].
        Cultivating public health initiatives and messages requires collaborations by sleep and circadian scientists who can define essential biomarkers and relevant outcome variables, epidemi- ologists, public health implementation expertise in lobbying, marketing to the public, associations, and policymakers to name a few. A recent example is healthy school start times initiatives that draw on indirect science (i.e. impact of deficient sleep), direct science (i.e. outcomes in specific school districts), national advocacy from providers (AAP statement) and activists (e.g. StartSchoolLater.org), and legislative effort championed by pol- iticians (e.g. California, Bill 328). These initiatives have resulted in increases in weeknight sleep duration, optimized sleep period timing, as well as improved school performance and fewer motor vehicle crashes [228].
        Future directions.
        Advancing public sleep and circadian health requires developing interdisciplinary collaborative teams including sleep and circa- dian scientists and public health scientists. There are national data available from many sources developed by the Center for Disease Control (Youth Risk Behavior Survey), National Institutes of Health (NIH; NEXT Generation Study, ECHO, Children’s Health Study), State Departments of Education (youth health and risk
        surveillance studies), The Census Bureau (American Time Use Survey) that require effort, but minimal funding to analyze and contribute to sleep and circadian science. Support for larger scale studies may come from special interest groups (e.g., automobile insurance companies interested in drowsy driving laws); federal agencies (NIH), and funding components such as Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute (PCORI) and the US Department of Education.
        To continue advancing the field of sleep and circadian science with a public health lens, we recommend the following areas for PHR policy:
        • Translate sleep/circadian health to valued public health outcomes
        • Study social determinants including structural barriers such as access to care
        • Drowsy driving laws and guidelines • Lighting in schools
        • Safe places to sleep
        • Supplement regulation
        • Pediatric sleep health education in schools
        • Community sleep awareness campaigns
        • Equating public health recommendations of sleep/circa-
        dian with exercise and nutrition
        • Understand the mechanisms linking sleep/circadian
        health to disease
        • Partner with policymakers to inform public policy
        It is imperative to intervene during these formative years. Improving sleep health and creating safe sleep environments should be a top public health priority. Pursuing the recommen- dations of this article could potentially inform new research and intervention efforts.
    </Sleep_and_Public_Health_Policy>
        
    <Conclusion>
        Section author: Mary A. Carskadon
        The value of this document lies primarily in identifying
        research gaps for studying the roles of sleep and circadian timing for pediatric wellness. No single section provides a deep literature review; however, each includes a rich overview of current knowl- edge, and the cited papers provide an excellent launch point for interested trainees. That said, trainees need to dig deeper and not take for granted what may be presented as ground truth; the low numbers of scientists and clinicians engaged in pediatric sleep and circadian rhythms work increases the propensity to accept conclusions at face value. The field of psychology science has gone far to recognize the need for replication, and we cannot deny the need in our own science as well.
        In the context of pediatrics, the nature of the core behavioral patterns of sleeping and waking are influenced by poverty, climate change, war, trauma, and so forth; as small and large shifts in cul- tural values and opportunities arise, they are likely to play major roles in the kinds of sleep and circadian outcomes we are exam- ining. For example, child sleep before television, Internet, and smartphones, YouTube, and so on occurred on a different play- ing field from today. I also note that the overwhelming amount of information on pediatric sleep and circadian rhythms comes from mostly industrialized, wealthy, and largely white countries, notwithstanding emerging information from other regions of the world, as noted in the opening section of this document high- lighting epidemiological findings from many regions.
        Reynolds et al. | 15
         Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/46/7/zsad060/7070629 by guest on 22 September 2024
        
        16 | SLEEP, 2023, Vol. 46, No. 7
        As you have read this brief overview of the field, its lists of gaps and opportunities, and roadmaps for trainees to use in pursuing research in each area, do not forget that virtually every specialty has roles to play. Whether you intend to train in a medical specialty, you crave fundamental neuroscience research, your interest lies in model organisms, your field is more oriented to omics research, you are drawn to clinical psychology and mental health, you want to focus on sleep disorders, your desire is to use experimental manipu- lations, or many hundreds of other approaches, pediatric sleep, and circadian rhythms research needs you and your skills and creativity.
        One final note is to recommend that all pediatric sleep and circadian scientists/clinicians read a paper written by one of my dissertation advisors. This article has influenced me and my thinking about how cross-sectional studies—which are necessary and form the bulk of our pediatric sleep knowledge—may con- strain or skew our conclusions about developmental processes: “How Can We Learn About Developmental Processes from Cross- Sectional Studies, or Can We,” (HC Kraemer, JA Yesavage, JL Taylor, and D Kupfer. Am J Psychiatry, 157:163-171, 2000).
        I wish you all the rich rewards of scientific exploration!
    </Conclusion>
        
    <other_idc>
        Supplementary Material
        Supplementary material is available at SLEEP online. Acknowledgments
        Dr. Carskadon’s effort on this publication was supported by the National Institute of General Medical Sciences of the National Institutes of Health under Award Number P20GM139743. The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the National Institutes of Health. Dr. Levenson’s effort on this publication was supported by the Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development of the National Institutes of Health under Award Number K23HD087433.
        Disclosure Statement
        None declared.
        References
        1. Buysse DJ. Sleep health: can we define it? Does it matter? Sleep. 2014;37(1):9–17. doi: 10.5665/sleep.3298
        2. Matricciani L, et al. Children’s sleep and health: a meta-review. Sleep Med Rev. 2019;46:136–150. doi: 10.1016/j.smrv.2019.04.011
        3. Hirshkowitz M, et al. National Sleep Foundation’s updated sleep duration recommendations: final report. Sleep Health. 2015;1(4):233–243. doi: 10.1016/j.sleh.2015.10.004
        4. Paruthi S, et al. Pediatric sleep duration consensus statement: a step forward. J Clin Sleep Med. 2016;12(12):1705–1706. doi: 10.5664/jcsm.6368
        5. Guglielmo D, et al. Racial/ethnic sleep disparities in US school- aged children and adolescents: a review of the literature. Sleep Health. 2018;4(1):68–80. doi: 10.1016/j.sleh.2017.09.005
        6. Smith JP, et al. Racial disparities and sleep among preschool aged children: a systematic review. Sleep Health. 2019;5(1):49–57. doi: 10.1016/j.sleh.2018.09.010
        7. Galland BC, et al. Normal sleep patterns in infants and children: a systematic review of observational studies. Sleep Med Rev. 2012;16(3):213–222. doi: 10.1016/j.smrv.2011.06.001
        8. Tham EKH, et al. Variations in longitudinal sleep duration trajectories from infancy to early childhood. Sleep Health. 2021;7:56–64.
        9. Mindell JA, et al. Cross-cultural differences in infant and toddler sleep. Sleep Med. 2010;11(3):274–280. doi: 10.1016/j. sleep.2009.04.012
        10. Schlieber M, et al. The sleeping patterns of Head Start children and the influence on developmental outcomes. Child Care Health Dev. 2018;44(3):462–469. doi: 10.1111/cch.12522
        11. Pena MM, et al. Racial/ethnic and socio-contextual correlates of chronic sleep curtailment in childhood. Sleep. 2016;39(9):1653– 1661. doi: 10.5665/sleep.6086
        12. Friel CP, et al. Child meet phys act screen time sleep guide. Am J Prev Med. 2020;59(4):513–521.
        13. Buxton OM, et al. Sleep in the modern family: protective family routines for child and adolescent sleep. Sleep Health. 2015;1(1):15–27. doi: 10.1016/j.sleh.2014.12.002
        14. El-Sheikh M, et al. Children’s sleep and adjustment over time: the role of socioeconomic context. Child Dev. 2010;81(3):870–883. doi: 10.1111/j.1467-8624.2010.01439.x
        15. Philbrook LE, et al. Sleep and cognitive functioning in childhood: ethnicity, socioeconomic status, and sex as moderators. Dev Psychol. 2017;53(7):1276–1285. doi: 10.1037/dev0000319
        16. Wheaton AG, et al. Short sleep duration among middle school and high school students - United States, 2015. Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2018;67(3):85–90. doi: 10.15585/mmwr.mm6703a1
        17. James S, et al. Disparities in adolescent sleep health by sex and ethnoracial group. SSM Popul Health. 2020;11:100581.
        18. Matthews KA, et al. Sleep in healthy black and white adolescents. Pediatrics. 2014;133(5):e1189–e1196. doi: 10.1542/peds.2013-2399 19. Moore M, et al. Correlates of adolescent sleep time and vari- ability in sleep time: the role of individual and health related characteristics. Sleep Med. 2011;12(3):239–245. doi: 10.1016/j.
        sleep.2010.07.020
        20. Twenge JM, et al. Decreases in self-reported sleep duration among U.S. adolescents 2009-2015 and association with new media screen time. Sleep Med. 2017;39:47–53. doi: 10.1016/j. sleep.2017.08.013
        21. Becker SP, et al. Intraindividual variability of sleep/wake pat- terns in relation to child and adolescent functioning: a system- atic review. Sleep Med Rev. 2017;34:94–121.
        22. Iglowstein I, et al. Sleep duration from infancy to adoles- cence: reference values and generational trends. Pediatrics. 2003;111(2):302–307. doi: 10.1542/peds.111.2.302
        23. Weissbluth M. Naps in children: 6 months–7 years. Sleep. 1995;18(2):82–87. doi: 10.1093/sleep/18.2.82
        24. Mirmiran M, et al. Development of fetal and neonatal sleep and circadian rhythms. Sleep Med Rev. 2003;7(4):321–334. doi: 10.1053/smrv.2002.0243
        25. Rivkees SA. Developing circadian rhythmicity in infants. Pediatr Endocrinol Rev. 2003;1(1):38–45.
        26. Hahn-Holbrook J, et al. Human milk as “chrononutrition”: implications for child health and development. Pediatr Res. 2019;85(7):936–942. doi: 10.1038/s41390-019-0368-x
        27. LeBourgeois MK, et al. Circadian phase and its relationship to nighttime sleep in toddlers. J Biol Rhythms. 2013;28(5):322–331. doi: 10.1177/0748730413506543
        28. Crowley SJ, et al. A longitudinal assessment of sleep timing, cir- cadian phase, and phase angle of entrainment across human adolescence. PLoS One. 2014;9(11):e112199.
        29. Jenni OG, et al. Understanding sleep-wake behavior and sleep disorders in children: the value of a model. Curr Opin Psychiatry. 2006;19(3):282–287. doi: 10.1097/01.yco.0000218599.32969.03
         Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/46/7/zsad060/7070629 by guest on 22 September 2024
        
        30. Kurth S, et al. Development of brain EEG connectivity across early childhood: does sleep play a role? Brain Sci. 2013;3(4):1445– 1460. doi: 10.3390/brainsci3041445
        31. Kurth S, et al. Sleep and early cortical development. Curr Sleep Med Rep. 2015;1(1):64–73. doi: 10.1007/s40675-014-0002-8
        32. Moorman JD, et al. The implications of screen media use for the sleep behavior of children ages 0–5: a systematic review of the literature. Curr Sleep Med Rep. 2019;5(3):164–172.
        33. Siversten B, et al. Delayed sleep phase syndrome in adolescents: prevalence and correlates in a large population based study. BMC Health. 2013;13(1163):1–10.
        34. Garrison MM. The feedback whirlpool of early childhood sleep and behavior problems. Jama Pediatr. 2015;169(6):525–526. doi: 10.1001/jamapediatrics.2015.0356
        35. Bennet L, et al. Waking up too early–the consequences of preterm birth on sleep development. J Physiol. 2018;596(23):5687–5708.
        36. Serón-Ferré M, et al. Circadian rhythms in the fetus. Mol Cell Endocrinol. 2012;349(1):68–75. doi: 10.1016/j.mce.2011.07.039
        37. Wittenbrink N, et al. High-accuracy determination of inter-
        nal circadian time from a single blood sample. J Clin Invest.
        2018;128(9):3826–3839. doi: 10.1172/JCI120874
        38. Woelders T, et al. Daily light exposure patterns reveal phase
        and period of the human circadian clock. J Biol Rhythms.
        2017;32(3):274–286.
        39. Higuchi S, et al. Influence of light at night on melatonin suppres-
        sion in children. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2014;99(9):3298–3303.
        doi: 10.1210/jc.2014-1629
        40. Akacem LD, et al. Sensitivity of the circadian system to eve-
        ning bright light in preschool-age children. Physiol Rep.
        2018;6(5):e13617. doi: 10.14814/phy2.13617
        41. Roenneberg T, et al. A marker for the end of adolescence. Curr
        Biol. 2004;14(24):R1038–R1039. doi: 10.1016/j.cub.2004.11.039
        42. Carskadon MA. Sleep in adolescents: the perfect storm. Pediatr
        Clin North Am. 2011;58(3):637–647. doi: S0031-3955(11)00019-8
        43. Owens J, et al. Insufficient sleep in adolescents and young adults: an update on causes and consequences. Pediatrics.
        2014;134(3):e921–e932.
        44. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Youth Risk
        Behavior Surveillance – United States. 2017;67:1–479. https://
        www.cdc.gov/healthyyouth/data/yrbs/pdf/2017/ss6708.pdf
        45. Beebe DW. Cognitive, behavioral, and functional consequences of inadequate sleep in children and adolescents. Pediatr Clin. 2011;58(3):649–665.
        46. Shochat T, et al. Functional consequences of inadequate sleep in adolescents: a systematic review. Sleep Med Rev. 2014;18(1):75– 87. doi: 10.1016/j.smrv.2013.03.005
        47. Crowley SJ, et al. An update on adolescent sleep: new evidence informing the perfect storm model. J Adol. 2018;67:55–65.
        48. Crowley SJ, et al. Free-running circadian period in adoles- cents and adults. J Sleep Res. 2018;27(5):e12678. doi: 10.1111/ jsr.12678
        49. Meltzer LJ, et al. Changing school start times: impact on sleep in primary and secondary school students. Sleep. 2021;44(7).
        50. Alfonsi V, et al. Later school start time: the impact of sleep on academic performance and health in the adolescent popula- tion. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17(7):2574
        51. Wahlstrom K, et al. Examining the impact of later school start times on the health and academic performance of high school students: a multi-site study. Center for Applied Research and Educational Improvement. St Paul, MN: University of Minnesota; 2014.
        52. Wolfson AR, et al. A survey of factors influencing high school starttimes. NASSP Bull. 2005;89(642):47–66.
        53. Gruber R. School-based sleep education programs: a knowl- edge-to-action perspective regarding barriers, proposed solu- tions, and future directions. Sleep Med Rev. 2017;36:13–28. doi: 10.1016/j.smrv.2016.10.001
        54. Blunden SL, et al. Are sleep education programs successful? The case for improved and consistent research efforts. Sleep Med Rev. 2012;16(4):355–370. doi: 10.1016/j.smrv.2011.08.002
        55. Blunden S, et al. Lessons learned from sleep education in schools: a review of dos and don’ts. J Clin Sleep Med. 2015;11(6):671–680. doi: 10.5664/jcsm.4782
        56. Cassoff J, et al. School-based sleep promotion programs: effec- tiveness, feasibility and insights for future research. Sleep Med Rev. 2013;17(3):207–214. doi: 10.1016/j.smrv.2012.07.001
        57. M Z, et al. Insomnia disorder in adolescence: diagnosis, impact, and treatment. Sleep Med Rev. 2018;39:12–24.
        58. Johnson EO, et al. Epidemiology of DSM-IV insomnia in adoles- cence: lifetime prevalence, chronicity, and an emergent gender difference. Pediatrics. 2006;117(2):e247–e256.
        59. Åslund L, et al. Cognitive and behavioral interventions to improve sleep in school-age children and adolescents: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Clin Sleep Med. 2018;14(11):1937– 1947. doi: 10.5664/jcsm.7498
        60. Dewald-Kaufmann J, et al. Cognitive behavioral therapy for insomnia (CBT-i) in school-aged children and adolescents. Sleep Med Clin. 2019;14(2):155–165.
        61. Meltzer LJ, et al. A scoping review of behavioral treatments for pediatric insomnia. Sleep Med Rev. 2020;56:101410.
        62. Harvey AG. A transdiagnostic intervention for youth sleep and circadian problems. Cogn Behav Pract. 2016;23(3):341–355.
        63. Harvey AG, et al. Modifying the impact of eveningness chrono- type (“night-owls”) in youth: a randomized controlled trial. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2018;57(10):742–754.
        64. Dong L, et al. A transdiagnostic sleep and circadian interven- tion for adolescents: six-month follow-up of a randomized controlled trial. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2020;61:653–661. doi: 10.1111/jcpp.13154
        65. Harvey AG, et al. Treating Sleep Problems: A Transdiagnostic Approach. New York, NY: Guilford Publications; 2017
        66. Honaker SM, et al. The Sleep Checkup: sleep screening, guid- ance, and management in pediatric primary care. Clin Pract Pediatr Psychol. 2018;6(3):201.
        67. Owens JA. The practice of pediatric sleep medicine: results of a community survey. Pediatrics. 2001;108(3):e51–e51.
        68. Meltzer LJ, et al. Sleep problems and sleep disorders in pedi- atric primary care. Treat Recomm Persistence Health Care Util. 2014;10(4):421–426.
        69. Sevecke JR, et al. It takes a village: multidisciplinary approach to screening and prevention of pediatric sleep issues. J Med Sci. 2018;6(3):77.
        70. Honaker SM, et al. Sleep in pediatric primary care: a review of the literature. Sleep Med Rev. 2016;25:31–39. doi:10.1016/j. smrv.2015.01.004
        71. Faruqui F, et al. Sleep disorders in children: a national assess- ment of primary care pediatrician practices and perceptions. Pediatrics. 2011;128(3):539–546.
        72. Campo JV, et al. Integration of pediatric behavioral health ser- vices in primary care: improving access and outcomes with col- laborative care. Can J Psychiatry. 2018;63(7):432–438.
        73. Thomas A, et al. Where are the behavioral sleep medicine provid- ers and where are they needed? Geogr Assess. 2016;14(6):687–698. 74. Kravitz RM. Shortage of Pediatric Sleep Specialist Puts Onus on Primary Care Doctors. https://www.aappublications.org/
        news/2017/08/31/Sleep083117. Accessed June 21, 2021.
        Reynolds et al. | 17
         Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/46/7/zsad060/7070629 by guest on 22 September 2024
        
        18 | SLEEP, 2023, Vol. 46, No. 7
        75. Balvin N, et al. The adolescent brain: a second window of oppor- tunity – A compendium, Miscellanea, UNICEF Office of Research - Innocenti, Florence. 2017.
        76. Somerville LH. The teenage brain: sensitivity to social evalua- tion. Curr Dir. 2013;22(2):121–127.
        77. Steinberg LA. A social neuroscience perspective on adolescent risk-taking. Dev Rev. 2008;28:78–106.
        78. Luciana M, et al. Incentive motivation, cognitive control, and the adolescent brain: is it time for a paradigm shift? Child Dev Perspect. 2012;6(4):392–399.
        79. McCrae RR, et al. Nature over nurture: temperament, personal- ity, and life span development. J Pers Soc Psychol. 2000;78(1):173– 186. doi: 10.1037//0022-3514.78.1.173.
        80. Spielberg JM, et al. Exciting fear in adolescence: does puber- tal development alter threat processing? Dev Cogn Neurosci. 2014;8:86–95.
        81. Hagenauer MH, et al. Adolescent sleep patterns in humans and laboratory animals. Horm Behav. 2013;64(2):270–279.
        82. Carskadon MA. The second decade. In: Guilleminault C, ed. Sleep and Waking Disorders. Menlo Park: Addison Wesley.
        83. Feinberg I, et al. Sleep EEG changes during adolescence: an index of a fundamental brain reorganization. Brain Cogn. 2010;72(1):56–65.
        84. Zhang ZY, et al. Longitudinal analysis of sleep spindle matu- ration from childhood through late adolescence. J Neurosci. 2021;41(19):4253–4261. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2370-20. 2021.
        85. Galván A. The need for sleep in the adolescent brain. Trends Cogn Sci. 2020;24(1):79–89.
        86. Simon EB, et al. Sleep loss and the socio-emotional brain. Trends Cogn Sci. 2020;24(6):435–450.
        87. Talbot LS, et al. Sleep deprivation in adolescents and adults: changes in affect. Emotion. 2010;10(6):831.
        88. Baum KT, et al. Sleep restriction worsens mood and emo- tion regulation in adolescents. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2014;55(2):180–190.
        89. Booth SA, et al. Sleep duration and mood in adolescents: an experimental study.Sleep. 2021;44(5):zsaa253. doi: 10.1093/ sleep/zsaa253.
        90. Tomaso CC, et al. The effect of sleep deprivation and restriction on mood, emotion, and emotion regulation: three meta-analy- ses in one. Sleep. 2021;44(6):zsaa289.
        91. Shen L, et al. Sleep and affect in adolescents: bidirectional daily associations over 28‐day ecological momentary assessment.. J Sleep Res. 2022;31(2):e13491.
        92. Gillett G, et al. Sleep and circadian rhythm actigraphy measures, mood instability and impulsivity: a systematic review. J Psychiatr Res. 2021;144:66–79.
        93. Logan RW, et al. Impact of sleep and circadian rhythms on addic- tion vulnerability in adolescents. Biol Psychiatry. 2018;83(12):987– 996. doi:10.1016/j.biopsych.2017.11.035.
        94. Porras-Segovia A, et al. Contribution of sleep deprivation to sui- cidal behaviour: a systematic review. Sleep Med Rev. 2019;44:37– 47. doi:10.1016/j.smrv.2018.12.005
        95. Bauducco SV, et al. Bidirectional associations between adoles- cents’ sleep problems and impulsive behavior over time. Sleep Med X. 2019;1:100009. doi: 10.1016/j.sleepx.2019.100009.
        96. Partin RD, et al. Sleep problems and self-control: an examination of reciprocal effects across childhood and adolescence. J Crim Justice. 2022;83:101975.
        97. Owens JA, et al. Effect of energy drink and caffeinated beverage consumption on sleep, mood, and performance in children and adolescents. Nutr Rev. 2014;72(suppl_1):65–71.
        98. Meltzer LJ, et al. Pediatric sleep health: It matters, and so does how we define it. Sleep Med Rev. 2021;57:101425. doi: 10.1016/j. smrv.2021.101425.
        99. Watling J, et al. Sleep loss and affective functioning: more than just mood. Behav Sleep Med. 2017;15(5):394–409.
        100. Konjarski M, et al. Reciprocal relationships between daily sleep and mood: a systematic review of naturalistic prospective stud- ies. Sleep Med Rev. 2018;42:47–58.
        101. Bacaro V, et al. Sleep duration and obesity in adulthood: an updated systematic review and meta-analysis. Obes Res Clin Pract. 2020;14:301–309. doi: 10.1016/j.orcp.2020.03.004
        102. Li L, et al. Sleep duration and obesity in children: a systematic review and meta-analysis of prospective cohort studies. J Pediatr Child Health. 2017;53:378–385. doi: 10.1111/jpc.13434
        103. Itani O, et al. Short sleep duration and health outcomes: a sys- tematic review, meta-analysis, and meta-regression. Sleep Med. 2017;32:246–256. doi: 10.1016/j.sleep.2016.08.006
        104. Quist JS, et al. Sleep and cardiometabolic risk in children and adolescents. Sleep Med Rev. 2016;29:76–100. doi: 10.1016/j. smrv.2015.09.001
        105. Arble DM, et al. Impact of sleep and circadian disruption on energy balance and diabetes: a summary of workshop discus- sions. Sleep. 2015;38:1849–1860. doi: 10.5665/sleep.5226
        106. McHill AW, et al. Role of sleep and circadian disruption on energy expenditure and in metabolic predisposition to human obesity and metabolic disease. Obes Rev. 2017;18:15–24. doi: 10.1111/ obr.12503
        107. Al Khatib HK, et al. The effects of partial sleep deprivation on energy balance: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Eur J Clin Nutr. 2017;71:614–624. doi: 10.1038/ejcn.2016.201
        108. Hart CN, et al. Changes in children’s sleep duration on food intake, weight, and leptin. Pediatrics. 2013;132:e14731473– e147e1480. doi: 10.1542/peds.2013-1274
        109. Simon SL, et al. Sweet/dessert foods are more appealing to adoles- cents after sleep restriction. PLoS One. 2015;10:e01154340115434. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0115434
        110. Arble DM, et al. Circadian timing of food intake contributes to weight gain. Obesity. 2009;17(11):2100–2102. doi: 10.1038/ oby.2009.264
        111. Miller AL, et al. Sleep patterns and obesity in childhood. Curr Opin Endocrinol Diabetes Obes. 2015;22:41–47.
        112. Danielsson K, et al. Delayed sleep phase disorder in a Swedish cohort of adolescents and young adults: prevalence and associ- ated factors. Chronbiol Int. 2016;10:1331–1339.
        113. Lovato N, et al. Delayed sleep phase disorder in an Australian school based sample of adolescents. J Clin Sleep Med. 2013;9:939– 944. doi: 10.5664/jcsm.2998
        114. Gradisar M, et al. Assessment and treatment of delayed sleep phase disorder in adolescents: recent innovations and cautions. Sleep Med Clinics. 2014;9:199–210.
        115. Richardson C, et al. A randomised controlled trial of bright light therapy and morning activity for adolescents and young adults with delayed sleep-wake phase disorder. Sleep Med. 2018;45:114– 123. doi: 10.1016/j.sleep.2018.02.001
        116. Blake MJ, et al. Who benefits from adolescent sleep interven- tions? Moderators of treatment efficacy in a randomized con- trolled trial of a cognitive-behavioral and mindfulness-based group sleep intervention for at-risk adolescents. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2018;59:637–649.
        117. Bonnar D, et al. Evaluation of novel school-based interventions for adolescent sleep problems: does parental involvement and bright light improve outcomes? Sleep Health. 2015;1:66–74. doi: 10.1016/j.sleh.2014.11.002
         Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/46/7/zsad060/7070629 by guest on 22 September 2024
        
        118. Illingworth G, et al. The Teensleep study: the effectiveness of a school-based sleep education programme at improving early adolescent sleep. Sleep Med X. 2020;2:100011.
        119. Micic G, et al. Readiness to change and commitment as predic- tors of therapy compliance in adolescents with delayed sleep- wake phase disorder. Sleep Med. 2019;55:48–55. doi: 10.1016/j. sleep.2018.12.002
        120. Auger RR, et al. Clinical practice guidelines for the treatment of intrinsic circadian rhythm sleep-wake disorders: advanced sleep-wake phase disorder (ASWPD), delayed sleep-wake phase disorder (DSWPD), non-24-hour sleep-wake rhythm disorder (N24SWD), and irregular sleep-wake rhythm disorder (ISWRD): an update. J Clin Sleep Med. 2015;11:1199–1236.
        121.Mantle D. Immediate-release supplemental melatonin for delayed sleep phase disorder in children: an overview. Br J Neurosc Nurs. 2019;15:32–39.
        122. Bauducco S, et al. Chronotype, circadian rhythms and mood. Curr Opin Psychol. 2020;34:77–83.
        123. Byars KC, et al. Parental functioning and pediatric sleep distur- bance: an examination of factors associated with parenting stress in children clinically referred for evaluation of insomnia. Sleep Med. 2011;12(9):898–905. doi: 10.1016/j.sleep.2011.05.002
        124.Roberts RE, et al. Chronic insomnia and its negative conse- quences for health and functioning of adolescents: a 12-month prospective study. J Adolesc Health. 2008;42(3):294–302. doi: 10.1016/j.jadohealth.2007.09.016
        125. Blank M, et al. Health correlates of insomnia symptoms and comorbid mental disorders in a nationally representative sam- ple of US adolescents. Sleep. 2015;38(2):197–204. doi: 10.5665/ sleep.4396
        126. Tietze AL, et al. Sleep disturbances in children with multiple disabilities. Sleep Med Rev. 2012;16(2):117–127. doi: 10.1016/j. smrv.2011.03.006
        127.Owens JA, et al. Pediatric insomnia. Pediatr Clin North Am. 2011;58(3):555–569. doi: 10.1016/j.pcl.2011.03.011
        128. Blake MJ, et al. Systematic review and meta-analysis of adoles- cent cognitive-behavioral sleep interventions. Clin Child Fam Psychol Rev. 2017;20(3):227–249. doi: 10.1007/s10567-017-0234-5
        129. Meltzer LJ, et al. Systematic review and meta-analysis of behav- ioral interventions for pediatric insomnia. J Pediatr Psychol. 2014;39(8):932–948. doi: 10.1093/jpepsy/jsu041
        130. Tikotzky L, et al. The role of cognitive-behavioral therapy in behavioral childhood insomnia. Sleep Med. 2010;11(7):686–691. doi: 10.1016/j.sleep.2009.11.017
        131.Edinger JD, et al. Cognitive–behavioral therapy for primary insomnia. Clin Psychol Rev. 2005;25(5):539–558. doi: 10.1016/j. cpr.2005.04.003
        132. Owens JA, et al. Use of pharmacotherapy for insomnia in child psychiatry practice: a national survey. Sleep Med. 2010;11(7):692– 700. doi: 10.1016/j.sleep.2009.11.015
        133. Barrett TJ, et al. To sleep or not to sleep: a systematic review of the literature of pharmacological treatments of insomnia in children and adolescents with attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2013;23(10):640–647.
        134. Owens JA, et al. Pharmacologic treatment of pediatric insom- nia. Child Adolesc Psychiatr Clin N Am. 2009;18(4):1001–1016. doi: 10.1016/j.chc.2009.04.009
        135. Wei S, et al. Efficacy and safety of melatonin for sleep onset insomnia in children and adolescents: a meta-analysis of ran- domized controlled trials. Sleep Med. 2020;68:1–8. doi: 10.1016/j. sleep.2019.02.017
        136.Fernandez-Mendoza J, et al. Natural history of insomnia symptoms in the transition from childhood to adolescence:
        population rates, health disparities and risk factors. Sleep.
        2021;44(3):zsaa187.
        137. Picchietti DL, et al. Pediatric restless legs syndrome diagnostic
        criteria: an update by the International Restless Legs Syndrome
        Study Group. Sleep Med. 2013;14:1253–1259.
        138. Picchietti DL. Restless legs syndrome and periodic limb move-
        ment disorder in children. Basow DS, ed. UpToDate. Waltham,
        MA: UpToDate; 2023.
        139. Picchietti D, et al. Restless legs syndrome: prevalence and impact
        in children and adolescents - the Peds REST study. Pediatrics.
        2007;120:253–266. doi: 10.1542/peds.2006-2767
        140. Pennestri MH, et al. Childhood restless legs syndrome: a longi- tudinal study of prevalence and familial aggregation. J Sleep Res.
        2020;30(3):e13161.
        141. Picchietti DL, et al. Pediatric restless legs syndrome and peri-
        odic limb movement disorder: parent-child pairs. Sleep Med.
        2009;10:925–931. doi: 10.1016/j.sleep.2008.10.006
        142. Al-Shawwa B, et al. Limb movements during sleep in children: effects of age, sex, and iron status in more than 1,000 patients referred to a pediatric sleep center. J Clin Sleep Med. 2020;16:49–
        54. doi: 10.5664/jcsm.8120
        143. Picchietti DL, et al. Pediatric restless legs syndrome: anal-
        ysis of symptom descriptions and drawings. J Child Neurol.
        2011;26:1365–1376. doi: 10.1177/0883073811405852
        144. Stubbs PH, et al. Tools for the assessment of pediatric restless
        legs syndrome. Front Psychiatry. 2020;11:356.
        145. Picchietti D, et al. Early manifestations of restless legs syndrome
        in childhood and adolescence. Sleep Med. 2008;9:770–781.
        146. DelRosso L, et al. Consensus diagnostic criteria for a newly defined pediatric sleep disorder: restless sleep disorder (RSD.
        Sleep Med. 2020;75:335–340.
        147. Romero-Peralta S, et al. Emerging concepts of the pathophysi-
        ology and adverse outcomes of restless legs syndrome. Chest.
        2020;158:1218–1229. doi: 10.1016/j.chest.2020.03.035
        148. Dye TJ, et al. Outcomes of long-term iron supplementation in pediatric restless legs syndrome/periodic limb movement dis- order (RLS/PLMD. Sleep Med. 2017;32:213–219. doi: 10.1016/j.
        sleep.2016.01.008
        149. Dye TJ, et al. How does one choose the correct pharma- cotherapy for a pediatric patient with restless legs syn- drome and periodic limb movement disorder?: expert Guidance. Expert Opin Pharmacother. 2019;20:1535–1538. doi: 10.1080/14656566.2019.1629418
        150. DelRosso LM, et al. Clinical efficacy and safety of intravenous ferric carboxymaltose treatment of pediatric restless legs syndrome and periodic limb movement disorder. Sleep Med. 2021;87:114–118. doi: 10.1016/j.sleep.2021.08.030
        151. Pullen SJ, et al. Psychiatric comorbidity in children and adoles- cents with restless legs syndrome: a retrospective study. J Clin Sleep Med. 2011;7:587–596. doi: 10.5664/jcsm.1456
        152. Ingram DG, et al. Intravenous iron therapy in the pediatric sleep clinic: a single institution experience. J Clin Sleep Med. 2022;18(11):2545–2551. doi: 10.5664/jcsm.10152
        153. DelRosso LM, et al. Comparison between oral ferrous sulfate and intravenous ferric carboxymaltose in children with restless sleep disorder. Sleep. 2021;44(2). doi: 10.1093/sleep/zsaa155
        154.Kanney ML, et al. Rethinking bedtime resistance in children with autism: is restless legs syndrome to blame? J Clin Sleep Med. 2020;16(12):2029–2035. doi: 10.5664/jcsm.8756
        155. Gurbani N, et al. Improvement of parasomnias after treatment of restless leg syndrome/ periodic limb movement disorder in children. J Clin Sleep Med. 2019;15:743–748. doi: 10.5664/ jcsm.7766
        Reynolds et al. | 19
         Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/46/7/zsad060/7070629 by guest on 22 September 2024
        
        20 | SLEEP, 2023, Vol. 46, No. 7
        156. Riar SK, et al. Restless legs syndrome in children with chronic kidney disease. Pediatr Nephrol. 2013;28(5):773–795. doi: 10.1007/ s00467-013-2408-9
        157. Salminen AV, et al.; International Restless Legs Syndrome Study Group (IRLSSG). Consensus guidelines on rodent models of rest- less legs syndrome. Mov Disord. 2021;36(3):558–569. doi: 10.1002/ mds.28401
        158. Benca RM. Sleep in psychiatric disorders. Neurol Clin. 1996;14(4):739–764. doi: 10.1016/s0733-8619(05)70283-8
        159. Pizza F, et al. Clinical and polysomnographic course of childhood narcolepsy with cataplexy. Brain. 2013;136(12):3787–3795. doi: 10.1093/brain/awt277
        160. Bassetti CLA, et al. Narcolepsy — clinical spectrum, aetio- pathophysiology, diagnosis and treatment. Nat Rev Neurol. 2019;15(9):519–539. doi: 10.1038/s41582-019-0226-9
        161. Dauvilliers Y, et al. Age at onset of narcolepsy in two large populations of patients in France and Quebec. Neurology. 2001;57(11):2029–2033. doi: 10.1212/wnl.57.11.2029
        162. Luca G, et al.; European Narcolepsy Network. Clinical, polysom- nographic and genome-wide association analyses of narcolepsy with cataplexy: a European Narcolepsy Network study. J Sleep Res. 2013;22(5):482–495. doi: 10.1111/jsr.12044
        163.Rocca F, et al. Narcolepsy during childhood: an update. Neuropediatrics.2015;46(03):181–198.doi:10.1055/s-0035-1550152 164. Peacock J, et al. Narcolepsy: clinical features, co-morbidities and
        treatment. Indian J Med Res. 2010;131(2):338.
        165.Thebault S, et al. Narcolepsy and H1N1 vaccination: a
        link? Curr Opin Pulm Med. 2013;19(6):587–593. doi: 10.1097/
        MCP.0b013e328365af97
        166. Moscovitch A, et al. The positive diagnosis of narcolepsy and narcolepsy’s borderland. Neurology. 1993;43(1 Part 1):55. doi: 10.1212/WNL.43.1_Part_1.55
        167.Morse AM. Narcolepsy in children and adults: a guide to improved recognition, diagnosis and management. Med Sci. 2019;7(12):106. doi: 10.3390/medsci7120106
        168. Pisko J, et al. Nightmares in narcolepsy: underinvestigated symptom? Sleep Med. 2014;15(8):967–972. doi: 10.1016/j. sleep.2014.03.006
        169. Bassetti CLA, et al. European guideline and expert statements on the management of narcolepsy in adults and children. Eur J Neurol. 2021;28(9):2815–2830. doi: 10.1111/ene.14888
        170. Nevsimalova S. The diagnosis and treatment of pediatric nar- colepsy. Curr Neurol Neurosci Rep. 2014;14(8):469. doi: 10.1007/ s11910-014-0469-1
        171. Maski K, et al. Treatment of central disorders of hypersomno- lence: an American Academy of Sleep Medicine clinical practice guideline. J Clin Sleep Med. 2021;17(9):1881–1893. doi: 10.5664/ jcsm.9328
        172. Blackwell JE, et al. Paediatric narcolepsy: a review of diagnosis and management. Arch Dis Child. 2022;107(1):7–11. doi: 10.1136/ archdischild-2020-320671
        173. Maski K, et al. Beyond daytime sleepiness: medical, behavioral, psychiatric, and sleep co-morbid conditions associated with pediatric narcolepsy. Curr Sleep Med Rep. 2016;2(1):31–37. doi: 10.1007/s40675-016-0032-5
        174. Marcus CL, et al.; American Academy of Pediatrics. Diagnosing and management of childhood obstructive sleep apnea syndrome. Pediatrics. 2012;130(3):576–584. doi: 10.1542/ peds.2012-1671
        175. Sexton-Radek K, et al. Sleep Disorders: Elements, History, Treatments, and Research. Santa Barbara, CA: Praeger Press; 2022.
        176.Hoban TF. Sleep disorders in children. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 2010;1184:1–14. doi: 10.1111/j.1749-6632.2009.05112.x
        177. Narayanasamy S, et al. Pediatric sleep-disordered breathing: a narrative review. Pediatr Med. 2019;2(52):52–52. doi: 10.21037/ pm.2019.09.05
        178. Paruthi S, et al. Consensus statement of the American Academy of Sleep Medicine on the recommended amount of sleep for healthy children: methodology and discussion. J Sleep Med. 2011;12(11):1549–1561.
        179. Kang M, et al. Trends in diagnosing obstructive sleep apnea in pediatrics. Children. 2022;9:306. doi: 10.3390/children9030306.
        180. Kennedy JD, et al. Reduced neurocognition in children who snore. Pediatr Pulmonol. 2009;37:330–337.
        181. Duman D, et al. Impaired right ventricular function in adenoton- sillar hypertrophy. Int J Cardiovasc Imaging. 2008;24:261–267. 182. Strohl KP, et al. Obstructive sleep apnea in family members. N
        Engl J Med. 1975;299:969–973.
        183. Mathre R, et al. Family studies in patients with sleep apnea-hy-
        popnea syndrome. Intern Med. 1995;122:174–178.
        184. Riha RL, et al. Tumour necrosis factor-alpha (-308) gene poly- morphism is obstructive sleep apnoea-hypopnoea syndrome.
        Eur Respir J. 2005;26:673–678.
        185. Ford ES, et al. C-reactive protein and body mass index in chil-
        dren: findings from the Third National Health and Nutrition
        Examination Survey. 1988-1998. J Pediatr. 2001;138:487–492. 186. Khayat A, et al. Polysomnographic findings in infant Pierre Robin sequence. Ann Thorac Med. 2017;12:25–29. doi: 10.4103/1817-
        1737.197770
        187. Gozal D. Obstructive sleep apnea in children: implications for the developing central nervous system. Semin Pediatr Neurol. 2008;15(27):100–106. doi: 10.1016/j.spen.2008.03.006
        188. Mbulo L, et al. Secondhand smoke exposure at home among one billion children in twenty-one countries: findings from the Global Adult Tobacco Survey (GATS. Tob Control. 2016;25:95–100.
        189.Kothare SV, et al. Quality measures for the care of pedi- atric patients with obstructive sleep apnea. J Sleep Med. 2015;11(3):385–404.
        190. Gozal D, et al. Treatment of obstructive sleep apnea in children: handling the unknown with precision. J Clin Med. 2020;9:888. www.mdpi.com/journal/jcm
        191. Thomas S, et al. You cannot hit snooze on OSA: sequelae of pedi- atric/obstructive sleep apnea. Children. 2022;9:261. doi: 10.3390/ children9020261
        192. Kotagal S, et al. Pediatric sleep-wake disorders. In: Avidan AY, ed. Review of Sleep Medicine. Philadelphia, PA: Elsevier Publishers; 2018:348–372.
        193. Hughes BH, et al. Sleep related breathing disorder: clinical fea- tures and evaluation. In: Avidan AY, ed. Review of Sleep Medicine. Philadelphia, PA: Elsevier Publishers; 2018:150–163.
        194. Kotagal S, et al. Pediatric sleep-wake disorders. In: Avidan AY, ed. Review of Sleep Medicine. Philadelphia, PA: Elsevier; 2012:348–372. 195. Mason TBA, et al. Pediatric insomnias. Sleep. 2007;30(2):141–151.
        doi: 10.1093/sleep/30.2.141
        196. Fleetham JA, et al. Parasomnias. Can Med Assoc J. 2014;186(8):E27
        8–E280.
        197. Goh DY, et al. Sleep architecture and respiratory disturbances in
        children with obstructive sleep apnea. Am J Respir Crit Care Med.
        1999;162:682–686.
        198.Mindell JA, et al.; American Academy of Sleep Medicine.
        Behavioral treatment of bedtime problems and night wakings
        in infants and young children. Sleep. 2006;29(10):1263–1276. 199. Galbiati A, et al. Behavioral and cognitive-behavioral treatment
        of parasomnias. Behav Neurol. 2015. Article no.: 786928. 200.Berry RB, et al. Sleep Medicine Pearls. 3rd ed. Philadelphia, PA:
        Sanders Elsevier; 2015.
         Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/46/7/zsad060/7070629 by guest on 22 September 2024
        
        201. Bonnet MH, et al. EEG arousal norms by age. J Clin Sleep Med. 2007;3(3):271–274.
        202. Watson D, et al. Explicating the psychopathological correlates of anomalouos sleep experience. Psychol Conscious Theory Res Pract. 2015;2(1):57–78.
        203. Ferber R, et al. Principles and Practice of Sleep Medicine in the Child. Philadelphia, PA: Sanders Elsevier; 1995.
        204. Yang Z, et al. Circadian-relevant genes are highly poly- morphic in autism spectrum disorder patients. Brain Dev. 2016;38(1):91–99.
        205. Harder R, et al. Heart rate variability during sleep in children with autism spectrum disorder. Clin Auton Res. 2016;26(6):423–432.
        206. Rossignol DA, et al. Melatonin in autism spectrum disorders: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Dev Med Child Neurol. 2011;53(9):783–792.
        207. Richdale AL. Sleep problems in autism: prevalence, cause, and intervention. Dev Med Child Neurol. 1999;41(1):60–66.
        208. Malow BA, et al. Parent-based sleep education for children with autism spectrum disorders. J Autism Dev Disord. 2014;44(1):216– 228. doi: 10.1007/s10803-013-1866-z
        209. Polanczyk GV, et al. ADHD prevalence estimates across three decades: an updated systematic review and meta-regression analysis. Int J Epidemiol. 2014;43(2):434–442. doi: 10.1093/ije/ dyt261
        210. Becker SP, et al. Advancing a biopsychosocial and contextual model of sleep in adolescence: a review and introduction to the special issue. J Youth Adolesc. 2015;44(2):239–270. doi: 10.1007/ s10964-014-0248-y
        211. Becker SP, et al. Difficult to bed and difficult to rise: complex interplay among ADHD, sleep, and adolescence. ADHD Rep. 2017;25(1):7–13.
        212. Gruber R, et al. Instability of sleep patterns in children with attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2000;39(4):495–501. doi: 10.1097/00004583- 200004000-00019
        213. Coogan AN, et al. A systematic review of circadian function, chronotype and chronotherapy in attention deficit hyperactiv- ity disorder. Atten Deficit Hyperact Disord. 2017;9(3):129–147.
        214. Frye SS, et al. Neurocognitive and behavioral significance of periodic limb movements during sleep in adolescents with attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder. Sleep. 2018. 41(10). doi: 10.1093/sleep/zsy129
        215.Kooij S. Circadian Rhythm and Sleep in ADHD – Cause or Life Style Factor? Paris, France: European College of Neuropsychopharmacology (ECNP); 2017.
        216. Gruber R, et al. Sleep and COMT polymorphism in ADHD chil- dren: preliminary actigraphic data. J Am Acad Child Adolesc
        Psychiatry. 2006;45:982–989. doi: 10.1097/01.chi.0000220848.
        48650.10
        217. Dueck A, et al. The role of sleep problems and circadian clock genes in attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder and mood dis- orders during childhood and adolescence: an update. J Neural Transm. 2017;124(S1):127–138.
        218. Owens JA. Clinical overview of sleep and Attention-Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder in children and adolescents. J Can Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2009;18(2):92–102.
        219. Gregory AM, et al. ADHD and sleep quality: longitudinal anal- yses from childhood to early adulthood in a twin cohort. J Clin Child Adolesc Psychol. 2017;46(2):284–294.
        220. American Academy of Pediatrics. Reduce the risk of SIDS and suf- focation. 2017; accessed online 2021.
        221. Paruthi S, et al. Consensus statement of the American Academy of Sleep Medicine on the recommended amount of sleep for healthy children: methodology and discussion. J Clin Sleep Med 2016;12:1549–1561.
        222. G ASW, et al. School start times for adolescents. Pediatrics. 2014;134:642–649.
        223. Tambalis KD, et al. Insufficient sleep duration is associated with dietary habits, screen time, and obesity in children. J Clin Sleep Med 2018;14:1689–1696.
        224.Perez-Lloret S, et al. A multi-step pathway connecting short sleep duration to daytime somnolence, reduced attention, and poor academic performance: an exploratory cross-sectional study in teenagers. J Clin Sleep Med 2013;9:469–473.
        225. Bagley EJ, et al. Community violence concerns and adolescent sleep. Sleep Health. 2016;2:57–62.
        226. Wang R, et al. Associations among neighborhood, race, and sleep apnea severity in children. A six-city analysis. Ann Am Thorac Soc. 2017;14:76–84. doi: 10.1513/AnnalsATS.201609-662OC
        227. Singh GK, et al. Rising prevalence and neighborhood, social, and behavioral determinants of sleep problems in US children and adolescents, 2003-2012. Sleep Disord. 2013;2013:394320.
        228. Wheaton AG, et al. School start times, sleep, behavioral, health, and academic outcomes: a review of the literature. J Sch Health. 2016;86:363–381.
        229. Wheaton AG, et al. Sleep duration and injury-related risk behav- iors among high school students–United States, 2007-2013. Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2016;65:337–341.
        230. Milan S, et al. The context of preschool children’s sleep: racial/ ethnic differences in sleep locations, routines, and concerns. J Fam Psychol. 2007;21:20.
        231. Hale L, et al. A longitudinal study of preschoolers’ lan- guage-based bedtime routines, sleep duration, and well-being. J Fam Psychol. 2011;25:423.
        Reynolds et al. | 21
         Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/46/7/zsad060/7070629 by guest on 22 September 2024
    </other_idc>
</paper>
    
