<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37123093</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">10143764</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">400944</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S400944</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Exploratory Validation of Sleep-Tracking Devices in Patients with Psychiatric Disorders</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Ogasawara et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Ogasawara et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6060-375X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Ogasawara</surname>
            <given-names>Masaya</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0614-7524</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Takeshima</surname>
            <given-names>Masahiro</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8676-3479</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Kosaka</surname>
            <given-names>Shumpei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5571-130X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Imanishi</surname>
            <given-names>Aya</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8384-8554</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Itoh</surname>
            <given-names>Yu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6738-6986</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Fujiwara</surname>
            <given-names>Dai</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0600-4515</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Yoshizawa</surname>
            <given-names>Kazuhisa</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7360-4898</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Ozaki</surname>
            <given-names>Norio</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2919-8180</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Nakagome</surname>
            <given-names>Kazuyuki</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1182-1181</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Mishima</surname>
            <given-names>Kazuo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Neuropsychiatry, Akita University Graduate School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Akita</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Psychiatry, Akita Prefectural Center for Rehabilitation and Psychiatric Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Daisen</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Pathophysiology of Mental Disorders, Nagoya University Graduate School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Nagoya</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Psychiatry, National Center of Neurology and Psychiatry</institution>, <addr-line>Tokyo</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Kazuo Mishima, <institution>Department of Neuropsychiatry, Akita University Graduate School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>1-1-1 Hondo</addr-line>, <addr-line>Akita</addr-line>, <addr-line>010-8543</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country>, <phone>Tel +81-18-884-6122</phone>, <fax>Fax +81-18-884-6445</fax>, Email clocksclub@gmail.com</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>24</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2023</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>15</volume>
      <fpage>301</fpage>
      <lpage>312</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>05</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2023 Ogasawara et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Ogasawara et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p>Sleep-tracking devices have performed well in recent studies that evaluated their use in healthy adults by comparing them with the gold standard sleep assessment technique, polysomnography (PSG). These devices have not been validated for use in patients with psychiatric disorders. Therefore, we tested the performance of three sleep-tracking devices against PSG in patients with psychiatric disorders.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Patients and methods</title>
          <p>In total, 52 patients (32 women; 48.1 ± 17.2 years, mean ± SD; 18 patients diagnosed with schizophrenia, 19 with depressive disorder, 3 with bipolar disorder, and 12 with sleep disorder cases) were tested in a sleep laboratory with PSG, along with portable electroencephalography (EEG) device (Sleepgraph), actigraphy (MTN-220/221) and consumer sleep-tracking device (Fitbit Sense).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>Epoch-by-epoch sensitivity (for sleep) and specificity (for wake), respectively, were as follows: Sleepgraph (0.95, 0.76), Fitbit Sense (0.95, 0.45) and MTN-220/221 (0.93, 0.40). Portable EEG (Sleepgraph) had the best sleep stage-tracking performance. Sleep-wake summary metrics demonstrated lower performance on poor sleep (ice, shorter total sleep time, lower sleep efficiency, longer sleep latency, longer wake after sleep onset).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>Devices demonstrated similar sleep-wake detecting performance as compared with previous studies that evaluated sleep in healthy adults. Consumer sleep device may exhibit poor sleep stage-tracking performance in patients with psychiatric disorders due to factors that affect the sleep determination algorithm, such as changes in autonomic nervous system activity. However, Sleepgraph, a portable EEG device, demonstrated higher performance in mental disorders than the Fitbit Sense and actigraphy.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>polysomnography</kwd>
        <kwd>actigraphy</kwd>
        <kwd>portable EEG</kwd>
        <kwd>consumer sleep technologies</kwd>
        <kwd>psychiatric patients</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>research grants from AMED</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Japanese Ministry of Education, Science, and Technology</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Center of Neurology and Psychiatry (2-1)</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>This research was supported by research grants from AMED (JP21dk0307103KM), the Japanese Ministry of Education, Science, and Technology (22H02992), and the National Center of Neurology and Psychiatry (2-1).</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="3"/>
        <table-count count="4"/>
        <ref-count count="37"/>
        <page-count count="12"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Assessment of sleep problems is an important clinical component of psychiatric treatment, as sleep problems coexist with a high percentage of psychiatric disorders. A cross-sectional study reported insomnia symptoms in 50% of patients with schizophrenia spectrum disorders and generalized anxiety disorder and in more than 80% of patients with depressive disorder.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1–3</xref> In addition, sleep disorders in psychiatric conditions are not limited to the acute phase of the disease but could also persist for longer periods of time. This could impact the patients’ quality of life, leading to impaired cognitive and social functioning, and increasing relapse and recurrence. In the STAR*D trial, which was conducted in the United States, insomnia was the most common residual symptom among patients with major depression who responded to antidepressant therapy but did not achieve remission. It was observed in 94.6% of these patients.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> A study evaluating quality of life measurements reported that patients with post-remission residual insomnia exhibited lower physical and mental daily role functioning compared to those without insomnia.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> An association has also been reported between sleep disturbances and the risk of recurrence of depressive disorders, bipolar disorders, and schizophrenia, suggesting that maintaining good sleep status is important for good clinical outcomes.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6–12</xref> Alternatively, cases of sleep state misrecognition have also been described, in which subjective insomnia symptoms persist despite objective sleep maintenance.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Insomnia frequently persists after the psychiatric disease that triggered the sleep problems has resolved, hence becoming the main symptom and primary theme in these patients’ lives. Prolonged experiences of insomnia could lead to escalated anxiety. Thus, it is necessary to understand and evaluate both subjective and objective symptoms when assessing sleep in patients with psychiatric disorders.</p>
      <p>In particular, it is essential to observe the relationship between psychiatric symptoms and sleep architecture in studies of the pathophysiology and clinical outcomes of mental disorders. For example, previous polysomnography (PSG) studies have reported rapid eye movement (REM) sleep abnormalities and alterations in slow wave sleep in schizophrenia patients, which are associated with psychiatric symptoms.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> It has also been reported that PSG REM sleep abnormalities are found in patients with depressive disorder and change after drug treatment.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> Continuous measurement of these sleep abnormalities by wearable devices is valuable, but the validity of the measurements needs to be verified.</p>
      <p>The recent development of wearable sleep-tracking devices has made it possible to measure sleep parameters and sleep stages easily at home. Various types of devices that measure sleep, including wristband-type, ring-type, and under-mattress devices, are available. Portable electroencephalograph (EEG) devices that can be used to measure sleep at home are also being further developed. The American Academy of Sleep Medicine (AASM) stated that validation of device accuracy is needed for these devices to be considered part of medical evaluation and treatment.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></p>
      <p>PSG is the main reference used to validate the performance of sleep-tracking devices. Several studies have demonstrated its use in healthy subjects. The validity of sleep-wake determination with sleep-tracking devices has been reported to be higher than that with actigraphy, which has been used to measure sleep at home.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> On the contrary, few studies have focused on the performance of sleep-tracking devices in patients with psychiatric illnesses, and this remains to be elucidated. Patients with psychiatric disorders have different sleep architecture compared to healthy subjects.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Since consumer sleep technology, such as Fitbit, evaluates sleep based on machine learning using healthy subjects as training data, the performance of these devices may be reduced when patients with psychiatric disorders use them. We therefore proposed an exploratory evaluation of the sleep-tracking performance of three wearable devices against PSG in patients with psychiatric disorders and aimed to compare performance across the devices. We tested a portable EEG and two devices relying primarily on an accelerometer and hypothesized that the portable EEG would show better agreement than the other devices.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <p>The flow diagram of the study is shown in <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>.
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Flow diagram of the study.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-301-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: Fifty-two patients aged 16 years or older, diagnosed with schizophrenia, depressive disorder, bipolar disorder, or sleep disorder, who were admitted to Akita University Hospital for a sleep study between December 2020 to November 2021 were included in the study. Three sleep-tracking devices were tested with PSG as a reference: Sleepgraph, Fitbit Sense, and MTN-220/221. PSG recordings were performed for two nights in 26 patients who gave consent. When two nights of data were available, the first night was used in the epoch-by-epoch analysis and Bland-Altman analysis, and the association of accuracy between the two nights was analyzed using Spearman correlation coefficient.</attrib></fig></p>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p>Fifty-two patients (20 males, 32 females) aged 16 years or older (mean age 48.1 ± 17.2 years, range 16–83 years) diagnosed with schizophrenia, depressive disorder, bipolar disorder, or sleep disorder who were admitted to Akita University Hospital for a sleep study between December 2020 to November 2021 were included in the study. The admissions were specifically for sleep tests and were of short duration. The diagnosis of psychiatric disorders was established by clinically experienced psychiatrists based on the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders-5 (DSM-5). Schizophrenia was diagnosed in 18 patients, depression in 19 patients, bipolar disorder in 3 patients, and sleep disorder in 12 patients. Exclusion criteria were as follows: patients under 16 years of age, and patients whose participation in the study was deemed inappropriate by the treating physician (eg, due to anticipated worsening of medical condition). Since sleep apnea is a common comorbidity in psychiatric patients, we did not exclude these patients.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Data regarding body mass index (BMI) and the medications taken by the patient on the day of recording were collected. Medications were compared and classified: chlorpromazine equivalents for antipsychotics, imipramine equivalents for antidepressants, and diazepam equivalents for sleeping pills and anti-anxiety medications.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> All patients were considered fit to provide informed consent for participation in research by their treating physician. Informed consent was obtained prior to participation in the study, and all patients received compensation. Parental or legal guardian consent was obtained for all study participants under the age of 18 years. The Ethics Commission of the National Center of Neurology and Psychiatry, set up as the Central Ethics Review Board, approved all the study protocols and experimental procedures (approval no. B2019-001). The ethics commission of the Akita University gave permission to conduct the study. The study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Sleep-Tracking Devices</title>
        <p>Three sleep-tracking devices were tested: Sleepgraph (Proassist, Ltd.; Osaka-shi, Osaka, Japan),<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Fitbit Sense (Fitbit, Inc.; San Francisco, CA, USA),<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> and MTN-220/221 (Kissei Comtec Co., Ltd.; Matsumoto-shi, Nagano, Japan).<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> The basic characteristics of each device have been demonstrated in previous studies. The Sleepgraph is a portable EEG device, which requires the attachment of electrodes at four locations: right frontal region, below the left eye, right mandible, and left mastoid process. EEG data were recorded at two channels: right frontal (Fp2)-mastoid (M1) and left ocular (EOG)-right mandible (EMG). Each sleep EEG was scored by a technologist skilled in the evaluation of minority-channel sleep EEG. The same technologist also scored the PSG. The sleep technologist was blinded to the study design. Sleep stages by Sleepgraph were used to score sleep at four stages, in accordance with the AASM criteria for PSG scoring.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> However, N1 and N2 were integrated as light sleep to compare scoring with the data obtained from Fitbit Sense that scores at three stages: light sleep, deep sleep and REM sleep. Fitbit Sense is a device worn on the wrist that uses machine learning to detect sleep using acceleration sensors and heart rate estimations obtained by photoplethysmography (PPG).<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> It was worn on the non-dominant arm and measured simultaneously with PSG. MTN-220/221 is an accelerometer worn on the waist. It determines sleep/wake status based on the activity intensity calculated from the activity value.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Epoch duration for sleep data output by Sleepgraph and Fitbit Sense was 30 seconds. However, MTN-220/221 only produced output 2 minutes of sleep data per epoch.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>PSG Recording and Scoring</title>
        <p>PSG recordings were acquired using a digital PSG recorder (Somno HD; Fukuda Denshi, Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo, Japan or Polymate Pro; Miyuki giken, Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo, Japan) in a hospital room. PSG sleep stages (N1, N2, N3, and REM) and wake status were manually scored by a polysomnographic technologist certified by the Japanese Society of Sleep Research. They were scored at another facility in accordance with AASM manual.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Light-off time and light-on time were determined based on position sensors. PSG recordings were performed for one night on all patients, and for two consecutive nights on 26 patients who gave consent.</p>
        <p>Recordings were started at 0 or 30 seconds for comparison with other sleep-tracking devices. PSG data were scored in 30-s epochs and were compared epoch-by-epoch (EBE) with sleep data obtained from Sleepgraph and Fitbit Sense devices. To align with the MTN-220/221 sleep data, the PSG data were additionally scored in 2-minutes epochs according to the following rule: If there were two or more occurrences of stage wake in four continuous epochs, this was defined as wake.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>For demographic data and data following a normal distribution, multiple comparisons were performed by one-way analysis of variance. The Scheffe method was used for between-group comparisons. The Steel-Dwass method was used for data not following a normal distribution.</p>
        <p>Analysis of the sleep data was performed using the open source R code by Menghini et al (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/SRI-human-sleep/sleep-trackers-performance" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/SRI-human-sleep/sleep-trackers-performance</ext-link></underline>).<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> The following EBE agreement statistics were calculated between PSG and each individual device for every night; sensitivity (the percentage of epochs scored as sleep by PSG that were also detected as sleep by the device), specificity (the proportion of epochs scored as wake by PSG that were also detected as wake by the device), positive predictive value (PPV; the proportion of epochs detected as sleep by the device that were also scored as sleep by PSG), negative predictive value (NPV; the proportion of epochs detected as wake by the device that were also scored as wake by PSG), accuracy (proportion of all PSG epochs correctly detected by the device), and bias-adjusted kappa (PABAK; Cohen’s kappa weighted to account for the amount of inequality between the number of sleep and wake epochs). For the Sleepgraph and Fitbit Sense devices, an error matrix was created that exhibited sensitivity and misclassification for each sleep stage. The mean, standard deviation, and 95% confidence interval for each parameter were calculated. The following sleep parameters were calculated for each device; total sleep time (TST; total time spent in all sleep stages), sleep efficiency (SE; percentage of TST divided by time in bed), sleep latency (SL; time taken to fall asleep from bedtime), and wake after sleep onset (WASO; total time awake after sleep onset), and REM latency (REML; time from sleep onset to first determination of REM). The light off/light on time for each device was set at the same time as the PSG. Sleep parameters were subjected to Bland-Altman analysis to estimate systematic and chance errors between PSG and each device. Bland-Altman plots were created to visualize discrepancies between the PSG and sleep measurement devices. For patients whose sleep data were recorded over two nights, the association of accuracy between the two nights was analyzed using Spearman correlation coefficient. All analyses were conducted by R version 4.2.0 (R Foundation, Vienna, Austria, 2022). Significance level was set at p&lt;0.05.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>Fifty-two patients participated in the study, with a combined total of 80 nights of recorded sleep data. After excluding total insomnia (1 sleep data) and incorrectly set PSG recording time (1 sleep data), PSG data for 78 nights in 52 patients was included in the analysis. Data loss occurred due to reasons such as failure to wear the device or loss of the device: Sleepgraph (15, 19.2%), Fitbit Sense (11, 14.1%), and MTN-220/221 (12, 15.4%). PSG recording was performed for two nights in 26 patients who gave consent. When two nights of data were available, the first night was used in the analysis. The disease distribution and characteristics of the participants are demonstrated in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The patients included in the depression group were significantly older than the patients included in the schizophrenia and sleep disorder groups. Individual clinical information and medications at the time of study participation are listed in <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=400944.xlsx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link></underline>.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Participants’ Demographic Data</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">All Patients</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Schizophrenia</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depressive Disorder</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bipolar Disorders</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Disorders</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of subjects</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.1 ± 17.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.8 ± 12.4 *</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.3 ± 16.4 *<sup>†</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.7 ± 13.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.4 ± 18.6<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (38.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (33.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (42.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (50.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (61.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (66.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (57.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (100%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (50.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.6 (13.7–42.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.3 (16.8–37.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.9 ± 4.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.5 ± 9.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.0 ± 6.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drugs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Antipsychotics (mg, CPZE)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.5 (0–880)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">491.8 ± 240.3*,**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0–200)*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">367.2 ± 239.8<sup>†</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0–100)**<sup>†</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Antidepressants (mg, IMPE)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (0–350)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0–350)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">112.5 (0–300)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0–0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0–200)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hypnotics (mg, DZPE)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.45 (0–50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3 ± 8.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5 (0–28.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3 ± 7.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0–50)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep parameters</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> TST (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">453.8 ± 86.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">455.4 ± 85.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">453.8 ± 84.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">436.8 ± 104.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">435.5 ± 98.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> SE (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.6 (55.4–97.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.4 (56.3–97.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.2 (55.4–96.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.9 ± 14.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.4 ± 12.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> SL (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (0.5–185.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.5 (3–168)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5 (0.5–75.5)<sup>†</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104.3 ± 76.7<sup>†</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (1.5–57.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> WASO (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (2.5–241)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.3 (2.5–219)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.5 (9.5–241)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.5 (26.5–32)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105.5 ± 63.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> AHI (events/h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 (0–96.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9 (0–72.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1 (0.4–62.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9 ± 4.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 (0–96.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Stage N1 (%TST)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5 (2.3–72.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1 (2.3–72.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1 ± 5.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7 ± 2.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0 (3.6–36.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Stage N2 (%TST)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0 (24.7–74.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.6 ± 9.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.0 ± 12.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.4 ± 2.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.1 ± 10.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Stage N3 (%TST)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.4 ± 8.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.6 ± 7.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9 ± 8.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.2 ± 5.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.7 ± 6.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Stage REM (%TST)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.1 ± 7.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.2 ± 7.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5 ± 6.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8 ± 5.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.6 ± 9.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> REM latency (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">153.5 (31.5–455.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">182.2 ± 96.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">204.9 ± 95.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">145.5 ± 36.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.5 (53.0–317.0)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Values are presented as mean ± standard deviation, median (min–max) or number (%). *, **p&lt;0.01 <sup>†</sup>p&lt;0.05.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: BMI, body mass index; CPZE, chlorpromazine equivalents; IMPE, imipramine equivalents; DZPE, diazepam equivalents; TST, total sleep time; SE, sleep efficiency; SL, sleep latency; WASO, wake after sleep onset; AHI, apnea hypopnea index; REM, rapid eye movement.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Epoch-by-Epoch Analysis</title>
        <p><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and <xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> demonstrate the results of the EBE analysis. In the sleep-wake assessment, the sensitivity was high for all devices, and the specificity of Sleepgraph was higher than that of Fitbit Sense and MTN-220/221. In the EBE analysis of sleep stages, Sleepgraph’s REM sleep demonstrated high sensitivity and specificity, while the sensitivity of deep sleep and light sleep was relatively low. Fitbit Sense exhibited lower sensitivity than Sleepgraph for all sleep stages. The specificity of Fitbit Sense was high for deep sleep and REM sleep, but low for light sleep. Fitbit Sense over-judged light sleep and demonstrated decreasing sensitivity for other sleep stages. The error matrix is displayed in <xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. Sleepgraph incorrectly classified stage of wake and deep sleep as light sleep, and Fitbit Sense also incorrectly classified stage of deep sleep and REM sleep as light sleep.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Epoch-by-Epoch Analysis for Sleep/Wake Detection</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Device</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensitivity</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specificity</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PPV</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NPV</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accuracy</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PABAK</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleepgraph</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 (0.07) [0.93, 0.97]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76 (0.17) [0.71, 0.81]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 (0.05) [0.93, 0.97]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 (0.17) [0.73, 0.83]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.07) [0.9, 0.94]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 (0.14) [0.81, 0.89]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fitbit Sense</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 (0.04) [0.94, 0.96]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45 (0.23) [0.38, 0.51]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88 (0.12) [0.84, 0.91]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58 (0.29) [0.49, 0.66]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 (0.09) [0.82, 0.88]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70 (0.18) [0.64, 0.75]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MTN-220/221</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 (0.09) [0.90, 0.96]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40 (0.24) [0.33, 0.47]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (0.10) [0.84, 0.90]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 (0.25) [0.55, 0.70]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 (0.09) [0.81, 0.86]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67 (0.18) [0.62, 0.72]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Sensitivity is the proportion of “true” sleep epochs that are correctly classified as sleep by the device. Specificity is the proportion of ‘true’ wake epochs that are correctly classified as wake by the device. Accuracy is the proportion of correctly classified sleep and wake epochs over the total number of epochs. PPV is the proportion of epochs classified as sleep by the device that are ‘true’ sleep epochs. NPV is the proportion of epochs classified as wake by the device that are ‘true’ wake epochs. PABAK is Cohen’s kappa weighted to account for the amount of inequality between the number of sleep and wake epochs. Values are presented as mean (standard deviation) [95% confidence interval].</p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: PPV, positive predictive value; NPV, negative predictive value; PABAK, prevalence and bias-adjusted kappa.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Epoch-by-Epoch Analysis for Sleep Stages Detection</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Stage</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Device</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensitivity</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specificity</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PPV</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NPV</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accuracy</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PABAK</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Light sleep</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleepgraph</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 (0.11) [0.75, 0.82]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 (0.10) [0.79, 0.85]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 (0.08) [0.81, 0.86]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77 (0.14) [0.73, 0.81]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80 (0.08) [0.78, 0.83]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61 (0.17) [0.56, 0.65]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fitbit Sense</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68 (0.12) [0.64, 0.71]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 (0.17) [0.51, 0.60]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64 (0.15) [0.60, 0.68]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59 (0.15) [0.55, 0.63]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61 (0.11) [0.58, 0.65]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 (0.22) [0.17, 0.30]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Deep sleep</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleepgraph</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 (0.18) [0.64, 0.74]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 (0.05) [0.95, 0.98]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 (0.22) [0.73, 0.86]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 (0.04) [0.94, 0.96]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 (0.05) [0.91, 0.94]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 (0.09) [0.83, 0.88]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fitbit Sense</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44 (0.31) [0.35, 0.54]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.05) [0.91, 0.94]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45 (0.28) [0.37, 0.53]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 (0.09) [0.87, 0.92]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 (0.10) [0.82, 0.87]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68 (0.19) [0.63, 0.74]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">REM sleep</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleepgraph</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.12) [0.88, 0.95]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 (0.07) [0.91, 0.95]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66 (0.25) [0.59, 0.73]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 (0.03) [0.98, 0.99]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.07) [0.91, 0.94]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 (0.13) [0.82, 0.89]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fitbit Sense</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49 (0.30) [0.40, 0.58]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 (0.07) [0.84, 0.88]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33 (0.24) [0.26, 0.40]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.06) [0.91, 0.94]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 (0.09) [0.80, 0.85]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64 (0.17) [0.59, 0.69]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Light sleep is the equivalent of PSG N1 + N2 sleep. Deep sleep is the equivalent of PSG N3 sleep. Sensitivity is the proportion of epochs classified as a given sleep stage by the reference that are correctly classified as that stage by the device. Specificity is the proportion of epochs not classified as a given stage by the reference that are correctly not classified as that stage by the device. PPV is the proportion of epochs classified as a target stage by the device that are classified as that stage by the reference. NPV is the proportion of epochs not classified as a target stage by the device that are not classified as that stage by the reference. Accuracy is the proportion of correctly classified epochs for a given stage over the total number of epochs. Values are presented as mean (standard deviation) [95% confidence interval].</p></fn><fn id="tfn0006"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: PSG, polysomnography; REM, rapid eye movement; PPV, positive predictive value; NPV, negative predictive value; PABAK, prevalence and bias-adjusted kappa.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Error Matrix of Epoch-by-Epoch Analysis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Stage</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Device</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wake (PSG)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Light Sleep (PSG)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deep Sleep (PSG)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM Sleep (PSG)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Wake (device)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleepgraph</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76 (0.18) [0.71, 0.81]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 (0.08) [0.04, 0.08]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.01) [0, 0.01]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 (0.03) [0.01, 0.03]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fitbit Sense</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43 (0.22) [0.37, 0.50]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 (0.05) [0.05, 0.07]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 (0.05) [0.01, 0.04]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 (0.12) [0.02, 0.09]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Light sleep (device)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleepgraph</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17 (0.15) [0.12, 0.21]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 (0.11) [0.75, 0.82]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30 (0.17) [0.25, 0.35]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07 (0.09) [0.04, 0.09]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fitbit Sense</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37 (0.21) [0.31, 0.43]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67 (0.12) [0.64, 0.71]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48 (0.25) [0.41, 0.56]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40 (0.26) [0.32, 0.48]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Deep sleep (device)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleepgraph</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 (0.02) [0, 0.01]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 (0.07) [0.03, 0.07]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 (0.18) [0.63, 0.74]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0) [0, 0]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fitbit Sense</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 (0.10) [0.02, 0.08]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10 (0.06) [0.09, 0.12]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43 (0.30) [0.34, 0.52]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 (0.11) [0, 0.07]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">REM sleep (device)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleepgraph</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07 (0.08) [0.04, 0.09]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10 (0.09) [0.07, 0.12]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 (0.03) [0, 0.01]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.12) [0.88, 0.95]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fitbit Sense</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 (0.13) [0.10, 0.18]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16 (0.10) [0.13, 0.19]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 (0.09) [0.02, 0.08]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49 (0.30) [0.41, 0.58]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0007"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Proportions for EBE agreement metrics are demonstrated for each sleep stage (versus the combination of all other possible classifications) for the devices compared with the corresponding epochs from the reference PSG. Values are presented as mean (SD) [95% confidence interval]. Higher values (closer to 1.0) indicate better performance on that metric. Results are displayed for all devices that output sleep stage classifications.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0008"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: PSG, polysomnography; REM, rapid eye movement.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Sleep Parameters</title>
        <p>Bland-Altman plots of sleep parameters are demonstrated in <xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A–E</xref>. Detailed results of Bland-Altman analysis are displayed in <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=400944.xlsx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Tables S2</ext-link></underline> and <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=400944.xlsx" ext-link-type="uri">S3</ext-link></underline>. The TST measured by Sleepgraph exhibited a low mean difference from PSG. Alternatively, Fitbit Sense and MTN-220/221 demonstrated a proportional bias, overestimating TST on nights when PSG TST was low. SE, SL and WASO demonstrated a proportional bias for Fitbit Sense and MTN-220/221, overestimating SE and underestimating SL and WASO in cases of low SE and long SL and WASO as determined by PSG, respectively. REML exhibited a proportional bias with Sleepgraph and Fitbit Sense, underestimating REML in cases of long PSG REML.
<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Bland-Altman plots.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-301-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: Plots depict the mean bias (solid red line) and upper and lower limits of agreement (solid gray lines) for deviation in sleep parameters for the devices compared with the reference PSG. Black circles depict individual nights. Dashed lines represent the 95% confidence intervals around the bias and limits of agreement lines. Gray shaded regions on the right y-axis are density plots demonstrate the distribution of individual night biases. Zero on the y-axis represents no difference, with positive and negative y-axis values indicating an overestimation or underestimation, respectively, compared with the reference. Diagonal mean bias lines indicate significant proportional bias. Non-parallel limits of agreement lines indicate significant heteroscedasticity.</attrib></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Intra-Subject Comparison</title>
        <p>A positive correlation for all devices was observed when the accuracy of PSG and each device was compared for the same patient, with measurements obtained over 2 nights (<xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>, Sleepgraph: r = 0.78, p&lt;0.001; Fitbit Sense: r = 0.70 p&lt;0.001; MTN-220/221: r = 0.68, p&lt;0.01).
<fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Plots of accuracy within the same patient measured over 2 nights.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-301-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: The x-axis indicates the first night’s accuracy, and the y-axis indicates the second night’s accuracy. Higher values for accuracy indicate higher agreement of sleep/wake detection.</attrib></fig></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In the present study, we validated the performance of sleep tracking devices by using PSG as a reference. This allowed us to directly compare the validity of each device’s sleep assessment in patients with psychiatric disorders. The sleep-tracking devices tested in this study demonstrated high sensitivity and moderate to high specificity in determining sleep/wake. Among the devices assessed, Sleepgraph, which is a portable EEG device, exhibited higher specificity than the other devices and was able to reliably determine sleep/wake in patients with psychiatric disorders. MTN-220/221 demonstrated a relatively low specificity, indicating that it underestimates wake status.</p>
      <p>In studies validating sleep tracking devices for healthy adults,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> the sensitivity of actigraphy, which determines sleep using only an accelerometer, was 0.91 to 0.96 and the specificity was 0.34 to 0.63. The sensitivity of devices that utilize PPG in addition to using accelerometers such as the Fitbit, Apple Watch, and Oura Ring is reported to be 0.93–0.98, and the specificity is 0.41–0.69. In the present study, Sleepgraph, Fitbit Sense, and MTN-220/221 validated in patients with psychiatric disorders also demonstrated similar or higher agreement than that of actigraphy. Our results support the at home use of these wearable devices for determining sleep/wake for patients with psychiatric disorders.</p>
      <p>In the EBE analysis of sleep stages, both devices often misclassified other sleep stages as light sleep (<xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). In a given sleep period, REM sleep, light sleep, and deep sleep periods compete with each other. Therefore, the sensitivity and specificity of each sleep stage in a device may be related, and each device may have certain associations, such as a higher sensitivity for REM sleep and a lower specificity of light sleep. Fitbit has been found to over-score light sleep in previous study, which may be a feature of the scoring algorithm.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></p>
      <p>The performance of the Fitbit Sense in determining each sleep stage in psychiatric patients was relatively low compared to the results of previous study conducted in healthy adults.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> Most wearable devices developed in the recent years use data obtained from heart rate variability (HRV) and acceleration sensors to determine sleep status. In healthy adults, HRV is useful for estimating sleep stages.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> HRV information is also used in Fitbit’s sleep assessment.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> There are several factors in patients with psychiatric disorders that physiologically affect the functional correlation between sleep stage and HRV. For example, HF power, which reflects parasympathetic activity in HRV analysis, is decreased in patients with depression and schizophrenia. It is also associated with disease severity.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> In addition, some antidepressants, such as tricyclic antidepressants, modify HRV through their anticholinergic and other effects.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> Although the characteristics of training data and features of classifiers on sleep stage of Fitbit Sense determination have not been disclosed, the accuracy of sleep stage determination was measured in this study using existing algorithms and found to be lower for patients with psychiatric disorders, as compared with studies that included healthy subjects. This could have resulted from the clinical factors modifying the HRV parameters. However, we have not included a healthy comparison group, so this hypothesis needs to be tested in future studies.</p>
      <p>The performance of all devices in measuring sleep parameters decreased with poor sleep: short TST, low SE, long SL, and long WASO. Similarly, low sleep efficiency decreased the validity of sleep parameters in a validation study that included healthy adults.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> REML demonstrated a proportional bias for both devices, and a study comparing PSG and Fitbit Alta HR in patients with hypersomnia exhibited a similar trend.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> A meta-analysis of PSG for psychiatric disorders reported that patients with depression and schizophrenia had lower TST and SE and longer SL and WASO compared with healthy controls.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> Participants in the present study included patients with poor sleep quality, which may have reduced the validity of sleep parameters related to sleep/wake.</p>
      <p>Intra-subject accuracy of PSG and each device was positively correlated for all devices. This suggests that for patients with low sleep-wake accuracy on the first night, it is also low on the second night. Patient-related factors led to the reduction in accuracy.</p>
      <p>Sensor accuracy is a major concern in consumer sleep technology, as inaccurate data and inaccurate recommendations for improving sleep from sleep-tracking devices have been reported to cause orthosomnia.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> Compared with Fitbit Sense and MTN-220/221, Sleepgraph demonstrated higher accuracy and greater sensitivity and specificity in determining each sleep stage, even in patients with psychiatric disorders. It also had a higher agreement rate for sleep parameters. This indicates the superiority of using a portable EEG device with a small number of channels for determining sleep quality in psychiatric patients. It is also less burdensome than PSG and can be performed at home. A study comparing portable EEG and actigraphy in healthy adults also demonstrated that portable EEG was more reliable for assessing sleep parameters, similar to our results, although different portable EEG devices were used.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> Portable EEG devices that can determine sleep using automatic determination are now available. They have been reported to be highly reliable in validation studies including psychiatric patients.<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> These EEG-based sleep assessment devices are expected to facilitate clinical and epidemiological studies that seek to assess natural sleep over consecutive nights in the home setting in patients with psychiatric disorders.</p>
      <p>This study had the following limitations: (1) As the measurements were obtained in a laboratory, they do not reflect the validity of measurements acquired in a natural environment, such as at home. The hospital environment may reduce the validity of these assessments by being more disruptive than normal everyday conditions. (2) As with many previous studies evaluating device performance, there were measurement failures for each device and not all measurements could be analyzed. (3) Due to the lack of drug restrictions, EEG and HRV could be impacted by pharmacological effects. (4) Consumer sleep technologies such as Fitbit may update their device models, apps, and sleep assessment algorithms, so these results only correspond to the versions available during the study period.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Our validation results indicate that sleep-tracking devices can be a promising tool for objective sleep state assessment in patients with psychiatric disorders. However, the validity of these devices may be compromised in patients with psychiatric disorders due to factors that affect the wearable device’s sleep assessment algorithm, such as changes in autonomic nervous system activity and drugs/medications taken by the patient. Sleepgraph, a portable EEG device with a few channels, demonstrated higher validity in sleep assessment than actigraphy and the Fitbit Sense.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We would like to thank Dr. Mari Oba of the National Center of Neurology and Psychiatry in Japan for her support with the statistical analysis. We would like to thank Editage (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="http://www.editage.com" ext-link-type="uri">www.editage.com</ext-link></underline>) for English language editing.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <p>EEG, electroencephalography; PSG, polysomnography; DSM-5, Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders-5; BMI, body mass index; AASM, American Academy of Sleep Medicine; REM, rapid eye movement; PPG, photoplethysmography; EBE, epoch-by-epoch; PPV, positive predictive value; NPV, negative predictive value; PABAK, prevalence and bias adjusted kappa; TST, total sleep time; SE, sleep efficiency; SL, sleep latency; WASO, wake after sleep onset; REML, rapid eye movement latency; HRV, heart rate variability.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p>Data will be made available by the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0008">
      <title>Ethics Approval and Informed Consent</title>
      <p>The Ethics Commission of the National Center of Neurology and Psychiatry, set up as the Central Ethics Review Board, approved all study protocols and experimental procedures (approval no. B2019-001). The ethics commission of the Akita University gave permission to conduct the study. Informed consent was obtained from patients prior to their participation in the study.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0009">
      <title>Consent for Publication</title>
      <p>As there is no patient identifying data, consent for publication was not required.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0010">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation, or in all these areas; took part in drafting, revising or critically reviewing the article; gave final approval of the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0011">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>Dr. Mishima has received speaker’s honoraria from EISAI Co, Ltd; Nobelpharma Co, Ltd; Takeda Pharmaceutical Co, Ltd; and MSD Inc and research grants from The Japan Agency for Medical Research and Development (AMED) (JP21dk0307103KM), grants from The Japanese Ministry of Education, Science, and Technology (22568378), grants from The National Center of Neurology and Psychiatry (2-1); Eisai Co, Ltd; Sumitomo Pharma Co, Ltd; and Takeda Pharmaceutical Co, Ltd.</p>
      <p>Dr. Ozaki has received research support or speakers’ honoraria from, or has served as a consultant to, Sumitomo Pharma Co, Ltd; Eisai Co, Ltd; Otsuka Pharmaceutical Co, Ltd; KAITEKI Mitsubishi Chemical Group Corporation; Mitsubishi Tanabe Pharma Corp; Shionogi &amp; Co, Ltd; Eli Lilly KK; MOCHIDA PHARMACEUTICAL CO, LTD; DAIICHI SANKYO Co, Ltd; Nihon Medi-Physics Co, Ltd; Takeda Pharmaceutical Co, Ltd; Meiji-Seika Pharma Co, Ltd; Kyowa Co, Ltd; EA Pharma Co, Ltd; Viatris Inc; Kyowa Kirin Co, Ltd; MSD Inc; Janssen Pharmaceutical KK; and Nippon Boehringer Ingelheim Co, Ltd, outside the submitted work.</p>
      <p>Dr. Nakagome has received speaker’s honoraria from Otsuka Pharmaceutical Co, Ltd; Sumitomo Pharma Co, Ltd; Meiji-Seika Pharma Co, Ltd; Janssen Pharmaceutical KK; MOCHIDA PHARMACEUTICAL CO, LTD; Mitsubishi Tanabe Pharma Corp; Viatris Inc; and Eisai Co, Ltd. He has received payment for advising from Takeda Pharmaceutical Co, Ltd; Lundbeck Japan; Nippon Boehringer Ingelheim Co, Ltd; Sumitomo Pharma Co, Ltd; and Otsuka Pharmaceutical Co, Ltd. He has also received research grants from Otsuka Pharmaceutical Co, Ltd; Sumitomo Pharma Co, Ltd; and Janssen Pharmaceutical KK, outside the submitted work; and grants from AMED during the conduct of the study.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sunderajan</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gaynes</surname>
<given-names>BN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wisniewski</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia in patients with depression: a STAR*D report</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">CNS Spectr</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>394</fpage>–<lpage>404</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1092852900029266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20625372</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Brenes</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stanley</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williamson</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knudson</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCall</surname>
<given-names>WV</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia in older adults with generalized anxiety disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Geriatr Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>465</fpage>–<lpage>472</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JGP.0b013e3181987747</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19472436</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Laskemoen</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simonsen</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Büchmann</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep disturbances in schizophrenia spectrum and bipolar disorders - a transdiagnostic perspective</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Compr Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.comppsych.2019.02.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30856497</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McClintock</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Husain</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wisniewski</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Residual symptoms in depressed outpatients who respond by 50% but do not remit to antidepressant medication</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Psychopharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>180</fpage>–<lpage>186</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JCP.0b013e31820ebd2c</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21346613</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nierenberg</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Husain</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trivedi</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Residual symptoms after remission of major depressive disorder with citalopram and risk of relapse: a STAR*D report</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Med</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0033291709006011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19460188</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Herz</surname>
<given-names>MI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Melville</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Relapse in schizophrenia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>1980</year>;<volume>137</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>801</fpage>–<lpage>805</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6104444</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sylvia</surname>
<given-names>LG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dupuy</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ostacher</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep disturbance in euthymic bipolar patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychopharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1108</fpage>–<lpage>1112</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0269881111421973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21965189</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dombrovski</surname>
<given-names>AY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mulsant</surname>
<given-names>BH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Houck</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Residual symptoms and recurrence during maintenance treatment of late-life depression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Affect Disord</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>103</volume>(<issue>1–3</issue>):<fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2007.01.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17321595</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Emslie</surname>
<given-names>GJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Armitage</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weinberg</surname>
<given-names>WA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rush</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mayes</surname>
<given-names>TL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoffmann</surname>
<given-names>RF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep polysomnography as a predictor of recurrence in children and adolescents with major depressive disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Neuropsychopharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>168</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1461145701002383</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11466166</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cho</surname>
<given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lavretsky</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olmstead</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Levin</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oxman</surname>
<given-names>MN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Irwin</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disturbance and depression recurrence in community-dwelling older adults: a prospective study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>165</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1543</fpage>–<lpage>1550</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.2008.07121882</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18765482</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sakurai</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suzuki</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yoshimura</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mimura</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Uchida</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Predicting relapse with individual residual symptoms in major depressive disorder: a reanalysis of the STAR*D data</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychopharmacology</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>234</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>2453</fpage>–<lpage>2461</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00213-017-4634-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28470399</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hiranyatheb</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nakawiro</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wongpakaran</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The impact of residual symptoms on relapse and quality of life among Thai depressive patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>3175</fpage>–<lpage>3181</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NDT.S124277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28003753</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Edinger</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fins</surname>
<given-names>AI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Glenn</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia and the eye of the beholder: are there clinical markers of objective sleep disturbances among adults with and without insomnia complaints?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Consult Clin Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>586</fpage>–<lpage>593</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0022-006X.68.4.586</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10965634</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Reeve</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sheaves</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Freeman</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The role of sleep dysfunction in the occurrence of delusions and hallucinations: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Psychol Rev</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>96</fpage>–<lpage>115</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cpr.2015.09.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26407540</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Riemann</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krone</surname>
<given-names>LB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wulff</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nissen</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep, insomnia, and depression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropsychopharmacology</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>74</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41386-019-0411-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31071719</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Khosla</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deak</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gault</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Consumer sleep technology: an American academy of sleep medicine position statement</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>877</fpage>–<lpage>880</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.7128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29734997</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chinoy</surname>
<given-names>ED</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cuellar</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huwa</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Performance of seven consumer sleep-tracking devices compared with polysomnography</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>zsaa291</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsaa291</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33378539</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lujan</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perez-Pozuelo</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grandner</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Past, present, and future of multisensory wearable technology to monitor sleep and circadian rhythms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Digit Health</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>721919</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fdgth.2021.721919</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34713186</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Benca</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Obermeyer</surname>
<given-names>WH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thisted</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gillin</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and psychiatric disorders. A meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Gen Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>651</fpage>–<lpage>668</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archpsyc.1992.01820080059010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1386215</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>KF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yung</surname>
<given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yeung</surname>
<given-names>WF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep in schizophrenia: a systematic review and meta-analysis of polysomnographic findings in case-control studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2016.03.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27061476</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stubbs</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vancampfort</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Veronese</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The prevalence and predictors of obstructive sleep apnea in major depressive disorder, bipolar disorder and schizophrenia: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Affect Disord</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>197</volume>:<fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>267</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2016.02.060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26999550</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kalucy</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grunstein</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lambert</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Glozier</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnoea and schizophrenia--a research agenda</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>357</fpage>–<lpage>365</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2012.10.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23528272</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Inada</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Inagaki</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Psychotropic dose equivalence in Japan</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>440</fpage>–<lpage>447</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pcn.12275</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25601291</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kataoka</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Takatani</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sugie</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Two-channel portable biopotential recording system can detect REM sleep behavioral disorder: validation study with a comparison of polysomnography</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Parkinsons Dis</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>2022</volume>:<fpage>1888682</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2022/1888682</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35251588</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Beattie</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oyang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Statan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Estimation of sleep stages in a healthy adult population from optical plethysmography and accelerometer signals</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiol Meas</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1968</fpage>–<lpage>1979</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1361-6579/aa9047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29087960</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nakazaki</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kitamura</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Motomura</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Validity of an algorithm for determining sleep/wake states using a new actigraph</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Physiol Anthropol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>31</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1880-6805-33-31</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25282356</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Berry</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Albertario</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harding</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <source><italic toggle="yes">The AASM Manual for the Scoring of Sleep and Associated Events: Rules, Terminology and Technical Specifications. Version 2.5</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Darien (IL)</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</publisher-name>; <year>2018</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Menghini</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cellini</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goldstone</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baker</surname>
<given-names>FC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Zambotti</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A standardized framework for testing the performance of sleep-tracking technology: step-by-step guidelines and open-source code</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>zsaa170</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsaa170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32882005</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>de Zambotti</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trinder</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Silvani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Colrain</surname>
<given-names>IM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baker</surname>
<given-names>FC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dynamic coupling between the central and autonomic nervous systems during sleep: a review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurosci Biobehav Rev</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>90</volume>:<fpage>84</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2018.03.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29608990</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jung</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jang</surname>
<given-names>KI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Heart and brain interaction of psychiatric illness: a review focused on heart rate variability, cognitive function, and quantitative electroencephalography</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Psychopharmacol Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>459</fpage>–<lpage>474</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.9758/cpn.2019.17.4.459</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31671483</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kemp</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quintana</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gray</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Felmingham</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gatt</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Impact of depression and antidepressant treatment on heart rate variability: a review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biol Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1067</fpage>–<lpage>1074</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2009.12.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20138254</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chinoy</surname>
<given-names>ED</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cuellar</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jameson</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Markwald</surname>
<given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Performance of four commercial wearable sleep-tracking devices tested under unrestricted conditions at home in healthy young adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Sci Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>493</fpage>–<lpage>516</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S348795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35345630</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cook</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eftekari</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dallmann</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sippy</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Plante</surname>
<given-names>DT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Ability of the Fitbit Alta HR to quantify and classify sleep in patients with suspected central disorders of hypersomnolence: a comparison against polysomnography</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e12789</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30407680</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baglioni</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nanovska</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Regen</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep and mental disorders: a meta-analysis of polysomnographic research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Bull</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>142</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>969</fpage>–<lpage>990</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/bul0000053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27416139</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baron</surname>
<given-names>KG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abbott</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jao</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Manalo</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mullen</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Orthosomnia: are some patients taking the quantified self too far?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>351</fpage>–<lpage>354</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.6472</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27855740</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Matsuo</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Masuda</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sumi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Comparisons of portable sleep monitors of different modalities: potential as naturalistic sleep recorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>110</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fneur.2016.00110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27471489</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Miyata</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Iwamoto</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Banno</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Performance of an ambulatory electroencephalogram sleep monitor in patients with psychiatric disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e13273</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.13273</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33372341</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
