<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37750168</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">10518154</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">413330</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S413330</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Characteristics of the Attentional Network in Children with Sleep-Disordered Breathing</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Wu et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Wu et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9046-7090</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>Yunxiao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Yan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Changming</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
            <given-names>Fujun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ma</surname>
            <given-names>Dandi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0006" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>Zhifei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0006" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0007" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ni</surname>
            <given-names>Xin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0007" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0002" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Beijing Key Laboratory of Pediatric Diseases of Otolaryngology, Head and Neck Surgery, Beijing Pediatric Research Institute, Beijing Children’s Hospital, Capital Medical University, National Center for Children’s Health</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Center on Aging Psychology, CAS Key Laboratory of Mental Health, Institute of Psychology</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Psychology, University of Chinese Academy of Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Neurosurgery, Xuanwu Hospital, Capital Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label><institution>Department of Otolaryngology, Head and Neck Surgery, Beijing Children’s Hospital, Capital Medical University, National Center for Children’s Health</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0006"><label>6</label><institution>Respiratory Department 1, Beijing Children’s Hospital, Capital Medical University, National Center for Children’s Health</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0007"><label>7</label><institution>MOE Key Laboratory of Major Diseases in Children, Beijing Children’s Hospital, Capital Medical University, National Center for Children’s Health</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Zhifei Xu, <institution>Respiratory Department 1, Beijing Children’s Hospital, Capital Medical University, National Center for Children’s Health</institution>, <addr-line>56 Nanlishi Road</addr-line>, <addr-line>Xicheng</addr-line>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <addr-line>100045</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, <phone>Tel +8613521660077</phone>, Email zhifeixu@aliyun.com</corresp>
        <corresp id="an0002">Xin Ni, <institution>Department of Otolaryngology, Head and Neck Surgery, Beijing Children’s Hospital, Capital Medical University, National Center for Children’s Health</institution>, <addr-line>56 Nanlishi Road</addr-line>, <addr-line>Xicheng</addr-line>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <addr-line>100045</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, <phone>Tel +8613370115099</phone>, Email nixin@bch.com.cn</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>20</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2023</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>15</volume>
      <fpage>719</fpage>
      <lpage>727</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>04</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2023 Wu et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Wu et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p>To explore the characteristics of the attentional network and related factors in children with sleep-disordered breathing (SDB).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Patients and Methods</title>
          <p>A total 228 children (200 children aged 6–10 years with snoring or mouth breathing, admitted to our hospital from May 2020 to July 2022, and 28 healthy children recruited from the community as the control group) were enrolled. All participants underwent polysomnography (PSG) and completed the ADHD rating scale and child version of the Attention Network Test. According to their SDB history and obstructive apnea hypopnea index (OAHI), the participants were divided into control (n = 28), primary snoring (PS; n = 67) and obstructive sleep apnea (OSA; n = 133) groups.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>The OSA and PS groups were younger than controls (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The proportion of boys was higher in the OSA than control group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Body mass index was higher in the OSA than control and PS groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01). Attention deficit and hyperactive impulsivity scores were independently associated with the OAHI (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001). The efficiency of the alerting network was higher in the OSA than in controls (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.020), but was not correlated with OAHI after adjusting for age, sex and SDB history duration (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>Children with OSA have impaired attention, characterized by excessive alerting network activation. However, alerting network efficiency did not change linearly with disease severity. More research is needed to elucidate the neural mechanisms underlying attention deficits in pediatric OSA.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>child</kwd>
        <kwd>obstructive sleep apnea</kwd>
        <kwd>attention</kwd>
        <kwd>alerting network</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="3"/>
        <table-count count="3"/>
        <ref-count count="21"/>
        <page-count count="9"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Sleep disordered breathing (SDB) in children is a syndrome of abnormal upper airway function during sleep that includes primary snoring (PS), upper airway resistance syndrome and obstructive sleep apnea (OSA). Repeated hypoxia and sleep fragmentation in OSA can induce chemical or structural damage to the central nervous system, affect children’s cognition, executive function and behavior, and lead to daytime sleepiness, attention deficits, hyperactivity, impulsivity and other symptoms. More than 30% of children with OSA exhibit attention deficits, which negatively affect learning ability and long-term intellectual development.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></p>
      <p>The attention network is divided into three subsystems: alerting, orienting and executive control networks.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> The child version of the Attention Network Test (ANT) can be used for reliable evaluation of the three attentional subnetworks in children.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> The ANT has mainly been used for investigating brain development in normal populations.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> The attentional network develops and matures with age and 6–7 years represents the most important period of development.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> The peak age for OSA occurrence among children is 4–8 years, which coincides with the key period of attentional network development.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Therefore, it is important to determine whether OSA impairs the development of the attentional network and its subnetworks; this could guide future targeted interventions.</p>
      <p>The aim of this study was to explore the characteristics of the attentional network in children with SDB (and related factors), obtain data that could inform the clinical diagnosis and treatment of childhood SDB and associated attention deficits, and shed light on the mechanisms underlying attention deficit.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p>Children aged 6–10 years with snoring or mouth breathing (breathe with mouth open), who underwent polysomnography (PSG) in the Sleep Center of Beijing Children’s Hospital, Capital Medical University between May 2020 to July 2022, were enrolled in this study. The exclusion criteria were craniofacial deformities, neuromuscular or hereditary diseases, a history of mental disorders (such as autism or epilepsy), systemic chronic diseases that may affect the development of the nervous system, and a history of adenotonsillectomy.</p>
        <p>Healthy controls aged 6–10 years were recruited from the community during the same period; OSA was ruled out by PSG in these participants. Other exclusion criteria are same to the SDB group.</p>
        <p>Written informed consent and assent were obtained from parents and children (for children &gt;8 years of age).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Study Design</title>
        <p>This was a prospective observational study. This study complies with the Declaration of Helsinki. The study was approved by the Ethics Committee of Beijing Children’s Hospital.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Clinical Data</title>
        <p>The staff of our sleep center asked the parents how long their children had exhibited snoring or mouth breathing. Height and weight were measured using standard methods (values accurate to within 0.1 kg and 0.1 cm, respectively) before PSG, and body mass index (BMI) was calculated as weight (kg)/height (m<sup>2</sup>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Psg</title>
        <p>A standard overnight PSG was performed using the E-series system (Compumedics, Melbourne, Australia) and the Alice 5 system (Respironics, Murrysville, PA, USA). The monitoring lasted for more than 7 hours. PSG included electroencephalography (C3/M2, C4/M1, O1/M2, and O2/M1), electrooculography, electromyography, electrocardiography, airflow monitoring (using a nasal pressure cannula and thermistor), and assessment of chest and abdomen respiratory movement, oxygen saturation, snoring, and body position. Sleep stage and respiratory events were scored manually according to the American Academy of Sleep Medicine manual.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> The results were consistent among the various devices used for monitoring. Obstructive sleep apnea-hypopnea index (OAHI) is the number of episodes of obstructive apnea, mixed apnea, and obstructive hypopnea per hour. According to diagnostic and treatment guidelines for pediatric OSA, PS is defined as having snoring symptom, but OAHI ≤1 time /h; OSA is diagnosed if the OAHI is &gt; 1/h, while OAHI values of 5–10/h and &gt; 10/h correspond to moderate and severe OSA, respectively.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>ADHD Rating Scale</title>
        <p>Staff at our sleep center interviewed the parents in the face-to-face setting and completed the ADHD rating scale, which comprises 18 items. Nine items are on attention deficit symptoms such as “Inattention to details or carelessness when studying or working”, “It is difficult to arrange daily study and life” and 9 on hyperactivity and impulsivity symptoms such as “Can’t sit still, make small movements or twist in the seat”, “Often interrupts or forces acceptance on others”. One point for a “yes” answer to each item and higher scores indicate more severe symptoms.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2006">
        <title>Child Version of the ANT</title>
        <p>The international version of the ANT was used in this study.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> It was administered by trained personnel during 2pm-5pm before PSG. E-Prime 2.0 software (Psychology Software Tools, Sharpsburg, PA, USA) was used to program and run the ANT. The task includes four cue types (no cue, central cue, double cue and spatial cue) and three flanker types (neutral, congruent and incongruent). The children were asked to press the left or right mouse buttons when the middle fish faced left and right, respectively. The paradigm consists of 24 practice sessions and 144 formal sessions, and takes about 25 minutes to complete. The experimental materials and flow chart of the task are shown in <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. The staff who administered the ANT test and parent interviews and/or scored the PSG were blind to the other results.
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Flow chart of the child version of Attention Network Test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-719-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: Flanker fishes indicate incongruent type.</attrib><attrib><bold>Abbreviation</bold>: RT, reaction time.</attrib></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2007">
        <title>Key Indicators for the ANT</title>
        <p>The reaction time (RT) and accuracy rate (ACC) were recorded under different cue type and flanker conditions. The efficiency of the three networks was determined as follows: alerting network = RT<sub>no cue</sub> - RT<sub>double cue</sub>, where a larger difference indicates better performance of the alerting network; orienting network = RT<sub>central cue</sub> - RT<sub>spatial cue</sub>, where a larger difference indicates better orientation ability; and executive control network = RT<sub>incongruent</sub> - RT<sub>congruent</sub>, where a larger difference indicates poorer executive control network function.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2008">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>SPSS 23.0 software (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, USA) was used for the statistical analysis. Normally distributed data are expressed as mean ± standard deviation and data with a skewed distribution are expressed as median (P<sub>25</sub>, P<sub>75</sub>). To compare the groups, one-way ANOVA with Fisher’s least significant difference post-hoc test was applied to normally distributed data, while the rank-sum test was used for skewed data. For numerical data, the chi-square test was used for group comparisons. Multiple linear regression was used to identify predictors of dependent variables (attention deficit score, hyperactive impulsivity score, efficiency of the alerting network and overall RT). All tests were two-sided and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>In total, 251 children underwent PSG and completed the ANT, whereas 23 were not included in the final analysis because of an ANT ACC &lt; 80%. Except for age (Z = −3.104, <italic toggle="yes">P =</italic> 0.002) and ACC (Z = −7.760, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), there were no differences between children who were and were not included in the final analysis (ie, in sex, BMI, disease severity, SDB history duration, or the attention deficit and hyperactive impulsivity scores; <italic toggle="yes">P &gt;</italic> 0.05).</p>
      <p>The control group included 28 children, the PS group included 67 children, and the OSA group included 133 children. Age and SDB duration were younger and longer, respectively, in the PS and OSA groups compared with the control group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The proportion of boys in the OSA group was higher than that in the control group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The BMI in the OSA group was higher than that in the control and PS groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01). The PSG results, ie, the respiratory and oxygen saturation parameters, were as expected (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Clinical and PSG Data of the Study Groups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PS</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSA</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Z/<italic toggle="yes">χ</italic><sup>2</sup></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n=28</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n=67</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n=133</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6(7.6, 9.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7(6.6, 8.3)**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7(6.7, 9.1)*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.558</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male, n, (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13(46.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37(55.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92(69.2%)*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.105</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, kg/m<sup>2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.3(13.9, 18.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.7(14.3, 18.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8(15.1, 20.9)**^^</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.654</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SDB history duration, m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0, 0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24(12, 36)**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24(12, 36)**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.213</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADHD rating scale</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Attention deficit score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0, 0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0(0, 5.3)**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0(1, 6.0)**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.310</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hyperactive impulsivity score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0, 1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0(0, 5.0)**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0(0, 5.0)**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.757</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> OAHI, h<sup>−1</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4(0.2, 0.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4(0.1, 0.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6(2.3, 9.4)**^^</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">158.069</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Average SpO<sub>2</sub>, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98(97, 98)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98(97, 98)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98(97, 98)^</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.135</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.077</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> SpO<sub>2</sub> nadir, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94(92, 96)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93(92, 95)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90(88, 93)**^^</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.250</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> T90, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0, 0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0, 0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0, 0.1)**^^</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.847</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Data are median (P<sub>25</sub>, P<sub>75</sub>). *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.01 (compared with control). ^<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05, ^^<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.01 (compared with PS).</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: PS, primary snoring; OSA, obstructive sleep apnea, BMI, body mass index; SDB, sleep disordered breathing; ADHD, attention deficit hyperactivity disorder; PSG, polysomnography; OAHI, obstructive apnea–hypopnea index; SpO<sub>2</sub>, oxygen saturation; T90, proportion of total sleep time with SpO<sub>2</sub> &lt; 90%.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p>As shown in <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, the efficiency of the alerting network was higher in the OSA than control group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.020) (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>) whereas did not change linearly with disease severity (<xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). The efficiency of orienting and executive control network did not differ among the groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&gt;0.05). The RT was longer in the PS and OSA groups compared with the control group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001 and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.001, respectively). There was no significant difference in overall ACC among the groups.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Efficiency of Attentional Networks, Overall Reaction Times and Accuracy Rates of the Study Groups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PS</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">F/Z</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n=28</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n=67</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n=133</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control vs PS</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control vs OSA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PS vs OSA</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alerting network efficiency, ms</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.9±63.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.2±66.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.5±64.1*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.179</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.044</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.236</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.144</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Orienting network efficiency, ms</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.0±81.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.9±63.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.9±57.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.369</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.692</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Executive control network efficiency, ms</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.0±55.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.6±59.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.1±60.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.602</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.204</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall reaction time, ms</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">786.0±97.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">878.2±114.0**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">864.1±119.6**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.646</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.416</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall accuracy rate,%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97(0.94, 0.98)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95(0.93, 0.98)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96(0.93, 0.98)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.404</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.496</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Data are mean ± SD or median (P<sub>25</sub>, P<sub>75</sub>). *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01 (compared with control).</p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: PS, primary snoring; OSA, obstructive sleep apnea.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Efficiency of the attentional networks of the study groups.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-719-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: PS, primary snoring; OSA, obstructive sleep apnea; ns, no significance.</attrib></fig>
<fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Efficiency of the alerting network according to disease severity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-719-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: Control vs PS, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.209; Control vs mild OSA, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.006; Control vs moderate OSA, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.036; Control vs severe OSA, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.669; PS vs mild OSA, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.049; PS vs moderate OSA, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.225; PS vs severe OSA, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.439; mild OSA vs moderate OSA, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.705; mild OSA vs severe OSA, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.021; moderate OSA vs severe OSA, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.091. Only the cases with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value &lt; 0.05 are marked in <xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>.</attrib><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: PS, primary snoring; OSA, obstructive sleep apnea.</attrib></fig></p>
      <p>Age, sex, SDB duration, BMI and OAHI were included in the multiple regression analysis of attention deficit and hyperactive impulsivity scores, alerting network efficiency and overall RT (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The attention deficit score was independently associated with BMI (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.040) and OAHI (<italic toggle="yes">P=</italic>0.005) and the hyperactive impulsivity score was independently associated with OAHI (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001). The overall RT was independently associated with age (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001). However, the alerting network efficiency was not correlated with any independent variable (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&gt;0.05).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Multiple Regression Analysis of Attention Deficit and Hyperactive Impulsivity Scores, Alerting Network Efficiency and Overall Reaction Time</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dependent Variable</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">t</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">R<sup>2</sup></italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="7" colspan="1">Attention deficit score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.358</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.239</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.811</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.163</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.129</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.897</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.081</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.418</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.194</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.846</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.118</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.057</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.065</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of medical history</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.387</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.167</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OAHI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.078</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.827</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.106</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7" colspan="1">Hyperactive impulsivity score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.616</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.323</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.733</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.123</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.144</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.852</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.395</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.450</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.369</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.221</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.223</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.307</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.759</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of medical history</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.147</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.253</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OAHI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.091</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.763</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.095</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7" colspan="1">Alerting network efficiency</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.344</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.527</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.082</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.281</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.286</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.763</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.608</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.544</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.226</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.597</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.336</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.737</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.037</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.328</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.781</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.436</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of medical history</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.262</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.211</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.243</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.215</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OAHI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.443</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.640</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.692</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.490</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.545</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7" colspan="1">Overall reaction time</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1272.500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.665</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.630</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−47.928</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.631</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.512</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−11.273</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.361</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.785</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.433</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.453</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.988</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.731</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.466</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of medical history</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.209</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.315</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.664</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.508</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OAHI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.725</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.958</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.756</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.450</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.301</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Abbreviation</bold>: OAHI, obstructive sleep apnea-hypopnea index.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The aim of this study was to investigate characteristics of the attentional network (and related factors) in children with SDB. Children with OSA had high ADHD rating scale attention deficit and hyperactivity impulsivity scores, and the scores were positively correlated with the OAHI. Contrary to our hypothesis, during the ANT, children with OSA exhibited excessive alerting network efficiency whereas that did not change linearly with the severity of the disease.</p>
      <p>The attentional network is divided into three sub-networks (alerting, orienting and executive control networks) that differ in function and anatomy. The alerting network underpins the brain’s ability to maintain a state of alertness to receive incoming information; the frontal and parietal regions of the right hemisphere and locus coeruleus are implicated in this network. The orienting network is the process of selecting input sensory information; its substrates are the fronto-parietal lobe, superior colliculus, and temporo-parietal connection. Finally, the executive control network refers to the ability of conflict resolution and coordination control; it is involved in processes including judgments, choices, and attention switching. The substrates of the executive control network include the prefrontal cortex, anterior cingulate gyrus, ventral thalamic nucleus, and basal ganglia.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></p>
      <p>The children with OSA in this study showed excessive alerting network activation, which is an unexpected but interesting finding. Why do children with OSA show hyper-alertness? One study on the relation between elevation and attentional network found that, with increased elevation exposure, attention first decreased, then increased, and finally decreased again; the increase was attributed to adaptive compensation.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Another study observed increased attention-related beta activity in healthy people who migrated from plains to high elevation, reflecting increased cortical excitability. It was speculated that compensatory mechanisms associated with long-term residence at high elevation may have been responsible for this effect, ie, enhanced attention to allow completion of daily activities.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> In a study using event-related potentials (ERPs) to explore the relationship between hypoxia and cognition, the latency of the P1 component in college students in the “plateau” group was significantly shorter than in the “plain” group on a perceptual task, suggesting that long-term hypoxia increased the conduction speed of the nerves responsible for early perception.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Another study found that, in patients with moderate-to-severe OSA, more neurons were activated in what was described as the “contour global recognition processing stage”. Moreover, there were compensatory effects of the frontal lobe appeared in the visual perception stage.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Against this background, we speculate that hyper-alertness in children with OSA may also be a compensatory response to long-term chronic intermittent hypoxia, although more research is needed to confirm this. A hyper-alert state is also consistent with the daytime performance of children with OSA; such children tend to be hyperactive and excited during the daytime, unlike adult OSA, which presents with excessive sleepiness. This was confirmed by the ADHD rating scale used in this study, where the hyperactive impulsivity scores of the children with OSA were significantly higher than those of the healthy controls. The neurotransmitter noradrenaline may underlie the hyper-alertness seen in children with OSA, given the regulatory role of noradrenaline in the effects of warning signals on alertness.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Furthermore, a recent meta-analysis reported that urinary noradrenaline levels were higher in children with SDB, suggesting sympathetic overactivity in such children.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></p>
      <p>Further analysis of our data showed that the alerting network efficiency did not change linearly with disease severity; in fact, it was highest in mild OSA cases and was not correlated with the OAHI. This disparity between cognitive function and disease severity was reported in previous study.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Some studies found that cognitive function was correlated with PSG indicators, while others reported no strong correlations between these variables.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> Therefore, factors other than hypoxia and sleep disruption may also be important with respect to the cognitive function of children with SDB, such as individual susceptibility, brain electrical activity, and brain oxygen saturation regulation. Tamanyan et al<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> found that individuals with SDB tended to have higher cerebral oxygenation levels than healthy controls. It was speculated that, although arterial oxygen saturation may decrease during apnea, if cerebral blood flow increases simultaneously, the increased blood flow could compensate for the reduced peripheral oxygenation, thereby maintaining the brain’s oxygen supply (cerebral autoregulation). However, in cases of more severe disease or a longer history thereof, this compensatory mechanism may be impaired, ultimately leading to cognitive deficits. Electrophysiological indicators from resting state and sleep electroencephalograms, as well as ERPs, may also provide new insight into, and biomarkers for, the cognitive impairment seen in children with OSA.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></p>
      <p>The executive control network assesses of the ability to resolve conflict and coordinate control when the direction of the target flanker was not congruent with that of the surrounding flankers. Reaction times were longer under incongruent conditions. Hu et al<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> found that attention was impaired in OSA patients, which was reflected in a decline in executive control network function. In ERP studies, OSA groups had higher-amplitude and longer-duration P300 components than healthy controls, indicating that more attentional resources are needed by children with OSA to process target stimuli. Moreover, deployment of these resources took longer in the children with OSA.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> In our study, there was no difference in executive control network efficiency between the OSA group and control and PS groups, which may be attributable to compensatory effects of hyper-alertness.</p>
      <p>In this study, the ADHD rating scale was used to evaluate clinical manifestations of SDB. The attention deficit and hyperactivity impulsivity symptoms of children with OSA were similar to those of the PS group but more obvious than those of the control group. There was no correlation between the efficiency of each attention subnetwork and the attention deficit and hyperactivity impulsivity scores, suggesting that the results of clinical scales and neurobehavioral tests evaluating attention can diverge.</p>
      <p>The RT in this study was negatively correlated with age, ie, with an increase in age the RT gradually shortened, consistent with the results of the ANT in healthy children of different ages. This finding suggests that RTs improve in children as the brain develops over time.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></p>
      <p>Our study has some limitations. First, the healthy control group had a small sample size. Second, the only performance metrics for the ANT are the RT and ACC. Angelelli et al<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> observed OSA patients had greater performance instability than the controls in alertness and fewer valid response in medium/long intervals, particularly 15–20 min in vigilance; therefore, more indexes of attention may be needed. Third, electrical activity and oxygen saturation of the brain were not evaluated, and the mechanisms underlying attention remain unclear.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>This study found that children with OSA have an abnormal attentional network, which mainly manifests as excessive activation of the alerting network. Notably, the efficiency of alerting network did not change linearly with disease severity. The mechanism underlying the attention network impairment seen in children with OSA merits further study, and efforts should be made to devise effective treatments and interventions to improve the attention span of such children. Finally, there is a need for greater experience in the application of neurocognitive assessments for the purposes of clinical practice and research.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>This study was supported by Beijing Natural Science Foundation [7212033], National Natural Science Foundation of China [82070092], the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities [2242022k30036], the Fundamental Research Funds for the central Universities [2242022k30037] and National Clinical Research Center for Respiratory Diseases (HXZX-20210401).</p>
    </ack>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0006">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Working Group of Chinese Guideline for the Diagnosis and Treatment of Childhood OSA; Subspecialty Group of Pediatrics, Society of Otorhinolaryngology Head and Neck Surgery, Chinese Medical Association; Subspecialty Group of Respiratory Diseases, Society of Pediatrics, Chinese Medical Association</collab>. <article-title>Chinese guideline for the diagnosis and treatment of childhood obstructive sleep apnea (2020)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatr Investig</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>187</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ped4.12284</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pozuelos</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paz-Alonso</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Castillo</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Development of attention networks and their interactions in childhood</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Dev Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2405</fpage>–<lpage>2415</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0037469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25069052</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rueda</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fan</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCandliss</surname>
<given-names>BD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Development of attentional networks in childhood</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropsychologia</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1029</fpage>–<lpage>1040</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2003.12.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15093142</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The developmental characteristics of attentional networks in children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">China J Health Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>797</fpage>–<lpage>800</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ye</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Medicine</italic></source>. <edition>2nd</edition> ed. <publisher-loc>Beijing</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>People’s Medical Publishing House</publisher-name>; <year>2022</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Berry</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Budhiraja</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gottlieb</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Rules for scoring respiratory events in sleep: update of the 2007 AASM manual for the scoring of sleep and associated events. Deliberations of the sleep apnea definitions task force of the American Academy of Sleep Medicine</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>05</issue>):<fpage>597</fpage>–<lpage>619</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.2172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23066376</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>The Subspecialty Group of Developmental and Behavioral Pediatrics, the Society of Pediatrics, Chinese Medical Association</collab>. <article-title>Consensus on pediatric clinical practice of early identification, standardized diagnosis and treatment of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin J Pediatr</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>188</fpage>–<lpage>193</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Davidson</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marrocco</surname>
<given-names>RT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Local infusion of scopolamine into intraparietal cortex slows covert orienting in rhesus monkeys</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurophysiol</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>83</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1536</fpage>–<lpage>1549</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jn.2000.83.3.1536</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10712478</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>An</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Attention network varied along with the time of residence at high altitude</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin J Clin Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>03</issue>):<fpage>502</fpage>–<lpage>506</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>An</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Research progress of impact of acute high altitude hypoxia on the resting-state EEG power</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin General Pract</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>29</issue>):<fpage>3683</fpage>–<lpage>3688</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tao</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of long-term exposure to high altitudes on perceptual closure</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin J Behav Med Brain Sci</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>446</fpage>–<lpage>451</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Event-related potential assessment of visual perception abnormality in patients with obstructive sleep apnea: a preliminary study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Hum Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>895826</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnhum.2022.895826</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35845244</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Level of urinary catecholamine in children with sleep disordered breathing: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>100</volume>:<fpage>565</fpage>–<lpage>572</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2022.10.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36327585</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>PK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Radcliffe</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gerry</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Neurobehavioral morbidity of pediatric mild sleep-disordered breathing and obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>5</issue>). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsac035</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>YX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Neuropsychological functioning after adenotonsillectomy in children with obstructive sleep apnea: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Huazhong Univ Sci Technolog Med Sci</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>453</fpage>–<lpage>461</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11596-017-1756-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28585127</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tamanyan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Walter</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weichard</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Age effects on cerebral oxygenation and behavior in children with sleep-disordered breathing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>197</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1468</fpage>–<lpage>1477</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201709-1825OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29351000</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gorgoni</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>D’Atri</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scarpelli</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep electroencephalography and brain maturation: developmental trajectories and the relation with cognitive functioning</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2019.06.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31786427</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pei</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A study of attention networks in patients with obstructive sleep apnea-hypopnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Zhonghua Jie He He Hu Xi Za Zhi</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>659</fpage>–<lpage>663</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26703769</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gosselin</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mathieu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mazza</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Attentional deficits in patients with obstructive sleep apnea syndrome: an event-related potential study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Neurophysiol</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>117</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2228</fpage>–<lpage>2235</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinph.2006.07.130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16934522</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kaihua</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fangqiao</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Event-related potentials and behavior performance scores in children with sleep-disordered breathing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Dev</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>662</fpage>–<lpage>670</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.braindev.2019.04.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31337524</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Angelelli</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macchitella</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Toraldo</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The neuropsychological profile of attention deficits of patients with obstructive sleep apnea: an update on the daytime attentional impairment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Sci</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>325</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/brainsci10060325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32471112</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
