<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37928369</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">10625320</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">424756</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S424756</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Serum Zonula Occludens-1 and Claudin-5 Levels in Patients with Insomnia Disorder: A Pilot Study</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Fan et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Fan et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6379-6216</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Fan</surname>
            <given-names>Mei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Deng</surname>
            <given-names>Fangyi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tang</surname>
            <given-names>Rui</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4443-6688</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Cai</surname>
            <given-names>Yixian</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Xiaotao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Hongyao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xiang</surname>
            <given-names>Ting</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pan</surname>
            <given-names>Jiyang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Psychiatry, Sleep Medicine Centre, The First Affiliated Hospital, Jinan University</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Jiyang Pan, <institution>Department of Psychiatry, Sleep Medicine Centre, The First Affiliated Hospital, Jinan University</institution>, <addr-line>613, West Huangpu Avenue</addr-line>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>510630</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, <phone>Tel +86 2038688651</phone>, Email jiypan@vip.163.com</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>31</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2023</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2023</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>15</volume>
      <fpage>873</fpage>
      <lpage>884</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>07</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2023</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2023 Fan et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Fan et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p>This research aimed to investigate serum Zonula occludens-1 (ZO-1) and Claudin-5 (CLDN5) levels to show whether or not their eventual changes in patients with insomnia disorder could have etiopathogenetic importance. There was no research investigating serum ZO-1 and CLDN5 concentrations in insomnia disorder.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Patients and Methods</title>
          <p>This study included 60 insomnia disorder patients and 45 normal controls. None of the patients received drugs for insomnia. The patients completed Insomnia Severity Index (ISI) and Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI), and Polysomnography (PSG) to score the insomnia disorder symptoms. Venous blood samples were collected, and serum ZO-1 and claudin-5 levels were analyzed by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>Serum ZO-1 level was significantly higher without a significant difference between age, sex, and body mass index, whereas the difference in serum claudin-5 level between the two groups was not statistically significant. In addition, ZO-1 levels were positively correlated with ISI and PSQI and negatively with N1 and N1_perc. We also demonstrated a positive correlation between the levels of CLDN5 and HAMA, and a negative correlation with total sleep time (TST), N1 and N1_perc.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>Our findings suggest an association between these intestinal and brain endothelial permeability markers and insomnia disorders. However, these remain modest and preliminary and need more extensive studies, including long-term follow-up populations and involving gut microbes, to further validate and explore the mechanisms involved.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>insomnia disorder</kwd>
        <kwd>blood-brain barrier</kwd>
        <kwd>intestinal permeability</kwd>
        <kwd>claudin-5</kwd>
        <kwd>zonula occludens-1</kwd>
        <kwd>biomarker</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Key R&amp;D Program of China</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="open-funder-registry">10.13039/501100001809</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported by the National Key R&amp;D Program of China (Grant No.: 2022YFC2503902) and the National Natural Science Foundation of China (Grant No.: 8187050617).</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="4"/>
        <table-count count="3"/>
        <ref-count count="50"/>
        <page-count count="12"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Insomnia disorder is one of the common sleep disorders. Epidemiological studies show that 10–15% of the general adult population suffers from insomnia disorder,<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> and more than 15% in China,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> characterized by difficulty falling and/or staying asleep, with a duration of more than three months, which can lead to daytime fatigue, low energy, reduced cognitive function,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> and is significantly associated with an increased risk of mood disorders and physical severe illnesses and death,<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> and has become a serious social and public health problem because of its profound impact on physical and mental health, quality of life, and social functioning. However, the pathogenesis of insomnia disorder is not yet fully understood. Benzodiazepine (BZD) and non-BZD drugs are commonly used to treat insomnia. However, both often cause drowsiness, dependence, withdrawal symptoms, and other side effects.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Therefore, further exploration of the underlying pathogenesis of insomnia disorder is vital for the precise treatment of insomnia disorder.</p>
      <p>Studies have confirmed that the gut microbiota may play a role in the pathogenesis of insomnia disorders.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6–8</xref> Gut flora changed in the stool of clinical insomnia patients,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8–10</xref> and evidence from brain imaging studies suggests that gut flora can influence brain function.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> The gut microbiome may regulate sleep through the microbiome-gut-brain (BGM) axis.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> The BGM axis has gained increasing attention in research on the biological and physiological basis of psychiatric, neurodevelopmental, aging-related, and neurodegenerative disorders.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Two dynamic barriers regulate signal transduction within the BGM axis: the intestinal mucosal barrier and Blood Brain Barrier (BBB), which consist of endothelial cells interconnected by tight junctions (TJ).<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> The intestinal barrier is impaired in various psychiatric disorders.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Furthermore, it is becoming increasingly clear that, in addition to impaired intestinal barrier, increased blood-brain barrier (BBB) permeability may also be part of the clinical picture in schizophrenia, bipolar disorder, major depression, autism,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> and early-onset psychosis.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></p>
      <p>Previous markers used to assess blood-brain barrier permeability are more or less limited, such as radiolabeled -mannitol, which requires a radiological license and entails high costs, and Evans blue, which is potentially toxic in vivo and its quantification is unreliable.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> In recent years several studies have shown that peripheral circulating tight junction proteins qualify as potential biomarkers for the assessment of BBB.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Plasma claudin-5 levels are significantly higher in depressed adolescents than in healthy controls and can be sufficient as a diagnostic marker for major depression in adolescents.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></p>
      <p>Claudin-5 is the most enriched tight junction protein and a critical integrin that regulates the permeability of BBB 15. In addition, claudin-5 links to cytoplasmic proteins, including ZO-1, ZO-2, and ZO-3, via its carboxyl terminus to form TJ 15. Current studies confirm that claudin-5 dysfunction is associated with psychiatric disorders such as major depression disorder,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> obsessive-compulsive disorder,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> bipolar disorder,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> schizophrenia,<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> and neurodegenerative diseases such as Alzheimer’s disease.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> However, no studies have examined the relationship between insomnia disorders and claudin-5.</p>
      <p>ZO-1, a 210–225 kDa phosphorylated protein, interacts with occludin, claudins, and ligand adhesion molecules and ZO-2, ZO-3, cingulin, and the actin cytoskeleton. Thus, it plays a crucial role in bringing together several components responsible for the paracellular barrier and attaching tight junction proteins to the cytoskeleton.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Elevated serum ZO-1 levels have been observed in several gastrointestinal and non-gastrointestinal disorders associated with increased intestinal paracellular permeability due to tight junction dysfunction (eg, celiac disease, inflammatory bowel disease, obesity, and rheumatoid arthritis).<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28–30</xref> These findings suggest that serum ZO-1 can be used as a marker of intestinal tight junction integrity and intestinal barrier function.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></p>
      <p>To our knowledge, serum ZO-1 and claudin-5 concentrations have not been assessed in patients with insomnia disorder. Therefore, in this study, we hypothesized that increased concentrations of ZO-1 and CLDN5 may occur in insomnia disorders and that disease severity may be related to ZO-1 and CLDN5 concentrations in patients with insomnia disorders. Therefore, this study aimed to investigate whether there are differences in serum ZO-1 and CLDN5 concentrations between patients with insomnia disorder and healthy controls.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants and Procedures</title>
        <p>The Medical Ethics Committee of the First Affiliated Hospital of Jinan University (IRB of First Affiliated Hospital of Jinan University, No. KY-2022-167) granted Ethics Committee approval for the study, and we followed the Declaration of Helsinki in conducting the survey. In this study, sixty patients with insomnia disorder from the outpatient clinic of the Sleep Medicine Center of the First Affiliated Hospital of Jinan University were in the insomnia disorder group (INS), and forty-five healthy subjects without any psychiatric disorders were in the normal healthy control group (NC) (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Inclusion criteria were (1) Han Chinese, (2) age 18–60 years (including upper and lower limits), (3) long-term living in Guangzhou city, (4) 18.5 kg/m<sup>2</sup> ≤BMI ≤ 26.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup> (the lower limit of obesity standards in China), and Insomnia Severity Index (ISI) and Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) scales were used to measure the severity of insomnia symptoms. 17-item Hamilton Depression Scale (HAMD-17); Hamilton Anxiety Scale (HAMA); Generalized Anxiety Disorder (GAD-7) and Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9) were used to measure the mood symptoms.
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Participants recruitment flow chart.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-873-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
        <p>Using the DSM-5 criteria, each patient received a comprehensive diagnostic evaluation by a senior psychiatrist. Patients with any other psychiatric comorbidities were excluded. We carefully evaluated all participants to exclude the presence of autoimmune diseases, pulmonary diseases, infectious diseases, endocrine disorders and treatments, and tumors. In addition, exclusion criteria included (1) co-morbid other sleep disorders, including excessive daytime sleepiness, sleep-related respiratory disorders, sleep-related movement disorders, or sleep circadian rhythm disorders, (2) HAMD-17 score ≥17, HAMA score ≥14, (3) history of regular alcohol consumption, (4) Menstruating, pregnant and lactating women, (5) taking CNS active agents (including sedative-hypnotic, psychotropic drugs) for at least two weeks (or five half-lives) before enrollment. (6) Receiving other insomnia interventions, such as CBT-I.</p>
        <p>In addition, body mass index (BMI) is body weight in kilograms divided by the square of height in meters (BMI = kg/m<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Our study obtained written informed consent for participation from the subjects after thoroughly understanding the study details.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Polysomnography (PSG)</title>
        <p>All subjects received two consecutive nights of PSG before enrollment, with the first night of PSG to exclude other sleep disorders such as sleep apnea syndrome (SAS) and periodic limb movement disorder (PLMD). Subjects completed polysomnography using a dynamic 64-lead PSG device (Compumedics, Australia) with a continuous recording time of at least 7 hours to assess objective sleep. All sleep recordings were interpreted by the same experienced registered PSG technologist using the American Academy of Sleep Medicine sleep scoring criteria. Sleep physiologic parameters obtained include: Apnea-Hypopnea Index (AHI), Periodic Limb Movement Index (PLMI), Sleep Efficiency (SE), Sleep Latency (SOL), Wake After Sleep Onset (WASO), Total Sleep Time (TST), Duration of sleep stage 1,2,3 and rapid eye movement (N1, N2, N3, and R), Percentage of N1, N2, N3, R in total sleep (N1_perc, N2_perc, N3_perc, R_perc), Arousal Index of total sleep (ArI_total), Arousal Index of REM (ArI_REM) and Arousal Index of Non-Rapid eye movement (ArI_NREM).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Biochemical Analysis</title>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3001">
          <title>Sample Collection and Pretreatment</title>
          <p>Venous blood samples were collected from the anterior elbow vein from 8 am to 10 am on the day following the PSG for patients and controls to determine the serum concentrations of ZO-1 and CLDN-5. Venous blood samples from patients included in the study were taken into biochemical tubes, centrifuged at 3000 rpm for 10 min, and the serum fraction was taken. The obtained serum samples were stored at −80 °C.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3002">
          <title>Determination of Serum ZO-1 and CLDN5</title>
          <p>Levels of human ZO-1 and human claudin-5 were determined using commercial enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) kits (Jiangsu Meimian Industrial Co., Ltd., Jiangsu, China) from the same manufacturer as that used by Guo et al.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> Standards, control sera, and samples are run in duplicate in each assay. Samples were diluted 5-fold at the beginning of the assay. We used a standard concentration-optical density plot to determine the levels of the parameters mentioned in the patient samples, and the results were multiplied by 5. The CLDN5 assay included 5-point calibrators at 7.5 pg/mL, 15 pg/mL, 30 pg/mL, 60 pg/mL, and 120 pg/mL, respectively. Similarly, the human ZO-1 assay includes five spot calibrators at 10 pg/mL, 20 pg/mL, 40 pg/mL, 80 pg/mL, and 160 pg/mL, respectively.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>Our data were analyzed on IBM SPSS Statistics software (version 27, IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, USA) and R 4.4.2. The Shapiro–Wilk test was used to assess the normality of data distribution. Normally distributed variables were described as mean ± standard deviation, <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test was used to compare the two groups. Non-normally distributed variables were described as median (interquartile range, IQR), Mann–Whitney test was used for comparison between the two groups. Enumeration data were analyzed by <italic toggle="yes">χ</italic><sup>2</sup> test, and correlation analysis was performed by partial correlation analysis, with gender, age, and weight as control variables. In the Receiver operating characteristic curve (ROC curve) analysis, binary logistic regression was used to obtain propensity scores to test the discriminatory power of two markers to diagnose insomnia disorder. Multiple comparison tests were performed using the False Discovery Rate (FDR) correction. All tests were two-sided, and differences were considered statistically significant at p &lt; 0.05.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>Demographic and clinical variables for each group are summarized in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. As shown in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, there were no significant differences between the two groups regarding age, male-to-female ratio, the prevalence of smoking, Marital status, and BMI. In addition, the lifestyle habits questionnaire found no significant differences in dietary habits, exercise habits, and recent stress between the two groups (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic and Clinical Characteristics of Patients with Insomnia Disorder (INS) and Normal Controls (NC)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">INS (N=60)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC (N=45)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">χ<sup>2</sup></italic>/Z/t</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (year)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.00 (18.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.00 (10.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.865<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.062</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender, Female (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (68.33%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (77.78%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.147<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.284</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marital status Single/married</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40/20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33/12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.539<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.463</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking (Yes/no)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.958</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.94±2.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.27±2.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.791<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.431</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of illness (year)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.46 (3.35)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="3" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="3" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.00 (5.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00 (5.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.008<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.00 (3.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00 (2.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.233<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00 (7.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00 (7.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.621<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.535</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HAMA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00 (3.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (3.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.971<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HAMD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00 (5.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (6.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.378<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAD-7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00 (6.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (3.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.970<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.049</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHQ-9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00 (5.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (3.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.016<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TST (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">366.55±81.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">408.09±53.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.158<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.002</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.45 (19.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.50 (10.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.911<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.004</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WASO (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.75 (82.90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.50 (49.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.228<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.026</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOL (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.00 (27.30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.50 (19.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.251<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.024</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM_L (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.00 (79.90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.00 (73.33)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.353<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.724</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wake duration (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106.50 (92.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.00 (66.30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.749<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.006</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N1 duration (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.50 (35.30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.50 (29.80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.250<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.024</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.25 (9.60)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.00 (8.40)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.101<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.271</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N2 duration (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">172.57±49.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">191.36±35.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.171<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.032</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N2_perc</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.85±7.075</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.07±7.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.151<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.880</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N3 duration (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.64±28.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.46±29.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.209<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.835</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N3_perc</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.48±8.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.72±6.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.837<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.069</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R duration (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.79±31.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.70±28.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.147<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.034</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R_perc</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.36±5.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.74±5.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.211<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.229</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ArI_REM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.80 (8.40)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30 (3.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.546<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ArI_NREM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.40 (8.30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.40 (4.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.981<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.327</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ArI_total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.65 (6.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.90 (4.70)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.192<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.028</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLMI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (2.90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (1.60)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.168<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.867</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70 (1.70)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 (0.90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.781<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.435</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>a</sup>Mann Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test. <sup>b</sup>Chi-square test. <sup>c</sup>Student <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test. Bold: p&lt;0.05.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: BMI, body mass index; ISI, Insomnia Severity index; PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index; HAMA, Hamilton Anxiety Scale; HAMD, Hamilton Depression Rating Scale; GAD-7, Generalized Anxiety Disorder; PHQ-9, Patient Health Questionnaire-9. TST, Total Sleep Time; SE, Sleep Efficiency; WASO, Wake After Sleep Onset; SOL, Sleep Onset Latency; REM, Rapid Eye Movement; NREM, Non-Rapid Eye Movement; REM_L, REM Latency; N1%, N2%, N3%, R%, Percentage of stage N1, N2, N3; R sleep; ArI, Arousal index; PLMI, Periodic Limb Movement Index; AHI, Apnea Hypopnea Index.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Exercise and Diet Habits</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">INS (N=60)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC (N=45)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">X</italic><sup>2</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exercise intensity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.798</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.447<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low intensity (eg walking)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (64.40%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (50.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low to medium intensity (eg jogging)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (24.40%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (31.70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medium to high intensity (such as badminton)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (8.90%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (16.70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High intensity (eg, fast race walking)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.20%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency of exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.759</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rarely or not</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (37.80%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (21.70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sometimes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (46.70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (48.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">More often</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (13.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (18.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Often</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.20%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (11.70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Work-life stress</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.337</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.720</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rarely or not</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (13.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (13.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (48.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (43.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (33.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (41.70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very high</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (4.40%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carbohydrate foods</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.619</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.916</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rarely or not</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.20%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sometimes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (11.10%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (15.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">More often</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (20.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (21.70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Often</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (66.70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (60.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fruits</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.825</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.609</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rarely or not</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (4.40%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sometimes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (24.40%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (30.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">More often</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (28.90%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (35.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Often</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (42.20%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (33.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuts (peanuts, walnuts)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.897</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.826</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rarely or not</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (20.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (13.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sometimes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (55.60%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (61.70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">More often</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (15.60%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (16.70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Often</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (8.90%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (8.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Berries (blueberries, grapes)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.098</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.777</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rarely or not</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (20.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (25.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sometimes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (48.90%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (51.70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">More often</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (22.20%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (18.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Often</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (8.90%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (5.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bean products</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.531</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.057</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rarely or not</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (4.40%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (8.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sometimes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (48.90%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (53.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">More often</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (24.40%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (33.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Often</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (22.20%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (5.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poultry meat (chicken and duck)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.368</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.054<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rarely or not</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.20%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sometimes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (22.20%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (33.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">More often</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (40.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (40.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Often</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (35.60%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (25.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Red meat (pork and beef)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.782</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rarely or not</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.20%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (5.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sometimes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (20.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (25.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">More often</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (28.90%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (46.70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Often</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (48.90%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (23.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fish or other fish products</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.223</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.101</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rarely or not</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (6.70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (6.70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sometimes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (46.70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (45.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">More often</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (15.60%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (33.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Often</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (31.10%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (15.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vegetables</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.036</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.793</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rarely or not</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.20%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sometimes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (11.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (6.70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">More often</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (28.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (35.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Often</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (57.80%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (55.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foods with high protein content</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.597</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.133</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rarely or not</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.20%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sometimes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (33.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (23.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">More often</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (17.80%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (38.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Often</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (46.70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (35.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foods with high fat content</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.134</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.066</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rarely or not</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (20.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (23.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sometimes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (46.70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (61.70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">More often</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (20.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (13.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Often</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (13.30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Note</bold>: <sup>a</sup>Fisher’s Exact Test.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p>The sixty patients with insomnia disorder who participated in this study had a minimum duration of 0.25 years and a maximum of 25.0 years since their illness. Compared to normal controls, patients with insomnia disorder had significantly higher ISI (3.00 [4.00] vs 15.00 [5.00], p &lt; 0.001), PSQI (4.00 [2.00] vs 9.00 [3.00], p &lt; 0.001), HAMD (1.00 [6.00] vs 7.00 [5.00], p &lt; 0.01), HAMA (1.00 [3.00] vs 7.00 [3.00], p &lt; 0.001), PHQ-9 (1.00 [3.00] vs 5.00 [5.00], p &lt; 0.001), and GAD-7 (1.00 [3.00] vs 2.00 [6.00], p = 0.049) scores. ESS scores of INS were higher than those of NC, with no significant difference between the two groups. In contrast to the above scales, which assess patients’ subjective sleep, the PSG sleep physiological parameters reflect patients’ objective sleep conditions. Compared with normal controls, patients with insomnia disorder had significantly decreased TST (t=3.158, p= 0.002), SE (Z=−2.911, p= 0.004), duration of N1 (Z=−2.25, p= 0.024), duration of N2 (t=2.171, p= 0.032) and period of R (t=2.147, p= 0.034), and significantly increased WASO (Z=−2.228, p= 0.026), SOL (Z=−2.251, p= 0.024), Wake duration (Z=−2.746, p= 0.006), ArI_total (5.90 [4.70] vs 8.65 [6.00], p= 0.028), and ArI_REM (1.30 [3.50] vs 5.80 [8.40], p&lt; 0.01). The differences in the percentage of each sleep stage between the two groups were not statistically significant (all p-values &gt; 0.05). AHI and PLMI were consistent in INS and NC (p-values =0.435 and 0.867, respectively). These results are mostly consistent with the clinical features of sleep onset and sleep maintenance difficulties in insomnia disorder.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></p>
      <p>We measured serum CLDN5 and ZO-1 concentrations using ELISA. ZO-1 was significantly elevated (117.29 [107.24] pg/mL in INS, 90.50 [52.69] pg/mL in NC, P=0.002). Although there was a higher level of CLDN5 in INS (143.74 [101.06] pg/mL in INS, 114.69 [85.69] pg/mL in NC) compared to NC, there was no significant difference (P = 0.368) (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> and <xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Serum Zonula Occludens-1 and Claudin-5 Levels of Patients with Insomnia Disorder and Controls</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Measures</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">INS (N=60)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC (N=45)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZO-1 (pg/mL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">117.29 (107.24)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.50 (52.69)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.082</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.002</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CLDN5 (pg/mL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">143.74 (101.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">114.69 (85.69)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.900</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.368</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Note</bold>: Bold: p&lt;0.05.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: CLDN5, Claudin-5; ZO-1, zonula occludens-1.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Boxplot representing the distribution of serum (<bold>A</bold>) CLDN5 and (<bold>B</bold>) ZO-1 concentration in insomnia disorder (INS) and normal controls (NC). **P &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-873-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviation</bold>: ns, no significance.</attrib></fig></p>
      <p>We performed a partial correlation analysis to understand the correlation between serum CLDN5, ZO-1 and clinical characteristics (<xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). ZO-1 levels positively correlated with ISI, PSQI, HAMA, and HAMD for the scales, while CLDN5 levels only positively correlated with HAMA. For PSG, ZO-1 levels negatively correlated with N1 and N1_perc, and CLDN5 levels positively correlated with N3_perc and negatively correlated with TST, N1 and N1_perc.
<fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Correlation between zonula occludens-1 or claudin-5 levels and clinical characters. *P &lt; 0.05; **P &lt; 0.01; ***P &lt; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-873-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index; ISI, Insomnia Severity Index; HAMA, Hamilton Anxiety Rating Scale; HAMD, Hamilton Depression Rating Scale; GAD-7, Generalized Anxiety Disorder; PHQ-9, Patient Health Questionnaire-9; TST, Total Sleep Time; SE, Sleep Efficiency; WASO, Wake After Sleep Onset; SOL, Sleep Onset Latency; REM, Rapid Eye Movement; NREM, Non-Rapid Eye Movement; REM_L, REM Latency; N1, N2, N3, R, Duration of stage N1, N2, N3, R sleep; ArI, Arousal index; PLMI, Periodic Limb Movement Index; AHI, Apnea-Hypopnea Index.</attrib></fig></p>
      <p>We performed ROC curve analysis using propensity scores from binary regression to quantify the diagnostic performance of the two markers (ZO-1 and claudin-5) with age, sex, BMI, and HAMA and HAMD as covariates. The ability of markers CLDN5 and ZO-1 to discriminate patients with insomnia disorders from the average population both decreased after adjustment for age, sex, and BMI, but after adjustment for HAMA and HAMD, the AUC value for marker zo-1 increased to 0.882, but not for CLDN5 (<xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>).
<fig position="float" id="f0004" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>ROC curve. <bold>Adjusteda</bold>: adjusted for age, gender and BMI. <bold>Adjustedb</bold>: adjusted for age, gender, BMI, HAMA and HAMD.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-873-g0004" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>To our knowledge, this is the first study on serum ZO-1 and claudin-5, markers of intestinal and brain endothelial permeability, in insomnia disorder. The main findings of our study were that ZO-1 levels were significantly higher in patients with insomnia disorder than in controls and that although levels of the tight junction protein claudin-5 were higher in patients with insomnia disorder than in controls, the difference between the two groups was not significant. In addition, correlation analysis showed that both correlated with clinical symptoms of insomnia disorder.</p>
      <p>CLDN5 and the TJs-associated protein ZO-1 are the main components of TJs in the blood-brain barrier. Detecting circulating tight junction proteins is a new approach to assessing the integrity of endothelial TJs.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></p>
      <p>Studies have shown that CLDN5 is closely associated with psychiatric disorders. Reduced claudin-5 levels have been observed in both the cadaveric brain and serum of schizophrenic patients,<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> and claudin-5 polymorphisms are associated with the risk of schizophrenia.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> In depressed patients and male mice, CLDN5 expression is reduced in the nucleus accumbens (NAc),<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> and serum claudin-5 levels are significantly elevated in bipolar disorder, suggesting a role for the blood-brain barrier in the pathogenesis of bipolar disorder.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Similarly, elevated serum claudin-5 levels have been observed in patients with Obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD) and Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD).<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> Our findings showed that serum ZO-1 concentrations were higher in patients with insomnia disorder compared to normal controls.</p>
      <p>Furthermore, we found that ZO-1 levels positively correlated with Sleep Assessment Scale scores. Patients with insomnia disorder often have sleep fragmentation, which may lead to disruption of the blood-brain barrier.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> Similarly, the present study found that patients with insomnia had significantly higher WASO and significantly reduced TST, N1, and N2 phase times. TST, N1, N1_perc and N3_perc negatively correlated with ZO-1 or CLDN5 levels. In addition, sleep fragmentation was associated with changes in the abundance of SCFA-producing flora (predominantly <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic>) in the gut,<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> with an increase in <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic> and a decrease in <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic> in patients with insomnia disorders<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> and sleep quality was positively correlated with the higher relative abundance of butyrate-producing flora.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> In addition, animal studies have shown that interventions targeting short-chain fatty acids increase NREM sleep<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> and sleep duration.<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> Fock Ekaterina and Rimma Parnova suggested that SCFA produced by intestinal microbiota regulates tight junction protein ZO-1 and claudin-5 expression directly or by suppressing peripheral inflammation with a protective effect on BBB.<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> The above findings suggest the presence of an impaired blood-brain barrier in patients with insomnia disorder, which may be related to the etiology of insomnia disorder. On the other hand, chronic sleep deprivation can also lead to impaired blood-brain barrier function by mechanisms including increased inflammatory mediators and down-regulation of tight junction proteins, such as TNF-α and IL-6, leading to reduced and mislocalized ZO-1 expression.<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> Therefore, the causal relationship between ZO-1 levels and disease may be unclear.</p>
      <p>Depression and anxiety are two common symptoms in patients with insomnia disorders,<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> and their common pathological mechanisms involve the dysregulation of inflammatory factors and neurotransmitter systems.<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> Indeed, our findings showed that although HAMA and HAMD scores of patients did not reach the diagnosis of depressive-anxiety disorder, they were significantly higher than normal controls, suggesting the presence of mood problems in patients with insomnia disorder. Our correlation analysis also showed that serum ZO-1 levels positively correlated with HAMA and HAMD, and the CLDN5 positively correlated with HAMA. The CLDN5 indicator was significantly reduced, and the ZO1 indicator was significantly increased in AUC after adjustment for HAMA and HAMD in the ROC analysis, suggesting that CLDN5 is associated with anxiety and depression. These correlations may be explained by the interaction of the blood-brain barrier with inflammatory factors.<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> Furthermore, claudin-5 levels were significantly elevated in depressed patients and negatively correlated with TNFα, suggesting that there may be a specific interaction between claudin-5 and inflammatory markers in the pathogenesis of depression.<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> These findings indicate that blood-brain barrier endothelial dysfunction is associated with mood and insomnia symptoms in patients with insomnia disorder, indirectly suggesting that targeting blood-brain barrier endothelial dysfunction is a potential novel intervention strategy to improve the clinical signs of insomnia disorder by modulating the levels of these markers. However, no studies have reported changes in blood-brain barrier-related markers claudin-5 and ZO-1 levels in patients with insomnia disorder.</p>
      <p>In contrast to claudin-5, which is abundantly expressed in the blood-brain barrier, ZO-1 is also one of the major proteins that constitute the intercellular junctions in the intestinal epithelium. Since the structure and function of ZO-1 are closely related to other members of TJs, the position of TJs, in most cases, is altered with the disruption of ZO-1. Therefore, ZO-1 has been used as an indicator and marker to observe various tissues’ barrier function and permeability.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> Our results also found that elevated serum ZO-1 levels positively correlated with PSQI and ISI but also, to some extent, suggest intestinal mucosal barrier damage may be present in patients with insomnia disorders.</p>
      <p>Although the correlations between CLDN5 and ZO-1 and some clinical symptoms of insomnia disorders in the correlation analyses were weak, they were both significant, suggesting that they are associated with insomnia disorders. In the ROC curves, the covariate-adjusted AUC value of ZO-1 was 0.883, sufficient to make ZO-1 biomarkers. However, Large and longitudinally tracked populations may ensure more reliable results.</p>
      <p>Although the insomnia disorder group included in our study was unmedicated or had not taken medication for at least two weeks recently, excluding the effect of drugs, and there were no significant differences between the insomnia disorder group and normal controls in terms of age, sex, weight, and lifestyle habits (exercise and diet). However, several limitations should also be considered. First, we did not test the gut microbiota. Second, the relatively small sample size may prevent the generalization of the study results, for example, the participants in this study were relatively young and did not include an older population. Third, our results that ZO-1 and CLDN5 correlate with subjective sleep (PSQI and ISI) but not with objective sleep measures of PSG major parameters (SOL and WASO) may require us to consider insomnia disorder subtypes further. Finally, the cross-sectional nature of the study is a significant limitation. It did not allow us to find any causal relationship for our findings. Larger samples, cohort studies, and animal studies are needed to validate further and further explore the mechanisms of impaired endothelial function in developing insomnia disorders.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>These findings suggest that ZO-1 and CLDN5 alterations play an essential role in the pathology of insomnia disorders and may be clinical markers of insomnia disorders. Regardless of the limitations, combined with our results, impaired endothelial barrier in the intestine and brain, especially ZO-1 and CLDN5, may be related to the etiology of insomnia disorders. However, more detailed and comprehensive cohort studies or Zoological and cytological experiments are highly needed to validate further and explore the mechanisms of impaired endothelial function in the development of insomnia disorders.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We would like to thank all the participants for their time and efforts.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation, or in all these areas; took part in drafting, revising or critically reviewing the article; gave final approval of the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0007">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Roth</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>New developments for treating sleep disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>62</volume>(<issue>Suppl 10</issue>):<fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Morin</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benca</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Chronic insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>379</volume>(<issue>9821</issue>):<fpage>1129</fpage>–<lpage>1141</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(11)60750-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22265700</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Edinger</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bonnet</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bootzin</surname>
<given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Derivation of research diagnostic criteria for insomnia: report of an American Academy of Sleep Medicine Work Group</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1567</fpage>–<lpage>1596</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/27.8.1567</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15683149</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>309</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>706</fpage>–<lpage>716</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2013.193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23423416</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Perlis</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Posner</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Riemann</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bastien</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Teel</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thase</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>400</volume>(<issue>10357</issue>):<fpage>1047</fpage>–<lpage>1060</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(22)00879-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36115372</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The microbiota-gut-brain axis in sleep disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>101691</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2022.101691</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36099873</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wagner-Skacel</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dalkner</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moerkl</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep and microbiome in psychiatric diseases</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nutrients</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>2198</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu12082198</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32718072</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Easson</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lyle</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Gut microbiome diversity is associated with sleep physiology in humans</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e0222394</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0222394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31589627</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Gut microbiota as an objective measurement for auxiliary diagnosis of insomnia disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1770</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.01770</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31456757</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Gut microbiota changes and their relationship with inflammation in patients with acute and chronic insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Sci Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>895</fpage>–<lpage>905</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S271927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33177907</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Interaction of gut microbiota and brain function in patients with chronic insomnia: a Regional Homogeneity Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>804843</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnins.2021.804843</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35069107</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Altered functional connectivity strength in chronic insomnia associated with gut microbiota composition and sleep efficiency</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1050403</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2022.1050403</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36483137</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fan</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The role of microbiome in insomnia, circadian disturbance and depression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>669</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2018.00669</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30568608</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shin</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>Y-K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Microbiota-gut-brain axis: pathophysiological mechanism in neuropsychiatric disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Adv Exp Med Biol</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>1411</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-981-19-7376-5_2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36949304</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wettschureck</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Strilic</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Offermanns</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Passing the vascular barrier: endothelial signaling processes controlling extravasation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiol Rev</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1467</fpage>–<lpage>1525</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physrev.00037.2018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31140373</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wasiak</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gawlik-Kotelnicka</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Intestinal permeability and its significance in psychiatric disorders - A narrative review and future perspectives</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Brain Res</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>448</volume>:<fpage>114459</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbr.2023.114459</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37121278</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kealy</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Greene</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Blood-brain barrier regulation in psychiatric disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurosci Lett</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>726</volume>:<fpage>133664</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neulet.2018.06.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29966749</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kadry</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Noorani</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cucullo</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A blood-brain barrier overview on structure, function, impairment, and biomarkers of integrity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Fluids Barriers CNS</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>69</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12987-020-00230-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33208141</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Increasing of blood brain barrier permeability and the association with depression and anxiety in systemic lupus erythematosus patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>852835</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmed.2022.852835</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Thal</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luh</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schaible</surname>
<given-names>EV</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Volatile anesthetics influence blood-brain barrier integrity by modulation of tight junction protein expression in traumatic brain injury</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>e50752</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0050752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23251381</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Si</surname>
<given-names>MY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>YZ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Circulating tight junction proteins mirror blood-brain barrier integrity in leukaemia central nervous system metastasis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hematol Oncol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>365</fpage>–<lpage>373</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hon.2289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26999811</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Teng</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Biomarkers of intestinal permeability and blood-brain barrier permeability in adolescents with major depressive disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Affect Disord</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>323</volume>:<fpage>659</fpage>–<lpage>666</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2022.11.058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36493942</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kılıç</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Işık</surname>
<given-names>Ü</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kumbul Doğuç</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Serum Claudin-5, but not zonulin, may be associated with obsessive-compulsive disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatr Danub</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>278</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24869/psyd.2022.273</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35772137</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kılıç</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Işık</surname>
<given-names>Ü</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Demirdaş</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Doğuç</surname>
<given-names>DK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bozkurt</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Serum zonulin and claudin-5 levels in patients with bipolar disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Affect Disord</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>266</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2020.01.117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32056901</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Usta</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kılıç</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Demirdaş</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ü</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Doğuç</surname>
<given-names>DK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bozkurt</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Serum zonulin and claudin-5 levels in patients with schizophrenia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Arch Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>271</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>767</fpage>–<lpage>773</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00406-020-01152-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32564127</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yuan</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Claudin-5 relieves cognitive decline in Alzheimer’s disease mice through suppression of inhibitory GABAergic neurotransmission</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Aging</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>3554</fpage>–<lpage>3568</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/aging.204029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35471411</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Itoh</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nagafuchi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yonemura</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kitani-Yasuda</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsukita</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsukita</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The 220-kD protein colocalizing with cadherins in non-epithelial cells is identical to ZO-1, a tight junction-associated protein in epithelial cells: cDNA cloning and immunoelectron microscopy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cell Biol</italic></source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>121</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>491</fpage>–<lpage>502</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.121.3.491</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8486731</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fasano</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Intestinal permeability and its regulation by zonulin: diagnostic and therapeutic implications</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1096</fpage>–<lpage>1100</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cgh.2012.08.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22902773</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wells</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brummer</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Derrien</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Homeostasis of the gut barrier and potential biomarkers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>312</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>G171</fpage>–<lpage>G193</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpgi.00048.2015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27908847</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Assimakopoulos</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Akinosoglou</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Lastic</surname>
<given-names>A-L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Skintzi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mouzaki</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gogos</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The prognostic value of endotoxemia and intestinal barrier biomarker ZO-1 in bacteremic sepsis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Med Sci</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>359</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>100</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjms.2019.10.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31812215</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Du</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yao</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Su</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names></string-name>
<article-title>Reducing particulates in indoor air can improve the circulation and cardiorespiratory health of old people: A randomized, double-blind crossover trial of air filtration</article-title>. <source>Sci Total Environ</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>798</volume>:<fpage>149248</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34325134</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baglioni</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Regen</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Teghen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep changes in the disorder of insomnia: a meta-analysis of polysomnographic studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2013.04.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23809904</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kazmierski</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Michalak</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wencel-Warot</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nowinski</surname>
<given-names>WL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Serum tight-junction proteins predict hemorrhagic transformation in ischemic stroke patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>79</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>1677</fpage>–<lpage>1685</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0b013e31826e9a83</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22993287</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nishiura</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ichikawa-Tomikawa</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sugimoto</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>PKA activation and endothelial claudin-5 breakdown in the schizophrenic prefrontal cortex</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Oncotarget</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>55</issue>):<fpage>93382</fpage>–<lpage>93391</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.21850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29212157</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Singh</surname>
<given-names>LN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of a functional Claudin-5 variant with schizophrenia in female patients with the 22q11.2 deletion syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Schizophr Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>215</volume>:<fpage>451</fpage>–<lpage>452</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.schres.2019.09.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31668493</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Greene</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kealy</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Humphries</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Dose-dependent expression of claudin-5 is a modifying factor in schizophrenia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2156</fpage>–<lpage>2166</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2017.156</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28993710</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Menard</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pfau</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hodes</surname>
<given-names>GE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kana</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>VX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bouchard</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Takahashi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Flanigan</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aleyasin</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>LeClair</surname>
<given-names>KB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Janssen</surname>
<given-names>WG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Labonté</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parise</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lorsch</surname>
<given-names>ZS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Golden</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heshmati</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tamminga</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Turecki</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fayad</surname>
<given-names>ZA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>CY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Merad</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Russo</surname>
<given-names>SJ.</given-names></string-name>
<article-title>Social stress induces neurovascular pathology promoting depression</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1752</fpage>–<lpage>1760</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29184215</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aydoğan Avşar</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ü</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aktepe</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kılıç</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Doğuç</surname>
<given-names>DK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Büyükbayram</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Serum zonulin and claudin-5 levels in children with attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Psychiatry Clin Pract</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13651501.2020.1801754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32757874</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hurtado-Alvarado</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Domínguez-Salazar</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pavon</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Velázquez-Moctezuma</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gómez-González</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Blood-brain barrier disruption induced by chronic sleep loss: low-grade inflammation may be the link</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Immunol Res</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>2016</volume>:<fpage>4576012</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2016/4576012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27738642</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Maki</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burke</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Calik</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep fragmentation increases blood pressure and is associated with alterations in the gut microbiome and fecal metabolome in rats</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiol Genomics</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>280</fpage>–<lpage>292</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physiolgenomics.00039.2020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32567509</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Grosicki</surname>
<given-names>GJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Riemann</surname>
<given-names>BL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Flatt</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Valentino</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lustgarten</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Self-reported sleep quality is associated with gut microbiome composition in young, healthy individuals: a pilot study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.04.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32795890</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Szentirmai</surname>
<given-names>É</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Millican</surname>
<given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Massie</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kapás</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Butyrate, a metabolite of intestinal bacteria, enhances sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>7035</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-43502-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31065013</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Beneficial effect of GABA-rich fermented milk on insomnia involving regulation of gut microbiota</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Microbiol Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>233</volume>:<fpage>126409</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micres.2020.126409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31927503</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fock</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parnova</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mechanisms of Blood-brain barrier protection by microbiota-derived short-chain fatty acids</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cells</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>657</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36831324</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cuddapah</surname>
<given-names>VA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sehgal</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Regulation of the blood-brain barrier by circadian rhythms and sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Trends Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>500</fpage>–<lpage>510</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tins.2019.05.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31253251</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pan</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>One-year course and effects of insomnia in rural Chinese adolescents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>384</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.2454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23450433</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Plante</surname>
<given-names>DT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jensen</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schoerning</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Winkelman</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Reduced γ-aminobutyric acid in occipital and anterior cingulate cortices in primary insomnia: a link to major depressive disorder?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropsychopharmacology</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1548</fpage>–<lpage>1557</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/npp.2012.4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22318195</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Blake</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trinder</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>NB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mechanisms underlying the association between insomnia, anxiety, and depression in adolescence: implications for behavioral sleep interventions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Psychol Rev</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cpr.2018.05.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29879564</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gan</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ren</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Factors influencing the blood-brain barrier permeability</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Res</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>1788</volume>:<fpage>147937</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainres.2022.147937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35568085</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hochman</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taler</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Flug</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Serum claudin-5 levels among patients with unipolar and bipolar depression in relation to the pro-inflammatory cytokine tumor necrosis factor-alpha levels</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Behav Immun</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>109</volume>:<fpage>162</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2023.01.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36706845</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
