<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38164242</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">10758159</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">437349</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S437349</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Sleep and Its Disturbance in Parents of Children and Adolescents with Epilepsy: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Tsai et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Tsai et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2874-5202</contrib-id><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>Shao-Yu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>Han-Yi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Ying-Ying</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Su-Ru</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>Shu-Yu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6574-8050</contrib-id><name><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>Meei-Fang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>School of Nursing, College of Medicine, National Taiwan University</institution>, <addr-line>Taipei</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Nursing, National Taiwan University Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Taipei</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Nursing, Taipei Veterans General Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Taipei</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan</country></aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>School of Nursing, College of Nursing, Taipei Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Taipei</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Shao-Yu Tsai, <institution>School of Nursing, College of Medicine, National Taiwan University</institution>, <addr-line>No. 1, Sec 1, Jen-Ai Road</addr-line>, <addr-line>Taipei</addr-line>, <addr-line>10051</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan</country>, <phone>Tel +886-2-2351-7770</phone>, <fax>Fax +886-2- 2321-9913</fax>, Email stsai@ntu.edu.tw</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><fpage>1139</fpage><lpage>1152</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>04</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2023 Tsai et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Tsai et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>Sleep disturbances are commonly reported by parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy. However, evidence synthesis including quality and quantity of sleep in parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy is lacking. This systematic review and meta-analysis was conducted to quantify pooled mean estimates of parental sleep variables and to determine the prevalence of sleep disturbances in parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy. Five electronic databases, PubMed, Medline, Embase, PsychINFO, and CINAHL, were systematically searched from inception to September 2021. Eleven observational studies examining parents of pediatric patients aged &lt;18 years with epilepsy using a quantitative measure of sleep duration, sleep quality, or sleep disturbance were reviewed. Our results showed that the pooled nocturnal sleep duration was 5.93 hours (95% CI: 4.64 to 7.21 hours). Overall sleep quality as estimated by the bias-adjusted pooled Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index total score was 6.65 (95% CI: 5.98 to 7.33). Parents of children with epilepsy had significantly higher Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index total scores compared to parents of healthy children (differences in means 1.84, 95% CI: 1.29 to 2.39). The pooled estimated prevalence of parental sleep disturbances was 58.1% (95% CI: 45.7% to 69.6%). Our findings demonstrate a high prevalence of sleep disturbances with poor sleep quality and substantial reductions in sleep time in parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy. Healthcare professionals in pediatric neurology clinics should proactively initiate screening for sleep disturbances in parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy and refer parents to a sleep specialist when necessary.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>adolescents</kwd><kwd>children</kwd><kwd>epilepsy</kwd><kwd>parents</kwd><kwd>sleep</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>work was supported by the Ministry of Science and Technology, Taiwan</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>The funder had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the Ministry of Science and Technology, Taiwan (grant number MOST 110 - 2628 - B - 002 – 039). The funder had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="2"/><ref-count count="36"/><page-count count="14"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Pediatric epilepsy is a complex and prevalent childhood neurological disorder characterized by unprovoked and repeated seizures, with approximately 1 in every 150 children being diagnosed with epilepsy in the first 10 years of life.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> It is a challenging condition that not only affects 0.3–1% of children worldwide,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2–4</xref> but also impacts their parents and families.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5–7</xref> Although seizures and their control are the main focus of clinical care, research shows that up to 80% of children and adolescents with epilepsy suffer from sleep disturbances, irrespective of whether seizures occur during nighttime sleep.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8–10</xref></p>
      <p>Epilepsy itself or seizures are associated with nocturnal arousals, sleep fragmentation, excessive daytime sleepiness, and alterations in sleep architectures.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11–13</xref> Antiepileptic drugs are the main treatment for epilepsy, but most of these medications degrade sleep architecture, impair sleep quality, and aggravate daytime sleepiness.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> A recent systematic review and meta-analysis further demonstrated that compared to healthy peers, children and adolescents with epilepsy had reduced sleep duration and sleep efficiency and experienced more sleep problems, particularly in the domains of night waking, parasomnia, and sleep-disordered breathing.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></p>
      <p>Sleep disturbances in pediatric epilepsy have been shown to have an adverse impact on sleep quality and quantity of parents, particularly when the child needs seizure monitoring and supervision during the night.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Existing observational studies demonstrate that sleep disturbances such as poor sleep, shortened sleep, and nocturnal awakenings are common in parents of children with epilepsy, and that these sleep disturbances are experienced by parents across the child’s age span and disease severity.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> Shaki et al even found that mothers of children with epilepsy had a 7-fold increase in the occurrence of sleep disturbances when compared to mothers of children without epilepsy after controlling for potential confounding factors.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> Psychological distress and caregiving burden further contribute to the disturbance of sleep and impair daytime functioning in parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> As demonstrated by Tsai et al’s study, up to 48.9% of mothers of children with epilepsy had clinically significant depressive symptoms, which together with child sleep disturbances, predicted poorer maternal sleep quality.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></p>
      <p>Sleep is a vital need, with adequate and restorative sleep necessary for maintaining optimal health and well-being.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19–21</xref> Sleep disturbances in the general adult population have been associated with metabolic dysregulation, immune function alterations, impaired inflammatory responses, and reduced cognitive performances.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20–22</xref> These negative and potentially cumulative health consequences may have significant implications for parents of children with epilepsy who are particularly at long-term risk of sleep disruption and sleep loss due to the high demands of nocturnal caregiving and the increased prevalence of sleep problems in these children.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Change of sleeping arrangements has also been reported in parents of children with epilepsy, with 63.6% parents not co-sleeping before the onset of their child’s seizures and 61.7% reporting decreased sleep quality and/or quantity with parent–child co-sleeping.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> However, there is currently no systematic review and meta-analysis examining sleep and its disturbances in parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy.</p>
      <p>The purpose of this systematic review and meta-analysis was to quantify pooled mean estimates of parental sleep variables and to determine the prevalence of sleep disturbances in parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy. A greater understanding of the characteristics of sleep patterns and sleep disturbances in parents of children with epilepsy is needed because when the sleep of the parents is compromised, the parents’ ability to provide quality care for the child may also be hampered. We also assessed the study design and methodological quality of the included studies to inform future research directions and sleep intervention development.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Search Strategy</title>
        <p>We performed a systematic review and meta-analysis according to the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) guidelines.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> The study protocol was registered with the International Prospective Register of Systematic Reviews (PROSPERO) on October 04, 2021 (registration number: CRD42021276820). Five electronic databases, PubMed, Medline, Embase, PsychINFO, and CINAHL, were systematically searched from inception to September 2021. Examples of key terms included “sleep” OR “sleep disturbance” OR “Sleep problem” OR “sleep quality” OR “sleep duration” AND “epilepsy” OR “childhood epilepsy” OR “pediatric epilepsy” AND children OR adolescents AND parents OR mothers OR fathers OR caregivers. A full list of search terms is presented in <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=437349.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Table S1</ext-link></underline>. The search strategies with the keywords for each database are provided in <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=437349.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Table S2</ext-link></underline>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Study Selection</title>
        <p>Two investigators (HYT and YYL) independently searched and screened for all relevant articles in accordance with the eligibility criteria. Any disagreement was resolved through discussion with a third investigator (SYT). The initial search obtained 203 papers, with a total of 102 duplicates removed (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). The remaining 101 papers were screened through the titles and abstracts for further review based on the following inclusion criteria: 1) participants included parents or caregivers of pediatric patients aged &lt;18 years with epilepsy, 2) articles included a quantitative measure of parents or caregivers’ sleep duration, sleep quality, or sleep disturbance, 3) not animal studies, and 4) not reviews, case reports, editorials, letters or comments. There were no language or study design restrictions. Studies involving parents or caregivers of adult epileptic patients aged 19 years and older or articles not published in peer-reviewed journals were excluded. After screening for eligibility using titles and abstracts, the full text of 19 articles with 9 from databases and registers and 10 from other methods were retrieved and assessed for inclusion. Hand searches were also performed on reference lists of included full-text articles. If more than one published article reported data from the same study, we adopted the one with the most complete data. Following this process, 11 articles were included in the final analysis (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Details of the 8 excluded articles are provided in <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=437349.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Table S3</ext-link></underline>.
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses (PRISMA) flow diagram for study selection and exclusion.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-1139-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: PRISMA figure adapted from Page MJ, McKenzie JE, Bossuyt PM, et al. The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews. <italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic>. 2021;372:n71. Creative Commons.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></attrib></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Data Extraction and Study Quality Assessment</title>
        <p>Two investigators (HYT and YYL) separately extracted data and assessed the quality of the final included studies, with a third investigator (SYT) to adjudicate when discrepancies occurred. The data extraction included author names, publication year, study design, country where the study was conducted, sample size, % of maternal caregiver, the average age of the study sample, main sleep measure, and sleep variables. In case of data unavailability, we contacted the authors by e-mail for further information. To assess methodological quality, we used the critical appraisal checklist recommended by the Joanna Briggs Institute.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> The checklist has 8 items for cross-sectional study, 11 items for cohort study, 10 items for case–control study, and 9 items for quasi-experimental study with each item rated as “yes”, “no”, “unclear”, or “not applicable”. A quality score was assigned to each study and was computed as number of items with yes divided by total number of items. The inter-rater agreement between the two investigators (HYT and YYL) for study quality assessment was high (kappa = 0.89, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.01).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Data Synthesis and Analysis</title>
        <p>A series of meta-analyses was performed to obtain the overall effect size for each sleep variable using Comprehensive Meta-Analysis Software version 3.0 (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.meta-analysis.com/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.meta-analysis.com/</ext-link></underline>). Results were expressed as mean, mean difference, or prevalence rate with corresponding 95% confidence intervals (CIs) and with its statistical significance assessed by the Z statistic. Cochran’s <italic toggle="yes">Q</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">I<sup>2</sup></italic> statistics were used to evaluate the between-study heterogeneity, with a p value of &lt;0.1 in the Cochrane’s <italic toggle="yes">Q</italic> test or an <italic toggle="yes">I<sup>2</sup></italic> value of &gt;50% indicative of substantial heterogeneity.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Random-effects models were used to meta-analyze data classified as of substantial heterogeneity. Otherwise, a fixed-effect model was used. Subgroup and meta-regression analyses were conducted to explore potential sources of heterogeneity on a range of study characteristics determined a priori, including sample size (both as a continuous and as a dichotomous variable; ≤50 versus &gt;50), study region (western countries versus eastern countries), child age, and study quality score. These analyses were limited to cases where groups consisted of a minimum of two studies to ensure there was enough data for analysis. Sensitivity analyses were conducted by excluding the study with the highest mean value or prevalence rate to evaluate the robustness of our study findings. Because of the limited number of studies, we evaluated publication bias using funnel plots and Egger’s tests only for analyses consisting of 5 studies or more, with the Duval and Tweedie’s trim and fill procedure applied as appropriate.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Ethical Consideration</title>
        <p>This study was a systematic review and meta-analysis and did not prospectively collect data from human subjects. All the data included in the current study were from previously published research articles. According to the Declaration of Helsinki and local guidelines, no institutional review board approval is required for this study method.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Characteristics of Included Studies</title>
        <p>We finally identified four cross-sectional studies,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> five case–control studies,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> one cohort study,<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> and one quasi-experimental study.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> Among the five case–control studies (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), the comparison groups were composed of parents of healthy children (n = 4) or parents of children with nonepilepsy-related neurodisability (n = 1). Articles were all published in English and from seven different countries, with the United States contributing the majority of 36.4%. Sample sizes ranged from 12 to 234 parents of children with epilepsy. All the caregivers of children with epilepsy were parents and largely mothers (86.4%). Seven studies reported data on parental age, with a mean age of between 32 and 40 years. All studies measured sleep through subjective reports. A meta-analysis could only be performed on a few sleep variables due to the sparsity of data. Ten of the 11 included studies used the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) with a sleep measurement period over the previous month, of which one study only used a single sleep quality item from the PSQI.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> One study used validated daily phone diaries to recall activities over a 24-hour period for one weekday and one weekend day.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> One study also used Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS) to assess daytime sleepiness in parents.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Study Participant Characteristics of the Included Studies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source, Year, Country</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample Size (% of Mother)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parental Age (Yr) Mean (SD)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Children’s Age (Yr)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Measure</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Variable and Result</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quality<sup>a</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>Cross-sectional study</underline></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cottrell et al, 2005, USA<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: 50 (100)<break/>C: NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: 32.3;<break/>range 21–39<break/>C: NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: &lt; 5<break/>C: NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nocturnal sleep duration: 4.5 hours<break/>Nighttime waking: 3 times/night<break/>Sleep problem: 59.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liu et al, 2021, China<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: 157 (57.3)<break/>C: NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: 37.14 (5.57); range 25–54<break/>C: NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: &lt; 18<break/>C: NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI total score: 6.41 (SD=3.79)<break/>PSQI total score ≥ 7: 37.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tsai et al, 2020, Taiwan<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: 133 (100)<break/>C: NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: 35.82 (4.32); range 23–46<break/>C: NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: 1.5–6<break/>C: NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI total score: 6.21 (SD=3.17)<break/>PSQI total score &gt; 5: 57.1%<break/>Sleep latency <sup>b</sup>: 25.0 (10.0, 30.0) minutes<break/>Nocturnal sleep duration: 6.57 (SD=1.45) hours<break/>Nocturnal sleep duration &lt; 6 hours: 25.6%<break/>Sleep efficiency: 86.86 (SD=13.89) %<break/>Sleep efficiency &lt; 85%: 33.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wood et al, 2008, Canada<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: 52 (100)<break/>C: NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: NR<break/>C: NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: 2–18<break/>C: NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI total score: 7.7<break/>PSQI total score &gt; 5: 67%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>Case-control study</underline></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Larson et al, 2012, USA<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: 105 (94.3)<break/>C: 79 (88.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: NR<break/>C: NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: 2–10<break/>C: 2–10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epilepsy vs Control<break/>PSQI total score*:<break/>6.37 (SD=3.49) vs 4.67 (SD=3.21)<break/>PSQI daytime dysfunction subscore*:<break/>1.07 (SD=0.78) vs 0.67 (SD=0.76)<break/>PSQI habitual sleep efficiency subscore*:<break/>0.67 (SD=0.98) vs 0.37 (SD=0.80)<break/>PSQI sleep latency subscore:<break/>0.93 (SD=0.97) vs 0.63 (SD=0.93)<break/>PSQI subjective sleep quality subscore:<break/>1.34 (SD=0.83) vs 1.09 (SD=0.08)<break/>PSQI use of sleep medication:<break/>0.33 (SD=0.79) vs 0.11 (SD=0.42)<break/>PSQI Sleep disturbances subscore*:<break/>1.24 (SD=0.52) vs 1.10 (SD=0.49)<break/>PSQI Sleep duration subscore:<break/>0.81 (SD=0.86) vs 0.70 (SD=0.95)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Painter et al, 2014, USA<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: 30 (86.6)<break/>C: 29 (100)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: NR<break/>C: NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: 2–12<break/>C: 2–12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daily phone diary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time spent in sleep: longer on the weekends versus the weekdays (41.66 minutes, p &lt; 0.01).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reilly et al, 2018, UK<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: Mother 47; Father 39<break/>C: Mother 48; Father 42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: Mother 35.29; Father 37.95<break/>C: Mother 33.71; Father 37.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: 1–7<break/>C: 1–7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epilepsy<break/>PSQI total score (mother): 7.91 (SD=4.28)<break/>PSQI total score (father): 6.36 (SD=3.9)<break/>PSQI total score &gt; 5 (mother): 62%<break/>PSQI total score &gt; 5 (father): 44%<break/>Nonepilepsy-related neurodisability<break/>PSQI total score (mother): 7.35 (SD=4.31)<break/>PSQI total score (father): 5.71 (SD=3.05)<break/>PSQI total score &gt; 5 (mother): 60%<break/>PSQI total score &gt; 5 (father): 55%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shaki et al, 2011, Israel<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: 39 (66.6)<break/>C: 42 (57.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: 39.92 (7.29)<break/>C: 36.43 (7.29)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: &lt; 18<break/>C: &lt; 18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epilepsy vs Control<break/>Nocturnal sleep duration:<break/>5.26 (SD=1.55) vs 6.04 (SD=1.27) hours<break/>PSQI total score &gt; 5:<break/>OR = 6.66, CI 95% (1.10–70.08)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yang et al, 2020, China<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: 234 (67.5)<break/>C: 230 (66.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: 37.56 (6.94)<break/>C: 39.02 (6.33)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: &lt; 18<break/>C: &lt; 18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epilepsy vs Control<break/>PSQI total score (all)*:<break/>6.94 (SD=3.81) vs 5.03 (SD=3.39)<break/>PSQI total score (infant)*:<break/>9.02 (SD=4.34) vs 4.93 (SD=3.74)<break/>PSQI total score (preschooler):<break/>6.57 (SD=3.42) vs 5.98 (SD=4.35)<break/>PSQI total score (schooler)*:<break/>6.14 (SD=3.46) vs 4.18 (SD=2.06)<break/>PSQI total score (adolescent)*:<break/>5.84 (SD=2.96) vs 4.18 (SD=2.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>Cohort study</underline></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Borusiak et al, 2016, Germany<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: 36 (NR)<break/>C: NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: NR<break/>C: NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: 1–16<break/>C: NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single item from PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep quality: improved from diagnosis to 5–7 months of follow-up (p = 0.03).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>Quasi-experimental study</underline></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ledet et al, 2016, USA<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: 12 (91.7)<break/>C: NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: 35.75 (6.62); range 25–49<break/>C: NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E: 2–17<break/>C: NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI<break/>ESS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI total score (pretest): 10.55 (SD=3.75)<break/>PSQI total score (posttest): 10.09 (SD=3.61)<break/>PSQI total score (pretest) &gt; 5: 100%<break/>PSQI total score (posttest) &gt; 5: 83%<break/>ESS total score (pretest): 10.58 (SD=3.82)<break/>ESS total score (posttest): 10.58 (SD=4.73)<break/>ESS total score (pretest) &gt; 10: 58%<break/>ESS total score (posttest) &gt; 10: 58%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/9</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>a</sup>Quality = Joanna Briggs Institute quality appraisal number of items with yes/total number of items; <sup>b</sup>Median and interquartile range were reported; <sup>c</sup>Children with nonepilepsy-related neurodisability formed the control group; *Significant differences between the epilepsy and control groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: CI, confidence interval; C, control; controls were formed by healthy children, unless otherwise indicated; E, epilepsy; ESS, Epworth Sleepiness Scale; NA, not applicable; NR, not reported; OR, odds ratio; PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index; SD, standard deviation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <p>The typology of seizures and/or their occurrence was reported in 6 studies. In the cross-sectional study by Tsai et al,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> 45.9% of the children had experienced at least one seizure within the past 3 months. Wood et al reported the seizure syndrome of the children in their study as follows: idiopathic generalized (8%), symptomatic generalized (12%), cryptogenic partial (6%), and symptomatic partial (75%).<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> In the case–control study by Larson et al,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> 64.2% of the children had at least one seizure within the previous month, and 36.8% experienced daily seizures. Painter et al reported the seizure type of the children in their study as follows: partial epilepsy (56.7%), generalized epilepsy (33.3%), and unclassified (10.0%).<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> In the case–control study by Reilly et al,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> 67% of the children had at least one seizure per month, of which 52% had predominantly generalized seizures and 48% had predominately focal seizures. Yang et al reported the seizure type of the children in their study as follows: generalized seizures (75.21%) and focal seizures (24.79).<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Quality of Included Studies</title>
        <p>The overall methodological quality of studies was mixed (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=437349.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Tables S4</ext-link></underline>–<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=437349.docx" ext-link-type="uri">S7</ext-link></underline>), with three out of 11 studies fulfilling all the criteria of a high-quality, bias-free study.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> All four cross-sectional studies clearly described the study subjects and settings (item 2) and measured the exposure and outcome in a valid and reliable way (items 3 and 7). One cross-sectional study did not clearly define the study sample and the disease condition,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> while two other studies either did not identify or did not clearly specify the confounding factors.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> All five case–control studies clearly defined the study samples (items 1 and 3), measured the exposure and outcome using valid and reliable methods for cases and controls (item 4, 5, 8), identified confounding factors and stated the strategies to handle these factors (items 6 and 7), and used appropriate statistical analyses (item 10). The cohort study measured sleep in a valid and reliable manner but did not clearly identify confounding factors and did not describe the strategies for addressing incomplete follow-ups.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> The quasi-experimental study included multiple measurements of the outcome both before and after the intervention and had a complete follow-up but did not have a control group.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Sleep Duration</title>
        <p>Nocturnal sleep duration in parents of children with epilepsy was reported in four studies ranging from 4.5 to 6.5 hours per night,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16–18</xref>,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> with one study specifically reporting that 25.6% of the parents in the study sample had an average nocturnal sleep of less than 6 hours.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Because one study did not report the standard deviation<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> and one showed significantly 41.66 minutes longer weekend sleep than weekday sleep without providing the raw data,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> estimates were therefore based on a meta-analysis of two studies with a total of 172 parents.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Results indicated that the average nocturnal sleep duration for parents of children with epilepsy was 5.93 hours, with substantial heterogeneity across the two studies (95% CI: 4.64 to 7.21; <italic toggle="yes">Q</italic> = 22.16, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01; <italic toggle="yes">I<sup>2</sup></italic> = 95.48%).</p>
        <p>Two case–control studies reported significantly higher scores on the PSQI sleep duration subscale in a total of 273 parents of children with epilepsy than 272 parents of healthy children,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> suggesting shorter sleep in parents of children with epilepsy than those of healthy children. Another case–control study did not find differences in the PSQI sleep duration subscale scores comparing 105 parents of children with epilepsy and 79 parents of healthy children.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Painter et al also did not find differences in daily sleep duration between parents of children with and without epilepsy. Because only two case–control studies provided the PSQI sleep duration subscale numerical data,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> a meta-analysis of these two studies found that parents of children with epilepsy had significantly higher PSQI sleep duration subscale scores in comparison to parents of healthy children with no evidence of heterogeneity observed (differences in means = 0.20, 95% CI: 0.06 to 0.34; <italic toggle="yes">Q</italic> = 0.62, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.42; <italic toggle="yes">I<sup>2</sup></italic> = 0%).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Sleep Quality</title>
        <p>Seven studies reported sleep quality in a total of 740 parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy using the PSQI total score.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> Because one study did not find differences in PSQI total score after intervention and another study did not find PSQI total score differences between maternal and paternal caregivers,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> pre-intervention PSQI total score and maternal PSQI total score were included in the meta-analysis for sleep quality, respectively. The pooled mean estimate for PSQI total score across the seven studies was 7.03 (95% CI: 6.43 to 7.63; <italic toggle="yes">Q</italic> = 25.76, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01; <italic toggle="yes">I<sup>2</sup></italic> = 76.71%, <xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>), with substantial heterogeneity observed and evidence of publication bias detected in the funnel plot and Egger’s test (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.02).
<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Forest plot of the mean for Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) total score in parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy; (<bold>B</bold>) funnel plot of studies estimating PSQI total scores in parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy, adjusted for unpublished reports (black dots).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-1139-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
        <p>Subgroup and meta-regression analyses (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) showed that study quality score was the only factor explaining the observed heterogeneity for PSQI total score (<italic toggle="yes">β</italic> = −0.09, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01). Using Duval and Tweedie’s trim and fill method to adjust for potentially unpublished reports revealed a slight decrease in the pooled mean for PSQI total score (random effect model point estimate: 6.65, 95% CI: 5.98 to 7.33, <xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>). Sensitivity analyses were conducted by excluding Ledet et al’s study (2016) in which the highest mean value (10.55) was reported. The pooled estimate changed to 6.76 (95% CI: 6.30 to 7.21) for the PSQI total score and remained statistically significant, showing similar results to our meta-analyses above.
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Subgroup Analysis and Meta-Regression of Sleep Quality and Prevalence of Parental Sleep Disturbance</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study No.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pooled Estimate</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>Sleep quality (n=7)</underline></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Country</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Western<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.49 to 9.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Eastern<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.08 to 6.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sample size</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.063</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  ≤ 50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.51 to 11.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  &gt; 50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.21 to 7.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sample size</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">β</italic> = −0.010</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.021 to −0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.452</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Child age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">β</italic> = 0.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.61 to 1.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.456</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Study quality score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">β</italic> = −0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.14 to −0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>Prevalence of sleep disturbances (n=6)</underline></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Country</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.115</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Western<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 to 0.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Eastern<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29 to 0.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sample size</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.351</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  ≤ 50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48 to 0.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  &gt; 50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36 to 0.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sample size</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">β</italic> = −0.008</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.014 to −0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Child age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">β</italic> = 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.20 to 0.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.924</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Study quality score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">β</italic> = −0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.02 to 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.453</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Note</bold>: <sup>a</sup>Indicates USA, UK, and Canada; <sup>b</sup>Indicates China and Taiwan.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <p>Two case–control studies reported significantly higher PSQI total scores in parents of children with epilepsy than in parents of healthy children, suggesting poorer sleep quality in parents of children with epilepsy than those of healthy children.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> A meta-analysis of these two studies found similar results with no evidence of heterogeneity (differences in means = 1.84, 95% CI: 1.29 to 2.39; <italic toggle="yes">Q</italic> = 0.12, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.72; <italic toggle="yes">I<sup>2</sup></italic> = 0%). One study specifically reported that the PSQI total score in parents of infants with epilepsy was significantly higher than other age groups, with no differences found between parents of healthy infants and preschool children, school-age children, or adolescents.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Another study reported no significant differences in the PSQI total score between mothers and fathers of children with epilepsy.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2005">
        <title>Sleep Latency</title>
        <p>Only one cross-sectional study with 133 mothers of children with epilepsy reported a median sleep latency of 25 minutes.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> One case–control study reported significantly higher scores on the PSQI sleep latency subscale in 234 parents of children with epilepsy than 230 parents of healthy children,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> suggesting parents of children with epilepsy taking longer to fall asleep than those of healthy children. Another two case–control studies did not find differences in the PSQI sleep latency subscale scores comparing a total of 144 parents of children with epilepsy and 121 parents of healthy children.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Because only two case–control studies provided the PSQI sleep latency subscale numerical data,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> a meta-analysis of these two studies found that parents of children with epilepsy had significantly higher PSQI sleep latency subscale scores in comparison to parents of healthy children with no evidence of heterogeneity (differences in means = 0.28, 95% CI: 0.15 to 0.42; <italic toggle="yes">Q</italic> = 0.01, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.91; <italic toggle="yes">I<sup>2</sup></italic> = 0%).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2006">
        <title>Sleep Efficiency</title>
        <p>Only one cross-sectional study with 133 mothers of children with epilepsy reported a mean sleep efficiency of 86.86%.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Another study found mothers of children with epilepsy had significantly higher scores on the PSQI habitual sleep efficiency subscale than fathers.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Because only two case–control studies provided the PSQI habitual sleep efficiency subscale numerical data,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> a meta-analysis of these two studies found that parents of children with epilepsy had significantly higher PSQI habitual sleep efficiency subscale scores in comparison to parents of healthy children with no evidence of heterogeneity (differences in means = 0.17, 95% CI: 0.03 to 0.32; <italic toggle="yes">Q</italic> = 1.16, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.91; <italic toggle="yes">I<sup>2</sup></italic> = 0%), suggesting parents of children with epilepsy having poorer sleep efficiency than those of healthy children.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2007">
        <title>Nocturnal Wake Frequency</title>
        <p>Only one study reported that parents of children with epilepsy awoke approximately 3 times during the night.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2008">
        <title>Sleep Disturbances</title>
        <p>Sleep disturbances in parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy were reported using various terms and definitions in 6 studies, including sleep problem, sleep disorder, disturbed sleep, sleep disturbance, and poor sleeper, with a prevalence between 37.6% and 100%. Five studies used the PSQI employing three different cut-off scores to define sleep disturbances (ie, ≥5, &gt;5, ≥7).<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> Nevertheless, the proportion of parents categorized as having sleep disturbances remained high (37.6%) under the highest PSQI cut-off of 7.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> One study reported that 59.9% of parents of children with epilepsy aged ≤5 years old perceived their sleep to be a problem but did not report how sleep problems were defined.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> One study using the PSQI cut-off of 5 found no significant differences in the proportion of mothers (62.0%) and fathers (44.0%) of children with epilepsy categorized as poor sleepers.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> The pooled estimated prevalence of parental sleep disturbance from the 6 studies was 58.1% (95% CI: 45.7% to 69.6%; <italic toggle="yes">Q</italic> = 26.33, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01; <italic toggle="yes">I<sup>2</sup></italic> = 81.01%, <xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>,), with substantial heterogeneity observed and no evidence of publication bias detected in the funnel plot (<xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B</xref>) and Egger’s test (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.09).
<fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Forest plot of the overall prevalence of sleep disturbances in parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy; (<bold>B</bold>) funnel plot of studies estimating the prevalence of sleep disturbances in parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-15-1139-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
        <p>Subgroup and meta-regression analyses (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) showed that sample size as a continuous variable was the only factor explaining the observed heterogeneity for prevalence of parental sleep disturbance (<italic toggle="yes">β</italic> = −0.008, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01), while sample size analyzed as a dichotomous variable (≤50 versus &gt;50) did not show such an association (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.35). The pooled prevalence estimate became slightly lower to 52.5% (95 CI: 47.7% to 57.2%) after conducting a sensitivity analysis by omitting Ledet et al’s study with the highest prevalence rate.</p>
        <p>Three case–control studies reported significantly higher scores on the PSQI sleep disturbance subscale in parents of epileptic children than parents of healthy children,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> suggesting more disturbed sleep in parents of children with epilepsy than those of healthy children. Because only two case–control studies provided the PSQI sleep disturbances subscale numerical data,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> a meta-analysis of these two studies found similar results that parents of children with epilepsy had significantly higher PSQI sleep disturbances subscale scores in comparison to parents of healthy children, with substantial heterogeneity observed (differences in means = 0.26, 95% CI: 0.03 to 0.49; <italic toggle="yes">Q</italic> = 6.23, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.01; <italic toggle="yes">I<sup>2</sup></italic> = 83.9%).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2009">
        <title>Daytime Sleepiness</title>
        <p>Only one interventional pilot study with 12 parents of children with epilepsy reported a mean score of 10.58 on the ESS and 58.0% of the parents had an ESS score ≥10 for both pre- and post-intervention,<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> suggesting parents of children with epilepsy experienced significant daytime sleepiness.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>This study provides a systematic review of the literature and meta-analysis of available data for seven sleep quantity- and quality-related variables reported in parent caregivers of children and adolescents with epilepsy: sleep duration, sleep quality, sleep latency, sleep efficiency, nocturnal wake frequency, sleep disturbance, and daytime sleepiness. In total, 11 observational studies with 934 parents of epileptic children and adolescents that capture populations from different global regions and cultures were reviewed, with the majority of included studies having moderate to high quality. Our analyses indicate that parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy have inadequate sleep duration, poor sleep quality, reduced sleep efficiency, severe sleep disturbances, and excessive daytime sleepiness. Case–control studies provided additional evidence supporting that parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy have significantly poorer sleep quality, lower sleep efficiency, and more severe sleep disturbances compared to parents of children and adolescents without epilepsy. Findings from this study suggest that poor and altered sleep in parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy is an important target of intervention requiring further investigation.</p>
      <p>Our analyses of sleep duration found parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy sleeping on average of 5.93 hours per night, which is below the national and international recommendations for healthy adults who should sleep 7 or more hours per night to promote optimal health.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> This pooled estimate for nocturnal sleep in our analyses was based on parental reporting rather than objective measures. Parents may actually obtain an even shorter sleep given that subjective report was shown to overestimate total sleep time when compared to objective actigraphy- or polysomnography-measured sleep.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> This finding is of concern because sleep duration of 7–8 hours per day was found most favorably associated with a variety of health outcomes, including reduced risk of all-cause mortality, incident cardiovascular disease, type 2 diabetes, depression, and obesity, according to a recent overview of systemic reviews.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> However, results from three case–control studies showed inconsistent differences in the PSQI sleep duration subscale scores between parents of children with and without epilepsy. It is possible that age of the children may explain some of the conflicting results. Obtaining an adequate amount of sleep may be equally challenging for parents of younger children regardless of whether the child has epilepsy.</p>
      <p>Our pooled estimate for sleep duration in parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy was only for nocturnal sleep. Most studies included in our analyses used the PSQI in which daytime sleep is not part of the questionnaire, so daytime sleep data were not collected. Parents may nap during the day, particularly parents of younger children who often synchronize their sleep-wake schedule with the child. Among the 11 included studies, only one study recorded parental sleep and activity patterns over a 24-hour period,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> but this study did not report nocturnal sleep separate from daily sleep, making direct comparisons between studies difficult. This study found that both parents of children with and without epilepsy slept 41.66 minutes longer on weekends than on weekdays (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01). Maintaining a consistent sleep schedule is essential for adequate sleep, which would be particularly important to be addressed for parents of children with epilepsy because weekday-weekend sleep irregularities could perpetuate the already reduced and disrupted sleep in parents of children with epilepsy. Screening parental sleep hygiene knowledge and providing parents with information about healthy sleep practices can inform both future research and the development of behavioral-educational sleep interventions for parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy.</p>
      <p>Our pooled PSQI global sleep quality score in this meta-analysis was 6.65, with 6 studies reporting an average PSQI score &gt;5<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> which is the original PSQI cut-off score used to classify individuals as having poor sleep quality.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Evidence from two case–control studies further showed that parents of children with epilepsy consistently having poorer sleep quality than parents of healthy children.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Night wakings may impair sleep quality, but this measure yielded the least amount of data in the current review.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Duration of sleep latency was also reported in only one study and was on average 25 minutes,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> which marginally fits within the cutoff for clinical significance because a sleep latency of &gt;30 minutes often suggests some difficulties with sleep initiation.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> However, results from three case–control studies showed inconsistent differences in the PSQI sleep latency subscale scores between parents of children with epilepsy and those of healthy children.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> One possible explanation is that sleep latency is related to the homeostatic sleep pressure and is influenced by multiple factors such as daytime napping and physical activity<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> which are not assessed in all of the included studies.</p>
      <p>In our included studies, only one cross-sectional study reported that parents of children with epilepsy had a mean sleep efficiency of 86.86%.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Two case–control studies reported that parents of children with epilepsy had poorer sleep efficiency than those of healthy children as evidenced by a higher PSQI habitual sleep efficiency subscale score.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Sleep efficiency is the ratio of the total time spent asleep at night compared to the total amount of time spent in bed. A person with poor sleep efficiency is closely linked to taking longer to fall asleep, waking up in the middle of the night, or both. These findings of the sleep efficiency, along with our aforementioned analyses on sleep latency, suggest that reduced sleep efficiency in parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy more likely resulted from frequent nighttime wakings or increased wake after sleep onset rather than prolonged sleep latency. Sleep efficiency is an important dimension of the PSQI to examine global sleep quality and level of sleep disturbances. Parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy experience a decrease in sleep efficiency which likely contributes to the reduced overall sleep quality and high prevalence of sleep disturbances as well as daytime sleepiness.</p>
      <p>The pooled prevalence of sleep disturbances in parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy is high (58.1%), with clear evidence of more disturbed sleep in parents of children with epilepsy than those of healthy children. Sleep disturbances in parents of children with epilepsy may influence not only their caregiver role but also their own health and ability to attend to daily tasks at work and home.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Symptoms of depression and anxiety have been linked to parental sleep disturbances in both cross-sectional and case–control pediatric epilepsy studies.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> These symptoms are likely to co-occur or to have a bi-directional relationship with parental sleep disturbances. Altered sleeping arrangements are another factor that needs to be taken into account when interpreting findings on parental sleep disturbances. Approximately 22–63.6% of parents change to co-sleep with their child following epilepsy diagnosis or onset of seizure.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> Co-sleeping has been reported more frequently in families of children with epilepsy than those of healthy children and linked to poorer and/or shorter parental sleep.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> The high pooled prevalence of parental sleep disturbances of our meta-analysis, together with the 53–57.1% previously reported in children with epilepsy,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> suggest that sleep disturbance is a shared problem in parents and children with epilepsy. While our review and analysis focused on parents of children with epilepsy, a dyadic approach to assessing the sleep and sleeping arrangement in the parent and child may uncover how the dyads’ influence each other’s sleep, and may facilitate the development of more tailored sleep interventions that benefit both the parent and child.</p>
      <p>Some limitations of this systematic review and meta-analyses should be acknowledged. First, although it is possible to conduct a meta-analysis with only two studies, having small numbers of studies could affect the assessment of between-study heterogeneity. Our subgroup and meta-regression analyses did not show the study region or child age as the source of heterogeneity. However, parental sleep quality and prevalence of parental sleep disturbance were negatively moderated by study quality score and sample size, respectively. Future studies should consider using rigorous study designs with an adequate sample size to generate high-quality evidence. Second, subgroup analyses such as gender differences were not analyzed because only two studies, not uniformly reporting the same sleep variables, considered gender, both with a sample size of &lt;50 parents.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> Lastly, although we pre-registered the protocol in a publicly available repository (PROSPERO) and performed a comprehensive literature search, publication bias was still present for the sleep quality measure. All of the reviewed studies were also observational and many were cross-sectional, with the lack of daytime sleep data and data from objective sleep measures. Multi-day sleep diary or actigraphy assessments of sleep with a more transparent report of research findings are needed to avoid publication bias and to have a better understanding of sleep habits and sleep hygiene practices in parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>The results of our systematic review and meta-analysis demonstrate a high prevalence of sleep disturbances with poor sleep quality and substantial reductions in sleep time in parent caregivers of children and adolescents with epilepsy. Our findings suggest that healthcare professionals in pediatric neurology clinics should proactively initiate screening for sleep disturbances in parents of children and adolescents with epilepsy and refer parents to a sleep specialist when it is deemed necessary. Future prospective studies with objective sleep measurements are needed to validate our results on sleep quality, quantity, and disturbance in parents of children with epilepsy as well as sleep pattern differences in parents of children with and without epilepsy. Future studies should also include daytime sleep analysis and examine whether parents of children with epilepsy may use daytime napping to compensate for reduced and poor nocturnal sleep.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We gratefully thank contacted authors who provided clarifying information and assistance.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p>The template data collection forms, data extracted from included studies, or other materials used in this review are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, execution, acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation, or in all these areas; took part in drafting, revising or critically reviewing the article; gave final approval of the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0008">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. The abstract of this paper was presented at the conference SLEEP 2023 as a poster presentation with interim findings. The poster’s abstract was published in “Poster Abstracts” in SLEEP as “Sleep and Its Disturbance in Parents of Children and Adolescents with Epilepsy: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis” (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/46/Supplement_1/A345/7182296" ext-link-type="uri">https://academic.oup.com/sleep/article/46/Supplement_1/A345/7182296</ext-link></underline>).</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aaberg</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gunnes</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bakken</surname>
<given-names>IJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Incidence and prevalence of childhood epilepsy: a nationwide cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatrics</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>139</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e20163908</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2016-3908</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28557750</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chiang</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>CY</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalence and neuro-psychiatric comorbidities of pediatric epilepsy in Taiwan: a national population-based study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsy Res</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>108</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1451</fpage>–<lpage>1460</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eplepsyres.2014.07.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25107685</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Russ</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Larson</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Halfon</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A national profile of childhood epilepsy and seizure disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatrics</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>129</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>256</fpage>–<lpage>264</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2010-1371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22271699</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gogou</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haidopoulou</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eboriadou</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pavlou</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disturbances in children with rolandic epilepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropediatrics</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0036-1593611</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27780283</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Qiao</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xiao</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Evaluation of anxiety, depression, and sleep quality among parents of children with epilepsy in Southern China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsy Behav</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>112</volume>:<fpage>107340</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yebeh.2020.107340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32861027</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>PP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yin</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>YH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sheng</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The correlation of family resilience with sleep quality and depression of parents of children with epilepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Pediatr Nurs</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>e49</fpage>–<lpage>e54</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pedn.2020.07.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32800618</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Reilly</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Atkinson</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Memon</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Parenting stress and perceived stigma in mothers of young children with epilepsy: a case-control study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsy Behav</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>112</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yebeh.2018.10.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30412923</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gibbon</surname>
<given-names>FM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maccormac</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gringras</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and epilepsy: unfortunate bedfellows</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Dis Child</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/archdischild-2017-313421</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30266875</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Reilly</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Atkinson</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Memon</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Child and parental sleep in young children with epilepsy: a population-based case-control study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsia Open</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>383</fpage>–<lpage>391</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/epi4.12241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30187009</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ekinci</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Isik</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gunes</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ekinci</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Understanding sleep problems in children with epilepsy: associations with quality of life, attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder and maternal emotional symptoms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Seizure</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>108</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.seizure.2016.06.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27394056</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Manokaran</surname>
<given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tripathi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chakrabarty</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pandey</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gulati</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep abnormalities and polysomnographic profile in children with drug-resistant epilepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Seizure</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>82</volume>:<fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.seizure.2020.09.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33011589</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep architecture and homeostasis in children with epilepsy: a neurodevelopmental perspective</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Dev Med Child Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>62</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>426</fpage>–<lpage>433</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/dmcn.14437</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31879946</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gupta</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dang</surname>
<given-names>LT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Brien</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shellhaas</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Parent-reported sleep profile of children with early-life epilepsies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatr Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>128</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pediatrneurol.2021.12.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34992036</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Winsor</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Richards</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bissell</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seri</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liew</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bagshaw</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disruption in children and adolescents with epilepsy: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>101416</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2021.101416</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33561679</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wood</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sherman</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hamiwka</surname>
<given-names>LD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blackman</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wirrell</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Maternal depression: the cost of caring for a child with intractable epilepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatr Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>418</fpage>–<lpage>422</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pediatrneurol.2008.08.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19027588</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cottrell</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Impact of childhood epilepsy on maternal sleep and socioemotional functioning</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Pediatr</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>613</fpage>–<lpage>616</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/000992280504400709</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shaki</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goldbart</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Daniel</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fraser</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shorer</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pediatric epilepsy and parental sleep quality</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>502</fpage>–<lpage>506</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/JCSM.1318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22003346</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tsai</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>WT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jeng</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weng</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep in mothers of children with epilepsy and its relation to their children’s sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Res Nurs Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>168</fpage>–<lpage>175</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/nur.22008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31903630</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Watson</surname>
<given-names>NF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Badr</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Belenky</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Recommended amount of sleep for a healthy adult: a joint consensus statement of the American Academy of sleep medicine and sleep research society</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>843</fpage>–<lpage>844</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.4716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26039963</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chaput</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dutil</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Featherstone</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration and health in adults: an overview of systematic reviews</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Appl Physiol Nutr Metab</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Medic</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wille</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hemels</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Short- and long-term health consequences of sleep disruption</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Sci Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>161</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S134864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28579842</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Irwin</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and inflammation: partners in sickness and in health</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Immunol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>702</fpage>–<lpage>715</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41577-019-0190-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31289370</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Larson</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ryther</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jennesson</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impact of pediatric epilepsy on sleep patterns and behaviors in children and parents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsia</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1162</fpage>–<lpage>1169</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1528-1167.2012.03515.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22594377</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Page</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McKenzie</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bossuyt</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>372</volume>:<fpage>n71</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33782057</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Moola</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Munn</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tufanaru</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <part-title>Chapter 7: systematic Reviews of Etiology and Risk</part-title>. In: <string-name><surname>Aromataris</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Munn</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, editors. <source><italic toggle="yes">JBI Manual for Evidence Synthesis</italic></source>. <publisher-name>The Joanna Briggs Institute</publisher-name>; <year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Higgins</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thompson</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deeks</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Altman</surname>
<given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Measuring inconsistency in meta-analyses</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>327</volume>(<issue>7414</issue>):<fpage>557</fpage>–<lpage>560</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.327.7414.557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12958120</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Duval</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tweedie</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Trim and fill: a simple funnel-plot-based method of testing and adjusting for publication bias in meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biometrics</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>455</fpage>–<lpage>463</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0006-341X.2000.00455.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10877304</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Egger</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davey Smith</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schneider</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Minder</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Bias in meta-analysis detected by a simple, graphical test</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>315</volume>(<issue>7109</issue>):<fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>634</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.315.7109.629</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9310563</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Painter</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rausch</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Modi</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Changes in daily activity patterns of caregivers of children with newly diagnosed epilepsy: a case-controlled design</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsy Behav</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yebeh.2013.11.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24291521</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Borusiak</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bast</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kluger</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A longitudinal, randomized, and prospective study of nocturnal monitoring in children and adolescents with epilepsy: effects on quality of life and sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsy Behav</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>192</fpage>–<lpage>198</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yebeh.2016.05.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27371884</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ledet</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aplin-Kalisz</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Filter</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dycus</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A pilot study to assess a teaching intervention to improve sleep-wake disturbances in parents of children diagnosed with epilepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurosci Nurs</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JNN.0000000000000179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26720316</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Matthews</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pantesco</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Similarities and differences in estimates of sleep duration by polysomnography, actigraphy, diary, and self-reported habitual sleep in a community sample</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Health</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>96</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleh.2017.10.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29332687</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>CF</given-names> 3rd</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monk</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berman</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kupfer</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Pittsburgh sleep quality index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0165-1781(89)90047-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2748771</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nixon</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thompson</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>DY</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Falling asleep: the determinants of sleep latency</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Dis Child</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>94</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>686</fpage>–<lpage>689</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/adc.2009.157453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19633062</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lange</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sharp</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Altered sleeping arrangements in pediatric patients with epilepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Pediatr</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>635</fpage>–<lpage>642</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/000992280003901102</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zambrelli</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Turner</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vignoli</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep disturbances in Italian children and adolescents with epilepsy: a questionnaire study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsy Behav</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>106</volume>:<fpage>107014</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yebeh.2020.107014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32229412</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
