<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38882924</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">11178088</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">458098</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S458098</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Differences and Risk Factors of Peripheral Blood Immune Cells in Patients with Obstructive Sleep Apnea</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Jiang et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Jiang et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0009-0006-6706-385X</contrib-id><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Ying</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0009-0000-3222-252X</contrib-id><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Chuankai</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Min</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Taiwen</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Xuhong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Wei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine, Zhongnan Hospital of Wuhan University</institution>, <addr-line>Wuhan</addr-line>, <addr-line>430071</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Medical and Nursing School, Wuhan Railway Vocational College of Technology</institution>, <addr-line>Wuhan</addr-line>, <addr-line>430205</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Wei Wang, <institution>Department of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine, Zhongnan Hospital of Wuhan University</institution>, <addr-line>Wuhan</addr-line>, <addr-line>430071</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, <phone content-type="general">Tel +86 15071128246</phone>, Email wangwei1069@163.com</corresp><fn id="ft0001"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>737</fpage><lpage>749</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>05</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Jiang et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Jiang et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) is a respiratory disorder characterized by chronic intermittent hypoxia and fragmented sleep, leading to inflammatory response and oxidative stress. However, the differences in immune inflammatory response in OSA patients with different severity remain unclear.</p></sec><sec><title>Purpose</title><p>This study aims to examine the differences in peripheral blood immune cells and their risk factors in OSA patients.</p></sec><sec><title>Patients and Methods</title><p>A total of 277 snoring patients from the Sleep Respiratory Disorder Monitoring Center of Zhongnan Hospital of Wuhan University were recruited in this study. According to the diagnosis and severity criteria of OSA, the included patients were further divided into simple snoring, mild, moderate, and severe groups. Peripheral blood immune cell counts including white blood cells, neutrophils, lymphocytes, monocytes, eosinophils, basophils, red blood cells, platelets, and polysomnography indicators were collected from the patients.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Compared with simple snoring patients, the OSA patients had increased circular monocyte and basophil count levels. In addition, correlation analysis results indicated that monocyte count was positively associated with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), smoking, apnea-hypopnea index (AHI), the longest apnea duration, and Oxygen desaturation index (ODI), and negatively correlated with average SpO<sub>2</sub> in snoring patients. Finally, multiple linear regression analysis revealed that AHI, COPD, smoking, and maximum heart rate were independent predictors of monocyte count.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>OSA patients had a significant increase in their peripheral blood monocyte count. AHI, COPD, smoking, and maximum heart rate were risk factors for increased peripheral blood monocyte count in OSA patients. These findings suggest that peripheral blood monocytes can be considered an inflammatory biomarker of OSA.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>obstructive sleep apnea</kwd><kwd>peripheral blood cell count</kwd><kwd>monocytes</kwd><kwd>polysomnography</kwd><kwd>inflammatory biomarker</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Zhongnan Hospital of Wuhan University Science, Technology and Innovation Cultivation Fund</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This study was supported by grants from Zhongnan Hospital of Wuhan University Science, Technology and Innovation Cultivation Fund (Grant Number CXPY2022084).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="7"/><ref-count count="47"/><page-count count="13"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) is characterized by upper respiratory collapse, intermittent hypoxia, recurrent arousals, and sleep fragmentation. This results in secondary sympathetic nerve activation, oxidative stress, and systemic inflammation.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Inflammatory response and oxidative stress in OSA patients are risk factors for the occurrence and development of various diseases, including cardiovascular and cerebrovascular diseases, metabolic diseases, cognitive impairment, and tumors.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> It is reported that recurrent intermittent hypoxia and increased oxidative stress during sleep play an important role in immune dysfunction in OSA patients.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4–6</xref></p>
      <p>Previous studies found that peripheral blood cells can reflect the immune inflammatory response.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> They often were regarded as easily measurable biomarkers of inflammation and oxidative stress in OSA, such as neutrophils, lymphocytes, monocytes, hemoglobin, and hematocrit, as well as new biomarkers including neutrophil to lymphocyte ratio (NLR), platelet to lymphocyte ratio (PLR), and systemic inflammatory index (SII).<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9–11</xref> In addition, immune cell-driven inflammation also plays a crucial role in the pathogenesis of OSA. Some pro-inflammatory markers released by peripheral blood cells such as C-reactive protein (CRP), interleukin (IL)‑6, tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-α), erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR) were also strongly associated with OSA severity.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> It is reported that long-term exposure to intermittent hypoxia promotes neutrophil and monocyte infiltration into the liver, leading to strong inflammatory pathways including IL-16 and TNF-α.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Polymorphonuclear neutrophils (PMN) are also key cells in the inflammatory process. The increased number of PMN has been found to play a potential role in the inflammation associated with OSA patients. IL-6, β<sub>2</sub>-adrenergic receptor (ADRB2), and IL-8 may contribute to regulating the activation of PMN, including migration, recruitment, degranulation, exocytosis, and respiratory burst.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></p>
      <p>Therefore, it is crucial to explore the differences in peripheral blood immune cells in patients with obstructive sleep apnea. We assume that peripheral blood cell parameters could indicate the inflammation degree and be a predictive tool for evaluating hypoxia severity in OSA. However, the results from previous studies have been inconsistent, and the reasons for the differences in peripheral blood cells remain unclear. As a cross-sectional study, this study aimed to analyze differences in immune cells in OSA patients of different severity and identify associated risk factors.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Study Population</title>
        <p>This retrospective study was approved by the Ethics Committee of Zhongnan Hospital of Wuhan University (No.2023297K, December 27, 2023) and waived written informed consent from all patients. This study collected 277 snoring patients receiving polysomnography (PSG) monitoring at the Sleep Respiratory Disorder Monitoring Center of Zhongnan Hospital of Wuhan University from 2021 to 2023. The screening process for 277 patients is shown in <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>.
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The screening process of 277 patients.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-737-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
        <p>Diagnosis and disease severity criteria for OSA were defined according to the guidelines.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> The Apnea hypopnea index (AHI) was calculated as the average number of apnea and hypopnea events per hour. Snoring patients were divided into the simple snoring group (AHI &lt;5) and the OSA group (AHI ≥5). The severity of OSA patients was further classified into subgroups of mild (5 ≤ AHI&lt;15), moderate (15 ≤ AHI&lt;30), and severe (AHI ≥30).<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> Patients diagnosed with central sleep apnea, liver or kidney disease, malignant tumors, chronic infectious diseases, inflammatory bowel disease, and hematological disorders such as leukemia, anemia, or myelodysplastic syndrome were excluded from this study.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Data Collection</title>
        <p>Data on the patient characteristics collected in this study included age, sex, body mass index (BMI), smoking status, and comorbidities. Peripheral blood immune cell was evaluated by complete blood count (CBC), including white blood cell (WBC), monocytes, lymphocytes, neutrophils, platelets, eosinophils, and basophils, hemoglobin, red blood cell count (RBC), NLR, PLR, systemic inflammation index (SII: neutrophils × platelets/lymphocytes) were recorded. Additionally, AHI, Oxygen desaturation index (ODI, number of oxygen desaturations per hour of sleep), the sum of all desaturations, the longest apnea duration, the minimum and average pulse oxygen saturation (SpO<sub>2</sub>), the minimum, average, and maximum heart rate during PSG were collected. Apnea was defined as a more than 90% decrease in airflow for 10 seconds. Hypopneas was defined as a reduction in airflow of at least 30% lasting for 10 seconds or more, accompanied by oxygen desaturation of 3% or more, or an electroencephalogram (EEG) awakening.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>Continuous variables were presented as median with interquartile range (IQR). Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test was performed for normally distributed variables, and the Mann–Whitney test was employed for non-normally distributed variables between two groups. The one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) test was used to compare normally distributed variables, and the Kruskal–Wallis <italic toggle="yes">H</italic>-test was used for non-normally distributed variables between OSA subgroups. Categorical variables were expressed as numbers (percentages). The chi-square or Fisher’s exact test was conducted for two groups, and the Kruskal–Wallis <italic toggle="yes">H</italic>-test was used for multiple groups. The Bonferroni test was conducted as a post-test for multiple comparisons. The correlation between variables was examined using Spearman’s or Pearson’s test. The point-biserial correlation, a special form of Pearson’s test was used to assess correlation between continuous variables and dichotomous chronic disease variables. Multiple linear regression analysis was conducted to assess the independent associations between biochemical, clinical, and polysomnography variables. Data analysis used SPSS software (version 25.0, IBM Corporation). Statistical significance was set at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt;0.05.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Demographic and Clinical Profiles</title>
        <p>After the screening, 277 snoring patients (196 with OSA and 81 simple snoring) were included in this study. The median age of OSA patients was 45 (34–61) years, with a body mass index (BMI) of 29 (25.4–33.2) kg/m<sup>2</sup> and 117 (59.7%) being male. The proportion of smokers, hypertension, diabetes, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), and asthma in OSA patients was 21.3%, 39.8%, 15.8%, 8.2%, and 7.7%, respectively. There were significant differences in BMI (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.009), age (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), sex (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), hypertension (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), and smoking (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.004) between the simple snoring and OSA group. Furthermore, significant differences were shown in age (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), hypertension (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), and smoking (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.017) between subgroups. The detailed demographic and clinical data are shown in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Clinical Characteristics of Snoring Patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (N=277)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Simple Snoring (N=81)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSA (N= 196)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild (N= 80)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate (N=46)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe (N=70)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sup>a</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>*</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sex</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001<sup>b,c,d</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">141 (50.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (29.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">117 (59.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (51.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (58.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (70)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">136 (49.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (70.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79 (40.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (48.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (41.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age</bold> (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (32–59)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (28.5–47)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (34–61)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (31–60)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (39.25–66.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.5 (38.75–61.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001<sup>b,c,d</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>BMI (</bold>kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (26–33.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.8 (27–34.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (25.4–33.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.1 (25–34.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (26–33.08)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.2 (26.0–32.13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.009</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.063</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Comorbidities</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hypertension</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (31.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (11.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (39.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (28.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (47.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (47.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001<sup>b,c</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Coronary disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (5.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (6.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (5.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (8.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (5.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.702</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Diabetes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (15.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (15.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (18.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (21.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (8.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.962</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.215</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> COPD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (7.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (4.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (8.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (8.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (5.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.346</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.597</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Asthma</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (5.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (7.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (11.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (6.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.072</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.045</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Smoking</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (17.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (7.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (21.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (28.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (26.92)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (21.21)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.004</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.017<sup>c</sup></bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Data are presented as median (IQR) or n (%). P<sup>a</sup> indicates differences between simple snoring and OSA groups. *The Kruskal–Wallis <italic toggle="yes">H</italic>-test or Chi-square test (post hoc: Bonferroni). <sup>b</sup>Comparison between simple snoring and severe OSA group. <sup>c</sup>Comparison between simple snoring and moderate OSA. <sup>d</sup>Comparison between simple snoring and mild OSA. Bold values indicate statistical differences. The criteria for hypertension: without the use of antihypertensive drugs, the systolic blood pressure (SBP) in the examination room is ≥ 140 mmHg and/or the diastolic blood pressure (DBP) is ≥ 90 mmHg. The criteria for coronary disease: coronary atherosclerotic heart disease, refers to the heart disease caused by myocardial ischemia, hypoxia or necrosis due to stenosis or occlusion of the lumen caused by coronary atherosclerosis. The criteria for diabetes: fasting plasma glucose ≥ 7.0 mmol/L or 2-h plasma glucose ≥ 11.1 mmol/L during oral glucose tolerance test or glycohemoglobin A1C ≥ 6.5% or in a patient with classic symptoms of hyperglycemia or hyperglycemic crisis, a random plasma glucose ≥ 11.1 mmol/L.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: BMI, body mass index; COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Differences in Blood Immune Cells in Snoring Patients</title>
        <p>The hematological profiles are shown in <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Compared with the simple snoring group, the OSA patients had increased levels of peripheral blood monocyte (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and basophil (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.012) counts. After conducting a post hoc analysis, there was a significant difference in the monocyte count between the simple snoring group and the severe OSA group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.001). Additionally, the post-test results showed a statistically significant difference in basophil count between the simple snoring group and the moderate OSA group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.036). No significant differences were observed in other peripheral blood parameters (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Peripheral Blood Immune Cells Expression in Snoring Patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (N=277)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Simple Snoring (N=81)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSA (N= 196)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild (N= 80)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate (N=46)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe (N=70)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sup>a</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>*</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>WBC (× 10<sup>9</sup>/L)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5 (5.3–7.84)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.49 (5.32–7.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5 (5.28–7.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 (5.1–7.45)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4 (5–8.64)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.56 (5.86–8.07)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.819</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.459</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Neutrophils (× 10<sup>9</sup>/L)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8 (3.02–4.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8 (3.15–4.63)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8 (2.9–4.81)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.73 (2.9–4.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.84 (2.8–5.32)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.97 (3.02–5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.777</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.504</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Lymphocytes (× 10<sup>9</sup>/L)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9 (1.43–2.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.92 (1.6–2.43)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9 (1.4–2.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.91 (1.4–2.23)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.88 (1.38–2.23)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8 (1.4–2.24)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.267</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.667</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Monocytes (× 10<sup>9</sup>/L)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47 (0.4–0.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 (0.31–0.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0.4–0.62)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47 (0.4–0.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0.38–0.64)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0.4–0.69)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.001<sup>b</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Eosinophils (× 10<sup>9</sup>/L)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125 (0.1–0.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 (0.009–0.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 (0.1–0.21)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 (0.1–0.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.175 (0.1–0.26)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16 (0.1–0.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.127</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.087</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Basophils (× 10<sup>9</sup>/L)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 (0–0.0475)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0–0.03)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 (0–0.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 (0–0.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 (0–0.053)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 (0–0.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.012</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.036<sup>c</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>RBC (× 10<sup>12</sup>/L)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.59 (4.19–4.89)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7 (4.3–4.89)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.55 (4.16–4.89)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.47 (4.13–4.87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.46 (4.05–4.76)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.67 (4.3–5.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.145</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hemoglobin (g/L)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">137 (127–148)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">137 (124.5–147.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">137.7 (128–149)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">136.1 (129.1–145.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">134.6 (124–146.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">141 (130–154.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.397</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.102</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Platelets (× 10<sup>9</sup>/L)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">228.5 (188.25–276)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">238 (203–283.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">226 (184–274.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">238 (190–278)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">227.5 (175.75–271)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">217.5 (182.75–272.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.175</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.337</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NLR</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.54–2.68)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06 (1.5–2.49)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.557–2.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94 (1.53–2.69)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.05 (1.47–2.71)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.05 (1.62–3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.375</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.669</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PLR</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">126.78 (100–160.87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125.52 (101.78–160.45)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">127.35 (99.05–160.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">129.6 (105–169.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128.22 (86.5–165.42)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125.12 (93.83–156.12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.889</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.649</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SII</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">456.91 (357.75–635.67)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">499.38 (359.87–620.52)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">456.73 (353.77–666.58)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">473.59 (366.36–625.45)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">442.1 (332.78–695.04)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">451.47 (348.7–667)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.968</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.992</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Data are presented as median (IQR). <italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sup>a</sup> indicates differences between simple snoring and OSA groups. *The Kruskal–Wallis <italic toggle="yes">H</italic>-test (post hoc: Bonferroni). <sup>b</sup>Comparison between simple snoring and severe OSA group. <sup>c</sup>Comparison between simple snoring and moderate OSA. Bold values indicate statistical differences.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: WBC, white blood cells; RBC, red blood cells; NLR, neutrophils to lymphocyte ratio; PLR, platelet to lymphocyte ratio; SII, systemic inflammatory index.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Polysomnographic Parameters in Snoring Patients</title>
        <p>The polysomnography indicators in snoring patients are presented in <xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. There were significant differences in AHI (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), the longest apnea duration (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), the sum of all desaturations (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), ODI (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), minimum SpO<sub>2</sub> (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), average SpO<sub>2</sub> (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), and minimum heart rate (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) between OSA patients and simple snoring patients. Moreover, significant differences were observed in AHI, the longest apnea duration, the sum of all desaturations, and ODI between four subgroups. However, no significant difference was observed in maximum and average heart rate between OSA and simple snoring patients.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Polysomnographic Parameters in Snoring Patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (N=277)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Simple Snoring (N=81)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSA (N= 196)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild (N= 80)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate (N=46)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe (N=70)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sup>a</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>*</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AHI</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8 (3.7–30.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9 (0.65–3.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.3 (11.05–38.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.75 (7.1–12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.75 (18.9–24.43)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.8 (36.28–61.63)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001<sup>e</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>The longest apnea duration</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.65 (18.28–57)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7 (0–24.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.9 (31–62.48)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (21.2–40.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.5 (33.6–50.38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.55 (48.85–81.18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001<sup>e</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>The sum of all desaturations</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.5 (46–219.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (17.5–69.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">158.5 (84.75–308.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (63–133)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">138.5 (98–200)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">329 (216–445.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001<sup>e</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ODI</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.95 (5.88–30.08)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8 (2.35–8.35)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1 (12.2–42.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2 (8.5–16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.85 (17.63–26.68)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.35 (30.08–58.43)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001<sup>e</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Minimum SpO<sub>2</sub> (%)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79 (67–86)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (73.5–90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.5 (65–84.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 (72–88)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (71.5–84.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.5 (60–79)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001<sup>b</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Average SpO<sub>2</sub> (%)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95 (93.6–96)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96 (95–97)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.4 (93–96)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95 (94–96.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94 (92.68–95.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93 (90.98–95)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001<sup>b,c</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Maximum heart rate</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109 (99–116.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110 (100–120)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107 (98–116)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109 (99–117)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109 (104.75–116.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103 (95–114)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.134</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.04<sup>b</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Minimum heart rate</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (43–56)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (48–59)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (41–54)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (43–54)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.5 (39–56.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (39.75–52.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001<sup>b,c,d</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Average heart rate</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.25 (63–75.28)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.2 (62.8–75.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.55 (63–75.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.2 (62.3–74.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70 (65.45–77.48)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.3 (63–75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.584</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.164</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Data are presented as median (IQR). <italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sup>a</sup> indicates differences between simple snoring and OSA groups. *The Kruskal–Wallis <italic toggle="yes">H</italic>-test (post hoc: Bonferroni). <sup>b</sup>Comparison between simple snoring and severe OSA group. <sup>c</sup>Comparison between simple snoring and moderate OSA. <sup>d</sup>Comparison between simple snoring and mild OSA. <sup>e</sup>Comparison between simple snoring, mild, moderate, and severe OSA subgroups. Bold values indicate statistical differences.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0006"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: AHI, apnea-hypopnea index; ODI, Oxygen desaturation index.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Correlation Between Peripheral Blood Cells with Clinical and Polysomnographic Parameters in Snoring Patients</title>
        <p>Spearman or Pearson test was conducted to investigate the relationship between blood immune cells with clinical and polysomnographic parameters (<xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Monocytes were associated positively with COPD (r = 0.224, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), smoking (r = 0.261, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), AHI (r = 0.261, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), the longest apnea duration (r = 0.181, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.002), the sum of all desaturations (r = 0.169, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.005), ODI (r = 0.194, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.001) respectively, and negatively with average SpO<sub>2</sub> (r = −0.179, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.003). Moreover, a significant correlation was observed between basophils and AHI (r = 0.12, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.046) and ODI (r = 0.136, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.024). The correlation analysis results for other blood parameters including WBC, neutrophils, lymphocytes, eosinophils, RBC, hemoglobin, platelets, NLR, PLR, and SII are presented in <xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. The differences in peripheral blood immune cells in snoring patients with or without hypertension, COPD, and smoking are shown in <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0004" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Correlation Between Blood Immune Cells with Clinical and Polysomnographic Parameters in Snoring Patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBC</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutrophils</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymphocytes</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monocytes</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eosinophils</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basophils</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">RBC</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemoglobin</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Platelets</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NLR</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLR</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SII</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>Age</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>r</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.306</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.197</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.493</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.060</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.406</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.269</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.412</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.258</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.223</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.317</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.568</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.593</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.800</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>BMI</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>r</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.192</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.168</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.219</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.113</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.064</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.025</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.238</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.148</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.173</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0</bold>.052</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0</bold>.107</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.036</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.060</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.292</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.677</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.000</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.013</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.004</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.391</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.075</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.553</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>Hypertension</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>r</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.122</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.052</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.259</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.117</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.142</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.094</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.307</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.166</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.403</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.415</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.604</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.060</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.023</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.130</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.008</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.261</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.842</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>Diabetes</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>r</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.066</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.036</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.069</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.087</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.065</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.095</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.825</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.296</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.570</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.950</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.277</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.756</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.630</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.856</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.671</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.165</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.304</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.132</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>COPD</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>r</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.052</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.232</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.224</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.059</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.018</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.091</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.208</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.149</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.136</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.853</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.415</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.457</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.885</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.357</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.773</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.152</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.019</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.032</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>Asthma</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>r</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.074</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.039</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.143</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.050</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.081</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.063</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.026</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.046</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.062</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.133</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.102</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.080</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.243</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.535</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.024</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.433</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.204</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.317</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.686</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.471</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.332</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.035</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.107</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.209</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>Smoking</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>r</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.089</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.099</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.054</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.261</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.176</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.065</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.126</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.050</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.101</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.159</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.117</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.395</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.594</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.942</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.623</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.306</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.045</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.433</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.109</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>AHI</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>r</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.087</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.084</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.050</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.261</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.149</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.120</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.120</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.118</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.079</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.043</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.004</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.149</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.163</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.407</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.013</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.046</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.650</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.046</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.050</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.190</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.478</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.942</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>The longest apnea duration</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>r</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−00.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.181</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.119</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.060</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.115</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.125</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.067</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.059</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.483</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.746</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.509</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.002</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.047</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.322</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.517</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.055</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.038</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.573</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.268</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.328</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>The sum of all desaturations</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>r</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.172</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.163</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.058</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.169</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.081</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.141</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.162</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.184</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.087</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.071</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.062</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.004</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.006</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.335</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.178</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.007</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.002</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.723</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.148</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.236</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.305</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>ODI</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>r</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.158</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.154</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.194</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.104</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.136</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.138</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.170</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.102</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.038</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.072</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.008</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.010</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.614</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.084</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.024</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.022</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.697</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.089</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.528</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.233</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>Minimum SpO<sub>2</sub></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>r</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.130</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.139</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.045</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.040</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.038</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.092</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.118</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.050</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.117</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.030</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.021</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.742</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.455</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.507</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.527</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.744</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.793</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.050</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.403</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>Average SpO<sub>2</sub></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>r</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.153</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.188</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.179</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.045</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.084</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.042</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.110</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.122</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.018</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.117</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.011</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.002</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.723</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.003</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.455</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.162</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.488</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.959</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.042</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.763</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.052</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>Maximum heart rate</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>r</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.234</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.200</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.203</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.054</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.190</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.287</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.027</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.141</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.853</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.371</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.002</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.447</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.658</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.715</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>Minimum heart rate</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>r</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.049</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.085</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.039</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.053</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.097</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.069</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.110</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.092</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.902</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.558</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.415</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.157</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.796</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.514</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.622</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.384</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.109</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.249</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.068</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.128</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>Average heart rate</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>r</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.275</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.255</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.142</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.102</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.005</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.122</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.032</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.239</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.076</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.183</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.018</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.110</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.090</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.929</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.044</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.598</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.210</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.600</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.002</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0007"><p><bold>Note</bold>: Bold values indicate statistical differences.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0008"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: WBC, white blood cells; RBC, red blood cells; NLR, neutrophils to lymphocyte ratio; PLR, platelet to lymphocyte ratio; SII, systemic inflammatory index; BMI, body mass index; COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; AHI, apnea-hypopnea index; ODI, Oxygen desaturation index.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Peripheral Blood Immune Cell Expression in Snoring Patients with and without Clinical Comorbidities</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Hypertension</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">COPD</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Smoking</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">With (N=87)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Without</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">With (N=20)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Without</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">With (N=49)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Without</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>WBC (× 10<sup>9</sup>/L)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.12 (4.78–7.39)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.70 (5.60–7.90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.04 (4.79–8.40)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.50 (5.30–7.80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.852</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.85 (5.60–8.49)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.35 (5.28–7.70)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.159</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Neutrophils (× 10<sup>9</sup>/L)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.73 (2.80–4.43)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.80 (3.10–4.80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.402</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.14 (2.88–5.61)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.79 (3.01–4.68)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.414</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.84 (3.29–5.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.78 (2.90–4.57)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.117</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Lymphocytes (× 10<sup>9</sup>/L)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65 (1.24–2.11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00 (1.65–2.45)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43 (1.08–1.69)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.91 (1.50–2.40)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90 (1.16–2.30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90 (1.50–2.31)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.394</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Monocytes (× 10<sup>9</sup>/L)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46 (0.39–0.63)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43 (0.40–0.60)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.414</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65 (0.45–0.83)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41 (0.39–0.60)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 (0.43–0.73)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41 (0.37–0.58)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Eosinophils (× 10<sup>9</sup>/L)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 (0.10–0.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11 (0.10–0.20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.603</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20 (0.10–0.23)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12 (0.10–0.20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.456</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15 (0.10–0.27)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 (0.10–0.20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.593</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Basophils (× 10<sup>9</sup>/L)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 (0.00–0.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00–0.04)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.060</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 (0.00–0.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00–0.04)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.885</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00–0.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00–0.04)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.942</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>RBC (× 10<sup>12</sup>/L)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.39 (4.00–4.83)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.59 (4.32–4.88)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.023</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.26 (3.86–4.98)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.56 (4.2–4.85)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.356</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.55 (4.18–4.87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.57 (4.16–4.84)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.622</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hemoglobin (g/L)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">133.00 (123.98–147.33)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">137.70 (129.30–147.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.130</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">133.70 (124.80–148.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">137.00 (126.63–146.88)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.772</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">143.00 (133.70–152.70)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">135.00 (125.00–145.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Platelets</bold> (× 10<sup>9</sup>/L)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">201.00 (170.00–242.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">246.00 (207.00–286.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">215.50 (177.25–233.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">230.50 (188.00–277.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.152</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">219.00 (191.50–260.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">231.00 (187.75–279.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.305</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NLR</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.22 (1.57–3.30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94 (1.53–2.41)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.008</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.86 (2.25–4.55)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.97 (1.52–2.47)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.26 (1.62–3.02)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.97 (1.52–2.47)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.045</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PLR</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">131.33 (98–171.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125.52 (99.64–158.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.259</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">173.79 (107.86–211.01)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125.62 (98.69–158.55)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.019</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">129.60 (95.70–181.11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">126.64 (99.18–158.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.432</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SII</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">463.79 (313.86–680.79)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">465.95 (364.00–612.89)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.841</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">609.72 (436.03–1076.48)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">453.43 (351.28–622.41)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.032</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">522.84 (356.97–697.59)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">453.36 (349.81–617.13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.109</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0009"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Data are presented as median (IQR). Bold values indicate statistical differences.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0010"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: WBC, white blood cells; RBC, red blood cells; NLR, neutrophils to lymphocyte ratio; PLR, platelet to lymphocyte ratio; SII, systemic inflammatory index; COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2005">
        <title>Risk Factors for Increased Peripheral Blood Monocyte and Basophil Count in Snoring Patients</title>
        <p>In multiple linear regression, monocytes were independently associated with AHI (β = 0.314, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.005), COPD (β = 0.15, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.029), smoking (β = 0.189, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.004), and maximum heart rate (β = 0.161, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.015) (<xref rid="t0006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). However, there was no significance of the basophil’s regression model (<xref rid="t0007" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0006"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Multiple Linear Regression Analysis for Peripheral Blood Monocyte Count in Snoring Patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">β</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<sup>2</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value of Model</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.882</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.139</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>BMI</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.034</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.611</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AHI</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.314</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>COPD</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.150</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.029</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Smoking</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.189</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.004</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>The longest apnea duration</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.814</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ODI</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.157</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.137</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Minimum SPO<sub>2</sub></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.093</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.196</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Average SPO<sub>2</sub></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.131</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Maximum heart rate</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.161</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.015</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Minimum heart rate</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.724</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0011"><p><bold>Note</bold>: Bold values indicate statistical differences.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0012"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: BMI, body mass index; AHI, apnea-hypopnea index; COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; ODI, Oxygen desaturation index.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0007"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Multiple Linear Regression Analysis for Peripheral Blood Basophil Count in Snoring Patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">β</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<sup>2</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value of Model</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AHI</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.058</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.581</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Asthma</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0. 082</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.198</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Smoking</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.044</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.493</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>The longest apnea duration</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.039</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.631</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ODI</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.163</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.105</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0013"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: AHI, apnea-hypopnea index; ODI, Oxygen desaturation index.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>OSA leads to various pathophysiological processes in the body such as sympathetic nervous system hyperactivity, oxidative stress, metabolic disorders, endothelial dysfunction, and airway inflammation, which causes systemic damage to multiple organs including immune dysfunction.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> In our study, we investigated the differences in all peripheral blood immune cells and further analyzed risk factors for these differences in snoring patients of different severity. We found that the OSA patients had increased peripheral blood monocyte and basophil counts compared with simple snoring patients. Moreover, they increased gradually with the OSA severity. In addition, multiple linear regression analysis identified AHI, COPD, smoking, and maximum heart rate as independent predictors of monocyte count in OSA patients.</p>
      <p>The level of blood monocytes is an indicator of the body’s inflammatory state.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Sleep deprivation or restriction increases circulating monocytes and inflammatory cytokine production.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> It was reported that the two fundamental pathophysiological mechanisms of OSA characterized by chronic intermittent hypoxia and sleep fragmentation interact with the immune system triggered by monocytes.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> In addition, monocytes increase NLRP3 (NLR family pyrin domain containing 3) signaling under intermittent hypoxia conditions, leading to systemic inflammatory response.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Consistent with our results, a previous study demonstrated a positive association between monocytes and the severity of OSA measured by AHI.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> At the same time, SpO<sub>2</sub> which considers the duration of intermittent oxygen desaturations was strongly and independently associated with specific inflammatory parameters including monocytes.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Besides, studies have demonstrated a positive correlation between basophils and the severity of OSA, which is consistent with our findings.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> However, we did not find any risk factors for elevated basophils in OSA patients, possibly due to insufficient sample size and data to analyze and draw correct conclusions. Thus, larger detailed investigations are needed to reveal the relationship between basophils and OSA in the future. Our findings suggest that intermittent hypoxia triggers systemic inflammation, leading to an increase in circulating monocytes. Therefore, peripheral monocyte count may be considered a valuable assessment tool for intermittent hypoxia in OSA.</p>
      <p>COPD is a chronic airway inflammatory disease with persistent airflow obstruction due to exposure to inhaled particulate matter such as cigarettes and air pollutants.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> COPD and OSA coexist and are accompanied by episodes in the same patient, defined as the “overlap syndrome”.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Patients with overlap syndrome experience a more significant reduction in nocturnal oxygen saturation and increased daytime hypercapnia compared to patients with either COPD or OSA alone.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> These patients exhibit elevated levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines and reduced levels of anti-inflammatory cytokines resulting in a sustained state of chronic inflammation.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> Therefore, more severe airway inflammatory states were observed in patients with overlap syndrome compared to those with COPD alone.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> Likewise, a clinical study indicated that patients with overlap syndrome exhibit more severe endothelial damage, stronger inflammatory response, and lower cellular immune function.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> Smoking can mobilize an increase in blood monocytes, which exacerbate inflammation in various diseases including chronic lung injury, tuberculosis, and ischemic brain injuries.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33–35</xref> A systematic review showed that smokers have elevated levels of AHI and reduced minimum SaO<sub>2</sub> levels in OSA patients.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> In brief, smoking leads to OSA development through various mechanisms, including airway inflammation, changes in sleep structure, unstable awakening mechanisms, and alterations in upper airway neuromuscular function.<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> Further, smoking increases systemic oxidative stress and inflammatory response.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> In our study, COPD and smoking were independently associated with peripheral monocyte count, suggesting concomitant COPD exacerbates inflammation levels in OSA patients. Therefore, assessing COPD comorbidities and smoking status might be important for OSA patients’ inflammation levels in clinical practice.</p>
      <p>In addition, our results showed that the maximum heart rate was associated with the monocytes. Hypoxemia and hypercapnia act on oxygen and carbon dioxide through peripheral and central chemoreceptors to increase the activity of the sympathetic nervous system in OSA.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Moreover, OSA patients experience elevated heart rate and muscle sympathetic activity during wakefulness, with further increases in blood pressure and sympathetic activity during sleep.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> The heart rate also increases during inflammation situations. Thus, the maximum heart rate in OSA patients may also be related to systematic inflammation conditions. OSA patients can conveniently monitor their sympathetic nervous activity and inflammatory response during sleep by measuring their heart rate.</p>
      <p>Lymphocytes also play an important role in inflammation and immune disease as executors of immune function.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> Vicente E et al found increased CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells in pharyngeal lavage of OSA patients than those in controls.<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> In a previous study investigating phenotypic changes of various peripheral blood immune cells in patients with sleep apnea/hypopnea syndrome (OSAHS), significant differences were found in CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> T lymphocytes, CD19<sup>+</sup> B cells, and natural killer (NK) like T cells between OSAHS patients and control group. The authors also found the CD4<sup>+</sup>/CD8<sup>+</sup> T lymphocyte ratio is positively correlated with AHI and negatively correlated with the lowest SaO<sub>2</sub>. However, no significant difference was observed in the percentage of CD3<sup>+</sup> total T cells and dendritic cells between the OSAHS and control groups.<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> Consistent with our results, no significant differences were observed in peripheral blood total lymphocyte count. We will analyze the differential expression of peripheral blood lymphocyte subsets in OSA patients in further studies.</p>
      <p>In addition, immune cell-driven inflammation is also associated with OSA and its severity. Increased IL-8 levels were observed in peripheral blood mononuclear cells supernatant of OSA children than in controls.<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> Likewise, a recent study involving different severe patients with OSA found that serum markers of high-sensitivity (hs)-CRP, TGF-β1, TNF-α, and IL-6 in OSA patients were significantly increased compared with normal controls.<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> However, Guasti L et al found that there was no difference in TNF-α releasing from peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) and IL-8 produced by PMNs between OSA and control groups when similar prevalence of cardiovascular risk factors and cardio-metabolic therapies.<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> These differences may have occurred because only moderate and severe OSA patients with AHI greater than 20 were included in this study. Besides, the different statistical power and designs of these researches may also have influenced the final results. This may explain the differences in results between these studies and also highlights that future studies may take into account cardiovascular risk factors and cardiovascular treatments when exploring the role of cytokine imbalance and inflammation in OSA patients.</p>
      <p>It was found that systemic inflammatory markers CRP, ESR, and NLR were correlated with OSA severity.<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> The SII, NLR, and PLR reflect the body’s extensive immune and inflammatory states and have been used as new white blood-cell-based inflammatory indices in OSA. A cross-sectional study consistent with our results demonstrated that no significant difference was observed in the SII, NLR, and PLR between the different severe OSA subgroups. The further subgroup analysis showed a significant positive correlation between AHI and SII in the severe OSA subgroup.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></p>
      <p>Our research has some limitations. Firstly, this study was a retrospective data analysis from a single center. The co-location of data collection and laboratory testing in a single hospital setting may lead to selection bias. Secondly, the sample size of OSA patients in our study was relatively small, which may limit the analysis and interpretation of the results. Thirdly, peripheral blood immune cell counts and polysomnography parameters from healthy subjects were absent. Therefore, further studies are required to validate the results in a more diverse and larger population.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Our study showed that increased levels of blood monocyte and basophil counts were found in OSA patients compared with simple snorers. AHI, COPD, smoking, and maximum heart rate were risk factors for elevated peripheral blood monocyte count in OSA patients. These findings suggest that monocytes in peripheral blood could serve as an inflammatory biomarker for OSA, which contributes to a better understanding of hypoxia and systemic inflammation levels in OSA patients.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Statement of Ethics</title>
      <p>This study adhered to the Guidelines for Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) and complied with the tenets underlying the Declaration of Helsinki. This retrospective study was approved by the Ethics Committee of Zhongnan Hospital of Wuhan University (No.2023297K) and waived written informed consent from all patients. We have de-identified all patient information to protect the participants’ privacy. The date of approval by the Ethics Committee was December 27, 2023.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation, or in all these areas; took part in drafting, revising or critically reviewing the article; gave final approval of the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0008">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lévy</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kohler</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McNicholas</surname>
<given-names>WT</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnoea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Dis Primers</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>15015</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrdp.2015.15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27188535</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Redline</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Azarbarzin</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peker</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnoea heterogeneity and cardiovascular disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>560</fpage>–<lpage>573</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41569-023-00846-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36899115</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gleeson</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McNicholas</surname>
<given-names>WT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Bidirectional relationships of comorbidity with obstructive sleep apnoea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Respir Rev</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>164</issue>):<fpage>210256</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/16000617.0256-2021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35508332</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>DK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>BC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Son</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effect of obstructive sleep apnea on immunity in cases of chronic rhinosinusitis with nasal polyps</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Exp Otorhinolaryngol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>390</fpage>–<lpage>398</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21053/ceo.2020.02250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33541034</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Geovanini</surname>
<given-names>GR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weng</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Elevations in neutrophils with obstructive sleep apnea: the Multi-Ethnic Study of Atherosclerosis (Mesa)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>257</volume>:<fpage>318</fpage>–<lpage>323</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijcard.2017.10.121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29506719</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Said</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Al-Abri</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Al-Saidi</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Altered blood cytokines, CD4 T cells, NK and neutrophils in patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Immunol Lett</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>190</volume>:<fpage>272</fpage>–<lpage>278</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.imlet.2017.08.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28830779</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nøst</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alcala</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Urbarova</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Systemic inflammation markers and cancer incidence in the UK Biobank</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>841</fpage>–<lpage>848</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10654-021-00752-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34036468</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thomassen</surname>
<given-names>JQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nordestgaard</surname>
<given-names>BG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tybjaerg-Hansen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frikke-Schmidt</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Neutrophil counts and cardiovascular disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Heart J</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>47</issue>):<fpage>4953</fpage>–<lpage>4964</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehad649</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37950632</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cho</surname>
<given-names>SW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Won</surname>
<given-names>TB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rhee</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Associations between systemic inflammatory markers based on blood cells and polysomnographic factors in obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Exp Otorhinolaryngol</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>164</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21053/ceo.2022.01368</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36916031</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zorlu</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ozyurt</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bırcan</surname>
<given-names>HA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Erturk</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Do complete blood count parameters predict diagnosis and disease severity in obstructive sleep apnea syndrome?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>4027</fpage>–<lpage>4036</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26355/eurrev_202106_26044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34156681</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Deniz Doğan 1 RÖ</collab>. <article-title>Possible changes in hematological parameters of the patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Gulhane Med J</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tan</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The causal relationships between obstructive sleep apnea and elevated CRP and TNF-α protein levels</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1578</fpage>–<lpage>1589</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07853890.2022.2081873</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35652886</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Popadic</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brajkovic</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Klasnja</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Correlation of dyslipidemia and inflammation with obstructive sleep apnea severity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Pharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>897279</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphar.2022.897279</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35694268</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gaucher</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Montellier</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vial</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Long-term intermittent hypoxia in mice induces inflammatory pathways implicated in sleep apnea and steatohepatitis in humans</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">iScience</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>108837</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.isci.2024.108837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38303705</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ferrari</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sica</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Bernardi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Reduction of IL-6, IL-8 and β2-ADRENOCEPTOR mRNA levels in circulating polymorphonuclear leukocytes after adenotonsillectomy in children with obstructive sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>114</volume>:<fpage>82</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2023.12.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38157624</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Berry</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brooks</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gamaldo</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, et al; <collab>for the American Academy of Sleep Medicine</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">The AASM Manual for the Scoring of Sleep and Associated Events: Rules, Terminology and Technical Specifications, Version 2.2</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Darien, Illinois</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</publisher-name>; <year>2015</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</collab>. <article-title>Sleep-related breathing disorders in adults: recommendations for syndrome definition and measurement techniques in clinical research. The report of an American Academy of sleep medicine task force</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>667</fpage>–<lpage>689</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10450601</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gottlieb</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Punjabi</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Diagnosis and Management of Obstructive Sleep Apnea: a Review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>323</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>1389</fpage>–<lpage>1400</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.3514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32286648</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Drager</surname>
<given-names>LF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Togeiro</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Polotsky</surname>
<given-names>VY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lorenzi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea a cardiometabolic risk in obesity and the metabolic syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>62</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>569</fpage>–<lpage>576</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2013.05.045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23770180</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pamer</surname>
<given-names>EG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Monocyte recruitment during infection and inflammation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Immunol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>762</fpage>–<lpage>774</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nri3070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21984070</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Carroll</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carrillo</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olmstead</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep deprivation and divergent toll-like receptor-4 activation of cellular inflammation in aging</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.4398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25325509</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lasselin</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rehman</surname>
<given-names>JU</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Åkerstedt</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lekander</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Axelsson</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effect of long-term sleep restriction and subsequent recovery sleep on the diurnal rhythms of white blood cell subpopulations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Behav Immun</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2014.10.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25451611</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Maniaci</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Iannella</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cocuzza</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Oxidative stress and inflammation biomarker expression in obstructive sleep apnea patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>277</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm10020277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33451164</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Díaz-García</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>García-Tovar</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alfaro</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Inflammasome activation: a keystone of proinflammatory response in obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>205</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1337</fpage>–<lpage>1348</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.202106-1445OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35363597</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fan</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Long</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The association of hemocyte profile and obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Lab Anal</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e22680</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcla.22680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30246267</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pau</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zinellu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mangoni</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Evaluation of inflammation and oxidative stress markers in patients with Obstructive Sleep Apnea (OSA)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Med</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>3935</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm12123935</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37373630</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cummins</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Waseem</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Piyasena</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Can the complete blood count be used as a reliable screening tool for obstructive sleep apnea?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>613</fpage>–<lpage>620</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-021-02383-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34185230</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Christenson</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bafadhel</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Putcha</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>399</volume>(<issue>10342</issue>):<fpage>2227</fpage>–<lpage>2242</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0140-6736(22)00470-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35533707</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McNicholas</surname>
<given-names>WT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease and obstructive sleep apnea: overlaps in pathophysiology, systemic inflammation, and cardiovascular disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>180</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>692</fpage>–<lpage>700</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.200903-0347PP</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19628778</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chaszczewska-Markowska</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Górna</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bogunia-Kubik</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brzecka</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kosacka</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The influence of comorbidities on chemokine and cytokine profile in obstructive sleep apnea patients: preliminary results</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Med</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>801</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm12030801</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36769452</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea exacerbates airway inflammation in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1123</fpage>–<lpage>1130</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2015.04.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26298789</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hou</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dong</surname>
<given-names>LX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cao</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Endothelial function and T-lymphocyte subsets in patients with overlap syndrome of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease and obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin Med J</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>132</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>1654</fpage>–<lpage>1659</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/cm9.0000000000000312</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31283649</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sangani</surname>
<given-names>RG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deepak</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Anwar</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghio</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cigarette smoking, and blood monocyte count correlate with chronic lung injuries and mortality</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Chronic Obstr Pulm Dis</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>431</fpage>–<lpage>446</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/copd.S397667</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baluku</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nabwana</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kansiime</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nuwagira</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cigarette smoking is associated with an increase in blood monocytes in people with tuberculosis: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Medicine</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>101</volume>(<issue>37</issue>):<fpage>e30737</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/md.0000000000030737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36123871</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>HD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>XP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Exposure to cigarette smoke augments post-ischemic brain injury and inflammation via mobilization of neutrophils and monocytes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Immunol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>2576</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2019.02576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31787973</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zeng</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ren</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association between smoking behavior and obstructive sleep apnea: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nicotine Tob Res</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>364</fpage>–<lpage>371</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ntr/ntac126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35922388</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pataka</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kotoulas</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kalamaras</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Does Smoking Affect OSA? What about smoking cessation?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Med</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>5164</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm11175164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36079094</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McNicholas</surname>
<given-names>WT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hansson</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schiza</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grote</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep in chronic respiratory disease: COPD and hypoventilation disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Respir Rev</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>153</issue>):<fpage>190064</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/16000617.0064-2019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31554703</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Caliri</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tommasi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Besaratinia</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Relationships among smoking, oxidative stress, inflammation, macromolecular damage, and cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mutat Res Rev Mutat Res</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>787</volume>:<fpage>108365</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mrrev.2021.108365</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34083039</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Somers</surname>
<given-names>VK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dyken</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clary</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abboud</surname>
<given-names>FM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sympathetic neural mechanisms in obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Invest</italic></source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>96</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1897</fpage>–<lpage>1904</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/jci118235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7560081</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Saigusa</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Winkels</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ley</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>T cell subsets and functions in atherosclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>387</fpage>–<lpage>401</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41569-020-0352-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32203286</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vicente</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marin</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carrizo</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Upper airway and systemic inflammation in obstructive sleep apnoea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Respir J</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1108</fpage>–<lpage>1117</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.00234-2016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27587551</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yin</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bai</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bai</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Differential expression of immune markers in the patients with obstructive sleep apnea/hypopnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>276</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>735</fpage>–<lpage>744</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00405-018-5219-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30560392</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ke</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kitamura</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lejtenyi</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mazer</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brouillette</surname>
<given-names>RT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Enhanced interleukin-8 production in mononuclear cells in severe pediatric obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Allergy Asthma Clin Immunol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>23</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13223-019-0338-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31015845</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tosun</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Babayigit</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dikmen</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dogan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dirican</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effect of continuous positive airway pressure treatment on inflammatory parameters and periostin levels in patients with obstructive sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-022-02616-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35478293</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Guasti</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marino</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cosentino</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cytokine production from peripheral blood mononuclear cells and polymorphonuclear leukocytes in patients studied for suspected obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-009-0315-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19924457</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zota</surname>
<given-names>IM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adam</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marcu</surname>
<given-names>DTM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>CPAP influence on readily available inflammatory markers in OSA-A Pilot study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Mol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>12431</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms232012431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36293288</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
