<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38974692</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">11225998</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">458294</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S458294</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Cerebrospinal Fluid Nitric Oxide Synthase is a Potential Mediator Between Cigarette Smoke Exposure and Sleep Disorders</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Lao et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Lao et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Lao</surname><given-names>Jiaying</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Hang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Yuyu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Ting</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Xinqian</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Lanrong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Xiyi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Chongrong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>Yiming</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Yu-Hsin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0006" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Chonghui</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0002" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7048-8166</contrib-id><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Fan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0007" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Yanlong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0006" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Neurosurgery, Affiliated Cixi Hospital, Wenzhou Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Ningbo</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>School of Mental Health, Wenzhou Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Wenzhou</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of neurosurgery, Hangzhou Mingzhou Brain Rehabilitation Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Hangzhou</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Infectious Diseases, The Affiliated Xiangshan Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Ningbo</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label><institution>Psychosomatic Medicine Research Division, Inner Mongolia Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Huhhot</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0006"><label>6</label><institution>Zhejiang Provincial Clinical Research Center for Mental Disorders, The Affiliated Wenzhou Kangning Hospital, Wenzhou Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Wenzhou</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0007"><label>7</label><institution>Beijing Hui−Long−Guan Hospital, Peking University</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Yanlong Liu, <institution>School of Mental Health, Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Wenzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>325035</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, Email benjaminlyl@wmu.edu.cn</corresp><corresp id="an0002">Chonghui Tang, <institution>Department of Neurosurgery, Affiliated Cixi Hospital, Wenzhou Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Ningbo</addr-line>, <addr-line>315300</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, Email tangegg@163.com</corresp><fn id="ft0001"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>01</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>897</fpage><lpage>906</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>05</day><month>6</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Lao et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Lao et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Objective</title><p>Cigarette smoking and low peripheral nitric oxide synthase (NOS) levels are strongly associated with sleep disorders. However, whether cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) NOS relates to sleep disorders and whether CSF NOS mediates the relationship between cigarette smoking and sleep disorders is unclear.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>We measured CSF levels of total NOS (tNOS) and its isoforms (inducible NOS [iNOS] and constitutive NOS [cNOS]) in 191 Chinese male subjects. We applied the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI).</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The PSQI scores of active smokers were significantly higher than those of non-smokers, while CSF tNOS, iNOS, and cNOS were significantly lower (all p &lt; 0.001). CSF tNOS, iNOS, and cNOS were negatively associated with PSQI scores in the general population (all p &lt; 0.001). Mediation analysis suggested that CSF tNOS, iNOS, and cNOS mediate the relationship between smoking and PSQI scores, and the indirect effect accounted for 78.93%, 66.29%, and 81.65% of the total effect, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Cigarette smoking is associated with sleep disorders. Active smokers had significantly lower CSF levels of tNOS, iNOS, and cNOS. Furthermore, tNOS, iNOS, and cNOS mediate the relationship between cigarette smoking and sleep quality. This study provides insights into how cigarette smoke affects sleep disorders.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>cerebrospinal fluid nitric oxide synthase</kwd><kwd>cigarette smoking</kwd><kwd>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index</kwd><kwd>sleep disorders</kwd><kwd>mediation</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>the following grants: The Technology Support Project of Xinjiang</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Natural Science Foundation of Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Tianshan Youth Project--Outstanding Youth Science and Technology Talents of Xinjiang</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Natural Science Foundation of China</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="open-funder-registry">10.13039/501100001809</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>The authors of this work were supported by the following grants: The Technology Support Project of Xinjiang (2017E0267), Natural Science Foundation of Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region (2018D01C228 and 2018D01C239), Tianshan Youth Project--Outstanding Youth Science and Technology Talents of Xinjiang (2017Q007), Natural Science Foundation of China (81560229 and 81760252).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="4"/><ref-count count="44"/><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Cigarette smoking is the most preventable cause of disease and death worldwide.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Clinical and laboratory studies showed that cigarette smoking is significantly associated with the risk of psychiatric disorders, including sleep disorders.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2–4</xref> Long-term smoking causes poor sleep quality, initiation, maintenance impairment, and daytime sleepiness.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> However, little is known about the mechanisms between cigarette smoke and sleep disorders. There are currently two possible explanations: changes in the chemistry of the nervous system and incidence of respiratory problems.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></p>
      <p>Cigarette smoke contains thousands of chemicals that produce several free radicals and reduce nitric oxide synthase (NOS) activity and expression.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> There are two forms of NOS synthase: (i) constitutive NOS (cNOS) (including neuronal [nNOS] and endothelial [eNOS]) and (ii) inducible NOS (iNOS), which responds to the generation of nitric oxide (NO).<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Animal and cell experiments showed that cigarette smoke exposure can decrease cNOS and iNOS.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Many laboratories have developed evidence linking NOS to sleep disorders. NOS is a calcium/calmodulin-dependent enzyme responsible for nitric oxide (NO) biosynthesis from L-arginine.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> The literature suggests that NOS is associated with sleep disorders.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Studies showed that iNOS and nNOS, although synthesizing the same messenger NO, play distinct roles in sleep regulation.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> The iNOS is produced by microglia and astrocytes, which ensures adequate rapid eye movement (REM) sleep and increases slow-wave sleep.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> The nNOS is distributed throughout the brain, with the highest distribution in the pons, where it maintains daily homeostatic sleep (including slow-wave and REM sleep).<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> In human umbilical vein endothelial cells subjected to intermittent hypoxia, NOS activity levels were significantly lower, and eNOS mRNA expression was downregulated.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> In clinical studies, patients with obstructive sleep apnea significantly decreased peripheral eNOS levels.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></p>
      <p>Cigarette smoke enters the brain quickly by many pathways and may cause a fall in CSF total NOS, iNOS, and cNOS levels.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> However, no study has yet used CSF NOS to investigate the relationship between active smoking and sleep disorders. Therefore, we determined the associations between cigarette smoking and sleep disorders by measuring CSF NOS.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p>Considering the low proportion of female smokers in China (3.2%), we enrolled only male subjects. We recruited 191 Chinese men (age range 17–64 years) scheduled for anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction surgery from September 2014 to January 2016. Of these, 87 were active smokers and 104 were non-smokers. Subjects who had never smoked were considered non-smokers. According to the fourth edition of the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, subjects who consume half a pack of cigarettes (ie, ten cigarettes) or more per day for more than a year are active smokers. For the purposes of this study, people who have ever smoked (ie, who have a history of smoking but have stopped smoking) were excluded to accentuate the difference between active smokers and non-smokers. The exclusion criteria were as follows:1) a history of drug abuse or dependence; 2) a family history of neurological diseases or psychosis; 3) systemic or central nervous system diseases determined using the Mini-International Neuropsychiatric Interview.</p>
        <p>We recorded age, body mass index (BMI), marriage, living status, and clinical data, including blood pressure, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) Global Score, and biochemical indicators. The Institutional Review Board of Inner Mongolian Medical University approved this study, and participants provided written informed consent before data collection.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Assessments, Biological Sample Collection, and Laboratory Tests</title>
        <p>Active smokers provided the age at which they started smoking, the years of active smoking, the average number of cigarettes they smoked daily, and the maximum amount of tobacco per day. The PSQI measures sleep quality in the previous month. We used the Chinese version of the questionnaire and asked subjects to make choices on a four-point Likert scale (from 0 = “no difficulty” to 3 = “severe difficulty”) one day before CSF extraction. Combining the resulting data generates seven subscales: subjective sleep quality, habitual efficiency, latency, use of sleep medication, duration, disturbances, and daytime dysfunction. The total score ranges from 0 to 21, with higher scores indicating poorer sleep quality. A PSQI score of 5 and above is considered a clinically relevant sleep disorders.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Sleep quality and latency fractions ≥2 were defined as low sleep quality and long sleep latency, respectively. Sleep efficiency &lt; 85% was defined as low sleep efficiency. The onset of subjective sleep disturbance within the last month was described as a sleep disturbance. The use of sleep medication in the previous month was defined as the use of sleep medication. Daytime activity disorders in the previous month was described as a daytime activity disorders.</p>
        <p>Before cruciate ligament reconstruction, a standard clinical procedure, CSF samples were obtained by lumbar puncture. The day before surgery, an anesthesiologist administered 3 mL 0.5% ropivacaine locally, collected 5 mL of CSF from the intrathecal space, and immediately froze the sample at –80 °C.</p>
        <p>After extraction, routine, biochemical, and cytological examinations were performed on the CSF, and nitrate reductase was used to measure. The method was as follows: NOS catalyzes the reaction of L-arginine with molecular oxygen to generate NO, which continues to create colored compounds. We configured the reagents according to the labeling method of the reagent kit and used a colorimetric method to detect the absorbance values of each tube. We calculated NOS content according to the formula given in the manual. The Nanjing Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute provided the NOS kit. Laboratory technicians were blinded to clinical data. These methods were described in detail previously.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>We used the Mann–Whitney rank-sum and Chi-square tests to compare the two groups’ general demographic data, clinical data, and raw biomarkers. Spearman correlation analysis calculated the relationship between raw biomarkers (total NOS [tNOS], iNOS, and cNOS) and PSQI scores. The tNOS, iNOS, and cNOS levels were categorized into low level (≤median) and high level (&gt; median). A variable composed of the following four groups combining iNOS and cNOS levels was created: 1) low iNOS levels with low cNOS levels, 2) low iNOS levels with high cNOS levels, 3) high iNOS levels with low cNOS levels, and 4) high iNOS levels with high cNOS levels. Logistic regression models (adjusted age, BMI, marriage, and living status) were used to estimate whether CSF iNOS levels and CSF cNOS levels measures predict CSF tNOS levels. Binary logistic regression models (adjusted for age, BMI, marriage, and living status) were used to estimate the adjusted odds ratio (OR) of sleep disorders (PSQI scores ≥5) and six domains according to smoking and CSF NOS levels.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, adjusting for age, BMI, marriage, and living companion status, a mediation effect analysis was performed to clarify whether CSF tNOS, iNOS, or cNOS mediated the relationship between smoking and PSQI global scores. The bootstrap sampling method was used to explore the effect decomposition from mediation models. Direct effect is the effect of an independent variable acting on a dependent variable after controlling for the mediating variable. After controlling for the mediating variables, the effects of the independent variables on the mediators and the effects of the mediators on the dependent variables constitute the indirect effects of the relationship between the variables. The total effect is equal to the direct effect plus the indirect effect, that is, the effect of the independent variable acting on the dependent variable when the mediating variable is not considered. All data were analyzed using the R programming language (version 4.2.2), and the significance level was set to 0.05.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Sociodemographic and Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <p><xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> presents our previously reported baseline clinical characteristics.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Non-smokers and active smokers differed significantly in age (34.4 ± 10.5 vs 29.6 ± 9.5, p &lt;0.05), sleep disorders (no or yes), marriage (married or unmarried), living status (low or high), BMI (25.9 ± 3.6 vs 24.9 ± 4.0, p &lt; 0.01), and PSQI scores (4.3 ± 2.5 vs 2.9 ± 2.5, p &lt; 0.001). Total NOS (14.7 ± 5.6 vs 28.3 ± 7.2, p &lt;0.001), iNOS (10.3 ± 2.7 vs 16.0 ± 5.4, p &lt; 0.001), and cNOS (4.4 ± 3.9 vs 12.4 ± 6.9, p &lt;0.001) of active smokers were significantly lower than those of non-smokers.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparisons Between Non-Smokers and Active Smokers</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variable</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Smokers</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Active Smokers</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(n=191) Mean ± SD</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(n=104) Mean ± SD</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(n=87) Mean ± SD</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.8±10.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.6±9.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.4±10.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, kg/m²</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.4±3.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.9±4.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.9±3.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI Global Score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5±2.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9±2.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3±2.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001***</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBP, mmHg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128.8±13.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">129.8±12.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">127.6±13.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DBP, mmHg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.0±10.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.2±9.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.9±11.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL, mmol/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3±0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3±0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2±0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL, mmol/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7±0.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7±0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7±0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG, mmol/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8±1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8±1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8±1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CHO, mmol/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7±0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7±1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8±0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT, U/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.7±22.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0±22.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.5±22.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AST, U/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1±8.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.5±9.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.6±7.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGT, U/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.4±38.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.4±30.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.3±45.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CSF Total NOS, U/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.2±9.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.3±7.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.7±5.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001***</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CSF Inducible NOS, U/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.9±8.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.0 ± 5.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3 ± 2.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001***</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CSF Constitutive NOS, U/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2±7.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4 ± 6.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4 ± 3.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001***</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age of smoking initiation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.1 ±3.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total duration of smoking</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.1 ±9.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average number of cigarettes smoked</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4 ±7.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum number of cigarettes smoked per day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5 ±9.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep disorders</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">131 (69%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79 (76%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (60%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (31%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (24%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (40%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marriage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Married</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 (40%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (50%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (29%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unmarried</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">114 (60%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (50%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (71%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living alone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (23%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (30%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (15%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living with others</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">147 (77%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (70%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 (85%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Marriage was tested using the chi-square test between non-smokers and active smokers, and other data were reported as Mann–Whitney sum tests between non-smokers and active smokers. *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: BMI, body mass index (calculated as weight in kilograms divided by height in meters squared); PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index; SBP, systolic blood pressures; DBP, diastolic blood pressures; HDL, high-density lipoprotein; LDL, low-density lipoprotein; TG, triglyceride; CHO, cholesterol; ALT, alanine transaminase; AST, aspartate aminotransferase; GGT, γ-glutamyltransferase; CSF, cerebral spinal fluid; NOS, nitric oxide synthase.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Correlation Between NOS and PSQI Scores</title>
        <p>Spearman correlation analysis was used to explore the relationship between NOS and PSQI scores (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=458294.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 1</ext-link></underline>). CSF tNOS, iNOS, and cNOS were negatively correlated with PSQI scores (p &lt; 0.001) in the general population, and the correlation coefficients ranged from −0.29 to −0.44.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Correlation of Physiological Indices with PSQI Global Scores in the General Group</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CHO</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGT</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AST</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">tNOS</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">iNOS</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">cNOS</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CHO</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.31***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.19*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AST</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tNOS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">iNOS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">cNOS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.14*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.29***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.37 ***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.44 ***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1***</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: All data were reported as Spearman correlation analyses. *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index; HDL, high-density lipoprotein; LDL, low-density lipoprotein; TG, triglyceride; CHO, cholesterol; ALT, alanine transaminase; AST, aspartate aminotransferase; GGT, γ-glutamyltransferase; tNOS, total nitric oxide synthase; iNOS, inducible nitric oxide synthase; cNOS, constitutive nitric oxide synthase.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Odds Ratios of Sleep Disorders and Six Domains According to Smoking and CSF NOS Level</title>
        <p><underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=458294.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link></underline> shows the results of binary logistic regression analyses in which the presence of sleep disorders was predicted according to smoking and levels of CSF tNOS, iNOS, and cNOS. Individuals with high CSF iNOS levels (&gt;median CSF iNOS level) had a lower prevalence of sleep disorders (OR: 0.40, 95% confidence interval [CI]: 0.17–0.92) compared to those with low CSF iNOS levels (≤median CSF iNOS level). Similarly, consistent results were observed for CSF cNOS levels, where individuals with high levels (&gt;median CSF cNOS level) had a lower prevalence of sleep disorders (OR: 0.28, 95% confidence interval [CI]: 0.12–0.63) compared to those with low levels (≤median CSF cNOS level).</p>
        <p>In addition, we used binary logistic regressions to further examine whether CSF tNOS level predicted sleep disorders and its six domains. The result of <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=458294.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 2</ext-link></underline> showed that CSF iNOS levels (OR: 1.59, 95% confidence interval [CI]: 1.39–1.87) and CSF cNOS levels (OR: 1.07, 95% confidence interval [CI]: 1.01–1.14) could predict tNOS levels. The results of logistic regressions showed that individuals with high levels of both iNOS and cNOS have a lower prevalence of sleep disorders (OR: 0.15, 95% confidence interval [CI]: 0.05–0.45) compared to those with low levels of both iNOS and cNOS (see <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=458294.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 3</ext-link></underline>). <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=458294.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 2</ext-link></underline> shows that CSF tNOS levels were not significantly associated with the six dimensions of sleep disorders.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Mediation Analysis</title>
        <p>The mediation model is based on correlation analysis and Linear regression analysis. Further mediation analyses were conducted to evaluate the influence of CSF tNOS, iNOS, and cNOS between smoking and sleep quality. First, we examined the effect of cigarette smoking on PSQI scores after adjusting for age, BMI, marriage, and living status (see <xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> and <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>); the linear regression analysis revealed that active smoking was associated with higher PSQI scores compared with nonsmoking (R² = 0.1112, β = c =0.109, t = 3.206, p &lt; 0.001). After adjusting for age, BMI, marriage, and living status, we tested the effect of cigarette smoking on CSF tNOS (see <xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> and <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>); there was a negative effect of tobacco on CSF tNOS (R² = 0.623, β =a1 =−0.451, t =−16.773, p &lt; 0.001). Finally, we tested the mediating effect of cigarette smoking on PSQI scores by adding the mediator variables CSF tNOS (see <xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> and <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>); the linear regression revealed a negative correlation between CSF tNOS level and PSQI score (R² = 0.132, β =b1 =−0.191, t =- 2.072, p &lt; 0.05). The mediation analysis (as shown in <xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> and <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>) revealed a significant mediating effect of CSF tNOS in the relationship between smoking and PSQI Scores (indirect effect: z=a1*b1 = 0.086, 95% CI [0.003–0.170], p &lt; 0.05; direct effect: z = c1’= 0.023, 95% CI [−0.080–0.130], p = 0.654; total effect: z = c = 0.109, 95% CI [0.041–0.170], p &lt;0.001).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Analysis of Smoking and PSQI Global Scores Association with CSF Total NOS as a Mediator</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model1 (PSQI)</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model2 (tNOS)</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model3 (PSQI)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">β</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">t</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">β</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">t</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">β</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">t</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.126</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.250</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.304</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.130</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.307</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.155</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.685</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.506</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.162</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.776</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marriage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.069</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.026</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.676</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.033</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.596</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.622</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.045</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.695</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoke</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.109***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.206</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.451***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−16.773</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.428</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CSF Total NOS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(--)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(--)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(--)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(--)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.191*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.072</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">R²</italic></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.111</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.623</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.132</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F (df)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">4.65*** (5, 185)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">61.10*** (5, 185)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">4.66*** (5, 185)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Model 1 was a linear regression model with smoke as the independent variable and PSQI as the dependent variable. Model 2 was a linear regression model with CSF Total NOS as the independent variable and PSQI as the dependent variable. Based on Model 1, Model 3 uses CSF total NOS and smoke as independent variables. All data were reported as mediation analyses. *p &lt; 0.05, ***p &lt; 0.001.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0006"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index; BMI, body mass index; CSF, cerebral spinal fluid; tNOS, total nitric oxide synthase.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Significance Test for Mediating Effects of Smoking, tNOS, and PSQI Global Scores</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Effect Decomposition</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Estimated</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">95% CI</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indirect effect</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.086</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.170</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Direct effect</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.080</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.130</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.654</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total effect</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.109</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.170</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001***</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0007"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: All data were reported as mediation analysis. Effect decomposition of the mediation model for the relationship between smoking and PSQI global score association with CSF Total NOS as mediator. *p &lt; 0.05, ***p &lt; 0.001.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0008"><p><bold>Abbreviation</bold>: 95% Cl, 95% confidence interval.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Effect decomposition of mediation models in PSQI global score.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-897-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: (<bold>A</bold>) Total effect between smoking and PSQI global score. (<bold>B</bold>) Effect decomposition of the mediation model for the relationship between smoking and PSQI global score association with CSF Total NOS as mediator. *p &lt; 0.05, ***p &lt; 0.001.</attrib></fig></p>
        <p>We also examined the mediating effects of iNOS and cNOS on the relationship between smoking and PSQI scores. As shown in <xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>, <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=458294.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 4</ext-link></underline> and <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=458294.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 5</ext-link></underline>, there was a significant mediating effect of CSF iNOS on the relationship between cigarette smoking and PSQI scores (indirect effect: z = a2*b2= 0.073, 95% CI [0.031–0.120], p &lt;0.001; direct effect: z =c2’ = 0.037, 95% CI [−0.040–0.110], p = 0.341; total effect: z =c = 0.109, 95% CI [0.041–0.170], p &lt;0.001). Similarly, CSF cNOS (indirect effect: z = a3*b3 = 0.089, 95% CI [0.046–0.140], p &lt;0.001; direct effect: z =c3’ = 0.019, 95% CI [−0.055–0.090], p = 0.608; total effect: z = c = 0.109, 95% CI [0.041–0.170], p &lt;0.001) significantly mediated the relationship between cigarette smoking and PSQI scores (see <xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>, <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=458294.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 6</ext-link></underline> and <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=458294.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 7</ext-link></underline>).
<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Effect decomposition of mediation models in the PSQI global score.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-897-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: (<bold>A</bold>) Effect decomposition of the mediation model for the relationship between smoking and PSQI global score association with CSF Inducible NOS as mediator. (<bold>B</bold>) Effect decomposition of the mediation model for the relationship between smoking and PSQI global score association with CSF Constitutive NOS as mediator. ***p &lt; 0.001.</attrib></fig></p>
        <p>These findings suggest that the mediating effect of tNOS, iNOS, and cNOS was complete, and the ratio of mediating effect (tNOS, iNOS, and cNOS) to the total impact were 78.93%, 66.29%, and 81.65%, respectively.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>There was a positive correlation between cigarette smoking and PSQI scores. Significantly lower CSF levels of tNOS, iNOS, and cNOS were found in active smokers. This result was reported in our previous study.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Furthermore, tNOS, iNOS, and cNOS positively correlated with PSQI scores in the general group. A mediation analysis showed that tNOS, iNOS, and cNOS in CSF mediated the relationship between cigarette smoking and sleep quality measured by PSQI scores. To our knowledge, this is the first study to investigate this relationship. Our findings suggest that NOS in CSF may be a critical factor linking cigarette smoking to sleep quality.</p>
      <p>A noteworthy observation was the negative correlation between CSF tNOS, iNOS, and cNOS levels and PSQI scores. NO produced by neuronal NOS is a potent sleep aid.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Multiple animal experiments have shown that nNOS knockout mice have less REM and non-REM sleep time and seizure frequency than normal mice.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Nevertheless, the relationship between iNOS and eNOS and sleep disorders is controversial. Mice lacking the iNOS gene have a longer REM time than normal mice.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> However, some studies indicated that the iNOS expression ensures adequate maintenance of REM sleep with aging.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Another study found that the basal forebrain of AD patients had higher levels of iNOS and NO, an essential mechanism for maintaining sleep homeostasis.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> In addition, the corpus cavernosum tissue of sleep-deprived rats has higher eNOS levels than normal rats.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> The role of iNOS and eNOS in sleep regulation requires further investigation.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> Our study focused on CSF NOS, providing an addition to the field of sleep research.</p>
      <p>Interestingly, the mediation analysis revealed that CSF tNOS, iNOS, and cNOS levels had a mediating effect on increased PSQI scores due to cigarette smoke exposure, and the indirect effect accounted for 78.93%, 66.29%, and 81.65% of the total effect. Studies have suggested nicotine may stimulate neurotransmitters involved in sleep-wake cycle regulation, including dopamine, norepinephrine, and γ-aminobutyric acid, disrupting sleep architecture.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> Other studies showed that chemicals in cigarette smoke may induce sleep disorders by increasing the inflammatory response in the upper respiratory tract.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> However, there are no reports on the role of CSF NOS content in the relationship between smoking and sleep quality. Therefore, our study provides clues for CSF NOS as a potential mediator between cigarette smoking and sleep quality.</p>
      <p>The physiological mechanisms underlying the relationship between cigarette smoking and sleep disorders are unclear.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Some scholars speculate that nicotine induces alterations in brain neurochemistry or disruptions to development, leading to sleep behavior disturbances.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> It is worth noting that toxic chemicals in cigarettes induce the generation of free radicals and a decrease in NOS and endogenous NO.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> The NOS family catalyzes the conversion of L-arginine to NO and citrulline.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> NO is a neurotransmitter and neuromodulator involved in sleep regulation.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> Kapa et al demonstrated that increasing NO levels in the brain promoted spontaneous sleep in rats.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> NO may function as a signal molecule in the steady-state regulation of slow-wave sleep.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> NO affects REM sleep by regulating acetylcholine, γ-aminobutyric acid, serotonin, and adenosine levels.<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> In addition, smokers have less basal endogenous nitric oxide synthesis in their airways and blood vessels than ordinary people. Subsequently, smokers may experience airway constriction due to nitric oxide’s involvement in maintaining airway dilation.<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> This is likely one of the mechanisms through which smoking causes sleep apnea syndrome.<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> Interestingly, NO produced by NOS can also inhibit the release of inflammatory mediators.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> Sleep disorders and inflammatory responses are related.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> IL-6 levels significantly increase in patients with insomnia, and IL-6 can spread in the periventricular area, sending immune signals to the brain that affect sleep-related processes.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></p>
      <p>There are several important research implications. Firstly, they emphasize the importance of considering the levels of CSF NOS when assessing the relationship between smoking and sleep quality. Increasing NOS levels in smokers may improve sleep quality. Clinicians may need to monitor the levels of NOS in smokers reporting poor sleep quality and consider targeted interventions aimed at increasing NOS levels, such as supplementation with antioxidant vitamins.<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> Secondly, the study results suggest that NOS may be one of the biological mechanisms underlying the relationship between smoking and sleep quality. This suggests that modulating NOS levels may be a potential target for improving sleep quality in smokers. Overall, our study contributes to understanding the complex interactions between smoking, NOS, and sleep quality.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Limitations</title>
      <p>There were some limitations to the present study. First, the participants were patients with anterior cruciate ligament injury, which may confound our results. Second, studies have shown that women and men who undergo surgery differ significantly in many postoperative reactions, including postoperative pain and postoperative sleep.<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> However, we only collected data on male smokers, which may have led to neglecting gender factors in the discussion. The investigation of gender differences may be a key direction for future research. Third, our study had a relatively small sample size (n = 191), with a minority of individuals experiencing sleep disorders (n = 60, 31.4%). In future research, we intend to increase the sample size to explore further the relationship between smoking, NOS, and sleep. Finally, we only dealt with a single aspect of NOS: its content. It acts via different mechanisms in inflammatory and immune diseases, insulin resistance, and tumors. NOS activity is also essential, as it provides direction for future research.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>This study found that cigarette smoking is associated with sleep disorders, and tNOS, iNOS, and cNOS in CSF mediate the relationship between smoking and sleep quality. Protective Effects of CSF tNOS, iNOS, and cNOS provide new therapeutic targets for improving sleep quality. However, the specific relationship between smoking and sleep disorders needs to be further validated and explained in vivo and in vitro studies with larger sample sizes.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We thank all the teachers, students and related participants for their involvement in this study.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <p>NOS, nitric oxide synthase; CSF, cerebrospinal fluid; tNOS, total NOS; iNOS, inducible NOS; cNOS, constitutive NOS; PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index; eNOS, endothelial NOS; NO, nitric oxide; REM, rapid eye movement; BMI, body mass index; SBP, systolic blood pressures; DBP, diastolic blood pressures; HDL, high-density lipoprotein; LDL, low-density lipoprotein; TG, triglyceride; CHO, cholesterol; ALT, alanine transaminase; AST, aspartate aminotransferase; GGT, γ-glutamyltransferase.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0008">
      <title>Inclusion of Identifiable Human Data</title>
      <p>No potentially identifiable human images or data is presented in this study.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0009">
      <title>Studies Involving Animal Subjects</title>
      <p>Generated Statement: No animal studies are presented in this manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0010">
      <title>Studies Involving Human Subjects</title>
      <p>The present study was approved by the Institutional Review Board of Inner Mongolian Medical University, and was performed in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. And there was no financial compensation provided to the subjects. The patients/participants provided their written informed consent to participate in this study. And there was no financial compensation provided to the subjects.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s0011">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p>The datasets used and/or analysed during the current study are available from the corresponding author, Yanlong Liu, on reasonable request.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0012">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>All of our authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation, or in all these areas; took part in drafting, revising or critically reviewing the article; At the same time, all authors have gave final approval of the version to be published and have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted. In addition, all authors have reviewed and agreed on all versions of the article prior to submission, during the revision process, acceptance of the final version for publication, and any significant changes introduced during the proofreading phase. All authors have agreed to take responsibility and responsibility for the content of the article.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0013">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lugg</surname>
<given-names>ST</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scott</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parekh</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Naidu</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thickett</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cigarette smoke exposure and alveolar macrophages: mechanisms for lung disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Thorax</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>77</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>94</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2020-216296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33986144</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Catoire</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nourredine</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lefebvre</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Tobacco-induced sleep disturbances: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>101544</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2021.101544</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34597890</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mathews</surname>
<given-names>HL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stitzel</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effects of oral nicotine administration and abstinence on sleep in male C57BL/6J mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychopharmacology</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>236</volume>:<fpage>1335</fpage>–<lpage>1347</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00213-018-5139-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30564868</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mojtabai</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crum</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cigarette smoking and onset of mood and anxiety disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>103</volume>:<fpage>1656</fpage>–<lpage>1665</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/ajph.2012.300911</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23327282</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep quality in cigarette smokers and nonsmokers: findings from the general population in central China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>808</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-019-6929-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31234809</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Active smoking, sleep quality and cerebrospinal fluid biomarkers of neuroinflammation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Behav Immun</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>623</fpage>–<lpage>627</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2020.07.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32717405</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chiurazzi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kiani</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miertus</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Genetic analysis of intellectual disability and autism</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Biomed</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>e2020003</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Barua</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ambrose</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Srivastava</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>DeVoe</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eales-Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Reactive oxygen species are involved in smoking-induced dysfunction of nitric oxide biosynthesis and upregulation of endothelial nitric oxide synthase: an in vitro demonstration in human coronary artery endothelial cells</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circulation</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>107</volume>:<fpage>2342</fpage>–<lpage>2347</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.Cir.0000066691.52789.Be</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12707237</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mazzio</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kolta</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reams</surname>
<given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Soliman</surname>
<given-names>KF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Inhibitory effects of cigarette smoke on glial inducible nitric oxide synthase and lack of protective properties against oxidative neurotoxins in vitro</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurotoxicology</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuro.2004.07.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15527873</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cespuglio</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amrouni</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meiller</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Nitric oxide in the regulation of the sleep-wake states</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>265</fpage>–<lpage>279</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2012.01.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22406306</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tseng</surname>
<given-names>IJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yuan</surname>
<given-names>RY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sheu</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Expression of inducible nitric oxide synthase (iNOS) and period 1 (PER1) clock gene products in different sleep stages of patients with cognitive impairment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>1140</fpage>–<lpage>1143</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jocn.2010.01.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20541418</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hoyt</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Robbins</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Habib</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cigarette smoke decreases inducible nitric oxide synthase in lung epithelial cells</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Exp Lung Res</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01902140303759</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12652813</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chow</surname>
<given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>ES</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cho</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cigarette smoke and its extract delays ulcer healing and reduces nitric oxide synthase activity and angiogenesis in rat stomach</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Exp Pharmacol Physiol</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>828</fpage>–<lpage>829</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1440-1681.1999.03134.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10549413</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cui</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Syringin may exert sleep-potentiating effects through the NOS/NO pathway</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Fundam Clin Pharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>178</fpage>–<lpage>184</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/fcp.12095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25377727</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kalinchuk</surname>
<given-names>AV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stenberg</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Inducible and neuronal nitric oxide synthases (NOS) have complementary roles in recovery sleep induction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>1443–1456. 10.1111/j.1460</fpage>–<lpage>9568.2006.05019.x</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16987226</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>HY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>BY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cao</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>[Effects of obstructive sleep apnea style intermittent hypoxia on endothelin-1, nitric oxide, and nitric oxide synthase in endothelium: experiment with human umbilical vein endothelial cells]</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Zhonghua Yi Xue Za Zhi</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>87</volume>:<fpage>2189</fpage>–<lpage>2192</lpage>. <comment>Chinese</comment>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3760/j.issn:0376-2491.2007.31.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18001528</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jelic</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Padeletti</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kawut</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Inflammation, oxidative stress, and repair capacity of the vascular endothelium in obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circulation</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>117</volume>:<fpage>2270</fpage>–<lpage>2278</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/circulationaha.107.741512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18413499</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of cigarette smoking with cerebrospinal fluid biomarkers of neurodegeneration, neuroinflammation, and oxidation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Network Open</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>e2018777</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.18777</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33006621</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Langade</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kanchi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salve</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Debnath</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ambegaokar</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Efficacy and Safety of Ashwagandha (Withania somnifera) root extract in insomnia and anxiety: a double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cureus</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e5797</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.5797</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31728244</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nsengimana</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mugabo</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Niyonsenga</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep quality among undergraduate medical students in Rwanda: a comparative study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>265</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-27573-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36609680</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mu</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Metal ions in cerebrospinal fluid: associations with anxiety, depression, and insomnia among cigarette smokers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">CNS Neurosci Ther</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>2141</fpage>–<lpage>2147</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cns.13955</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36168907</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chittora</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jain</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shukla</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bhatnagar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cytomorphological analysis and interpretation of nitric oxide-mediated neurotoxicity in sleep-deprived mice model</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/09727531211059925</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35875423</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Majde</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krueger</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Spontaneous sleep in mice with targeted disruptions of neuronal or inducible nitric oxide synthase genes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Res</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>973</volume>:<fpage>214</fpage>–<lpage>222</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0006-8993(03)02484-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12738065</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kisiela</surname>
<given-names>DI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rodriguez</surname>
<given-names>VB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tchesnokova</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Conformational inactivation induces immunogenicity of the receptor-binding pocket of a bacterial adhesin</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>19089</fpage>–<lpage>19094</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1314395110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24191044</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Parness</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zlotkin</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Action of the toxic skin secretion of the flatfish pardachirus marmoratus on the guinea-pig ileum</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Toxicon</italic></source>. <year>1976</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0041-0101(76)90097-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1273865</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dittrich</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morairty</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Warrier</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kilduff</surname>
<given-names>TS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Homeostatic sleep pressure is the primary factor for activation of cortical nNOS/NK1 neurons</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropsychopharmacology</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>632</fpage>–<lpage>639</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/npp.2014.212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25139062</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Choi</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sohn</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Impact of sleep deprivation on the hypothalamic-pituitary-gonadal axis and erectile tissue</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sex Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsxm.2018.10.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30621925</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wisor</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gerashchenko</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kilduff</surname>
<given-names>TS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep-active neuronal nitric oxide synthase-positive cells of the cerebral cortex: a local regulator of sleep?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Top Med Chem</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>2483</fpage>–<lpage>2489</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/156802611797470367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21906016</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Riehm</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rojo-Wissar</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feder</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>E-cigarette use and sleep-related complaints among youth</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Adolesc</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>48</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.adolescence.2019.08.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31442814</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Samet</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caffo</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Punjabi</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cigarette smoking and nocturnal sleep architecture</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>164</volume>:<fpage>529</fpage>–<lpage>537</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwj231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16829553</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Krishnan</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dixon-Williams</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thornton</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Where there is smoke…there is sleep apnea: exploring the relationship between smoking and sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>146</volume>:<fpage>1673</fpage>–<lpage>1680</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.14-0772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25451354</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>YN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>QY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>XJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Interaction between smoking and obstructive sleep apnea: not just participants</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin Med J</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>125</volume>:<fpage>3150</fpage>–<lpage>3156</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22932197</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghastine</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Um</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rovit</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Environmental exposures and sleep outcomes: a review of evidence, potential mechanisms, and implications</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Environ Res</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>196</volume>:<fpage>110406</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2020.110406</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33130170</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hsu</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>YS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>CN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chuang</surname>
<given-names>HL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ling</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lan</surname>
<given-names>CT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep deprivation inhibits expression of NADPH-d and NOS while activating microglia and astroglia in the rat hippocampus</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cells Tissues Organs</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>173</volume>:<fpage>242</fpage>–<lpage>254</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000070380</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12766354</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kapás</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krueger</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Nitric oxide donors SIN-1 and SNAP promote nonrapid-eye-movement sleep in rats</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Res Bull</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>293</fpage>–<lpage>298</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0361-9230(96)00227-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8924040</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ribeiro</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gilligan</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kapás</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Systemic injection of a nitric oxide synthase inhibitor suppresses sleep responses to sleep deprivation in rats</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>278</volume>:<fpage>R1048</fpage>–<lpage>1056</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpregu.2000.278.4.R1048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10749794</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Virarkar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alappat</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bradford</surname>
<given-names>PG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Awad</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>L-arginine and nitric oxide in CNS function and neurodegenerative diseases</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>1157</fpage>–<lpage>1167</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10408398.2011.573885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24007420</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vleeming</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rambali</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Opperhuizen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name> . <article-title>The role of nitric oxide in cigarette smoking and nicotine addiction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nicotine Tob Res</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>341</fpage>–<lpage>348</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14622200210142724</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12215243</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Forte</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Airway growth in preoperative patients with crouzon syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Facial Plast Surg Aesthet Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>197</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/fpsam.2020.0441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33577380</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yan</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Qinghua</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mengyuan</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>High flow nasal cannula therapy for obstructive sleep apnea in adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>783</fpage>–<lpage>791</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-021-02453-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34383275</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kuna</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gabryelska</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Białasiewicz</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ditmer</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Strzelecki</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sochal</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Potential role of sleep deficiency in inducing immune dysfunction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biomedicines</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>10</volume>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biomedicines10092159</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Okazaki</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Otani</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shimazu</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yoshioka</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fujita</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Iwasaka</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Ascorbic acid and N-acetyl cysteine prevent uncoupling of nitric oxide synthase and increase tolerance to ischemia/reperfusion injury in diabetic rat heart</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Free Radic Res</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>1173</fpage>–<lpage>1183</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/10715762.2011.605361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21756052</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Alaverdyan</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maeng</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>PK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Perioperative risk factors for persistent postsurgical pain after inguinal hernia repair: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Pain</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>:<fpage>104532</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpain.2024.104532</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38599265</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Influencing factors for the development of obstructive sleep apnea after orthognathic surgery in skeletal class III patients: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Craniomaxillofac Surg</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>503</fpage>–<lpage>513</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcms.2024.02.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38383249</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
