<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39071543</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">11283788</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">468444</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S468444</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Excessive Daytime Napping Increases the Risk of Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease: A Meta-Analysis and a Mendelian Randomization Study</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Qiao et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Qiao et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0009-0006-0816-0078</contrib-id><name><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>Xiuqi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Xiaoxia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Lixin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Qi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Endocrinology, Beijing Hospital, National Center of Gerontology, Institute of Geriatric Medicine, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <addr-line>100730</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Graduate School of Peking Union Medical College, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <addr-line>100730</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Lixin Guo; Qi Pan, Email glx1218@163.com; panqi621@126.com</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>1067</fpage><lpage>1074</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Qiao et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Qiao et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Prior research based on observations has furnished evidence that supports a connection between daytime napping and the prevalence of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD). Nevertheless, the question of whether this correlation is indicative of a causal link has not been definitively answered.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>We used meta-analysis and Mendelian randomization (MR) to synthesize genetic and observational data. A two-sample MR analysis was conducted, leveraging 105 single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) known to be associated with daytime napping patterns. Additionally, summary-level data pertaining to NAFLD outcomes were acquired from the comprehensive UK Biobank study. Network meta-analyses were employed to investigate the relationship between excessive daytime napping and NAFLD, while subgroup was also performed.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Significant associations were observed between daytime napping and NAFLD. The systematic review/meta-analysis uncovered a heightened risk of NAFLD development among individuals who engaged in daytime naps exceeding 30 minutes, when compared to those who did not nap(odds ratio [OR] = 1.32, 95% confidence interval [CI]: 1.05 to 1.66). Furthermore, MR analysis indicated that a genetic propensity towards longer daytime napping was significantly linked to an increased likelihood of NAFLD (OR = 2.26, 95% CI: 1.38 to 3.73).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Daytime napping has been found to be causally related to a higher risk of NAFLD. Furthermore, across all participants, napping for an average duration over 30 minutes was linked to an elevated likelihood of NAFLD.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>daytime napping</kwd><kwd>non-alcoholic fatty liver disease</kwd><kwd>genetic variants</kwd><kwd>Mendelian randomization</kwd><kwd>network meta-analysis</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>the National High Level Hospital Clinical Research Funding</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the National High Level Hospital Clinical Research Funding (BJ-2022-195).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><ref-count count="29"/><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The worldwide occurrence of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) stands at roughly 25% and is estimated to reach 56% by 2030.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> The expanding scale of NAFLD, along with its array of complications, has emerged as a significant public health challenge, largely due to shifts in lifestyle and dietary patterns. The spectrum of NAFLD-related liver damage is broad, encompassing conditions from simple fatty liver (hepatic steatosis) to more severe inflammation (steatohepatitis), advanced fibrosis, cirrhosis, and even hepatocellular carcinoma.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Often asymptomatic, individuals with NAFLD can progress to terminal liver disease or liver cancer. In China, it is approximated that 20% of the population is affected by NAFLD, while in the United States, the prevalence soars to 35%.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Urgent focus is thus required to mitigate the risks of NAFLD and its potential complications and mortality.</p>
      <p>Daytime napping is a widely-accepted habit in numerous nations around the globe, particularly in China.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> In Chinese cultural traditions, the practice of afternoon napping has long been hailed as a beneficial habit for overall health.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Contradictorily, research indications point to the potential adverse health effects of daytime napping under specific circumstances. Empirical studies have validated a positive association between daytime napping and the likelihood of NAFLD.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Data from a recent study showed NAFLD was significantly related to usually nap during day.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></p>
      <p>To date, the existence of a causal link between napping and the incidence of NAFLD remains to be definitively established. Despite this, traditional observational studies, including well-constructed prospective studies with substantial sample sizes, remain vulnerable to lingering confounding factors and the possibility of reverse causality. In contrast, instrumental variables (IVs) are randomly allocated at conception, making the Mendelian randomization (MR) method a type of “natural randomized control trial”.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> MR is a widely employed analytical approach for elucidating causal connections between clinical outcomes and exposure variables, utilizing genetic variations as instrumental variables. The inherent nature of the genotype, being innate and predating the occurrence of the outcome, coupled with its insulation from a host of confounding elements such as environmental factors, positions it as a potent instrument in the study of causal links between exposures and outcomes.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Utilizing publicly accessible genome-wide association study (GWAS) data from a substantial cohort, we conducted a two-sample MR approach to assess the effect of daytime napping on the risk of NAFLD, thereby providing further clarity on the causal connection to better understand the risk factors for NAFLD and provide new insights for its prevention.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis</title>
        <p>This network meta-analysis (NMA) was performed adhering to the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Review and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) guidelines.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Search Strategy</title>
        <p>Utilizing the Population, Intervention, Comparator, Outcomes, and Study (PICOS) framework as our guiding principle, we conducted a comprehensive search across the PubMed, Embase, and Cochrane Library databases from inception to December 7, 2023 to determine how daytime napping impacts NAFLD risk. Our search strategy employed a combination of targeted keywords, truncation symbols, relevant Medical Subject Headings (MeSH) terms, and Boolean operators (AND/OR) to ensure a thorough and precise retrieval of relevant literature, which included the following terms related to NAFLD and daytime napping: (NAFLD[Title/Abstract]) OR (MAFLD[Title/Abstract]) OR (Nonalcoholic Fatty Liver Disease[Title/Abstract]) OR (Fatty Liver, Nonalcoholic[Title/Abstract]) OR (Liver, Nonalcoholic Fatty[Title/Abstract]) OR (Nonalcoholic Fatty Liver[Title/Abstract]) OR (Nonalcoholic Steatohepatitis[Title/Abstract]) OR (Nonalcoholic Steatohepatitides[Title/Abstract]) OR (Non-alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease[Title/Abstract]) combined with daytime napping (daytime napping[Title/Abstract]) OR (nap[Title/Abstract]) OR (doze[Title/Abstract]) OR (snooze[Title/Abstract]) OR (siesta[Title/Abstract]) OR (napping duration[Title/Abstract]).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Inclusion Criteria</title>
        <p>For the purposes of this systematic review, we assessed the likelihood of NAFLD in both adolescent and adult populations with and without a habit of daytime napping. We included studies that consecutively enrolled participants diagnosed with NAFLD to ensure a comprehensive analysis of the available data. For study inclusion, NAFLD was diagnosed based on ultrasonography, which has been used in different populations.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> The following trials were excluded: i) animal experiments; ii) editorials, letters, reviews, commentaries, conference abstracts, or interviews; and iii) those with incomplete NAFLD data. Duplicate records were removed using EndNote X9. Teams of paired reviewers independently used EndNote X9 to first screen titles and abstracts, followed by full-text manuscripts. Then, data on sample size, napping duration, odds ratio (OR) (95% confidence interval [CI]), NAFLD events, and diagnostic method were extracted. Differences were resolved through discussion or, if necessary by third--party adjudication.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Data Collection and Registered Protocols</title>
        <p>Articles that met the criteria for potential eligibility were gathered in accordance with the predefined inclusion and exclusion criteria. The following information was extracted from the articles selected for inclusion: basic study attributes (including author, year of publication, geographical location, participant age, study design, and sample size), exposure groups (napping duration), NAFLD events, and the definition of NAFLD.</p>
        <p>The systematic review and meta-analysis protocols were registered on PROSPERO (CRD42023485932).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>The primary endpoints were the odds of NAFLD in people with/without daytime napping. This study was conducted within a frequentist random-effect NMA to assess the associations of the likelihood of developing NAFLD in relation to particular lengths of daytime napping. We calculated the OR to estimate the pooled prevalence. Sensitivity analysis was performed to assess the impact of country (China versus Iran) and napping duration (no naps, 0–30 min, 30–60 min, &gt; 60 min). STATA 14 and R software was used for data analysis.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2006">
        <title>Risk of Bias Assessment</title>
        <p>The Newcastle-Ottawa Scale (NOS) was employed in this NMA to assess the quality of observational studies.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Scores of 7–9, 4–6, and 4 were classified as having a low, moderate, or high risk of bias, respectively.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Mendelian Randomization (MR)</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Two-Sample MR</title>
        <p>Single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) are randomly assigned at the moment of conception, signifying that they are not influenced by environmental factors that occur after birth.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> The expanding availability of open databases has greatly aided in conducting two-sample MR studies. Employing this methodology, we utilized a two-sample MR analysis to evaluate the causal association between daytime napping and the risk of NAFLD. Initially, we identified IVs for MR analysis by treating napping-related traits as the “exposures” and NAFLD, along with associated liver parameters, as the “outcomes”. We then evaluated heterogeneity through Cochran’s <italic toggle="yes">Q</italic>-test. To further ensure the robustness of the causal inferences, we conducted sensitivity analyses to validate the reliability of the obtained causal estimates.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Data Sources</title>
        <p>We accessed summary-level data from a GWAS on self-reported daytime napping within the UK Biobank, which included individuals of European descent (n = 452,633).<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> In parallel, we retrieved NAFLD-related data from the Open GWAS database, specifically the GWAS catalog (n = 377,998).<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Selection of Instrumental Variables</title>
        <p>A rigorous selection process was employed to identify suitable IVs. Initially, 107 SNPs with a strong association with daytime napping in individuals of European ancestry were identified as potential IVs, meeting a stringent significance threshold (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 5.00E-08). SNPs were then excluded if they exhibited linkage disequilibrium (r<sup>2</sup> &lt; 0.001) or were palindromic with intermediate allele frequencies. We searched for IVs using PhenoScanner (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="http://www.phenoscanner.medschl.cam.ac.uk/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.phenoscanner.medschl.cam.ac.uk/</ext-link></underline>) to identify any previous associations with potential confounders. Additionally, SNPs that were not available in the outcome GWAS or their proxy SNPs were not utilized in the analysis. The selection of qualified IVs was based exclusively on summary-level GWAS data from European descent populations. The strength of the association between the IVs and daytime napping was quantified using F statistics, with only SNPs having an F statistic greater than 10 considered robust and valid for use as IVs in relation to daytime napping.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> Ultimately, the selected SNPs were incorporated as IVs for the MR analysis. Detailed information on these IVs is shown in <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=468444.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link></underline>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>In applying the MR methodology, adherence to three fundamental premises is imperative: (1) the chosen IVs must exhibit a robust correlation with the exposure; (2) these IVs ought to remain uncorrelated with any potential confounding factors; and (3) the IVs’ impact on the outcomes is solely mediated by the exposure pathway, excluding alternative routes. The primary investigation employed the conventional random effects inverse variance weighting approach (IVW) to ascertain the causal relationship between napping and the incidence of NAFLD. Complementing this, four additional analytical techniques were utilized: the weighted median, weighted mode, simple mode methodologies, and the MR-Egger method. Sensitivity assessments were conducted utilizing Cochran’s <italic toggle="yes">Q</italic>-test and a leave-one-out strategy, deeming <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values below 0.05 statistically meaningful. The entirety of the analyses was executed within a two-sample MR framework, facilitated by the MR PRESSO package in R software, version 4.3.1.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0004-s2001">
        <title>NMA of Daytime Napping Duration and NAFLD Incidence</title>
        <p>The NMA of napping duration and the risk of incident NAFLD encompassed a total of 35,928 participants from six studies (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=468444.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 2</ext-link></underline>). <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=468444.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 1</ext-link></underline> depicts a flowchart of the study selection procedure. Studies selected via systematic review suggested an association between excessive daytime napping and the odds of NAFLD (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). For all studies,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18–22</xref> subjects with more than 30 min of napping duration were found to have an elevated risk of incident NAFLD compared to the “no naps” group (OR<sub>30–60 min, &gt; 60 min</sub> and 95% [CI]: 1.40, 1.03 to 1.89; 1.78, 1.30 to 2.43). Additionally, a significant discrepancy was noted between the groups designated as “&gt; 30 min” and “0–30 min” in terms of napping duration. A subsequent analysis involving five studies indicated that daily napping exceeding 30 minutes was associated with a greater likelihood of developing NAFLD compared to shorter daytime naps (OR = 1.41, 95% CI: 1.06 to 1.86) (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>In the network plot, participants with varying lengths of napping were categorized into four distinct time-based groups: “no naps”, “0–30 min”, “30–60 min”, and “&gt; 60 min.” The size of each node represented the number of subjects within each napping duration category, with the edges between nodes visually weighted to reflect the frequency of comparisons across different exposure groups, facilitating a comparative analysis among all groups.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1067-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig>
<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Forest plot for the odds ratio of Non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) in different comparisons.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1067-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval.</attrib></fig></p>
        <p>In the sensitivity analyses, after excluding studies individually, we observed findings similar to those of our primary analyses (<xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>), with no evidence of small study effects on the analysis of funnel plot symmetry (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=468444.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 2</ext-link></underline>). An evaluation of the risk of bias using NOS indicated that none of the studies fall into the high-risk category. (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=468444.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 3</ext-link></underline>).
<fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Subgroup analysis plot. The forest plot depicts a subgroup analysis examining the relationship between daytime napping and the incidence of NAFLD among individuals who nap, as compared to those who do not, within subgroups defined by geographical region and napping duration.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1067-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval.</attrib></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0004-s2002">
        <title>Cause-and-Effect Relationship Between Daytime Napping and NAFLD</title>
        <p>The causal link between daytime napping and NAFLD was supported by the finding that a genetic inclination toward more regular daytime napping was robustly correlated with an elevated likelihood of NAFLD development in the IVW model (OR = 2.26, 95% CI: 1.38 to 3.73, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0008) (<xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). As shown in the scatter plots, the risk of NAFLD increased with excessive daytime napping (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>). The MR estimates for NAFLD did not alter the inference of the results after removing two palindromic SNPs (rs10772659, rs285815). The analysis of NAFLD did not reveal any appreciable heterogeneity or pleiotropic influences (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=468444.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 4</ext-link></underline>). Additionally, the leave-one-out sensitivity analysis did not pinpoint any SNPs that had a substantial impact on the causal estimates (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=468444.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 3</ext-link></underline>). As depicted in the plot, where all lines are clustered on one side of the y-axis and remain in close proximity, even extending beyond the axis, this convergence signifies the robustness of the results under investigation. All sensitivity analyses yielded results similar to those of the main analyses. Forest maps of the results are shown in <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=468444.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 4</ext-link></underline>.
<fig position="float" id="f0004" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Findings from a two-sample Mendelian Randomization analysis examining the association between daytime napping and the risk of NAFLD.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1067-g0004" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: NAFLD, Non-alcoholic fatty liver disease; SNP, single nucleotide polymorphisms; OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval.</attrib></fig>
<fig position="float" id="f0005" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Scatter plots illustrating the impact of daytime napping on NAFLD risk are presented. Each black dot represents a genetic instrumental variable incorporated into the Mendelian Randomization analysis. The corresponding grey error bars indicate the 95% confidence intervals for the coefficients of these genetic instrumental variables.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1067-g0005" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>As far as we know, this study represents the first effort to comprehensively evaluate the causal relationships between self-reported daytime napping and NAFLD using a MR framework. By employing a dual approach that combines systematic review/meta-analysis and MR, we have compiled robust evidence to suggest a significant causal link between napping duration and NAFLD risk. In our two-sample MR analysis involving 830,631 participants, we uncovered compelling evidence indicating that genetically predisposed self-reported daytime napping is positively linked to the risk of NAFLD. Furthermore, the NMA corroborated this finding, indicating that individuals with a daytime napping duration of more than 30 minutes have a higher risk of NAFLD compared to those with a duration of less than 30 minutes or no napping at all. Our findings regarding the effect of daytime napping are consistent with those from a previous MR study in which NAFLD was found to be significantly associated with usual naps during the day (hazard ratio [HR]: 1.28; 95% CI: 1.02 to 1.61) compared to never or rarely nap.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> The findings of this previous study corroborated that daytime napping was associated with NAFLD risk. However, due to the unavailability of daytime nap duration data in the UK Biobank using only MR, their analyses did not reveal a dose-dependent relationship. Furthermore, the results of our subgroup analyses revealed that the positive correlation between napping and the incidence of NAFLD was notable across all subgroups, encompassing geographical distribution and the duration of follow-up.</p>
      <p>Our study revealed a dose–response association between the duration of daytime napping and the occurrence of NAFLD. Although the precise mechanism linking napping duration to NAFLD risk remains elusive, several hypotheses have been proposed to explain this relationship. Epidemiological research has demonstrated a correlation between extended daytime napping and disrupted glucose metabolism, which is significantly associated with NAFLD.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> Research has compellingly shown that the sleep homeostatic and circadian systems, with the sleep-wake cycle as their principal manifest rhythm, exert profound influences on a variety of physiological processes.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> These include the secretion of adrenal corticosterone and pituitary hormones, as well as energy metabolism regulation, encompassing lipolysis, insulin sensitivity, and basal metabolic rate. Further, the awakening response after prolonged daytime naps may elevate cortisol levels in the blood,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> potentially leading to insulin resistance and disordered glucose and lipid metabolism.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Cortisol is known to promote the accumulation of lipids and visceral fat, including in the liver.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Lastly, frequent daytime nap duration has been linked to increased levels of proinflammatory cytokines in the body, such as C-reactive protein,<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> which are known to be risk factors for NAFLD development. This observation underscores the significance of prolonged napping as an unhealthy lifestyle practice that could potentially compromise an individual’s health and hinder efforts to prevent disease. NAFLD is swiftly emerging as the predominant cause of hepatocellular carcinoma.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> Critically, numerous risk factors for the onset of NAFLD also contribute to the development of hepatocellular carcinoma. Consequently, risk-stratified interventions could diminish the incidence of NAFLD and, subsequently, mitigate the associated mortality. Our research indicates that extended napping duration elevates the likelihood of NAFLD, underscoring the potential efficacy of lifestyle interventions targeting increased physical activity and improved dietary choices.</p>
      <p>Our study boasts several strengths and also acknowledges certain limitations. Firstly, a notable strength of our research lies in the integration of NMA and MR to delve into the causal link between napping and NAFLD. NMA has traditionally been employed to synthesize findings from disparate epidemiological studies, while MR leverages genetic variants as IVs to ascertain whether a risk factor has a causal impact on a health outcome. Secondly, none of our IVs exhibited weak instrument bias, as evidenced by their F statistics exceeding 10. Moreover, we conducted a range of methods to assess pleiotropy and heterogeneity, thereby ensuring that the IVs conformed to the fundamental assumptions. Thirdly, we conducted a multitude of sensitivity analyses to minimize potential biases. We used the strict criteria of SNP selection and found no SNPs associated with potential confounders via online Phenoscanner. In terms of limitations, the evidence for the NMA is derived from Asian populations, while the MR evidence comes from European populations. Differences in ethnicity, lifestyle and age may affect the generalizability of results. As the age of the study population included in our meta-analysis fluctuated little, we did not incorporate subgroup analyses for elderly and younger adults in the NMA. Further, NAFLD was measured by ultrasonography in the meta-analysis, which is an imperfect indicator of NAFLD; therefore, the findings should be approached with circumspection. Leveraging IVW methods, we found that excessive daytime napping was significantly associated with NAFLD. However, further research is necessary to elucidate the underlying biological mechanisms linking these factors.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>MR analysis indicates a causal relationship between daytime napping and an augmented risk of incident NAFLD. Similarly, in NMA, participants with an average napping duration exceeding 30 minutes were found to have a heightened risk of NAFLD compared to those with shorter or no naps.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Ethics Approval and Consent to Participate</title>
      <p>This study utilizes aggregated data rather than individual-level data. The data involved all originate from publicly published GWAS summary databases, which complies with the conditions for exemption from review as stated in the “Ethical Review Measures for Life Sciences and Medical Research Involving Humans”.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0008">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors affirm that the research was carried out free from any commercial or financial ties that could be interpreted as a potential conflict of interest.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fan</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Investigating the association between seven sleep traits and nonalcoholic fatty liver disease: observational and Mendelian randomization study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Genet</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>792558</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fgene.2022.792558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35656325</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dowman</surname>
<given-names>JK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tomlinson</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Newsome</surname>
<given-names>PN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pathogenesis of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">QJM</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>103</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/qjmed/hcp158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19914930</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease in mental disorder inpatients in China: an observational study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hepatol Int</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>136</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12072-020-10132-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33512644</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Browning</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Szczepaniak</surname>
<given-names>LS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dobbins</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence of hepatic steatosis in an urban population in the United States: impact of ethnicity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hepatology</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1387</fpage>–<lpage>1395</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.20466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15565570</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Longer habitual afternoon napping is associated with a higher risk for impaired fasting plasma glucose and diabetes mellitus in older adults: results from the Dongfeng-Tongji cohort of retired workers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>950</fpage>–<lpage>954</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2013.04.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23831240</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cacchione</surname>
<given-names>PZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hodgson</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Afternoon napping and cognition in Chinese older adults: findings from the China health and retirement longitudinal study baseline assessment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Geriatr Soc</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>373</fpage>–<lpage>380</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jgs</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27995615</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yamada</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shojima</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yamauchi</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>J-curve relation between daytime nap duration and type 2 diabetes or metabolic syndrome: a dose-response meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>38075</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep38075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27909305</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Qu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deng</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Associations between longer habitual day napping and non-alcoholic fatty liver disease in an elderly Chinese population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e105583</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0105583</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25140521</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hingorani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Humphries</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Nature’s randomised trials</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>366</volume>(<issue>9501</issue>):<fpage>1906</fpage>–<lpage>1908</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(05)67767-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16325682</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stegeman</surname>
<given-names>BH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Bastos</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosendaal</surname>
<given-names>FR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Different combined oral contraceptives and the risk of venous thrombosis: systematic review and network meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>:<page-range>347:f5298</page-range>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.f5298</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Page</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McKenzie</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bossuyt</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>:<page-range>372:n71</page-range>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.n71</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bedogni</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bellentani</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miglioli</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The fatty liver index: a simple and accurate predictor of hepatic steatosis in the general population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Gastroenterol</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>33</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-230X-6-33</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17081293</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zelber-Sagi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Webb</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Assy</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Comparison of fatty liver index with noninvasive methods for steatosis detection and quantification</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">World J Gastroenterol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3748/wjg.v19.i1.57</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23326163</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fahmy</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fahmy</surname>
<given-names>UA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alhakamy</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Single-port versus multiple-port robot-assisted radical prostatectomy: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>5723</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm10245723</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34945018</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dashti</surname>
<given-names>HS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Daghlas</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lane</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Genetic determinants of daytime napping and effects on cardiometabolic health</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Commun</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>900</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-20585-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33568662</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fairfield</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drake</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pius</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Genome-wide association study of NAFLD using electronic health records</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hepatol Commun</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>308</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep4.1805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34535985</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pierce</surname>
<given-names>BL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ahsan</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>VanderWeele</surname>
<given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Power and instrument strength requirements for Mendelian randomization studies using multiple genetic variants</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>740</fpage>–<lpage>752</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyq151</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20813862</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hong</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Positive association of nap duration with risk of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease in an occupational population in Guangdong Province, China: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Gastroenterol</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>185</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12876-022-02246-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35413791</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Short sleep duration and longer daytime napping are associated with non-alcoholic fatty liver disease in Chinese adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Diabetes</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>827</fpage>–<lpage>836</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1753-0407.12489</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27701849</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep factors in relation to metabolic dysfunction-associated fatty liver disease in middle-aged and elderly Chinese</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Endocrinol Metab</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>107</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2874</fpage>–<lpage>2882</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/clinem/dgac428</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35900115</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zarean</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Looha</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amini</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep characteristics of middle-aged adults with non-alcoholic fatty liver disease: findings from the Shahrekord PERSIAN cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>312</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-023-15251-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36774488</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A double-edged sword: the association of daytime napping duration and metabolism related diseases in a Chinese population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Clin Nutr</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>291</fpage>–<lpage>298</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41430-020-00777-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33082534</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Laposky</surname>
<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bass</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kohsaka</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep and circadian rhythms: key components in the regulation of energy metabolism</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">FEBS Lett</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>582</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>142</fpage>–<lpage>151</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.febslet.2007.06.079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17707819</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vgontzas</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pejovic</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zoumakis</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Daytime napping after a night of sleep loss decreases sleepiness, improves performance, and causes beneficial changes in cortisol and interleukin-6 secretion</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Physiol Endoc Metab</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>292</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>E253</fpage>–<lpage>261</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpendo.00651.2005</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Devine</surname>
<given-names>JK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wolf</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Determinants of cortisol awakening responses to naps and nighttime sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychoneuroendocrino</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>128</fpage>–<lpage>134</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psyneuen.2015.09.016</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Abulizi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Camporez</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jurczak</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Adipose glucocorticoid action influences whole-body metabolism via modulation of hepatic insulin action</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">FASEB J</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>8174</fpage>–<lpage>8185</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.201802706R</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30922125</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Abulizi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Camporez</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Ectopic lipid deposition mediates insulin resistance in adipose specific 11β-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase type 1 transgenic mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Metabolism</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>93</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.metabol.2018.12.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30576689</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mantua</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spencer</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The interactive effects of nocturnal sleep and daytime naps in relation to serum C-reactive protein</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1213</fpage>–<lpage>1216</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2015.06.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26429748</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Juanola</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martínez-López</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Francés</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Non-alcoholic fatty liver disease: metabolic, genetic, epigenetic and environmental risk factors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>5227</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph18105227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34069012</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
