<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39131164</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">11316483</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">467433</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S467433</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Cross-Lagged Panel Networks of Sleep Inertia Across Its Distinct Change Patterns Among Intern Nurses with Shift Work in China</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Ma et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Ma et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2260-1862</contrib-id><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Zijuan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Yunge</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Zhijun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Wenxuan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xiangting</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Huolian</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Shaochen</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0009-0003-1361-9806</contrib-id><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Yang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Yuanyuan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Dongfang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Fang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Center for Studies of Psychological Application, School of Psychology, and Guangdong Key Laboratory of Mental Health and Cognitive Science, South China Normal University</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Research Center for Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macao Policing Model Innovation, China People’s Police University</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Educational Psychology, Faculty of Education, The Chinese University of Hong Kong</institution>, <addr-line>Hong Kong</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Guangdong Provincial Hospital of Chinese Medicine, The Second Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou University of Chinese Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Dongfang Wang; Fang Fan, <institution>School of Psychology, South China Normal University</institution>, <addr-line>Shipai Road</addr-line>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>510631</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, Email wdfpsyc@126.com; fangfan@scnu.edu.cn</corresp><fn id="ft0001"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>1201</fpage><lpage>1212</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>05</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2024 Ma et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Ma et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Purpose</title><p>Although experimental psychopathology using PET, EEG, and fMRI is at the forefront of understanding the underlying mechanisms of sleep inertia, many questions concerning causality remain unanswerable due to ethical constraints and the use of small and heterogeneous samples in experimental methods. There is a pressing need for a novel perspective in a large and relatively homogeneous population to fully capture and elucidate longitudinal processes and dynamic causality that culminate in episodes of sleep inertia over time. Therefore, this study aimed to reveal the causal relationships between symptoms of sleep inertia across its distinct patterns.</p></sec><sec><title>Patients and Methods</title><p>A total of 1636 intern nurses participated in the first survey (94.1% validity rate), then 1277 intern nurses were followed up (82.9% tracing rate). Symptoms of sleep inertia were self-reported using the Sleep Inertia Questionnaire. The cross-lagged panel network models were used to examine unique longitudinal relationships between symptoms of sleep inertia across distinct trajectories.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Four distinct trajectories of sleep inertia were established. Additionally, we found differences in those symptoms with the highest influence on other symptoms at the subsequent point across the networks of four trajectories, particularly, “Difficulty in concentrating” in the persistent-high group and “Feeling tense” in the deteriorating groups.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The current study highlights changes in sleep inertia based on the long-term course over time. Notably, symptoms of “Difficulty in concentrating” and “Feeling tense” are imperative to address these specific symptoms within subpopulations.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>sleep inertia</kwd><kwd>change patterns</kwd><kwd>network structures</kwd><kwd>intern nurse</kwd><kwd>shift work</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Natural Science Foundation of Guangdong Province, China</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Young Talent Support Project of Guangzhou Association for Science and Technology</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>the 2023 Young Teacher Research and Training Fund Project of South China Normal University: Humanities and Social Sciences</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (Grant No.31871129, 32271135), Natural Science Foundation of Guangdong Province, China (Grant No. 2023A1515012200), Young Talent Support Project of Guangzhou Association for Science and Technology (Grant No. QT-2023-025), and the 2023 Young Teacher Research and Training Fund Project of South China Normal University: Humanities and Social Sciences (23SK16).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="3"/><ref-count count="55"/><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta></front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Sleep inertia, characterized by temporarily degraded vigilance, impaired neurobehavioral cognitive performance, worsened mood, and sleepiness, is the unavoidable transitional state from sleep to wakefulness.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1–3</xref> Individuals with sleep inertia while performing safety-critical tasks are at greater risk of performance errors or accidents, posing threats to the safety of themselves and those around them.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> For example, on May 29, 2010, the 3252gt Norwegian-registered platform supply vessel (Skandi Foula) made heavy contact with the moored Panamanian-registered supply vessel (OMS Resolution) in Victoria Dock, Aberdeen.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Analysis of the chief officer’s hours of rest suggested that he was suffering from sleep inertia at the time of the accident, which may have impaired his ability to control Skandi Foula effectively.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Furthermore, the prevalence rates of severe sleep inertia increased from 2.9% in 2000 to 15.2% in 2014 among the general population.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Notably, a sample of 92 employed and volunteer Australian emergency service personnel completed an online survey to determine whether sleep inertia is perceived as a concern among emergency service personnel.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Results found that 25% of shift workers reported that, despite having the opportunity to nap or rest while on shift, they chose not to nap to avoid sleep inertia.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Given the increasing prevalence of severe sleep inertia and the extensive demands of 24/7 service, it is essential to deepen our understanding of sleep inertia to minimize its potential risks for emergency service personnel.</p>
      <p>Decades of research using PET, EEG, and/or fMRI have investigated the neurophysiological mechanisms of sleep inertia.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9–13</xref> To illustrate, a simultaneous EEG-fMRI study has revealed that sleep-like features such as slow EEG power and reduced BOLD activity persist during sleep inertia.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Vallat et al found that awakening in deep sleep is characterized by a global loss of brain functional segregation between task-negative (default mode) and task-positive (dorsal attention, salience, sensorimotor) networks.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Although experimental psychopathology using PET, EEG, and fMRI is at the forefront of understanding the underlying mechanisms of sleep inertia, many questions concerning causality remain unanswerable due to ethical constraints and the use of small and heterogeneous samples in experimental methods. Notably, as a complement to experimental approaches, network analysis aims to clarify the causal processes among symptoms that culminate in episodes of psychological phenomena or disease using data from large-scale self-report surveys.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></p>
      <p>Recently, the network analysis based on network theory has emerged as an alternative framework for conceptualizing mental disorders and psychological phenomena.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> Network theory posits that symptoms of psychopathology are causally connected through various biological, psychological, and societal mechanisms. When these causal associations are sufficiently strong, symptoms may generate feedback loops that sustain themselves.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> While undirected networks with cross-sectional data have involved correlational analyses,<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> the cross-lagged panel network (CLPN) could illuminate longitudinal processes and dynamic causality occurring within and across constructs over time.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> This approach is well-suitable for elucidating the causal associations between symptoms proposed by the network theory.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Network parameters, such as edges and thresholds, are statistical representations of psychological and biological processes, derived from material referents in the real world.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> In brief, network analysis could identify connections that appear consistently across many people, which may provide some leverage for thinking about innovative prevention strategies in the real word.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></p>
      <p>In summary, by using longitudinal data, we would like to employ CLPN to uncover the temporal and causal relationships between symptoms of sleep inertia. Notably, several studies have highlighted significant individual differences in people’s responses and adaptation processes to sleep inertia,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> indicating that there may be distinct change patterns of sleep inertia over time. Therefore, the current study aimed to deepen our understanding of sleep inertia across these varied change patterns.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p>Participants were recruited from a nursing school in Huizhou, China. The sample size was calculated according to established formula:<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
<disp-formula-group><disp-formula id="um0001"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1201-e0001.jpg" position="float"/><tex-math id="Tex001">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}$${\mathrm{N=}}{{{\mathrm{Z}}_{{\mathrm{1-\alpha/2}}}^{\mathrm{2}}{\mathrm{pq}}}\over{{{\mathrm{d}}^{\mathrm{2}}}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></disp-formula></disp-formula-group></p>
        <p>In the above formula, <italic toggle="yes">p, d</italic>, and Z<italic toggle="yes"><sub>1-α/2</sub></italic> represents the expected minimum rate by a previous study,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> allowable error, and statistic for significance test.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Specifically, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.152, <italic toggle="yes">q</italic> = 1 – <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 1–0.152 = 0.848, <italic toggle="yes">d</italic> = 0.2<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.2 * 0.152 = 0.0304, Z<italic toggle="yes"><sub>1-α/2</sub></italic> = 1.96. According to this formula, the minimum required sample size for this study is 536 people. To accommodate potential missed responses, refusals, and dropout risks during a longitudinal study, the sample size was adjusted to a ratio of 1:2.</p>
        <p>This study included two surveys: the first survey (Time 1, T1) was conducted half a month after their clinical internship from June 28 to July 5, 2022) and the second wave (Time 2, T2) occurred three and a half months later from October 11 to 31, 2022. In the first survey, 1636 intern nurses participated, with 1540 providing valid questionnaires (94.1% validity rate). For the second survey, 1277 intern nurses were followed up (82.9% tracing rate), and, 1156 successfully completed all measurements. After excluding 77 individuals with day work, the current study included 1079 intern nurses with shift work.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Procedure</title>
        <p>An electronic invitation letter including a QR code for the questionnaire, was initially sent to the target population via their teachers. The participants volunteered to complete the online questionnaires via their phones or computers with the assistance of trained staff from the nursing school. All participants were free to withdraw from the study at any time. If they feel uncomfortable during or after participating in this study, they could get psychological counseling services from South China Normal University (SCNU) according to the contact information we provided. We assessed various variables in both surveys, including demographic characteristics, willingness to continue working as a nurse, circadian rhythm, sleep inertia, sleep problems, and emotional problems. Electronic informed consent was obtained from all participants or their guardians (if necessary) before starting this survey. Our study was approved by the Human Research Ethics Committees of SCNU and carried out in line with the Helsinki Declaration as revised in 1989.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Measures</title>
        <p>The subjective sleep inertia over the past week was assessed by the Chinese version of the Sleep Inertia Questionnaire (SIQ) in both surveys.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Previous studies demonstrated that the SIQ has robust reliability and validity among different populations.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> Each item of the SIQ is rated on a 5-point Likert scale (1 = Not at all, 2 = A little, 3 = Somewhat, 4 = Often, 5 = All the time). With a total of 21 items, the SIQ yields scores ranging from 21 to 105, where higher scores indicate more severe sleep inertia. The cut-off score of 69 indicates severe sleep inertia in the current sample. Another study, currently under review in the Journal of Sleep Research, offers a more detailed analysis of the cut-off score of 69 used to classify severe sleep inertia among intern nurses. The Cronbach’s α for the SIQ in this study were 0.95 at T1 and 0.96 at T2, respectively.</p>
        <p>Sex, subjective sleep quality at T1, and sleep duration at T1 were evaluated separately using single items. The morningness–eveningness type was determined at T2 through the Chinese version of the 5-item Morningness/Eveningness Questionnaire (MEQ-5).<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> The two dimensions (flexibility and languid) of the Chinese Version of the Circadian Type Inventory (CTI) were used to measure the flexibility of the rhythm (items 1–6) and the ability to overcome drowsy (items 7–11), respectively.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Statistical Analyses</title>
        <sec id="s0002-s2004-s3001">
          <title>Change Patterns of Sleep Inertia</title>
          <p>The change patterns of sleep inertia were disentangled based on the following two steps. Firstly, participants were classified into non- or severe sleep inertia with a cut-off value of 69 at T1 and T2, respectively. Second, the change patterns of sleep inertia from T1 to T2 after their clinical internship were revealed according to the methodology of previous research.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> We further summarized four patterns of sleep inertia: persistent-low, alleviating, deteriorating, and persistent-high. More specifically, individuals in the persistent-high group showed severe sleep inertia at both time points. Intern nurses who reported no severe sleep inertia at T1 but symptoms at T2 were assigned to the deteriorating group. Participants with severe sleep inertia at T1 but without symptoms at T2 were included in the alleviating group. For the persistent-low group, severe sleep inertia was absent at both time points.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2004-s3002">
          <title>The Cross-Lagged Panel Network Models</title>
          <p>The CLPN models were constructed using a series of regularized regression models to estimate both the autoregressive and cross-lagged coefficients. The autoregressive coefficients depict a variable’s influence on itself at the subsequent measurement after controlling for covariates, while the cross-lagged coefficients illustrate the influence of one variable on another variable at the subsequent measurement.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> Demographic and sleep-related factors (see <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=467433.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link></underline>) were incorporated as covariates in all CLPN models, as recommended by Funkhouser et al.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> All models were estimated using the R-package <italic toggle="yes">glmnet</italic>, and all network graphs were visualized using the <italic toggle="yes">Fruchterman-Reingold</italic> algorithm in R-package <italic toggle="yes">qgraph</italic>. In a network graph, nodes represent the symptoms, edges depict the relationships between two symptoms, and the thickness of the edges represents the strength of associations between symptoms.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></p>
          <p>Centrality indices, namely the in-expected influence (in-EI) and out-expected influence (out-EI), were computed using the R-package <italic toggle="yes">qgraph</italic>.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> The in-EI quantifies the proportion of variance for a given variable at follow-up that is accounted for by nodes at baseline, whereas the out-EI signifies the effect a given node at baseline has on nodes at follow-up.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> As in previous studies,<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> the threshold for identifying key symptoms was set at in-EI &gt; 1 and out-EI &gt; 1.</p>
          <p>The bootstrapping function in the R-package <italic toggle="yes">boonet</italic> was utilized to evaluate the accuracy and stability of all networks.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> First, we employed nonparametric bootstrapping to examine the edge-weight accuracy and the significance between edge-weights, with 95% confidence intervals (CIs) based on 1000 bootstrap iterations. Then, we calculated the correlation stability coefficient (CS-C) using the case-dropping bootstrap procedure. The CS-C quantifies the maximum proportion of cases that can be dropped while maintaining a correlation above 0.7 between the centrality indices of the sample with and without dropouts with 95% possibility. The CS-C values ≥0.25 were considered acceptable, whereas CS-C values ≥0.50 were regarded as good.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Change Patterns of Sleep Inertia</title>
        <p>As shown in <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>, four distinct patterns of sleep inertia were established: persistent-low group, alleviating group, deteriorating group, and persistent-high group. The persistent-low group, characterized by SIQ total scores below the cut-off value of 69 at both T1 and T2, comprised 717 (66.5%) participants. The alleviating group (n = 89, 8.2%) was characterized by SIQ scores being equal or above the cut-off value at T1 but below at T2; while the deteriorating group (n = 142, 13.2%) was characterized by SIQ scores being below the cut-off value at T1 but equal or above at T2. Additionally, the persistent-high group comprised 131 participants (12.1%) who had SIQ scores equal or above the cut-off value at two waves. More detailed information on the four patterns of sleep inertia is shown in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Differences on Demographic and Sleep-Related Factors Between the Four Change Patterns of Sleep Inertia</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">%</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Persistent-Low Group (n = 717)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alleviative Group (n = 89)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deteriorated Group (n = 142)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Persistent-High Group (n = 131)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">χ<sup>2</sup></italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">η<sup>2</sup></italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sex<sup>a</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.433</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">675</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">124</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Morningness–eveningness type<sup>b</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101.812***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.292</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">702</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">509</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">278</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">123</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Flexibility of the rhythm<sup>b</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.567**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.102</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">238</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">153</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">593</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">379</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">248</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">185</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Ability to overcome drowsy<sup>b</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">213.291***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.436</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">230</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">201</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">582</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">420</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">267</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Subjective sleep quality<sup>a</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105.677***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.271</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">498</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">389</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">501</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">305</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep duration<sup>a</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.732***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.224</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">707</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">520</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">325</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">164</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>a</sup>Variables were assessed at T1; <sup>b</sup>Variables were assessed at T2. **p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The four SI’s trajectories from half a month to three and half months after their clinical internship among 1079 intern nurses.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1201-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: SI, sleep inertia; T1, Time 1; T2, time 2.</attrib></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Temporal Networks Across Four Distinct Change Patterns of Sleep Inertia</title>
        <sec id="s0003-s2002-s3001">
          <title>Network Structure</title>
          <p>The CLPN network structures of four distinct change patterns of sleep inertia are depicted in <xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>. Overall, the persistent-low group exhibited the highest number of estimated edges (n = 181), followed by the persistent-high (n = 94), alleviating (n = 62), and deteriorating (n = 40) groups. As shown in <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, all estimated edges and autoregressive edges showed no significant differences among four networks, while the cross-lagged edges were significantly different (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic> = 3.121, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, <italic toggle="yes">η</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.028). Furthermore, we applied the Bonferroni correction to adjust the significance levels for multiple comparisons. The results found a significant difference in the cross-lagged edges between the persistent-low and alleviating groups (Difference of mean = 0.03, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Notably, the strongest cross-lagged edges were observed: “React more slowly (SIQ18) - Think more slowly (SIQ17)” in the persistent-low group (edge-weighted value =0.20), “Dread starting your day (SIQ14) - Anxious about the upcoming day (SIQ13)” in the alleviating group (edge-weighted value =0.38), “Feeling tense (SIQ12) - Resist to wake up (SIQ20)” in the deteriorating group (edge-weighted value =0.20), and “Difficulty in getting up (SIQ1) - Hit the snooze button on the alarm (SIQ3)” in the persistent-high group (edge-weighted value =0.19). More detailed information for edge-weighted values can be found in <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=467433.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Tables 1</ext-link></underline>–<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=467433.docx" ext-link-type="uri">4.</ext-link></underline><table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparison on Edge Weights and Centrality Indicators in Four Networks of Distinct Change Patterns of Sleep Inertia</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Persistent-Low Group (n = 717)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Alleviative Group (n = 89)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Deteriorated Group (n = 142)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Persistent-High Group (n = 131)</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">F</italic></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">η<sup>2</sup></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">M</italic>±<italic toggle="yes">SD</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">M</italic>±<italic toggle="yes">SD</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">M</italic>±<italic toggle="yes">SD</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">M</italic>±<italic toggle="yes">SD</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Edge weights</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> All estimated edges</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04±0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">181</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01±0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04±0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05±0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.503</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> All autoregressive edges</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15±0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26±0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15±0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20±0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.929</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> All cross-lagged edges</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03±0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">160</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.01±0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02±0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03±0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.121*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Centrality indicators</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> In-EI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20±0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02±0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03±0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11±0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.973***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.375</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Out-EI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20±0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02±0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03±0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11±0.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.382*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.113</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Note</bold>: *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, ***<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: M, mean; SD, standard deviation; in-EI, in expected influence; out-EI, out expected influence.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Cross-lagged panel networks across four distinct SI’s trajectories. A threshold of all edge weights was manually set to 0.05 to make the figures more interpretable.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1201-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: Each curved arrow “loop” reflects an autoregressive association; White nodes indicate depressive symptoms; Blue lines indicate positive relations, whereas red lines signal negative relations, and line thickness and boldness reflect the strength of associations. (<bold>A</bold>) Persistent-low group; (<bold>B</bold>) Alleviative group; (<bold>C</bold>) Deteriorated group; (<bold>D</bold>) Persistent-high group; SIQ, Sleep Inertia Questionnaire; SIQ1, Difficulty in getting up; SIQ2, Need an alarm to wake up; SIQ3, Hit the snooze button on the alarm; SIQ4, Bump into and drop things; SIQ5, Move more slowly; SIQ6, Feel sleepy; SIQ7, Heavy, sore, or itchy eyes; SIQ8, Tired or heavy arms and/or legs; SIQ9, Groggy, fuzzy or hazy mind; SIQ10, Get winded more easily; SIQ11, Difficulty in keeping balance; SIQ12, Feel tense; SIQ13, Anxious about the upcoming day; SIQ14, Dread starting your day; SIQ15, Wish to sleep more; SIQ16, Difficulty in concentrating; SIQ17, Think more slowly; SIQ18, React more slowly; SIQ19, Make more mistakes/errors; SIQ20, Resist to wake up; SIQ21, Difficulty in getting your thoughts together.</attrib></fig></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2002-s3002">
          <title>Network Inference</title>
          <p>More specifically, symptoms with the high out-EI in the persistent-high group included “Difficulty in concentrating” (SIQ16; out-EI = 1.80), “Difficulty in getting your thoughts together” (SIQ21; out-EI = 1.71), and “Groggy fuzzy or hazy mind” (SIQ9; out-EI = 1.34); while symptoms in the deteriorating groups were “Feeling tense” (SIQ12; out-EI = 3.02) and “Get winded more easily” (SIQ10; out-EI = 1.49). <xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref> shows further details regarding the standardized values of in-EI and out-EI. <xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> provides the results of multiple comparisons using the Bonferroni correction between in EI and out EI.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>The Results of Multiple Comparisons Using the Bonferroni Correction Between in EI and Out EI</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group (I)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group (J)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean(I) - Mean(J)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">In-EI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Persistent-low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alleviative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.13, 0.32]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deteriorated</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.08, 0.27]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Persistent-high</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.00, 0.19]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alleviative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Persistent-low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.22*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[−0.32, −0.13]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deteriorated</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.940</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[−0.14, 0.04]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Persistent-high</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.13*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[−0.22, −0.03]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deteriorated</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Persistent-low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.17*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[−0.27, −0.08]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alleviative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.940</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[−0.04, 0.14]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Persistent-high</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.153</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[−0.17, 0.01]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Persistent-high</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Persistent-low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.10*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[−0.19, 0.00]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alleviative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.03, 0.22]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deteriorated</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.153</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[−0.01, 0.17]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Out-EI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Persistent-low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alleviative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.02, 0.43]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deteriorated</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.137</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[−0.03, 0.38]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Persistent-high</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[−0.11, 0.30]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alleviative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Persistent-low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.22*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[−0.43, −0.02]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deteriorated</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[−0.25, 0.15]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Persistent-high</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.555</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[−0.33, 0.08]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deteriorated</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Persistent-low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.137</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[−0.38, 0.03]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alleviative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[−0.15, 0.25]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Persistent-high</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[−0.28, 0.12]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Persistent-high</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Persistent-low</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[−0.30, 0.11]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alleviative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.555</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[−0.08, 0.33]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deteriorated</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[−0.12, 0.28]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Note</bold>: *p &lt; 0.05.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Abbreviation</bold>: 95% CI, 95% confidence interval.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Centrality estimates of in-EI (Left) and out-EI (Right) using z values between four distinct SI’s trajectories.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-16-1201-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Notes</bold>: Higher values indicate more centrality. SIQ, Sleep Inertia Questionnaire; SIQ1, Difficulty in getting up; SIQ2, Need an alarm to wake up; SIQ3, Hit the snooze button on the alarm; SIQ4, Bump into and drop things; SIQ5, Move more slowly; SIQ6, Feel sleepy; SIQ7, Heavy, sore, or itchy eyes; SIQ8, Tired or heavy arms and/or legs; SIQ9, Groggy, fuzzy or hazy mind; SIQ10, Get winded more easily; SIQ11, Difficulty in keeping balance; SIQ12, Feel tense; SIQ13, Anxious about the upcoming day; SIQ14, Dread starting your day; SIQ15, Wish to sleep more; SIQ16, Difficulty in concentrating; SIQ17, Think more slowly; SIQ18, React more slowly; SIQ19, Make more mistakes/errors; SIQ20, Resist to wake up; SIQ21, Difficulty in getting your thoughts together.</attrib></fig></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2002-s3003">
          <title>Network Stability and Accuracy</title>
          <p>The bootstrapped 95% CIs tests indicated that 95% CIs of all edges were small to moderate (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=467433.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 1</ext-link></underline>). Statistical significance was observed in the results of the bootstrap difference test for edges and centrality indicators <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=467433.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figures 2</ext-link></underline>–<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=467433.docx" ext-link-type="uri">4</ext-link></underline> Stability analyses for in-EI and out-EI centrality suggested partial stability (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=467433.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary Figure 5</ext-link></underline>). Specifically, in-EI centrality is 0.51 in the persistent-low group, 0.11 in the alleviating group, 0.11 in the deteriorating group, and 0.05 in the persistent-high group, and out-EI centrality is 0.34 in the persistent-low group, 0.07 in the alleviating group, 0.18 in the deteriorating group, and 0.15 in the persistent-high group.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>To the best of our knowledge, this study is the first to uncover temporal networks of sleep inertia across its distinct change patterns using longitudinal data. We have two main findings in this study. On the one hand, we established four distinct patterns of sleep inertia. On the other hand, we found differences in those symptoms with the highest influence on other symptoms at the subsequent point across the networks of four change patterns. Particularly, “Difficulty in concentrating” in the persistent-high group and “Feeling tense” in the deteriorating groups should be prioritized for attention in interventions targeting sleep inertia.</p>
      <p>In the current study, we established four change patterns for long-term sleep inertia among intern nurses with shift work: persistent-low (66.5%), alleviating (8.2%), deteriorating (13.2%), and persistent-high (12.1%) groups. This finding is partially consistent with our prior investigation,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> indicating distinct latent profiles of sleep inertia among Chinese college students. Additionally, according to previous research regarding change patterns in sleep-related problems,<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> we could postulate that sleep inertia has large individual differences in people’s responses and adaptation processes to shift work. Several plausible explanations can elucidate this finding. First, sleep inertia, as the third process of sleep regulation, reflects the interplay between a homeostatic drive or pressure for sleep and a circadian rhythm of arousal.<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> Given that shift work has a profound impact on the pressure for sleep over time,<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> sleep inertia might consequently display a different pattern in the long-term period. Second, people perceive the world differently, leading to individual differences in vulnerability to sleep inertia.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> Further studies are needed to validate the specific explanations mentioned above.</p>
      <p>Our findings suggest that central symptoms with the highest out-EI values vary across the four heterogeneous networks of sleep inertia. Due to the lack of network analysis results for sleep inertia subgroups, there is no reference basis for the current findings. However, previous network analysis studies on subgroups of depression or posttraumatic stress symptoms have shown that the key symptoms across subgroups are different.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> These studies can partially support the current finding. Taken together, sleep inertia exhibits significant individual differences, highlighting the importance of future research to further explore its long-term heterogeneity.</p>
      <p>Evidence has suggested that symptoms with the highest out-EI play a role in the onset or development of psychological symptoms.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> Given the availability and effectiveness of clinical interventions,<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> priority should be given to focusing on those symptoms with the highest out-EI in the deteriorating d and persistent-high groups. More specifically, our study reveals firstly that “Difficulty in concentrating” exhibited the greatest influence on other symptoms within the network with the persistent-high sleep inertia among intern nurses with shift work. Several experimental studies provide partial support for significant impairment of vigilance due to sleep inertia.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41–44</xref> For example, Santhi et al found that alertness was most strongly affected by sleep inertia followed by other cognitive functions.<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> Notably, shift work involves exposure to light and eating during the biological night while sleeping during the biological day, causing misalignment with the endogenous circadian system,<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> which may contribute to persistent-high sleep inertia. Alertness has emerged as a fundamental and crucial component of human performance in many work environments.<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> Consequently, the aforementioned evidence helps explain why “Difficulty in concentrating” could strongly predict other symptoms three and a half months after the clinical internship among intern nurses with shift work. A recent study indicated that mindfulness-based interventions can help individuals feel less stressed improve their ability to concentrate.<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> Therefore, these interventions should be employed to enhance concentration in individuals experiencing persistent high sleep inertia.</p>
      <p>Furthermore, “Feeling tense” exhibited the most significant influence on other symptoms within the network characterized by deteriorating sleep inertia. Similar to our previous published study,<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> “Dread starting your day” emerged as a central symptom within the cross-sectional network of sleep inertia among Chinese college students. These findings indicate that negative effects such as irritability and anxiety tend to manifest during the sleep-wake transitional state sleep inertia.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> It is noteworthy that the desire to return to sleep is one of the characteristics of sleep inertia,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> potentially indicating that individuals with more severe sleep inertia might endure insufficient sleep. Sleep loss is closely associated with worsened mood and decreased ability to regulate negative emotions, even exhibiting somatic symptoms.<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> Further, nurses with shift work report frequently poorer sleep quality and reduced sleep duration, which could impact an individual’s positive effects.<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> Therefore, we thought that “Feeling tense” may activate and maintain other symptoms within the network with the deteriorating sleep inertia among intern nurses with shift work. According previous studies,<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> techniques such as deep breathing exercises, progressive muscle relaxation, and mindfulness meditation have been shown to reduce anxiety and tension. Therefore, these techniques can be beneficial for individuals experiencing worsening sleep inertia.</p>
      <p>Notably, this study made a unique contribution to the underlying mechanisms of sleep inertia at the symptom level across distinct change patterns over time. However, it is crucial to acknowledge several limitations. First, the sample only consisted of intern nurses with shift work, potentially limiting the generalizability of findings to other populations such as firefighters, police officers, or pilots due to sex, workplace stability, anticipating a stressful task, frequency of on call.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref> Second, the reliance on subjective self-reports of sleep inertia may introduce potential biases into our findings. Therefore, future studies need reliable and objective measures (eg, psychomotor vigilance task) to measure sleep inertia. The emergency services sectors can prioritize The possible reason is that the temporal nature of symptoms remains unresolved, which is a crucial consideration when selecting a sampling scheme for within-subject studies<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> (ie, How many time points per day or week should be planned?). Fourth, we considered only a limited range of variables and omitted other important information, such as details about the clinical internship and the participants’ shift work schedules (ie, nights per week, rotation direction/speed, days off, or work days). Fifth, similar to previous studies,<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53–55</xref> categorizing individuals into groups based on whether they have a disease or not will inevitably lead to an imbalance in the number of people in each group. Finally, due to the low stability and accuracy of the estimated network for the three small sample groups, the results should be interpreted with caution. Future research should prioritize expanding the sample size to validate the these results.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>The current study highlights changes in sleep inertia based on the long-term course over time. Notably, symptoms of “Difficulty in concentrating” in the persistent-high group and “Feeling tense” in the deteriorating groups were most predictive of other symptoms at follow-up. Taken together, it is imperative to address these specific symptoms within subpopulations.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We thank all the participants of the study.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s0006">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p>The data that support the findings in the current study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Ethics Approval</title>
      <p>Our study was approved by the Human Research Ethics Committees of SCNU and carried out in line with the Helsinki Declaration as revised in 1989.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0008">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors report no other conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kovac</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vincent</surname>
<given-names>GE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paterson</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hilditch</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferguson</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A preliminary framework for managing sleep inertia in occupational settings</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Adv</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>2023</volume>:<fpage>4</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hilditch</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pradhan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Costedoat</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sex differences in perceptions of sleep inertia following nighttime awakenings</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Adv</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>2022</volume>:<fpage>4</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Trotti</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Waking up is the hardest thing I do all day: sleep inertia and sleep drunkenness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2016.08.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27692973</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Branch</surname>
<given-names>MAI</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Heavy Contact by Skandi Foula with OMS Resolution, Aberdeen Harbour 29 May 2010</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>UK Department for Transport</publisher-name>; <year>2011</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Armentrout</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holland</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Toole</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ercoline</surname>
<given-names>WR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Fatigue and related human factors in the near crash of a large military aircraft</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Aviat Space Environ Med</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>963</fpage>–<lpage>970</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16964748</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ohayon</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mahowald</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leger</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Are confusional arousals pathological?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>83</volume>:<fpage>834</fpage>–<lpage>841</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000000727</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25156346</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ohayon</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Priest</surname>
<given-names>RG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zulley</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smirne</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The place of confusional arousals in sleep and mental disorders: findings in a general population sample of 13,057 subjects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Nerv Ment Dis</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>188</volume>:<fpage>340</fpage>–<lpage>348</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005053-200006000-00004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10890342</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kovac</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vincent</surname>
<given-names>GE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paterson</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferguson</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>“I want to be safe and not still half asleep”: exploring practical countermeasures to manage the risk of sleep inertia for emergency service personnel using a mixed methods approach</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Sci Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1493</fpage>–<lpage>1510</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S370488</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36052102</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hsu</surname>
<given-names>C-F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lei</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Loss of frontal regulator of vigilance during sleep inertia: a simultaneous EEG-fMRI study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hum Brain Mapp</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>4288</fpage>–<lpage>4298</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.25125</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32652818</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vallat</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meunier</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nicolas</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruby</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Hard to wake up? The cerebral correlates of sleep inertia assessed using combined behavioral, EEG and fMRI measures</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">NeuroImage</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>184</volume>:<fpage>266</fpage>–<lpage>278</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2018.09.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30223060</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gorgoni</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferrara</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>D’Atri</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>EEG topography during sleep inertia upon awakening after a period of increased homeostatic sleep pressure</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>883</fpage>–<lpage>890</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2015.03.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26004680</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Marzano</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferrara</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moroni</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Gennaro</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Electroencephalographic sleep inertia of the awakening brain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroscience</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>176</volume>:<fpage>308</fpage>–<lpage>317</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroscience.2010.12.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21167917</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Balkin</surname>
<given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Braun</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wesensten</surname>
<given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The process of awakening: a PET study of regional brain activity patterns mediating the re-establishment of alertness and consciousness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>125</volume>:<fpage>2308</fpage>–<lpage>2319</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awf228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12244087</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fried</surname>
<given-names>EI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cramer</surname>
<given-names>AOJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Moving forward: challenges and directions for psychopathological network theory and methodology</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Perspect Psychol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>999</fpage>–<lpage>1020</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1745691617705892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28873325</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McNally</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Can network analysis transform psychopathology?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Res Ther</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>86</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brat.2016.06.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27424882</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Haslbeck</surname>
<given-names>JMB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Waldorp</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>How well do network models predict observations? On the importance of predictability in network models</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Res Methods</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>853</fpage>–<lpage>861</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3758/s13428-017-0910-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28718088</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Borsboom</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A network theory of mental disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">World Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wps.20375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28127906</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Funkhouser</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chacko</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Correa</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaiser</surname>
<given-names>AJE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shankman</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Unique longitudinal relationships between symptoms of psychopathology in youth: a cross‐lagged panel network analysis in the ABCD study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Child Psychol Psyc</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>184</fpage>–<lpage>194</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpp.13256</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rhemtulla</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bork</surname>
<given-names>RV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cramer</surname>
<given-names>AOJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cross-lagged network models</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Multivar Behav Res</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>2017</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prospective network of post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) symptoms across adolescent survivors with distinct trajectories of PTSD: a cohort study of the Wenchuan earthquake</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Anxiety Disord</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>99</volume>:<fpage>102767</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.janxdis.2023.102767</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37708597</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>XY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Who is the hardest to wake up from sleep? An investigation of self‐reported sleep inertia using a latent profile analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>31</volume>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.13552</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lundholm</surname>
<given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Honn</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Skeiky</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Muck</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Dongen</surname>
<given-names>HPA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Trait interindividual differences in the magnitude of subjective sleepiness from sleep inertia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clocks Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>298</fpage>–<lpage>311</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/clockssleep3020019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34204864</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Serdar</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cihan</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yücel</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Serdar</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sample size, power and effect size revisited: simplified and practical approaches in pre-clinical, clinical and laboratory studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biochem Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>010502</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11613/BM.2021.010502</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Reliability and validity of the Chinese vision of sleep inertia questionnaire</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chinese J Clin Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>102</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kanady</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harvey</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Development and validation of the sleep inertia questionnaire (SIQ) and assessment of sleep inertia in analogue and clinical depression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cognitive Ther Res</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>601</fpage>–<lpage>612</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10608-015-9686-4</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wei-Xia</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aizezi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>XZ-TLW-hZ</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Validity and reliability of the Chinese version of Morningness/Eveningness Questionnaire-5 items (MEQ-5) in students of technical schools</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chinese Ment Heal J</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>406</fpage>–<lpage>412</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>H-y</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>X-l</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fan</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Reliability and validity of the Chinese version of circadian type inventory in nurses on shifts</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chinese J Clin Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>258</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>XY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Change patterns of sleep problems predict mental health problems among adolescents: a 10-year cohort study of Chinese Wenchuan earthquake</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Affect Disord</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>287</volume>:<fpage>138</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2021.02.080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33780829</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhai</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Longitudinal trajectories of insomnia symptoms among college students during the COVID-19 lockdown in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychosom Res</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>157</volume>:<fpage>110795</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychores.2022.110795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35364373</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="newspaper"><collab>qgraph</collab>. <article-title>Network visualizations of relationships in psychometric data [computer program]</article-title>; <year>2012</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Savelieva</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Komulainen</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elovainio</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jokela</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Longitudinal associations between specific symptoms of depression: network analysis in a prospective cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Affect Disord</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>278</volume>:<fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2020.09.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32956966</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rubin</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bicki</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Papini</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smits</surname>
<given-names>JAJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Telch</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gray</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Distinct trajectories of depression symptoms in early and middle adolescence: preliminary evidence from longitudinal network analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychiatr Res</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>142</volume>:<fpage>198</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2021.07.053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34365068</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fan</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Temporal network of depressive symptoms across college students with distinct depressive trajectories during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Depress Anxiety</italic></source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>2023</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2023/8469620</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sánchez Hernández</surname>
<given-names>MO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carrasco</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holgado-Tello</surname>
<given-names>FP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Anxiety and depression symptoms in Spanish children and adolescents: an exploration of comorbidity from the network perspective</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Child Psychiat Hum D</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>2021</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="newspaper"><string-name><surname>Epskamp</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Borsboom</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fried</surname>
<given-names>EI</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Estimating psychological networks and their accuracy: A tutorial paper [computer program]. Version 2017/03/28</article-title>; <year>2018</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tomfohr</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buliga</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Letourneau</surname>
<given-names>NL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>TS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Giesbrecht</surname>
<given-names>GF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Trajectories of sleep quality and associations with mood during the perinatal period</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1237</fpage>–<lpage>1245</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.4900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25845691</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hilditch</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McHill</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep inertia: current insights</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Sci Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>165</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S188911</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31692489</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kecklund</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Axelsson</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Health consequences of shift work and insufficient sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>355</volume>:<fpage>i5210</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.i5210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27803010</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Saksvik</surname>
<given-names>IB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bjorvatn</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hetland</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sandal</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pallesen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Individual differences in tolerance to shift work--a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>235</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2010.07.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20851006</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xi</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The unique role of sleep problems among symptoms of posttraumatic stress disorder: a cross-lagged panel network analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Psychologica Sinica</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>1206</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3724/SP.J.1041.2022.01206</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hilditch</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dorrian</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Centofanti</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Dongen</surname>
<given-names>HP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Banks</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep inertia associated with a 10-min nap before the commute home following a night shift: a laboratory simulation study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Accident Anal Prev</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>99</volume>:<fpage>411</fpage>–<lpage>415</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aap.2015.11.010</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mulrine</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Signal</surname>
<given-names>TL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van den Berg</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gander</surname>
<given-names>PH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Post-sleep inertia performance benefits of longer naps in simulated nightwork and extended operations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chronobiol Int</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>1249</fpage>–<lpage>1257</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/07420528.2012.719957</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23002951</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kubo</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Takahashi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Takeyama</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>How do the timing and length of a night-shift nap affect sleep inertia?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Chronobiol Int</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>1031</fpage>–<lpage>1044</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/07420528.2010.489502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20636214</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Santhi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Groeger</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Archer</surname>
<given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gimenez</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schlangen</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dijk</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Morning sleep inertia in alertness and performance: effect of cognitive domain and white light conditions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e79688</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24260280</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Querstret</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Brien</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Skene</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maben</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Improving fatigue risk management in healthcare: a scoping review of sleep-related/ fatigue-management interventions for nurses and midwives (reprint)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Nurs Stud</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>112</volume>:<fpage>103745</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2020.103745</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32847675</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Warm</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parasuraman</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matthews</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Vigilance requires hard mental work and is stressful</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hum Fac Ergon Soc</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>433</fpage>–<lpage>441</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1518/001872008X312152</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Simpson</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mercer</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simpson</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lawrence</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wyke</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mindfulness-based interventions for young offenders: a scoping review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mindfulness</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1330</fpage>–<lpage>1343</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12671-018-0892-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30294385</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>An exploration of self-reported sleep inertia symptoms using network analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Sci Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>661</fpage>–<lpage>674</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S347419</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35450224</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hou</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huangfu</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miao</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Changes in cognition and mood due to sleep inertia after 30-hour sleep deprivation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Ment Health</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baum</surname>
<given-names>KT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Desai</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Field</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>LE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rausch</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beebe</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep restriction worsens mood and emotion regulation in adolescents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Child Psychol Psyc</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>180</fpage>–<lpage>190</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpp.12125</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tsitsi</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Charalambous</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Papastavrou</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raftopoulos</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effectiveness of a relaxation intervention (progressive muscle relaxation and guided imagery techniques) to reduce anxiety and improve mood of parents of hospitalized children with malignancies: a randomized controlled trial in Republic of Cyprus and Greece</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Oncol Nurs</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejon.2016.10.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28069156</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kovac</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vincent</surname>
<given-names>GE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jay</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The impact of anticipating a stressful task on sleep inertia when on-call</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Appl Ergon</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>82</volume>:<fpage>102942</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apergo.2019.102942</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31479838</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ross</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Longitudinal trajectories of depression and anxiety among adolescents during COVID-19 lockdown in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Affect Disord</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>299</volume>:<fpage>628</fpage>–<lpage>635</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2021.12.086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34952127</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>XY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fan</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Longitudinal associations between adolescents’ trajectory membership of depressive symptoms and suicidality in young adulthood: a 10-year cohort of Chinese Wenchuan earthquake survivors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epidemiol Psychiatr Sci</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>e175</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S2045796020000827</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33070799</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0055">
        <label>55.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fan</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Long</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Longitudinal trajectories of post-traumatic stress disorder symptoms among adolescents after the Wenchuan earthquake in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>2885</fpage>–<lpage>2896</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0033291715000884</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25990926</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
