<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">NSS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32346318</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7167267</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">226834</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S226834</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>The Relationship of Sleep Duration with Ethnicity and Chronic Disease in a Canadian General Population Cohort</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Singh et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Singh et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3393-8586</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Singh</surname>
            <given-names>Mandeep</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0002">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0003">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hall</surname>
            <given-names>Kelly A</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0004">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9534-8699</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Reynolds</surname>
            <given-names>Amy</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0005">5</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1628-3055</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Palmer</surname>
            <given-names>Lyle J</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0004">4</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FT0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5021-1648</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Mukherjee</surname>
            <given-names>Sutapa</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="AN0001"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0006">6</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0007">7</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FT0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="AFF0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Anesthesiology and Pain Management, Women’s College Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Toronto</addr-line>, <country>Canada</country></aff>
        <aff id="AFF0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Anaesthesiology and Pain Management, Toronto Western Hospital, University Health Network</institution>, <addr-line>Toronto</addr-line>, <country>Canada</country></aff>
        <aff id="AFF0003"><label>3</label><institution>Toronto Sleep and Pulmonary Centre</institution>, <addr-line>Toronto</addr-line>, <country>Canada</country></aff>
        <aff id="AFF0004"><label>4</label><institution>School of Public Health, University of Adelaide</institution>, <addr-line>Adelaide</addr-line>, <addr-line>SA</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff>
        <aff id="AFF0005"><label>5</label><institution>Appleton Institute, CQ University Australia</institution>, <addr-line>Wayville</addr-line>, <addr-line>SA</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff>
        <aff id="AFF0006"><label>6</label><institution>Respiratory and Sleep Services, Southern Adelaide Local Health Network</institution>, <addr-line>Adelaide</addr-line>, <addr-line>SA</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff>
        <aff id="AFF0007"><label>7</label><institution>Adelaide Institute for Sleep Health, Flinders University</institution>, <addr-line>Adelaide</addr-line>, <addr-line>SA</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="AN0001">Correspondence: Sutapa Mukherjee <institution>Adelaide Institute for Sleep Health, Flinders University</institution>, <addr-line>Adelaide</addr-line>, <addr-line>SA</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country><phone>Tel +61 8 8201 7925</phone> Email Sutapa.Mukherjee@sa.gov.au</corresp>
        <fn id="FT0001">
          <label>*</label>
          <p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2020</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2020</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>12</volume>
      <fpage>239</fpage>
      <lpage>251</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2019</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>02</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2020</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2020 Singh et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2020</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Singh et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="S2001">
          <title>Study Objectives</title>
          <p>Sleep duration is an important marker of sleep quality and overall sleep health. Both too little and too much sleep are associated with poorer health outcomes. We hypothesized that ethnicity-specific differences in sleep duration exist.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="S2002">
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>This cross-sectional study utilized questionnaire data from the Ontario Health Study (OHS), a multi-ethnic population-based cohort of Canadian adult residents aged 18 to 99 years, who provided medical, socio-demographic, and sleep information. Generalised linear models were used to investigate the association of sleep duration with ethnicity.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="S2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>The study sample consisted of 143,307 adults (60.4% women). The sample was multi-ethnic, including self-identified Aboriginal, Arab, Black, Chinese, Filipino, Hispanic, Japanese, Korean, Mixed (&gt;1 ethnicity), South Asian, South-East Asian, West Asian, and White ethnicities. Univariate analyses found that mean sleep duration compared to the White reference group (7.34 hours) was shorter in the Filipino (6.93 hours, 25 min less), Black (6.96 hours, 23 min less), Japanese (7.02 hours, 19 min less), Chinese (7.23 hours, 7 min less), and Mixed (7.27 hours, 4 min less) groups (all P&lt;0.001). Mean sleep duration was shorter in men (7.25 hours) compared to women (7.37 hours) in the cohort as a whole (P&lt;0.001), and in all ethnic groups (P&lt;0.001). Multivariate analyses, adjusted for a wide range of potential risk factors, and analysis of sleep duration as a categorical variable (“short”, “average”, and “long” sleepers) confirmed these relationships. Both sleep duration and ethnicity were independent significant predictors of a range of physician-diagnosed morbidities including diabetes, stroke, and depression.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="S2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>Important differences exist in sleep duration between ethnic groups and may contribute to observed health disparities. Our results highlight the need for ethnicity-specific targeted education on the importance of prioritizing sleep for good health, and the need to account appropriately for ethnicity in future epidemiological, clinical, and translational research into sleep and related conditions.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>sleep health</kwd>
        <kwd>sleep duration</kwd>
        <kwd>ethnicity</kwd>
        <kwd>population health</kwd>
        <kwd>health disparity</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <table-count count="7"/>
        <ref-count count="60"/>
        <page-count count="13"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="S0001">
      <title>Plain Language Summary</title>
      <p>Sleep that is too short or too long in duration is an important marker of sleep quality, general health, and chronic disease risk. Little is known regarding the inter-relationship of ethnic background with sleep duration. We studied a large, population-based, multi-ethnic sample of adults (aged at least 18 years) from Canada - the Ontario Health Study - in order to address this question. We found significant differences in self-reported average sleep duration by ethnic group. Subjects in all ethnic groups were, on average, either at the lower end or below recommended guidelines for healthy sleep. Average sleep duration was highest in White adults, and lowest in Black and Filipino adults. Differences in sleep duration, especially short sleep, were highly correlated with an increased risk of poor health outcomes, and may contribute to observed health disparities amongst ethnic groups. Further research is needed to investigate the factors that contribute to ethnicity-specific variations in sleep duration.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="S0002">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Sleep is essential for good health.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Sleep habits are influenced by social, behavioural, environmental, and genetic factors, and impact sleep quality, timing, and duration. Sleep duration has been investigated in numerous studies, is commonly obtained by self-report, and is generally defined by the average number of hours of sleep (including naps) in a 24-hour period. Extremes of sleep duration (short and long) are associated with adverse health outcomes, including increased risk of cardiovascular disease (CVD)<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> and diabetes,<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> and poor self-rated general health.<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> There is some evidence of an association between variation in sleep duration and all-cause mortality,<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>–<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> and emerging evidence of an interactive association between obstructive sleep apnoea and short sleep duration and the development of hypertension.<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Current recommendations are that adults sleep between 7 and 9 hours per night for good health.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> However, it is clear that in many industrialized countries average sleep duration has declined over the past 50 years, due in part to longer work schedules and increased screen time.<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> There is growing concern that adults are becoming systematically sleep deprived.<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> This is illustrated by recent prevalence estimates of sleep duration among adolescents which suggest that 60% of adolescents in developed countries are sleep deprived (&lt;8 hours sleep per night).<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> These findings are problematic for both current and future generations and suggest that sleep disorders and concomitant adverse health outcomes such as hypertension, diabetes, and poor general health will continue to rise. Identifying correlates of poor sleep in the population is consequently important, in order to inform public policy and interventions.</p>
      <p>There are well-documented gender-based differences in sleep duration,<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> with sleep duration and quality generally found to be higher in women than men.<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> This may be due to an increased biological need for slow wave sleep in women.<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> The National Sleep Foundation poll of 1007 respondents from the United States found significant differences in sleep duration related to ethnicity.<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> African Americans reported the lowest average weekday sleep duration (6 hours, 14 minutes) compared to White Americans (6 hours, 52 minutes), Asians (6 hours 48 minutes), and Hispanics (6 hours, 34 minutes). Another study from the US showed that African Americans demonstrated more variation in habitual sleep time than White Americans.<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> However, there are few such studies globally. Up to 30% of the Canadian adult population have been estimated to have insufficient sleep based on data from the Canadian Health Measures Survey data (n=10,976 individuals).<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Poor quality and reduced duration of sleep thus appear to be common in Canada, although the limited information available adversely impacts the ability to intervene and manage sleep problems in the community.</p>
      <p>Ontario is the most populous province of Canada with a large multi-ethnic population.<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> The capital city, Toronto, is among the most ethnically diverse cities in the world.<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Ontario thus provides a rich sampling frame to investigate whether differences in ethnicity might be associated with variation in sleep duration. The Ontario Health Study (OHS) is a population-based cohort of adults resident in Ontario. Using cross-sectional baseline questionnaire data, we evaluated variation in self-reported sleep duration by gender and ethnicity among participants in the OHS. We hypothesized that, independent of other risk factors, self-reported sleep duration would be associated with ethnicity. Ours is the largest research study to date to report the inter-relationships among sleep duration and ethnicity.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S0003">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="S0003-S2001">
        <title>Study Design</title>
        <p>The OHS is a population-based cohort study comprising a large, ethnically diverse sample from the province of Ontario, Canada.<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> The current study was based upon the self-reported data collected at baseline recruitment from adult (≥18 years) residents of Ontario using a comprehensive web-based questionnaire. Data collected included: health-related behaviour, personal medical history, education history, socio-demographic characteristics, and health service utilization. Data provided as part of this study were collected from study participants between September 29, 2010 and April 29, 2013. Institutional review ethics board approval was obtained (Women’s College Hospital REB#2013-0010-E). Informed consent was obtained from all participants. The sampling frame was all adults aged 18 years and above and resident in the province of Ontario. Online recruitment and measurement were used to enrol large numbers of adult participants at low marginal cost from a broad cross-section of Ontario society. The recruitment of participants at baseline was supported by extensive province-wide advertising in various media, including radio, print and television in addition to online media. Incentive programs were also employed in order to encourage participation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0003-S2002">
        <title>Questionnaire Data</title>
        <p>All questions asked (with the exception of current age and sex) had the additional possible answers of “don’t know” and “prefer not to answer.”</p>
        <sec id="S0003-S2002-S3001">
          <title>Sleep History</title>
          <p>Self-reported sleep duration was recorded based on the response to the question: “On average, how many hours per day do you usually sleep, including naps?” The response was recorded as a continuous variable in hours and minutes. Sleep quality was determined by the response to the question: “How often do you have trouble going to sleep or staying asleep?” Possible responses were: “never”, “part of the time”, “some of the time”, “most of the time”, or “all of the time”.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="S0003-S2002-S3002">
          <title>Ethnicity</title>
          <p>Ethnicity was recorded as a positive answer to at least one of the following options: “Aboriginal” (eg, First Nations, Métis, Inuit), “Arab” (eg, Egypt, Iraq, Jordan, Lebanon), “Black” (African or Caribbean descent), “Chinese”, “Filipino”, “Japanese”, “Korean”, “Latin American/Hispanic”, “South Asian” (eg, India, Sri Lanka, Pakistan, Bangladesh), “Southeast Asian” (eg, Malaysia, Indonesia, Vietnam, Cambodia, Laos), “West Asian” (eg, Turkey, Iran, Afghanistan), or “White” (European ancestry). Where more than one ethnicity was recorded, ethnicity was defined as “Mixed”.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0003-S2003">
        <title>Socio-Demographic Variables and Morbidities</title>
        <p>Current age and gender were reported by all participants. Nativity was recorded as the answer to the question “Were you born in Canada?”. The number of years spent resident in Canada was recorded as the answer to the question “How old were you when you first came to Canada to live?” Body mass index (BMI; kg/m<sup>2</sup>) was calculated using self-reported height and weight. Morbidities of participants were self-reported physician diagnosed conditions (ie, “Has a doctor ever told you that you had any of the following conditions?”). Conditions reported included: high blood pressure (hypertension), blood glucose disorder (high blood glucose/sugar), diabetes (gestational, type 1, or type 2), high cholesterol, depression, stroke, sleep apnoea, and cardiovascular conditions (heart disease and myocardial infarction). Additionally, self-reported general health perception was evaluated (ie, “How would you rate your general health?”) on an ordinal scale from 1 (poor) to 5 (excellent). Geographic residential status (rural or urban, according to Canada Post designations), household income (ie, “What is the approximate total household income (from all sources) before taxes last year?”, with categorical responses: 1= &lt; $10,000, 2=$10,000–$24,999, 3=$25,000–$49,999, 4=$50,000–$74,999, 5=$75,000–$99,999, 6=$100,000–$149,999, 7=$150,000–$199,999, 8= &gt;$200,000), education level (ie, “What is the highest level of education you have completed?”, with responses: 1=none, 2=elementary, 3=high school, 4=trade, 5=diploma, 6=certificate, 7=bachelor’s, 8=graduate degree), current working status (i.e, “Which of the following best describes your working schedule in your current job?, with responses 1=regular daytime shift, 2=regular evening shift, 3=regular night shift, 4=rotating shift, 5=split shift, 6=irregular schedule/on call), smoking status (ie, “Have you ever smoked at least 100 cigarettes in your life?”, with yes or no responses). Physical activity was recorded based on International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ) activity score is included as “Total met/min/week”,<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> based on the response to questions, “During the last 7 days, on how many days did you do vigorous physical activities like heavy lifting, digging, aerobics or fast bicycling?’, “During the last 7 days, on how many days did you do moderate physical activities like carrying light loads, bicycling at a regular pace or doubles tennis?” or “During the last 7 days, on how many days did you walk for at least 10 minutes at a time?”. The IPAQ sedentary score was calculated as “Total sitting mins/week”, based on question, “During the last 7 days, on how much time did you spend sitting on a weekday?”. Alcohol consumption (ie, “On average, over the last year, how often did you drink alcohol?”, with responses 0=never, 1=less than monthly, 2=about once a month, 3=two to three times a month, 4=once a week, 5=two to three times a week, 6=four to five times a week, 7=six to seven times a week) and binge drinking behaviour (ie, “During the past 12 months, how often did you have five or more drinks at the same sitting or occasion?”, with responses 0=never, 1=1 to 5 times a year, 2=6 to 11 times a year, 3=about once a month, 4=2 to 3 times a month, 5=once a week, 6=2 to 3 times a week, 7=4 to 5 times a week, 8=6 to 7 times a week) were also recorded.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0003-S2004">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>Data were analysed using the R statistical software (Version 3.5.1)<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Descriptive statistics used mean and standard deviation for continuous variables, and frequencies and percentages for categorical variables. To investigate the association of ethnic category and sex with sleep duration, multivariate generalized linear models<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> were fitted. The principal outcome was continuous sleep duration in minutes. Potential covariates investigated in multivariate modelling included: age, nativity (born in Canada or born elsewhere); years spent resident in Canada; body mass index (BMI), general health perception, physician diagnosis of morbidities (high blood pressure [hypertension], high blood glucose, diabetes [gestational, type 1, or type 2], high cholesterol level, depression, stroke, sleep apnoea, cardiovascular conditions [heart disease and previous myocardial infarction], total physical activity (IPAQ score), tobacco smoke exposure, alcohol consumption, binge drinking, highest education level, residential location (rural/urban), employment status, total household income, and current shift worker.</p>
        <p>Quadratic terms for age and BMI were investigated in order to account for non-linear association of these variables with sleep duration. Interaction terms for sex:ethnicity, age:ethnicity, and sex:age were investigated.</p>
        <p>Secondary analyses were performed on sleep duration as a categorical variable to enable comparison with previous studies<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> and with the current recommendations of 7–9 hours of sleep per day from the National Sleep Foundation<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> and American Thoracic Society.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Sleep duration was categorized as: “short sleep” (&lt;7 hours), “average sleep” (7 to 9 hours), or “long sleep” (&gt;9 hours). Univariate analyses were conducted to investigate the association of ethnic category and categorical sleep duration using a Chi-square test of independence. Multivariate analyses were conducted by fitting a multinomial logistic regression model with principal explanatory variables ethnicity (categorical) and sex (binary).</p>
        <p>In order to fully assess the clinical implications of the current study, secondary analyses were performed to investigate the univariate and multivariate associations (logistic regression) of the morbidity outcomes investigated with (a) ethnicity and (b) sleep duration.</p>
        <p>Questions answered as “Prefer not to answer” or “Do not know” were coded as missing. All P-values were two-tailed.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S0004">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>The final study population consisted of 143,307 participants with complete data on sleep duration, ethnicity, age, sex and residential location. Of these, 87,357 (61.0%) had missing values in one or more other variables.</p>
      <sec id="S0004-S2001">
        <title>Demographic Characteristics</title>
        <p><xref rid="T0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> describes the demographic characteristics of the cohort. Compared to Statistics Canada Census data from 2011,<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> there was a higher percentage of women in the OHS cohort and participants were older than the general population. In the OHS cohort, there was an overrepresentation of participants of “White” ancestry (79% vs 74% in the 2011 Census data). All other ethnic groups were slightly underrepresented in the OHS; however, the overall pattern of distribution was similar to that of the Census data (<xref rid="T0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). A total of 8.3% of participants reported more than one ethnicity and were classified as “Mixed” ethnicity, in contrast to the 2011 Census data where only 0.8% reported more than 1 ethnicity. Of the study sample, approximately 20% of the cohort belonged to ethnic minorities of which Chinese (3.8%), South Asian (3.4%) and Black (1.4%) ethnicities formed the majority (<xref rid="T0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). All other ethnicity minority groups (Aboriginal, Arab, East-Asian, Filipino, Japanese, Korean, Hispanic, South-East Asian and West Asian) each formed &lt;1% of the cohort.<table-wrap id="T0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic Characteristics of the OHS Cohort Compared to the Ontario General Population Using Statistics Canada 2011 Census Data</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Measure</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complete Cohort (OHS)*</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ontario Census Data<sup>#</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men (OHS)*</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men (Census)#</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women (OHS)*</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women (Census)<sup>#</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total individuals</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">143,307</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,651,795</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56,760 (39.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.181,445 (48.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86,547 (60.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,470,345 (51.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median Age, years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Aboriginal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">869 (0.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34,5870 (2.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">278 (0.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">165,000 (2.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">591 (0.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">180,875 (2.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Arab</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">804 (0.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">151,645 (1.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">454 (0.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79,620 (1.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">362 (0.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72,025 (1.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Black</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1930 (1.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">539,205 (4.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">694 (1.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">251,295 (4.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1236 (1.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">287,915 (4.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Chinese</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5504 (3.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">629,140 (5.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2645 (4.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">301,575 (4.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2859 (3.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">327,570 (5.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Filipino</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">915 (0.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">275,380 (2.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">324 (0.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">116,825 (1.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">591 (0.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">158,555 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Japanese</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">297 (0.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29,085 (0.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.080</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">135 (0.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,345 (0.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.283</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">162 (0.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,740 (0.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Korean</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">365 (0.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78,290 (0.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">176 (0.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38,045(0.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">189 (0.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40,250 (0.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hispanic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1046 (0.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">172,560 (1.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">456 (0.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83,205(1.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">590 (0.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89,360 (1.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mixed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,885 (8.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96,735 (0.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4057 (4.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46,765 (0.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7828 (9.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49,970 (0.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> South Asian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4862 (3.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">965,990 (7.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2831 (5.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">484,355 (7.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2031 (2.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">481,635 (7.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Southeast Asian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">584 (0.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">137,875 (1.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">268 (0.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67,645 (1.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">316 (0.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70,230 (1.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> West Asian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">558 (0.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">122,530 (1.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">304 (0.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62,515 (1.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">254 (0.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60,010 (0.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> White</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">113,688 (79.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,372,225 (74.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44,138 (77.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,598,965 (74.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69,550 (80.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,773,260 (73.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><bold>Notes:</bold> Data are n (%) unless otherwise stated. *OHS data is for participants aged 18 and over; Ontario Census Data is for total population. <sup>#</sup>Ethnicity and Age-distribution data for Ontario population obtained from Statistics Canada.<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> First Nations coded as Aboriginal from Census data.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0004-S2002">
        <title>Sleep Duration as a Continuous Outcome</title>
        <p><xref rid="T0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> summarizes the distribution of average sleep duration stratified by gender and ethnicity. Univariate analyses indicated that average sleep duration varied significantly between ethnic groups in the cohort as a whole and in men and women separately (all <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001). Women reported sleeping longer on average than men across all ethnic groups, with the longest average sleep times observed in West Asian women (<xref rid="T0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>; 7.49 hours, SD 1.44). For women, the shortest average sleep durations were observed in Filipino (6.99 hours, SD 1.19), Black (6.99 hours, SD1.44), and Japanese participants (7.08, SD 0.98). Similarly, Filipino (6.82 hours, SD 1.08), Black (6.91 hours, SD 1.33) and Japanese men (6.94 hours, SD 1.14) reported the shortest sleep durations.<table-wrap id="T0002" orientation="landscape" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Average Sleep Duration by Gender and Ethnicity (in Hours)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Entire Cohort</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aboriginal</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arab</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chinese</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Filipino</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japanese</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Korean</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Asian</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">South-East Asian</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">West Asian</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">White</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All <sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.32 (1.21)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.26 (1.48)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.23 (1.19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.96 (1.40)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.23 (1.12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.93 (1.16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.02 (1.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.24 (1.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.33 (1.19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.27 (1.35)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.30 (1.22)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.26 (1.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.39 (1.31)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.34 (1.20)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women <sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.37 (1.24)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.34 (1.48)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.32 (1.27)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.99 (1.44)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.27 (1.13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.99 (1.19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.08 (0.98)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.30 (1.23)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.44 (1.17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.32 (1.37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.37 (1.26)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.28 (1.32)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.49 (1.44)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.39 (1.22)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men <sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.25 (1.17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.08 (1.48)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.15 (1.13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.91 (1.33)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.18 (1.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.82 (1.08)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.94 (1.14)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.18 (1.28)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.20 (1.19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.18 (1.29)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.25 (1.18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.23 (1.17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.31 (1.18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.27 (1.16)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><bold>Notes:</bold> Data are Mean (Standard Deviation). <italic>χ</italic><sup>2</sup><sub>12</sub>=1264.8, <sup>#</sup>P value &lt;0.001.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
        <p>Multivariate linear models (<xref rid="T0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>) fitted to mean sleep duration in the entire cohort confirmed the univariate observations. Independently significant covariates included in the final multivariate model were: age, age<sup>2</sup>, BMI, measures of physical activity (IPAQ), location (urban/rural), general health perception, household income, current employment, highest education level, shift work status, alcohol intake, frequency of binge drinking, diagnosed stroke and high blood glucose, trouble sleeping, nativity, and years resident in Canada.<table-wrap id="T0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Association of Ethnicity with Mean Sleep Duration (in Minutes): Final Linear Regression Model, Adjusted for Significant Covariates</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Term</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimate (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> White (Reference)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Aboriginal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.82 (−10.49, 4.86)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.472</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Arab</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.63 (−15.50, 2.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.143</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Black</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−22.19 (−27.38, −16.99)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Chinese</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−12.83 (−15.96, −9.69)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Filipino</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24.57 (−32.24, −16.90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Japanese</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−27.14 (−38.18, −16.11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Korean</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−14.54 (−25.55, −3.53)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hispanic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.68 (−10.98, 1.63)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.146</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mixed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.27 (−7.59, −2.96)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> South Asian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.86 (−7.78, 0.86)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.054</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> South-East Asian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−17.87 (−27.64, −8.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> West Asian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.95 (−13.47, 7.58)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.583</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Women (Reference)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Men</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−11.44 (−12.65, −10.24)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><bold>Notes:</bold> Model adjusted for the following significant covariates: IPAQ total activity (met/min/week), IPAQ total sitting (min/week), BMI, age, age<sup>2</sup>, location (urban/rural), general health perception, diagnosed depression (yes/no), diagnosed high cholesterol (yes/no), diagnosed stroke (yes/no), diagnosed blood glucose (yes/no), diagnosed sleep apnoea (yes/no), household income, current job involving shift work (yes/no), current employment, highest education level, frequency of alcohol consumption, frequency of binge drinking, trouble sleeping, nativity, and years resident in Canada. Chi-Square of income and highest education level P&lt;0.001 and therefore only income was included in the final model. * Overall P value for categorical covariate from “Ethnicity” analysis of variance. Effect size for the linear regression model was 0.02 (Cohen’s <italic>f<sup>2</sup></italic>=0.02).</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> BMI, Body mass index; CI, Confidence interval; IPAQ, International Physical Activity Questionnaire.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
        <p>After adjustment for extensive demographic and risk factors, estimated average sleep duration was significantly shorter (P&lt;0.001) in Black, Chinese, Filipino, Japanese, and mixed ethnicity participants compared to White participants (<xref rid="T0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Similarly, Korean (P=0.01) and South Asian (P=0.05) participants had significantly shorter sleep duration than White participants (<xref rid="T0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Sleep duration for the Aboriginal, Arab, Hispanic, and West Asian ethnic groups did not significantly differ either from each other or from the White reference category. Multivariate analysis estimated that on average men slept less than women (P&lt;0.001). There was evidence of a significant interactions between sex:age (P&lt;0.001) and sex:ethnicity (P=0.034) but not age:ethnicity (P=0.969); the effects of both age and ethnicity were greater in men.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0004-S2003">
        <title>Sleep Duration as a Categorical Outcome</title>
        <p>Univariate analysis of sleep duration as a categorical variable produced consistent results for men and women (<xref rid="T0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>), with a high proportion of short sleepers (sleep duration &lt;7 hours) in those of Filipino (51% men, 44% women), Black (46% men, 44% women), and Japanese (41% men, 31% women) ancestry. The ethnic group with the highest proportion of long sleepers (sleep duration &gt;9 hours) was the Aboriginal group (men 7.2%, women 8%) (<xref rid="T0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). West Asian (7%) and Black (5%) women had high proportions of long sleepers; Korean men had a high proportion (6.8%) of long sleepers.<table-wrap id="T0004" orientation="landscape" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Sleep Duration as a Categorical Variable by Gender and Ethnicity</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Entire Cohort</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aboriginal</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arab</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chinese</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Filipino</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japanese</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Korean</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Asian</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">South-East Asian</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">West Asian</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">White</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">143,307</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">869</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">804</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1930</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5504</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">915</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">297</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">365</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1046</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,885</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4862</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">584</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">558</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">113,688</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39,030 (27.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">294 (33.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">248 (30.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">862 (44.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1621 (29.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">424 (46.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105 (35.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101 (27.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">288 (27.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3702 (31.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1414 (29.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">185 (31.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">157 (28.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29,629 (26.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97,919 (68.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">507 (58.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">525 (65.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">972 (50.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3701 (67.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">460 (50.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">189 (63.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">242 (66.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">714 (68.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7524 (63.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3222 (66.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">374 (64.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">367 (65.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79,122 (69.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6358 (4.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (7.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (3.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96 (5.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">182 (3.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (3.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (1.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (6.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (4.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">659 (5.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">226 (4.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (4.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (6.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4937 (4.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86,547</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">591</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">350</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1236</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2859</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">591</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">162</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">189</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">590</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7828</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2031</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">316</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">254</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69,550</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,438 (25.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">183 (31.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102 (29.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">539 (43.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">817 (28.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">260 (44.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (30.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (22.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">144 (24.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2304 (29.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">571 (28.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 (31.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (25.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,261 (24.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59,898 (69.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">360 (60.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">232 (66.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">631 (51.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1936 (67.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">312 (52.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111 (68.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">136 (72.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">418 (70.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5046 (64.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1342 (66.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">202 (63.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">171 (67.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49,001 (70.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4211 (4.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (8.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (4.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (5.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106 (3.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (3.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (5.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (4.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">478 (6.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">118 (5.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (4.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (7.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3288 (4.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56,760</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">278</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">454</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">694</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2645</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">324</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">176</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">456</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4057</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2831</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">268</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">304</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44,138</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,592 (29.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111 (39.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">146 (32.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">323 (46.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">804 (30.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">164 (50.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (40.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (33.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">144 (31.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1398 (34.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">843 (29.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (31.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93 (30.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,368 (28.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38,021 (67.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">147 (52.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">293 (64.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">341 (49.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1765 (66.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">148 (45.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (57.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106 (60.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">296 (64.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2478 (61.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1880 (66.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">172 (64.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">196 (64.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30,121 (68.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2147 (3.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (7.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (3.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (4.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76 (2.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (3.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (6.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (3.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">181 (4.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108 (3.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (4.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (4.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1649 (3.7)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><bold>Notes:</bold> Data are n (%); *<italic>χ</italic><sup>2</sup><sub>24</sub>=825.65.0, P&lt;0.001; **<italic>χ</italic><sup>2</sup><sub>24</sub>=519.7, P&lt;0.001; ***<italic>χ</italic><sup>2</sup><sub>24</sub>=331.1, P&lt;0.001.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
        <p>Multivariate logistic models (<xref rid="T0005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>) fitted to categorical sleep duration confirmed the univariate associations. Relative to the White reference groups, the prevalence of short sleeping was significantly more common in all ethnic groups except for Hispanics. Short sleeping was common in the Filipino (OR=3.00, 95% CI=2.59 to 3.47), Black (OR=2.51, 95% CI=2.26 to 2.78), and Southeast Asian (OR=1.69, 95% CI=1.39 to 2.06) ethnic groups, consistent with the data in <xref rid="T0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. Long sleepers were most prevalent in the Aboriginal (OR=2.04, 95% CI=1.57 to 2.66), West Asian (OR=1.81, 955 CI=1.24 to 2.66), Korean (OR=1.77, 95% CI=1.09 to 2.88), and Black (OR=1.53, 95% CI=1.20 to 1.96) ethnic groups (<xref rid="T0005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). Independently significant covariates included in the final multivariate model were: sex, age, BMI, nativity, and years resident in Canada.<table-wrap id="T0005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>The Association of Ethnicity with Sleep Duration (Short or Long): Multinomial Logistic Regression Comparing Short (&lt;7 Hours) and Long (&gt;9 Hours) to Average (7–9 Hours) Sleep Time*</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Short (&lt;7 hours) (N = 97,919)</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Long (&gt;9 hours) (N = 6358)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> White (reference)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Aboriginal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40 (1.20, 1.65)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04 (1.57, 2.66)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Arab</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26 (1.07, 1.49)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (0.68, 1.51)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.943</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Black</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.51 (2.26, 2.78)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.53 (1.20, 1.96)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Chinese</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40 (1.31, 1.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (0.84, 1.19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.975</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Filipino</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00 (2.59, 3.47)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 (0.76, 1.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.516</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Japanese</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62 (1.26, 2.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35 (0.11, 1.11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.074</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Korean</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41 (1.10, 1.82)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.77 (1.09, 2.88)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hispanic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 (0.98, 1.33)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.094</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 (0.71, 1.43)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.950</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mixed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34 (1.27, 1.41)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30 (1.16, 1.45)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> South Asian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33 (1.24, 1.44)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 (1.01, 1.42)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Southeast Asian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.69 (1.39, 2.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27 (0.80, 2.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.310</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> West Asian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35 (1.10, 1.65)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81 (1.24, 2.66)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Women (Reference)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Men</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13 (1.10, 1.16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80 (0.75, 0.84)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><bold>Notes:</bold> *Model adjusted for sex, age, BMI, nativity, and years resident in Canada. Reference category is Average sleep (7–9 hours).</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> OR, Odds ratio; CI, Confidence interval.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0004-S2004">
        <title>The Association of Morbidity Outcomes with Ethnicity and Sleep Duration</title>
        <p>The prevalence of morbidities differed significantly between ethnic groups (all P &lt;0.001) (<xref rid="T0006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). Physician diagnosed high blood glucose, diabetes, heart disease, myocardial infarction, stroke, depression, sleep apnoea, and poor general health perception were all most prevalent in participants of Aboriginal descent (<xref rid="T0006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). The proportion of participants reporting a diagnosis of high cholesterol level was highest amongst participants of Japanese followed by those of Arab, Aboriginal, and White descent. Hypertension was most prevalent amongst Japanese participants, followed by the Aboriginal, White and Black ethnic groups (<xref rid="T0006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). Multivariate logistic models (analyses not shown) confirmed the univariate associations; after adjustment for many other risk factors including sleep duration, ethnicity was independently associated with risk of self-reported high blood pressure, high blood glucose, diabetes, high cholesterol levels, depression, stroke, OSA (all P&lt;0.001), and heart disease (P=0.028).<table-wrap id="T0006" orientation="landscape" position="float"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Characteristics of the Study Sample by Ethnicity</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aboriginal<break/>n=869</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arab n=804</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black<break/>n=1930</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chinese<break/>n=5504</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Filipino<break/>n=915</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japanese<break/>n=297</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Korean<break/>n=365</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic<break/>n=1046</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed<break/>n=11,885</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Asian n=4862</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">South-East Asian<break/>n=584</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">West Asian<break/>n=558</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">White<break/>n=113,688</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">278 (32.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">445 (56.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">694 (36.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2645 (48.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">324(35.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">135 (45.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">176 (48.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">456 (43.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4057 (34.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2831 (58.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">268 (45.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">304 (54.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44,138 (38.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women #</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">591 (68.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">350 (43.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1236 (64.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2859 (51.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">591 (64.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">162 (54.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">189 (51.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">590 (56.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7828 (65.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2031 (41.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">316 (54.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">254 (45.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69,550 (61.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age * years Mean (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.5 (12.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.2 (14.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.9 (12.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.8 (13.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.7 (12.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.5 (12.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.3 (12.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.5 (12.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.9 (14.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.9 (14.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.8 (12.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.2 (13.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.9 (14.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI * Mean (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.6 (7.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.2 (5.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3 (5.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.1 (3.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.01 (5.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.7 (4.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.6 (3.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.34 (5.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.1 (6.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0 (4.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.2 (4.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.06 (4.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.2 (5.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">General health perception #</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (4.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (2.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (2.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (0.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (1.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (1.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (1.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">327 (2.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (1.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (1.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (0.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2020 (1.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fair</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">147 (16.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 (10.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">206 (10.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">564 (10.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (10.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (7.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (9.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91 (8.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1224 (10.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">465 (9.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (11.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (8.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9672 (8.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">337 (38.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">230 (28.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">572 (29.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015 (36.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">322 (35.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102 (34.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111 (30.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">318 (30.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3948 (33.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1665 (34.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200 (34.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">180 (32.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35,778 (31.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very good</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">262 (30.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">319 (39.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">762 (39.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2120 (38.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">365 (39.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125 (42.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">139 (38.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">445(42.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4619 (38.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1849 (38.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">216 (37.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250 (44.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47,152 (41.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excellent</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 (9.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">152 (18.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">348 (18.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">735 (13.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">119 (13.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (15.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (20.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">172 (16.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1749 (14.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">801 (16.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93 (15.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 (13.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,936 (16.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood glucose disorder #</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110 (12.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (5.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102 (5.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">292 (5.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (6.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (11.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (4.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (3.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">762 (6.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">321 (6.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (3.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (3.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7018 (6.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes mellitus #</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107 (12.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (5.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120 (6.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">196 (3.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (7.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (8.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (3.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">781 (6.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">362 (7.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (3.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (3.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6799 (6.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depression #</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">137 (15.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (7.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">130 (6.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">144 (2.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (3.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (4.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 (7.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1466 (12.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">182 (3.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (2.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (4.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,228 (10.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart disease #</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (3.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (1.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (1.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (1.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (1.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (4.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 (0.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">295 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98 (2.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (0.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (1.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3569 (3.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High Cholesterol #</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">143 (16.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">150 (18.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">210 (10.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">782 (14.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">137 (15.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95 (31.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (10.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">131 (12.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1757 (14.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">752 (15.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (8.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (10.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,524 (16.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension #</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">213 (24.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">123 (15.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">402 (20.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">642 (11.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">165 (18.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 (28.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (7.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">141 (13.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2177 (18.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">688 (14.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (9.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (10.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24,887 (21.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myocardial infarction #</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (2.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (1.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (0.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (0.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (0.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (1.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (0.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">213 (1.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 (1.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (0.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2344 (2.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stroke #</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (1.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (0.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (0.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (0.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(0.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (0.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">121 (1.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (0.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1192 (1.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Apnoea #</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (8.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (6.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90 (4.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">215 (3.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (5.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (5.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (5.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">633 (5.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">160 (3.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (2.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5764 (5.1)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><bold>Notes:</bold> Data are n (%) unless otherwise stated. <sup>#</sup><italic>χ</italic><sup>2</sup>test, P value &lt;0.001; *ANOVA, P value &lt;0.001.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> BMI, Body mass index (kg/m<sup>2</sup>); SD, standard deviation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
        <p>Univariate analyses suggested that higher average sleep duration was associated with physician diagnosed depression and stroke (all P&lt;0.001; <xref rid="T0006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). Conversely, lower average sleep duration was associated with physician diagnosed hypertension, high cholesterol levels, and sleep apnoea (all P&lt;0.001; <xref rid="T0006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). Average sleep duration was highest for those with both the best and worst perceptions of general health (P&lt;0.001; data not shown). Multivariate logistic models (analysis not shown) confirmed the univariate associations; after adjustment for many other risk factors including ethnicity, longer sleep duration (continuous covariate) was independently associated with an increased risk of physician diagnosed: high blood glucose (OR=1.05, 95% CI=1.02 to 1.08, P&lt;0.001), diabetes (OR=1.03, 95% CI=1.01 to 1.06, P=0.016), high cholesterol levels (OR=1.05, 95% CI=1.03 to 1.07, P&lt;0.001), depression (OR=1.21, 95% CI=1.18 to 1.23, P&lt;0.001), and stroke (OR=1.10, 95% CI=1.03 to 1.16, P=0.002). Similarly, shorter sleep duration (continuous covariate) was independently associated with an increased risk of physician diagnosed OSA (OR=0.96, 95% CI=0.93 to 0.98, P=0.002).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0004-S2005">
        <title>Ethnicity and Sleep Quality</title>
        <p>Self-reported sleep quality was associated with a linear trend in average sleep duration; poorer sleep was associated with decreasing sleep duration (P&lt;0.001; data not shown) Troubled sleep differed significantly by ethnicity (<inline-formula id="ILM0001"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="NSS-12-239-e0001.jpg"/><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$$\chi $$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula><sup>2</sup><sub>48</sub>=1794.2, P&lt;0.001) (<xref rid="T0007" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>). Aboriginal participants reported experiencing the most trouble sleeping compared to other ethnic groups, with over 25% of participants reporting troubled sleep most or all of the time. Approximately 6% of Chinese participants reported experiencing trouble sleeping most or all of the time, compared to 10% of Filipino, Japanese, South Asian, West Asian or Korean participants; 12% of Hispanic participants, 14% of Arab and Black participants, 21% of Mixed participants, 17% of White participants, and 9% of South-East Asian participants (<xref rid="T0007" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>).<table-wrap id="T0007" orientation="landscape" position="float"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Distribution of “Trouble Sleeping” Question by Ethnicity*</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aboriginal<break/>N=862</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arab<break/>N=797</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black<break/>N=1905</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chinese<break/>N=5448</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Filipino<break/>N=908</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japanese<break/>N=295</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Korean<break/>N=360</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic<break/>N=1040</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed<break/>N=11,846</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Asian<break/>N=4862</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">South-East Asian<break/>N=582</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">West Asian<break/>N=551</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">White<break/>N=113,377</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">181 (21.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">231 (29.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">568 (29.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1710 (31.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">213 (23.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 (23.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">112 (31.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">376 (36.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2762 (23.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1773 (37.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">151 (26.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">194 (35.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26,911 (23.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Part of the time</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">157 (18.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">231 (29.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">397 (20.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1806 (33.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">241 (26.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (31.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">117 (32.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250 (24.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2615 (22.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1018 (21.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">169 (29.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">141 (25.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27,387 (24.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some of the time</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">291 (33.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">220 (27.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">637 (33.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1592 (29.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">354 (39.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96 (32.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95 (26.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">289 (27.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3927 (33.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1521 (31.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">206 (35.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">156 (28.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37,905 (33.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Most of the time</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">149 (17.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 (10.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">228 (12.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">272 (5.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 (8.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (8.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (6.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99 (9.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1801 (15.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">390 (8.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (7.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (8.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,740 (13.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All of the time</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84 (9.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (4.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (3.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (1.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (2.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (2.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (3.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">741 (6.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97 (2.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (2.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (2.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5434 (4.8)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><bold>Notes:</bold> Data are n (%). *<italic>χ</italic><sup>2</sup><sub>48</sub>=1794.2, P&lt;0.001.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S0005">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <sec id="S0005-S2001">
        <title>Principal Findings</title>
        <p>We have conducted the largest research study to date that has examined ethnic differences in sleep duration in a general adult population sample. We report significant ethnic differences in sleep duration that were further modified by sex. In our study, mean sleep duration was shorter in Filipino, Black, Japanese, Chinese, and Mixed participants compared to participants of White origin. We found that women on average sleep longer than men in all ethnic groups, consistent with previous findings.<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> We have further demonstrated the independent associations of sleep duration and ethnicity with a number of important morbidities: depression, diabetes, high cholesterol levels, heart disease, stroke, sleep apnoea, and perception of general health (<xref rid="T0006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0005-S2002">
        <title>Strengths and Weaknesses of the Current Study</title>
        <p>The ethnicity related differences in self-reported sleep duration were independent of a large range of socioeconomic, environmental, and biological risk factors. The modulating effect of sex was apparent in the multivariate models. However, the effect sizes and odds ratios observed in our study were of modest magnitude, suggesting that biological, environmental/cultural, and/or psychosocial factors<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>-<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> other than ethnicity also play a role in determining average sleep duration. In addition, differences between the White ethnic group and the Chinese (7 min less than White) and Mixed (4 min less than White; <xref rid="T0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) groups were small and may not be clinically significant.</p>
        <p>A strength of the current study is the large and ethnically diverse population-based sample available from the OHS and the use of standardized data capture in the form of an online questionnaire that ensured internal validity. Our study is both substantially larger than all previous published studies - the next largest study was of 29,818 adults<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> - and considered a far more heterogenous and ethnically diverse sample of adults, which increases generalizability to other populations. Ethnic diversity related to ongoing immigration and admixture is an increasingly relevant characteristic of industrialized societies such as Canada and other Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD) nations and has been under-investigated apropos sleep.</p>
        <p>The limitations of our study primarily relate to the cross-sectional study design, to potential selection and reporting biases, and potential confounding factors. Although more robust than many “conventionally” recruited epidemiology cohorts, the OHS is not a perfectly representative sample of the general adult population of Ontario. Uniquely for a large cohort study at the time all data were collected using an online questionnaire. The available evidence suggests that responses to online questionnaires are comparable in accuracy to questionnaires administered in person or self-reported on paper.<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> It is possible that our recruitment strategy may have encouraged participants more proficient in use of the internet or with better internet access to participate, thus affecting the external validity of the study and limiting the generalizability of the findings. However, comparison to Ontario census data (<xref rid="T0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) suggested that a robust sample broadly representative of the general population of Ontario was collected, making this unlikely. Objective measurements of sleep duration and morbidities were not collected, which may contribute to lack of precision in the outcome data. However, there is evidence that self-reported history of physician-diagnosed chronic health conditions can have high specificity and sensitivity.<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> Only self-reported items were used (with no use of standardized questionnaires or objective measurements of sleep duration or morbidities) which may contribute to recall and assessment bias. Another limitation is that the one question on sleep duration requested the subject to include nap time. The current study thus cannot discriminate between individuals with excessive daytime sleepiness or those with poor sleep hygiene due to split sleep times, and cannot, therefore, be directly compared to previous studies that asked questions on nocturnal sleep duration.</p>
        <p>It has been observed that comparison of objective measures of sleep duration (actigraphy and polysomnography) and self-reported sleep duration leads to an overestimation of sleep time for subjective recall of sleep duration.<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> In addition, the cross-sectional design of the study does not account for variability in sleep duration and timing between weekdays and weekends, or seasonally.<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> Future research will thus be needed in order to explore these relationships.</p>
        <p>A possible explanation for the observed differences in sleep duration between ethnic groups may be potential “confounding” due to disparity in socio-economic position among ethnic groups, as socio-economic position differs by ethnicity (ie, inequality)<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> and has been previously associated with reduced sleep duration and quality.<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> Note that this is not true confounding, as socio-economic factors cannot cause ethnicity. The effect of socioeconomic status (eg, the clustering of education level, rural/urban residential location, employment status or household income), across ethnic groups may be particularly important and influential as it may emphasize differences within Whites and between average-to-high socioeconomic status Whites and all other ethnic groups, potentially regardless of SES.<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></p>
        <p>Health disparities among different ethnic minorities are similarly “confounded” by differences in psychosocial factors such as stress, self-esteem, mental illness, access to health care, neighbourhood characteristics (crime, safety, air pollution, noise) which can all disrupt normal physiological functioning including sleep.<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> However, we found significant differences in sleep duration in multivariate analysis after controlling for many of these variables (<xref rid="T0003" ref-type="table">Tables 3</xref> and <xref rid="T0005" ref-type="table">5</xref>), suggesting that the associations are robust. It is possible that more sensitive indicators of neighbourhood stress and disruption are required<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> and may explain some of the disparity in sleep duration in the cohort.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0005-S2003">
        <title>Comparison to Previous Studies</title>
        <p>Our findings should be considered in the context of previous studies in both Canadian and other populations exploring sleep duration and ethnicity. Prior literature on sleep duration has been largely based on data from populations of predominantly European ancestry.<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> The Canadian population, particularly that of Ontario, is ethnically diverse and hence advantageous to study because of the relatively large proportion of visible minorities with sufficient cases to meaningfully explore ethnic differences in sleep. Differences in sleep duration among the largest ethnic groups in the US (White, Black and Hispanic groups) have been identified.<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> However, there is a dearth of data on sleep duration in other ethnic minorities. There is also no obvious explanation for the differences in sleep duration observed.</p>
        <p>The 2010 General Social Survey (GSS)<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> reported mean sleep duration in a small sample (n=15,390) of the general Canadian population (aged 15 years and over) to be 8 hours 18 mins. In contrast, the crude estimate of mean sleep duration in the OHS (aged 18 years and over) was almost 1 hour less (7 hours 21 mins in the entire cohort). These differences could reflect differences in age distribution, sampling biases, and/or a more accurate estimate in the much larger OHS sample.</p>
        <p>Our findings are consistent with the many prior studies that have documented the close and potentially causal relationships of both sleep duration and ethnicity with a range of morbidities,<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>–<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> including cardio-metabolic outcomes,<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>–<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> hypertension,<xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref> stroke,<xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> and depression.<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref> Our findings and those of prior studies highlight the potential clinical impact of ethnicity-driven short and long sleep duration. Despite Canada being a high-immigration country and non-Western immigrants’ having systematically higher morbidity than ethnic White Canadians, no national strategy targeting immigrants’ health has been implemented. Future research should emphasize a life-course perspective and include the children of immigrants.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0005-S2004">
        <title>Clinical Implications</title>
        <p>Sleep duration has been consistently shown to be an independent predictor of health.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Consistent with previous research, sleep duration was associated a range of important physician-diagnosed clinical outcomes in our study, including depression<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> and stroke<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> (long sleep duration), and hypertension,<xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> hypercholesterolemia<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> and sleep apnea<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> (short sleep duration). Almost all adults sampled in the current study were on the lower range or below accepted norms for healthy sleep.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> This finding is even more striking given the known tendency of self-report to overestimate sleep duration.<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> Important differences exist in self-reported mean sleep duration between ethnicities and may contribute to ethnic group differences in the prevalence of sleep disorders and other chronic diseases. To the best of our knowledge, there are no published guidelines regarding the threshold for “clinical significance” in sleep duration in the general population. Using RCTs of pharmacotherapy in insomnia patients as a guide,<xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref> a “clinically significant” difference in total sleep duration can be as little as 8–10 minutes. However, we feel that a difference of at least 20 minutes total sleep duration is a more reasonable threshold for “clinical significance”. Our study reaches this threshold for the Black, Filipino, and Japanese ethnic groups relative to the White reference group (<xref rid="T0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Measures to increase sleep duration in ethnic minority populations may help to reduce ethnic health inequalities. Our results highlight the need for gender- and ethnicity-specific targeted education on the importance of prioritizing sleep for overall health, and the need to account appropriately for ethnicity in future clinical and translational research into sleep and related conditions. Further study and elucidation of the factors involved in determining differences in sleep duration among different ethnic groups is warranted.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S0006">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Poor sleep has an impact on general health and lifestyle and is also associated with increased morbidity. On average, Canadian adults are sleep restricted or at the lower end of recommended guidelines for healthy sleep. We found that significant ethnic differences exist for self-reported sleep duration among residents of Ontario, and that both ethnicity and sleep duration were independent risk factors for common chronic diseases. Further research is warranted to investigate the possible factors that contribute to the shorter sleep duration observed in certain ethnic groups and in men, and to implement strategies to improve sleep duration and sleep quality in the Canadian and other populations.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We thank Woganee Filate for technical assistance. We also thank the participants in the Ontario Health Study. </p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="S0007" sec-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>Financial disclosure: This work was supported by the Ontario Institute for Cancer Research; Cancer Care Ontario; Public Health Ontario and the Canadian Partnership Against Cancer. Amy Reynolds reports financial reimbursement from Sealy Australia to provide expert scientific commentary on findings of the Sealy Global Sleep Census. The authors report no other conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
      <p>Non-financial disclosure: The data used for this research was made available by the Ontario Health Study with the financial support from the Canadian Partnership Against Cancer, Health Canada and the Ontario Institute for Cancer Research. The views expressed herein represent the views of the authors and do not necessarily represent the views of Health Canada or the Government of Ontario.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CIT0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mukherjee</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kales</surname>
<given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>An official American Thoracic Society statement: the importance of healthy sleep. Recommendations and future priorities</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>191</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1450</fpage>–<lpage>1458</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201504-0767ST</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26075423</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gallicchio</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kalesan</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep duration and mortality: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>148</fpage>–<lpage>158</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.2008.00732.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19645960</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wheaton</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chapman</surname>
<given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Croft</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep duration and chronic diseases among U.S. adults age 45 years and older: evidence from the 2010 behavioral risk factor surveillance system</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1421</fpage>–<lpage>1427</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.3028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24082301</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zizi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pandey</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Murrray-Bachmann</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Race/ethnicity, sleep duration, and diabetes mellitus: analysis of the National Health Interview Survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Med</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>125</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>162</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjmed.2011.08.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22269619</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gangwisch</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heymsfield</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boden-Albala</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration as a risk factor for diabetes incidence in a large U.S. sample</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1667</fpage>–<lpage>1673</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/30.12.1667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18246976</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cho</surname>
<given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yoo</surname>
<given-names>KB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kwon</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The association between sleep duration and self-rated health in the Korean general population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1057</fpage>–<lpage>1064</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.3082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24127150</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cappuccio</surname>
<given-names>FP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>D’Elia</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Strazzullo</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep duration and all-cause mortality: a systematic review and meta-analysis of prospective studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>585</fpage>–<lpage>592</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/33.5.585</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20469800</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gangwisch</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heymsfield</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boden-Albala</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration associated with mortality in elderly, but not middle-aged, adults in a large US sample</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1087</fpage>–<lpage>1096</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18714780</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cai</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shu</surname>
<given-names>X-O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xiang</surname>
<given-names>Y-B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration and mortality: a prospective study of 113,138 middle-aged and elderly Chinese men and women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>529</fpage>–<lpage>536</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.4564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25348122</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Priou</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Le Vaillant</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meslier</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cumulative association of obstructive sleep apnea severity and short sleep duration with the risk for hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>e115666</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0115666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25531468</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Watson</surname>
<given-names>NF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Badr</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Belenky</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Recommended amount of sleep for a healthy adult: a joint consensus statement of the American Academy of Sleep Medicine and Sleep Research Society</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>843</fpage>–<lpage>844</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.4716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26039963</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>National Sleep Foundation</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Summary Findings of Sleep in America; Sleep and Ethnicity</italic></source>; <year>2010</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hale</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Screen time and sleep among school-aged children and adolescents: a systematic literature review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>50</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2014.07.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25193149</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Knutson</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sociodemographic and cultural determinants of sleep deficiency: implications for cardiometabolic disease risk</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Soc Sci Med</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2012.05.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22682665</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lauderdale</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knutson</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yan</surname>
<given-names>LL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Objectively measured sleep characteristics among early-middle-aged adults: the CARDIA study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>164</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwj199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16740591</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Redline</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kirchner</surname>
<given-names>HL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quan</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gottlieb</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kapur</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Newman</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effects of age, sex, ethnicity, and sleep-disordered breathing on sleep architecture</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>164</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>406</fpage>–<lpage>418</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.164.4.406</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14980992</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nunes</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jean-Louis</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zizi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration among black and white Americans: results of the National Health Interview Survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Natl Med Assoc</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>100</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>322</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0027-9684(15)31244-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18390025</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chaput</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Michaud</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Duration and quality of sleep among Canadians aged 18 to 79</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Health Rep</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>28</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28930365</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="data"><collab>Statistics Canada</collab>. <article-title>Visual census. 2006 Census. Ottawa</article-title>; <year>2010</year>
<comment>Available from:</comment>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www12.statcan.gc.ca/census-recensement/2006/dp-pd/fs-fi/index.cfm?Lang=ENG&amp;TOPIC_ID=11&amp;PRCODE=35">http://www12.statcan.gc.ca/census-recensement/2006/dp-pd/fs-fi/index.cfm?Lang=ENG&amp;TOPIC_ID=11&amp;PRCODE=35</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>7</month><day>22</day>, 2017</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Statistics Canada</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Canada’s Ethnocultural Mosaic, 2006 Census</italic></source>; <year>2008</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="data"><collab>Ontario Health Study</collab>. <comment>Available from:</comment>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ontariohealthstudy.ca">https://ontariohealthstudy.ca</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <day>30</day><month>7</month> 2017</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Craig</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marshall</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sjostrom</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>International physical activity questionnaire: 12-country reliability and validity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Med Sci Sports Exerc</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1381</fpage>–<lpage>1395</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/01.MSS.0000078924.61453.FB</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12900694</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ihaka</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gentleman</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>R: a language for data analysis and graphics</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Comput Graph Stat</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>299</fpage>–<lpage>314</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>McCullagh</surname>
<given-names>PNJ</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Generalized Linear Models</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Chapman and Hall</publisher-name>; <year>1989</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hirshkowitz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whiton</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Albert</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>National Sleep Foundation’s updated sleep duration recommendations: final report</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Health</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>243</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleh.2015.10.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29073398</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Statistics Canada</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">National Household Survey Profile, Ontario</italic></source>; <year>2011</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dijk</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beersma</surname>
<given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bloem</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sex differences in the sleep EEG of young adults: visual scoring and spectral analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>500</fpage>–<lpage>507</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/12.6.500</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2595173</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Walsemann</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ailshire</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fisk</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>LL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Do gender and racial/ethnic disparities in sleep duration emerge in early adulthood? Evidence from a longitudinal study of U.S. adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>140</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2017.03.031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28735911</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Adenekan</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pandey</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McKenzie</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zizi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Casimir</surname>
<given-names>GJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jean-Louis</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep in America: role of racial/ethnic differences</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2012.07.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23348004</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ali</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Finlay</surname>
<given-names>AY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salek</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Equivalence of electronic and paper-based patient-reported outcome measures</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Qual Life Res</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1949</fpage>–<lpage>1961</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11136-015-0937-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25702266</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Oksanen</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kivimaki</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pentti</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Virtanen</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Klaukka</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vahtera</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Self-report as an indicator of incident disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>547</fpage>–<lpage>554</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.annepidem.2010.03.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20538198</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Okura</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Urban</surname>
<given-names>LH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mahoney</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jacobsen</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rodeheffer</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Agreement between self-report questionnaires and medical record data was substantial for diabetes, hypertension, myocardial infarction and stroke but not for heart failure</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1096</fpage>–<lpage>1103</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2004.04.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15528061</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kurina</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McClintock</surname>
<given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Waite</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thisted</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lauderdale</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep duration and all-cause mortality: a critical review of measurement and associations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>361</fpage>–<lpage>370</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.annepidem.2013.03.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23622956</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cespedes</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>FB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Redline</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Comparison of Self-Reported Sleep Duration With Actigraphy: results From the Hispanic Community Health Study/Study of Latinos Sueno Ancillary Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>183</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>561</fpage>–<lpage>573</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwv251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26940117</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Roenneberg</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allebrandt</surname>
<given-names>KV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Merrow</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vetter</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Social jetlag and obesity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Biol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>939</fpage>–<lpage>943</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2012.03.038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22578422</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kasper</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wehr</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bartko</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gaist</surname>
<given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosenthal</surname>
<given-names>NE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Epidemiological findings of seasonal changes in mood and behavior. A telephone survey of Montgomery County, Maryland</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Gen Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>823</fpage>–<lpage>833</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2789026</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stamatakis</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaplan</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roberts</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Short sleep duration across income, education, and race/ethnic groups: population prevalence and growing disparities during 34 years of follow-up</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>948</fpage>–<lpage>955</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.annepidem.2007.07.096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17855122</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Geroldi</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frisoni</surname>
<given-names>GB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rozzini</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Leo</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trabucchi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Principal lifetime occupation and sleep quality in the elderly</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Gerontology</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>169</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000213788</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8796375</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Puckrein</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Egan</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Howard</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Social and medical determinants of cardiometabolic health: the big picture</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ethn Dis</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>521</fpage>–<lpage>524</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18865/ed.25.4.521</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26673674</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wi</surname>
<given-names>CI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>St Sauver</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jacobson</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Ethnicity, socioeconomic status, and health disparities in a mixed rural-urban US Community-Olmsted County, Minnesota</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mayo Clin Proc</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>91</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>612</fpage>–<lpage>622</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mayocp.2016.02.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27068669</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thorpe</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McGrath</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jackson</surname>
<given-names>WB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jackson</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Black-White Differences in Housing Type and Sleep Duration as Well as Sleep Difficulties in the United States</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>564</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph15040564</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Loredo</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Soler</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bardwell</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ancoli-Israel</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dimsdale</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Palinkas</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep health in U.S. Hispanic population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>962</fpage>–<lpage>967</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/33.7.962</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20614856</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Statistics Canada</surname></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">General Social Survey-2010 Overview of the Time Use of Canadians</italic></source>. <year>2010</year> Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www150.statcan.gc.ca/n1/pub/89-647-x/89-647-x2011001-eng.htm">https://www150.statcan.gc.ca/n1/pub/89-647-x/89-647-x2011001-eng.htm</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Itani</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jike</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Watanabe</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaneita</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Short sleep duration and health outcomes: a systematic review, meta-analysis, and meta-regression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>246</fpage>–<lpage>256</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2016.08.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27743803</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jervelund</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malik</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ahlmark</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Villadsen</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nielsen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vitus</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Morbidity self-perceived health and mortality among non-western immigrants and their descendants in Denmark in a life phase perspective</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Immigr Minor Health</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>448</fpage>–<lpage>476</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10903-016-0347-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27002626</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jike</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Itani</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Watanabe</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaneita</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Long sleep duration and health outcomes: A systematic review, meta-analysis and meta-regression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2017.06.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28890167</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cappuccio</surname>
<given-names>FP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and cardio-metabolic disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Cardiol Rep</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>110</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11886-017-0916-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28929340</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Graham</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Disparities in cardiovascular disease risk in the United States</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Cardiol Rev</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>238</fpage>–<lpage>245</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1573403X11666141122220003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25418513</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gazzola</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reeskamp</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van den Born</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Ethnicity, lipids and cardiovascular disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Opin Lipidol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>230</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MOL.0000000000000412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28338521</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>St-Onge</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grandner</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration and quality: impact on lifestyle behaviors and cardiometabolic health: a scientific statement from the American Heart Association</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circulation</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>134</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<fpage>e367</fpage>–<lpage>e386</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIR.0000000000000444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27647451</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Modesti</surname>
<given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reboldi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cappuccio</surname>
<given-names>FP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Panethnic differences in blood pressure in Europe: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e0147601</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0147601</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26808317</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mei</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>YR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Relationship between duration of sleep and hypertension in adults: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1047</fpage>–<lpage>1056</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.5024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25902823</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Boehme</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Esenwa</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elkind</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>stroke risk factors, genetics, and prevention</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circ Res</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>120</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>472</fpage>–<lpage>495</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.116.308398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28154098</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McDermott</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chervin</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disorders and the risk of stroke</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Expert Rev Neurother</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>523</fpage>–<lpage>531</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14737175.2018.1489239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29902391</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0055">
        <label>55.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhai</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep duration and depression among adults: a meta-analysis of prospective studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Depress Anxiety</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>664</fpage>–<lpage>670</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/da.22386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26047492</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0056">
        <label>56.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Patil</surname>
<given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Porche</surname>
<given-names>MV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shippen</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dallenbach</surname>
<given-names>NT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fortuna</surname>
<given-names>LR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Which girls, which boys? The intersectional risk for depression by race and ethnicity, and gender in the U.S</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Psychol Rev</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cpr.2017.12.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29310973</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0057">
        <label>57.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Elie</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruther</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Farr</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Emilien</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salinas</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep latency is shortened during 4 weeks of treatment with zaleplon, a novel nonbenzodiazepine hypnotic. Zaleplon clinical study group</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>536</fpage>–<lpage>544</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4088/JCP.v60n0806</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10485636</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
