<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">NSS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32607035</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7320888</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">253375</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S253375</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Effects of Mobile Use on Subjective Sleep Quality</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Rafique et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Rafique et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1565-415X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Rafique</surname>
            <given-names>Nazish</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0371-2367</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Al-Asoom</surname>
            <given-names>Lubna Ibrahim</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5402-1091</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Alsunni</surname>
            <given-names>Ahmed Abdulrahman</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="AN0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Saudagar</surname>
            <given-names>Farhat Nadeem</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Almulhim</surname>
            <given-names>Latifah</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0002">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Alkaltham</surname>
            <given-names>Gaeda</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0002">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="AFF0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Physiology, College of Medicine, Imam Abdulrahman Bin Faisal University</institution>, <addr-line>Dammam</addr-line>, <country>Saudi Arabia</country></aff>
        <aff id="AFF0002"><label>2</label><institution>College of Medicine, Imam Abdulrahman Bin Faisal University</institution>, <addr-line>Dammam</addr-line>, <country>Saudi Arabia</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="AN0001">Correspondence: Ahmed Abdulrahman Alsunni <phone>Tel +966 53 525 5577</phone><fax>Fax +966 13 3857 8048</fax> Email aalsunni@uod.edu.sa</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>23</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2020</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2020</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>12</volume>
      <fpage>357</fpage>
      <lpage>364</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2020</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2020</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2020 Rafique et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2020</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Rafique et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="S2001">
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p>The objective of this study was to find out the association between mobile use and physiological parameters of poor sleep quality. It also aimed to find out the prevalence of mobile-related sleep risk factors (MRSRF) and their effects on sleep in mobile users.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="S2002">
          <title>Materials and Methods</title>
          <p>This cross-sectional study was conducted on 1925 students (aged 17–23yrs) from multiple Colleges of Imam Abdulrahman Bin Faisal University, Dammam, Saudi Arabia. The study tools used were Pittsburgh sleep quality index (PSQI) and MRSRF online questionnaires.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="S2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>The mean age (±SD) of participants was 19.91 ± 2.55 years. Average mobile screen usage time was 8.57±4.59/24 hours, whereas average mobile screen usage time in the bed after the lights have been turned off was 38.17±11.7 minutes. Only 19.7% of subjects used airplane mode, while 70% kept the mobile near the pillow while sleeping. The blue light filter feature was used by only 4.2% of the participants. “Screen usage time of ≥8 hours” was positively correlated with sleep disturbances and decrease in the length of actual sleeping time (p =0.023 and 0.022). “Using the mobile for at least 30 minutes (without blue light filter) after the lights have been turned off” showed positive correlation with poor sleep quality, daytime sleepiness, sleep disturbances and increased sleep latency (p= 0.003, 0.004 and 0.001). “Keeping the mobile near the pillow while sleeping” was also positively correlated with daytime sleepiness, sleep disturbances and increased sleep latency (p =0.003, 0.004 and 0.001).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="S2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>This study concludes that using mobile screen ≥8 hours/24 hours, using the mobile for at least 30 minutes before sleeping after the lights have been turned off and keeping the mobile near the pillow are positively associated with poor sleep quality. Moreover, we observed that MRSRF were highly prevalent amongst the mobile users.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>mobile use</kwd>
        <kwd>sleep quality</kwd>
        <kwd>mobile-related sleep risk factors</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <table-count count="5"/>
        <ref-count count="37"/>
        <page-count count="8"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="S0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Sleep is a physiological state of unawareness which is regulated homeostatically.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Almost one-third of our lives are spent while sleeping.<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Sleep plays an important role in cognitive and physical functions, cellular toxin removal, disease prevention and restoration of both mind and body.<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>–<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> A major decline in the sleep hours and its strong correlation with obesity, diabetes, and other chronic debilitating diseases have been documented in the past 20–30 years.<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></p>
      <p>Proper sleep is especially important for children and adolescents.<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Lack of sleep in adolescents is becoming an important health issue worldwide.<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Many factors can affect sleep hygiene<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> but the role of mobile use in causing sleep problems in adolescence has gained huge attention in the past few years.<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> A recent review by Sohn et al reported that one in every four children and young people are suffering from Problematic cell phone use (PSU), which is linked to depression, anxiety and poor sleep quality.<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Current metaanalysis by Carter et al showed that bedtime use of media devices was positively associated with poor sleep quality and excessive daytime sleepiness.<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></p>
      <p>Mobile use at bedtime (after the lights have been turned off), can cause poor sleep quality (PSQ) by various mechanisms.<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Due to technology revolution, most of the mobile phone users now have smartphones which enable them to access internet and social networks, watching videos, online chatting and playing games.<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> This results in exposure to stimulating content, mobile phone overuse and phone addiction thus contributing to hyper arousal in pre bedtime period and poor sleep quality.<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></p>
      <p>A major factor which can contribute to PSQ is the blue light emitted by screens of mobile phones.<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> This blue light can decrease the production of melatonin, the hormone which controls the sleep/wake cycle or circadian rhythm. Reduction in melatonin makes it difficult to fall and stay asleep.<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Some studies have found that exposure to blue light increases brain alertness<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> and can stimulate cognitive functions, which in turn can lead to PSQ.<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></p>
      <p>Moreover, the mobile phones receive and transmit the signals through radiofrequency electromagnetic fields (RF-EMFs).<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> It is well documented that RF-EMFs can pass through the skull, and reach the brain.<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Therefore, this technology may pose dangers for human health, of particular interest are its effects on sleep parameters and sleep electroencephalogram (EEG).<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Some studies have reported that RF-EMFs exposure can result in changes in EEG during rapid eye movement (REM) sleep, non-REM sleep, and sleep latency.<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>–<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> All these findings further strengthen the role of mobile in causing PSQ.</p>
      <p>Limited availability of the data regarding the “Prevalence of mobile use and its association with sleep quality in the Saudi population” compelled us to design this project. To our knowledge, the current study recruited the largest number of samples of young Saudi population for investigating the link between mobile phone use and sleep quality. We hypothesize that a positive association exists between mobile use and poor sleep quality. We also aimed to find out the prevalence of mobile-related sleep risk factors (MRSRF) in mobile users and their effects on sleep, ie, using mobile before sleeping after the lights have been turned off, not enabling airplane mode on mobiles, putting the mobiles near or below the pillows and bedside while sleeping. As no previous studies are available to highlight these important findings.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <p>This cross-sectional study was conducted from January 2018 till August 2019 on 1925 students (aged 17–23yrs) from multiple colleges of Imam AbdulRahman Bin Faisal University, Dammam (IAU).</p>
      <p>Sample size calculation was done by using open source epidemiologic statistics for public health tools software (accessed at: <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://epitools.ausvet.com.au/content.php?page=1Proportion&amp;Proportion">http://epitools.ausvet.com.au/content.php?page=1Proportion&amp;Proportion</ext-link></underline>). The calculation was based on estimated prevalence of poor sleep quality in mobile users in a target population of 5000 students and desired precision as 0.02 (2%), confidence interval as 0.95 (95%). The calculated sample size was 2017.</p>
      <p>The study tool included two questionnaires: mobile-related sleep risk factors Questionnaire (MRSRF) and Pittsburg sleep quality index (PSQI) (<underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=253375.pdf">Supplementary material</ext-link></underline>).</p>
      <sec id="S0002-S2001">
        <title>Identification of Mobile-Related Sleep Risk Factors (MRSRF)</title>
        <p>This online questionnaire (generated by using Google forms) was designed by the authors based on relevant required information, extracted from few previous studies.<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> The face validity of the questionnaire was confirmed by professors of physiology and respiratory therapy at IAU, whereas test retest technique was used to verify the reliability (interval of three weeks) with a group of 30 students (P = 0.002; r = 0.84).</p>
        <p>MRSRF Questionnaire includes seven items which focus on the following areas: Total duration of mobile use/day, using mobile while in the bed when the lights have been turned off, using blue light filters on mobile, keeping the mobile under pillow, keeping the mobile 2 meters away from the bed and putting the mobile on airplane mode while sleeping.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0002-S2002">
        <title>Identification of Sleep Quality</title>
        <sec id="S0002-S2002-S3001">
          <title>The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)</title>
          <p>Various questionnaires are used to identify the sleep quality. But PSQI has been found to be most effective in terms of reliability and validity. It includes 19 self-rated items, which focus on seven main areas including: subjective sleep quality, sleep latency (time taken to fall asleep), sleep duration, habitual sleep efficiency (the ratio of total sleep time to time in bed), sleep disturbances, the use of sleep-inducing medicines and daytime dysfunction.<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0002-S2003">
        <title>PSQI Scoring</title>
        <p>The PSQI includes a scoring key for calculating a patient’s seven subscores, each of which ranges from 0 to 3.
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A score of 0 indicates no difficulty.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A score of 3 indicates severe difficulty.</p></list-item></list></p>
        <p>The 7 component scores are then added to make a global score with a range of 0–21.
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>A score of 0 means no difficulty.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A score of 5 or more indicates poor sleep quality.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A score of 21 means severe difficulties in all areas.</p></list-item><list-item><p>(The higher the score, the worse the quality).</p></list-item></list></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0002-S2004">
        <title>Data Collection</title>
        <p>Data were collected by convenience sampling technique, and response rate was 38.5%, as 1925 out of 5000 students volunteered and completed the questionnaire. A five minutes briefing session was given in the class to explain the rational of study and terminologies used in the questionnaire (Average strength of students/class was 50). The online questionnaire was shared with each class on their WhatsApp groups, and a time of 8 minutes was provided to the students to fill the questionnaire. The students were assured about the confidentiality of their personal information.</p>
        <sec id="S0002-S2004-S3001">
          <title>Inclusion Criteria</title>
          <p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>The students between 17 and 26 years who were willing to participate in the study.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>The students who use mobile phone daily, even if they use it for a brief moment.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="S0002-S2004-S3002">
          <title>Exclusion Criteria</title>
          <p>The students suffering from
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Any diagnosed sleep disorder.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Any diagnosed chronic respiratory problem (including nasal congestion, chest infections, asthma, adenoids, allergic rhinitis)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Any chronic physical or mental illness, affecting their sleep.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Using any prescription medication for at least last 3 months.</p></list-item></list></p>
          <p>Finally, 156 students were excluded, and 1925 were selected.</p>
          <p>Ethical approval of the study was taken by Deanship of Scientific Research College of Medicine (IAU).</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S0002-S2005">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>The data were analyzed using Statistical Package for Social Sciences (SPSS) for Windows, Version 20.0. Descriptive statistics were used to determine the demographic data.</p>
        <p>Comparison of sleep quality and sleep parameters in the participants with various “Mobile-related sleep risk factors” (MRSRF) was done by using Cross tab Chi square test for nominal variables, and independent <italic>t</italic> test for qualitative data. A p value of &lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p>
        <p>Correlation of Poor sleep quality and various sleep parameters with MRSRF was done by using Pearson and Spearman tests.</p>
        <p>Binary regression analysis test was run using the quality of sleep (poor PSQI&gt;5 versus good PSQI&lt;5) as the dependent variable and the following variables were the independent factors: age, gender, screen usage time &gt;8 hours, using the mobile phone during two hours before sleep, using mobile in bed after lights are turned off, duration of cell phone use after the lights are turned off (minutes), keeping the mobile phone near the pillow while sleeping.</p>
        <p>A shapiro-Wilk’s test (p&gt;0.05) and visual inspection of histogram showed that the data were approximately normally distributed.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>The mean age (±SD) of participants was 19.91 ± 2.55 years. Number of female participants was 1502 (77%), whereas the number of male participants was 423 (21%). 98% of the participants owned smart phones. Average screen usage time was 8.57±4.59/24 hours, and 38% of the participants reported of using mobile for more than 8/24 hours. Almost 88.7%of the subjects were using the mobile after the lights have been turned off with an average screen usage time of 38.17±11.7 minutes. Out of these 88.7% subjects, 84.5% were not using the blue light filters on their mobiles. Average time spent on watching videos was 1.8±1.74 hours. Poor sleep quality was seen in 33% of males and 37% of females. Comparison of these parameters between male and female subjects is given in <xref rid="T0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.<table-wrap id="T0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of Screen and Sleep-Related Parameters, Between Male and Female Subjects</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mobile screen usage time (hours)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.07±3.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.71±4.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time spent on watching videos (hours) on mobile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06±1.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.73±1.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mobile screen usage time in the bed after the lights are turned off (minutes)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.43±53.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.97±48.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor sleep quality</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.260</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><bold>Note:</bold> P value &lt;0.05 is considered statistically significant.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      <p>Prevalence of mobile usage, and various MRSRF are shown in <xref rid="T0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Only 19.7% of subjects used airplane mode, while 70% kept the mobile near the pillow while sleeping. The blue light filter feature was used by only 4.2% of the participants. It was observed that the greater number of females as compared to males keep the mobiles near their pillow while sleeping (p = 0.029). Whereas the number of females who use airplane mode on their mobiles while sleeping was greater than the number of males using this function (p = 0.021).<table-wrap id="T0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Prevalence of Mobile Usage and “Mobile-Related Sleep Risk Factors” in Study Participants</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mobile Usage and MRSRF</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Males (%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Females (%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mobile screen usage time ≥8 hours/24 hours</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.293</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Watching video ≥3 hours/24 hours</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.063</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Using mobile for at least 30 minutes after the lights are turned off (without a blue light filter in mobile)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.073</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Keeping the mobile near the pillow while sleeping</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putting mobile on airplane mode while sleeping</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Using blue light filter on mobile while using mobile in dark</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2.%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.723</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><bold>Note:</bold> P value &lt;0.05 is considered statistically significant.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Abbreviation:</bold> MRSRF, mobile-related sleep risk factors.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      <p>Comparison of sleep quality in the participants with various MRSRF is shown in <xref rid="T0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. Data indicated that the subjects who use the mobile after the lights have been turned off for at least 30 minutes (without a blue light filter in mobile), and who put the mobile near their pillow while sleeping have a statistically significant poor sleep quality (P=0.001, 0.001) respectively.<table-wrap id="T0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Comparison of Sleep Quality in the Participants with Various “Mobile-Related Sleep Risk Factors”</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">MRSRF</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Sleep Quality (%)</th><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">P value</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI ≥5</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI &lt;5</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Poor Sleep)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Normal Sleep)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Screen usage time ≥8 hours</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.333</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Watching video ≥3 hours/24 hours</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.056</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Using mobile for at least 30 minutes after the lights are turned off (without a blue light filter in mobile)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Keeping the mobile near the pillow while sleeping</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not putting mobile on airplane mode while sleeping</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.973</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><bold>Note:</bold> P value &lt;0.05 is considered statistically significant.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Abbreviation:</bold> MRSRF, mobile-related sleep risk factors.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      <p>Further analysis revealed a strong positive correlation of poor sleep quality with Using Mobile for at least 30 minutes after the lights are turned off (without a blue light filter in mobile) (p=0.018) <xref rid="T0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>.<table-wrap id="T0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Correlation of Poor Sleep Quality with Various “Mobile-Related Sleep Risk Factors”</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MRSRF</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(OR, 95% CI)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Screen usage time ≥8 hours</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.547</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.091 (0.821–1.451)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Using mobile for at least 30 minutes after the lights are turned off (without a blue light filter in mobile)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.958 (1.352–2.836)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Keeping the mobile near the pillow while sleeping</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.091</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.368 (0.952–1.967)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not putting mobile on airplane mode while sleeping</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.681</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.067 (0.758–1.528)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><bold>Note:</bold> P value &lt;0.05 is considered statistically significant.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Abbreviation:</bold> MRSRF, mobile-related sleep risk factors.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      <p>Correlation of various sleep parameters with MRSRF is highlighted in <xref rid="T0005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>. Screen usage time of &gt;8 hours was positively but weakly correlated with sleep disturbances and decrease in the length of actual sleeping time (P value 0.023 and 0.022, respectively). Using the mobile after the lights have been turned off for at least 30 minutes (without a blue light filter in mobile) showed positive but weak correlation with daytime sleepiness, sleep disturbances and increased sleep latency (p= 0.003, 0.004 and 0.001). Keeping the mobile near the pillow while sleeping was also positively but weakly correlated with daytime sleepiness, sleep disturbances and increased sleep latency (p =0.003, 0.004 and 0.001).<table-wrap id="T0005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Correlation of Various Sleep Parameters with “Mobile-Related Sleep Risk Factors”</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daytime Sleepiness</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Disturbances</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Latency</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of Actual Sleeping</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Screen usage time (≥8 hours &lt;8 hours)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Correlation Coefficient=</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.052</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.054</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value=</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.161</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.170</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Using mobile for at least 30 minutes after the lights are turned off (without a blue light filter in mobile).<break/>(Yes, No)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Correlation Coefficient=</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.094</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.075</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.112</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.008</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value=</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.734</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Keeping the mobile near the pillow while sleeping.<break/>(Yes, No)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Correlation Coefficient=</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.083</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.094</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.065</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.023</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value=</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.317</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Putting mobile on airplane mode while sleeping.<break/>(Yes, No)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Correlation Coefficient=</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value=</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.496</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.655</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.948</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.650</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><bold>Note:</bold> P value &lt;0.05 is considered statistically significant.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Abbreviation:</bold> MRSRF, mobile-related sleep risk factors.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Our study showed a high prevalence and prolonged duration of mobile use in young adults. Average mobile screen usage time was 8.57±4.59/24 hours, and 38% of the participants reported of using mobile for more than 8/24 hours. Almost similar results have been demonstrated by other authors, Rideout et al and Strasburger found that school-aged children and adolescents spend almost a 7 hours/day in front of a screen.<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Moreover, a recent review of literature reported that one in every four children and young people are suffering from (PSU).<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></p>
      <p>Using Mobile after the lights have been turned off was reported by 88.7% of the subjects (average duration 38 minutes). About 75% of study participants of Munezawa et al reported of using mobile after lights out. Whereas a large study conducted on 90,000 young participants showed that only 17% of their subject use mobile after the lights have been turned off. This difference may be due to the reason that their study population included younger subjects from grades 7 to 12 only, who are under strict supervision of their parents as compared to the older adults.<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></p>
      <p>One supreme finding of this study was that using mobile for at least 30 minutes after the lights have been turned off (without a blue light filter in mobile) correlates with poor sleep quality, daytime sleepiness, sleep disturbances and increased sleep latency. A study on 844 Flemish subjects (18–94 years old) also revealed that using mobile after lights out negatively affects PSQI scores, sleep latency, sleep efficiency and causes more sleep disturbance and daytime dysfunction.<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> Almost similar results were reported by a Japanese study on younger subjects (aged 13 to 19 years).<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> But these studies did not mention the exact duration of mobile use; moreover, they have not specified that either or not their subjects were using a blue light filter mode on their mobiles. The data regarding the use of blue light filers on mobile screens are scarce, but our study indicated that only 4.4% of the subjects are using this filter. So we can assume that most of the participants in the above-mentioned studies were also using their mobiles without a blue light filter.</p>
      <p>Some recent studies have indicated that the blue light emitted by the mobile screens is the major culprit behind the PSQ in late night mobile users. As most of the mobile screens emit blue light in wave length between 400−495 nm and blue light in the range of 460–480 nm can cause a phase-shifting in human circadian clock by decreasing the production of melatonin.<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> Reduced melatonin levels have been linked to prolonged sleep latency and sleep disturbances.<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Moreover, exposure to blue light increases brain alertness and stimulates cognitive functions, resulting in PSQ.<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Our study findings were also supportive of the above-mentioned facts, we observed that participants who “used the mobile for at least 30 minutes after the lights have been turned off (without a blue light filter),” showed strong positive correlation with poor sleep quality, daytime sleepiness, sleep disturbances and increased sleep latency. Moreover, a comparative study of Mortazavi et al found that using amber blue light filter in the mobiles, significantly improves the sleep quality, but this study used a small sample size of 43 participants only.<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> We therefore recommend further case control and experimental studies with larger sample size to confirm these findings.</p>
      <p>In addition to the blue light effects of mobile screen, using mobile in pre bed time, ie, surfing the web, playing a game, seeing something exciting on facebook, or reading a negative email can also cause physical and psychological hyperexcitability contributing to hyper arousal state and PSQ.<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></p>
      <p>Another important finding of this study was that putting the mobile near pillow while sleeping caused increased sleep latency, sleep disturbances and daytime sleepiness. These effects may be caused by; a continuous urge to see notifications and updates on the nearly placed phone,<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> disturbance created by the vibrations from receiving notifications and messages, heat generated by charging phones and RF-EMF exposure from the mobile phone. RF-EMF exposure can cause changes in EEG during REM and non-REM sleep.<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>–<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> During the sleep time, when the mobile phones are not in use, they still emit RF-EMFs; however, the levels are much lower than that of a phone call. Moreover, the smart phones are constantly scanning for signals, text updates, emails, and software updates. Even notifications that we receive through apps require a certain level of radiation to be released.<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> These RF-EMFs can cross the skull and reach the brain<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> causing neuronal hyper-excitability resulting in various sleep problems.<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> The above-mentioned findings may be the underlying reason of the sleep problems (daytime sleepiness, sleep disturbances and increased sleep latency) seen in our study subjects who placed their mobiles near their pillows while sleeping. But further experimental and case control studies are required to confirm this causal relationship.</p>
      <p>To our knowledge, this is the first study which also aimed to find out the prevalence of MRSRF in mobile users. To our surprise, there was limited awareness about the possible hazardous effects of the mobile phone on human health, especially on sleep. As 88.7% of the subjects mentioned that they used mobile for at least 30 minutes after the lights are turned off, blue light filter feature was used by only 4.2% of the participants. Only 19.7% of the subjects used airplane mode, whereas 70% kept the mobile near their pillow while sleeping. Although we consider smartphone use to be a source of PSQ, many adolescents mistakenly believe that these media facilitate them to sleep.<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> It is therefore strongly recommended that health authorities should conduct seminars and awareness sessions in schools, colleges and universities. And students should be educated about the “hazardous effects of mobile phone use on sleep” and should be encouraged to implement the safety practices to prevent these effects.</p>
      <p>This study incorporated a large sample size and showed a positive association between bedtime mobile use and poor sleep quality. It also provided an insight into the causal relationship between mobile use and poor sleep quality, ie, hazardous effects of RF-EMFs and blue light emitted from the mobiles phones on sleep. But due to study limitations, and lack of objective measures we were not able to measure these effects directly. So we recommend further experimental and case control studies to probe the role of these causal factors, especially (RF-EMF and Blue light emitted from mobile screens), in causing poor sleep quality.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S0005">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>This study concludes that
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>“Using the mobile for at least 30 minutes (without blue light filter) after the lights have been turned off” results in poor sleep quality, daytime sleepiness, sleep disturbances and increased sleep latency.</p></list-item><list-item><p>“Keeping the mobile near the pillow while sleeping” positively correlates with daytime sleepiness, sleep disturbances and increased sleep latency.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Mobile-related sleep risk factors (MRSRF), ie, “using mobile before sleeping after the lights have been turned off, not using blue light filter, not using airplane mode, putting the mobile near the pillow while sleeping” were highly prevalent amongst the mobile users.</p></list-item></list></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgment</title>
      <p>The authors are thankful to Dr. Afzal Haq Asif, Dr. Faisal Fahad Essa Alousi, Dr. Hina Khan, Saira Saeed, and Dr. Samina Bashir for their help in data collection.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="S0006" sec-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CIT0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>LK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Can sleep deprivation studies explain why human adults sleep?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Opin Pulm Med</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>541</fpage>–<lpage>545</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MCP.0b013e3283596740</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22990662</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Webb</surname>
<given-names>WB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Friel</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Characteristics of “natural” long and short sleepers: a preliminary report</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Rep</italic></source>. <year>1970</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2466/pr0.1970.27.1.63</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5454124</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Curcio</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferrara</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Gennaro</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep loss, learning capacity and academic performance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>323</fpage>–<lpage>337</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2005.11.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16564189</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Davies</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ang</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Revell</surname>
<given-names>VL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of sleep deprivation on the human metabolome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>111</volume>:<fpage>10761</fpage>–<lpage>10766</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1402663111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25002497</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cappuccio</surname>
<given-names>FP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elia</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Strazzullo</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration and all-cause mortality: a systematic review and meta-analysis of prospective studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>585</fpage>–<lpage>592</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/33.5.585</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20469800</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Max</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaitlyn</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Steven</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>National Sleep Foundation’s sleep time duration recommendations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Health</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>01</volume>:<fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Owens</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Adolescent Sleep Working Group, Committee on Adolescence. Insufficient sleep in adolescents and young adults: an update on causes and consequences</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatrics</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>134</volume>:<fpage>921</fpage>–<lpage>932</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2014-1696</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dagmara</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frances</surname>
<given-names>LC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patrick</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The role of environmental factors on sleep patterns and school performance in adolescents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>01</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Duygu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bulent</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effect of mobile phone usage on sleep quality in adolescents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neuro Behav Sci</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sohn</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rees</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wildridge</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence of problematic smartphone usage and associated mental health outcomes amongst children and young people: a systematic review, meta-analysis and GRADE of the evidence</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>356</fpage>–<lpage>360</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12888-019-2350-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31779637</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Carter</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rees</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hale</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bhattacharjee</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paradkar</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between portable screen-based media device access or use and sleep outcomes: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Pediatr</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>170</volume>:<fpage>1202</fpage>–<lpage>1208</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapediatrics.2016.2341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27802500</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mireku</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barker</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mutz</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Night-time screen-based media device use and adolescents’ sleep and health-related quality of life</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Environ Int</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>124</volume>:<fpage>66</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2018.11.069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30640131</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Haug</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Castro</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kwon</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Smartphone use and smartphone addiction among young people in Switzerland</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Behav Addict</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>299</fpage>–<lpage>307</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1556/2006.4.2015.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26690625</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sahin</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ozdemir</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Unsal</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Evaluation of mobile phone addiction level and sleep quality in university students</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pak J Med Sci</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>913</fpage>–<lpage>918</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12669/pjms.294.3686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24353658</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shechter</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Onge</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Blocking nocturnal blue light for insomnia: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychiatr Res</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>196</fpage>–<lpage>202</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2017.10.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29101797</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aeschbach</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duffy</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Evening use of light-emitting e-Readers negatively affects sleep, circadian timing, and next-morning alertness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PNAS</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>112</volume>:<fpage>1232</fpage>–<lpage>1237</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1418490112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25535358</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lockley</surname>
<given-names>SW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gooley</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Circadian photoreception: spotlight on the brain</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Biol</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>795</fpage>–<lpage>799</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2006.08.039</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Daneault</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hébert</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Albouy</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Aging reduces the stimulating effect of blue light on cognitive brain functions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.3314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24381372</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="data">Patel N. Cell phone radiations and its effects in public health - Comparative review study. <italic>MOJ Public Health</italic>. 2018;7(2):14–17. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15406/Mojph.2018.07.00197</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tattersall</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scott</surname>
<given-names>IR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wood</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of low intensity radiofrequency electromagnetic fields on electrical activity in rat hippocampal slices</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Res</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>904</volume>:<fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-8993(01)02434-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11516410</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Loughran</surname>
<given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wood</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barton</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The effect of electromagnetic fields emitted by mobile phones on human sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">NeuroReport</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1973</fpage>–<lpage>1976</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.wnr.0000186593.79705.3c</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16272890</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Borbely</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huber</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Graf</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Pulsed high-frequency electromagnetic field affects human sleep and sleep electroencephalogram</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurosci Lett</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>275</volume>:<fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-3940(99)00770-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10580711</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mann</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roschke</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of pulsed high-frequency electromagnetic fields on human sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neuropsychobiology</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000119247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8821374</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wagner</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roschke</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mann</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Human sleep under the influence of pulsed radiofrequency electromagnetic fields: a polysomnographic study using standardized conditions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Bioelectromagnetics</italic></source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>202</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1521-186X(1998)19:3&lt;199::AID-BEM8&gt;3.0.CO;2-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9554698</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>CF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monk</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The Pittsburgh sleep quality index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0165-1781(89)90047-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2748771</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Rideout</surname>
<given-names>VJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Foehr</surname>
<given-names>UG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roberts</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Generation M2. Media in the Lives of 8-To 18-Year-Olds</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Henry J Kaiser. Family Foundation</publisher-name>; <year>2010</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Strasburger</surname>
<given-names>VC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Children, adolescents, obesity, and the media</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatrics</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>128</volume>:<fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>208</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21708800</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Saling</surname>
<given-names>LL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haire</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Are you awake? Mobile phone use after lights out</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Comput Human Behav</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>101</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Munezawa</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaneita</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Osaki</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The association between use of mobile phones after lights out and sleep disturbances among Japanese adolescents: a nationwide cross-sectional survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>1013</fpage>–<lpage>1020</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/SLEEP.1152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21804663</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Exelmans</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vanden</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Bedtime mobile phone use and sleep in adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Soc Sci Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>148</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2015.11.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26688552</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lockley</surname>
<given-names>SW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brainard</surname>
<given-names>GC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Czeisler</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>High sensitivity of the human circadian melatonin rhythm to resetting by short wavelength light</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Endocrinol Metab</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>88</volume>:<fpage>502</fpage>–<lpage>505</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.2003-030570</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ruger</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hilaire</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brainard</surname>
<given-names>GC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Human phase response curve to a single 6.5 h pulse of short-wavelength light</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>591</volume>:<fpage>353</fpage>–<lpage>356</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2012.239046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23090946</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mortazavi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parhoodeh</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hosseini</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Blocking short-wavelength component of the visible light emitted by smartphones’ screens improves human sleep quality</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Biomed Phys Eng</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>375</fpage>–<lpage>380</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.31661/jbpe.v8i4Dec.647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30568927</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bosquillon</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Del</surname>
<given-names>VF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Delanaud</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of co-exposure to 900 MHz radiofrequency electromagnetic fields and high-level noise on sleep, weight, and food intake parameters in juvenile rats</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Environ Pollut</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>256</volume>:<fpage>113461</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2019.113461</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31706765</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Cell phone radio frequency radiation</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Final Report from Rat Studies</italic></source>. <publisher-name>National Toxicology Program, US Department of Health and Human Services</publisher-name>; <year>2018</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ferreri</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Curcio</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pasqualetti</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Mobile phone emissions and human brain excitability</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>188</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ana.20906</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16802289</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Eggermont</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Nodding off or switching off? The use of popular media as a sleep aid in secondary-school children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Paediatr Child Health</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>428</fpage>–<lpage>433</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1754.2006.00892.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16898880</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
