<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33162761</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7643769</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">258471</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S258471</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Glasgow Sleep Effort Scale: Translation, Test, and Evaluation of Psychometric Properties of the Persian Version</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Doos Ali Vand et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Doos Ali Vand et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1814-979X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Doos Ali Vand</surname>
            <given-names>Hoda</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ahmadian Vargahan</surname>
            <given-names>Fahimeh</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Charkhabi</surname>
            <given-names>Morteza</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0003">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0004">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sadeghniiat Haghighi</surname>
            <given-names>Khosro</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0005">
            <sup>5</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1468-6029</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Dutheil</surname>
            <given-names>Frederic</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0006">
            <sup>6</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Habibi</surname>
            <given-names>Mojtaba</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0007">
            <sup>7</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0008">
            <sup>8</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label>Department of Clinical Psychology, <institution>School of Medicine, Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Tehran</addr-line>, <country>Iran</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>School of Behavioral Sciences and Mental Health (Tehran Institute of Psychiatry), Iran University of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Tehran</addr-line>, <country>Iran</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>National Research University, Higher School of Economics</institution>, <addr-line>Moscow</addr-line>, <country>Russia</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label>Department of Psychology, <institution>University of Clermont Auvergne</institution>, <addr-line>Clermont-Ferrand</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label><institution>Occupational Sleep Research Center, Baharloo Hospital, Tehran University of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Tehran</addr-line>, <country>Iran</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0006"><label>6</label><institution>Université Clermont Auvergne, CNRS, LaPSCo, CHU Clermont-Ferrand</institution>, <addr-line>Clermont-Ferrand</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0007"><label>7</label><institution>Health Promotion Research Center, Iran University of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Tehran</addr-line>, <country>Iran</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0008"><label>8</label>Department of Health Psychology, <institution>School of Behavioral Sciences and Mental Health (Tehran Institute of Psychiatry), Iran University of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Tehran</addr-line>, <country>Iran</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Mojtaba Habibi<institution>Department of Health Psychology, School of Behavioral Sciences and Mental Health (Tehran Institute of Psychiatry), Iran University of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Mansouri St; Niayesh St; Sattarkhan Blvd, 1445613111</addr-line>, <addr-line>Tehran</addr-line><addr-line>14565/441</addr-line>, <country>Iran</country><phone>Tel +98-21- 66551655</phone><fax>Fax +98-21-66506853</fax> Email Habibi.m@iums.ac.ir</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2020</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2020</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>12</volume>
      <fpage>843</fpage>
      <lpage>854</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2020</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>31</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2020</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2020 Doos Ali Vand et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2020</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Doos Ali Vand et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p>The purpose of the current study is to translate, test and evaluate the psychometric properties of the Glasgow Sleep Effort Scale (GSES) in Persian language.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>Participants consisted of two samples: a clinical sample of 120 patients (58%) with insomnia disorder meeting DSM-5 criteria for insomnia and a non-clinical sample of 110 participants (42%) with normal sleep. Both samples completed the following measures: GSES, Pittsburg Sleep Quality Index, Insomnia Severity Index, Dysfunctional Beliefs and Attitudes about Sleep Scale-10, Pre Sleep Arousal Scale-cognitive subscale, Depression-Anxiety-Stress Scale-21 and sleep diary.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>Significant correlations were found between GSES and related measures in both groups. Principal component analysis indicated a single component accounted for 64.77% of total variance in the clinical group. Results of the fit estimates for the one-factor model were consistent with the previously specified fit criteria and adequately fitted the data in the non-clinical group. Statistical analyses showed that the GSES has acceptable internal consistency in terms of Cronbach’s Alpha in the clinical (0.75) and non-clinical (0.77) samples. Test–retest reliability for a 4-week interval was significant (r = 0.70). The cut-off point, sensitivity, and specificity of the scale were 6, 85% and 94.5%, respectively.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>The Persian translated and validated version of the GSES obtained adequate values in psychometric properties in both clinical and non-clinical samples and it can be used for research and clinical purposes in Iran.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>GSES</kwd>
        <kwd>insomnia</kwd>
        <kwd>sleep effort</kwd>
        <kwd>psychometric properties</kwd>
        <kwd>Persian scale</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
            <institution-wrap>
              <institution>the Occupational Sleep Research Center of the Baharloo Hospital at Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran</institution>
            </institution-wrap>
          </funding-source>
        </award-group>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="1"/>
        <table-count count="6"/>
        <ref-count count="57"/>
        <page-count count="12"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Insomnia is defined as a predominant complaint of dissatisfaction with sleep quantity or quality accompanied with considerable distress or impairment.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Studies show that insomnia is not a context-specific issue and it has been widely recognized as a public health problem in the UK,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> U.S,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Australia,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Africa,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> and Asia.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Most relevant studies on insomnia have been conducted in western countries and little is known about the epidemiology of insomnia as a disorder in eastern countries such as Iran. The current statistics show that the number of individuals with poor sleep quality is growing in Iran.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>–<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> There is a need for greater research attention for the implementation of psychological and medical services to these patients.</p>
      <p>Prior studies have demonstrated that sleep problems are coexisting with a wide range of psychiatric disorders.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Insomnia, as a sleep problem, has been associated with a variety of individual and work-related outcomes. At the individual level, it has been found to be associated with future episodes of anxiety and depression,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> medications and health care services<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> and suicidal ideation.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> At the workplace level, it has been found that individuals with insomnia are more likely to experience work-related accidents in comparison with individuals without insomnia.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Moreover, in spite of the psychiatric disorders, insomnia can detrimentally influence an individual’s quality of life.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> The effects of insomnia are not limited to the individual and workplace levels; they may even influence the performance of students in schools. For instance, a meta-analysis conducted by Dewald et al<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> showed that sleep quality, sleep duration, and sleepiness are negatively associated with school performance.</p>
      <p>The detrimental impacts of insomnia are not limited to western countries as they have also been reported in Iran. For example, a qualitative study on patients with chronic insomnia referred to the sleep disorders center in the Kermanshah, Iran, identified the following five subthemes: insomnia as an unpleasant experience, insomnia as a worrying experience, treatment-seeking behavior, a boring new daily routine and being overshadowed by depressed mood.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> Another cross-sectional study conducted in Iran found that poor sleep quality is associated with low academic performance in Iranian medical students.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> The negative outcomes associated with insomnia reveal that the effects of insomnia are detrimental and there is great need for it to be identified and measured by standard and appropriate psychological scales.</p>
      <p>There are several cognitive-behavioral models by which we can explain the maintenance of insomnia; however, each of them suggests various factors (i.e., physiological, cognitive, emotional and behavioral) that play a central role in the maintenance of insomnia.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Espie, Broomfield, MacMahon, Macphee, and Taylor<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> studied psychophysiological insomnia through the attention-intention-effort pathway. They studied three essential processes including selective attention to sleep-related cues, explicit intention (an attention for action mechanism) and sleep effort that impede sleep-wake automaticity. Sleep effort, a central factor in the maintenance of insomnia, was introduced as a multicomponent construct, including cognitive (e.g., “I must sleep” schema) and behavioral (e.g., performance effort) elements.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Sleep effort itself involves two related processes: direct effort (e.g., vigorously attempt to fall asleep) and indirect effort (e.g., expand sleep opportunity).<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></p>
      <p>Previous research demonstrated that in patients with mood and anxiety disorders, the sleep effort is negatively related to quality of sleep, even after controlling for other factors (e.g., trait vulnerabilities for emotional disorders).<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> This suggests the notion that the role of sleep effort in sleep disturbances which occurred in the context of emotional disorders is more than vulnerabilities caused merely by those disorders.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> In addition, sleep effort is one of the basic mechanisms that explains differences in subjective and objective insomnia. For example, some studies show that the sleep effort is the predictor of severity of subjective insomnia, while dysfunctional beliefs about sleep are the predictor of objective insomnia.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> The available treatments to reduce the sleep effort in patients with insomnia show that patients who received paradoxical intention therapy (e.g., deliberate practice of remaining awake) had lower sleep effort and performance anxiety in comparison with control group.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> This urges researchers to develop measures that can precisely identify the individuals with high sleep effort for treatment purposes. Therefore, a correct identification of sleep effort would facilitate the treatment procedure. In addition, it encourages researchers to develop new treatments for individuals with insomnia and new insomnia prevention programs for larger populations.</p>
      <p>The Glasgow Sleep Effort Scale (GSES) is a seven-item self-report scale developed by Broomfield and Espie.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> The GSES measures the core components of an overall model on persistent preoccupation with sleep.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Broomfield and Espie<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> state that although there are some instruments available to measure sleep effort, measuring sleep effort requires a specific instrument which detects this construct diagnostically. This is the main reason they developed the GSES.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Kohen and Espie<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> introduced GSES as one of the best instruments to differentiate insomniac patients from good sleepers.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></p>
      <p>The pilot version of the GSES was developed after a rigorous analysis of the existing instruments which led to a model of sleep effort, incorporating seven central components.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Although this version was used earlier in two separate studies,<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> the psychometric properties of this scale were not examined in detail. In the first validation study,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> the GSES was conducted on a sample of 89 patients diagnosed with insomnia based on the DSM-IV, and 102 of good sleepers. Internal consistency of the scale using Cronbach’s Alpha was 0.77 in patients. The GSES was statistically correlated with Dysfunctional Beliefs and Attitudes About Sleep Scale (DBAS) (r = 0.50, <italic>p</italic> = 0.0001) which represented its concurrent validity. The GSES also had good discriminant validity even after controlling for age, and it could differentiate good sleepers from insomniac patients. Results showed a cut-off point of 2 on the GSES could accurately detect 93.2% of insomniac patients and 87.3% of good sleepers. Factor analysis of the scale explored one factor which could explain 62.6% of the total variance of the scale.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Another research in a sample of Portuguese higher education students (n = 2995, age mean = 23.9) suggested the Cronbach’s Alpha of 0.79. Factor analysis of the scale demonstrated one factor which explained 45% of total variance.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> However, both studies lack to report test-retest reliability of the GSES. In this study, we will cover this deficit by measuring and reporting the test-retest reliability of this scale in Iran.</p>
      <p>Although the psychometric properties of this scale have been studied in some other languages and countries,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> this scale has not been extensively tested, validated and used in non-western populations such as Asian and Middle Eastern countries. Therefore, the main aim of this study is to translate, test and evaluate the psychometric properties of the Glasgow Sleep Effort Scale (GSES) for the first time in Iran. Evaluating the psychometric properties of the GSES in Iran, using two clinical and non-clinical samples, we aim to provide more empirical evidence in support of this scale in eastern countries. In addition, as the previous studies have not reported the test-retest reliability of this scale; thus, testing and reporting the test-retest reliability of this scale is the second goal of this study. Additionally, this study will determine an appropriate cut-off that can respond to the sensitivity and specificity of the Persian version of the GSES based on DSM-5 criteria.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Participants and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p>This study included two clinical (n =120) and non-clinical (n = 110) samples. The clinical samples were recruited from the Sleep Disorders Clinic of the Baharloo Hospital located in Tehran, Iran from September 2017 to July 2018. Participants were included if they met the DSM-5 criteria (sleep initiation, sleep maintenance, or early morning awakening problems which occurs three times per week, lasting for at least three months and makes clinically significant distress) for insomnia disorder.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Individuals diagnosed by other sleep disorders (e.g., sleep apnea, restless leg syndrome), severe psychiatric disorders (such as bipolar disorder), substance abuse, and instable use of sleep or psychotropic medications were excluded. The non-clinical sample were good sleepers who were recruited from study announcements published at different locations. They met Research Diagnostic Criteria (RDC) for Normal Sleepers.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> Of the total sample that was primarily invited to participate, less than 20% (n = 19) refused to participate. Fifty-three percent of the clinical sample and 58% of the non-clinical sample were female. In the clinical sample, 37.4% of the sample identified their education level as diploma, 39.4% as bachelor, 20.6% as masters, and 2.6% as Ph.D. In the non-clinical sample, 41.2% of the sample identified their education level as diploma, 35.6% as bachelor, 19.8% as masters, and 3.4% as Ph.D. The clinical sample had an average age of 39.20 years (SD = 5.61, range: 18–71) and the non-clinical sample had an average age of 36.5 (SD = 4.82, range: 18–72). No significant difference (t = 1.58, df = 228, p =0.11) was found between clinical (M = 39.2, SD = 5.61) and non-clinical (M = 36.5, SD = 4.82) groups regarding age. Insomnia duration mean of the clinical sample was 8.42 years (SD = 7.41) with an age mean of 29.64 years (SD = 14.23). The average sleep onset latency (SOL), total time of awakenings after sleep onset (WASO), early morning awakening (EMA), total actual sleep time (TST), and total time spent in bed (TIB) as reported from the sleep diary were 97.31, 115.26, 48.61, 358.2, and 619.8 minutes, respectively. In addition, sleep efficiency of the clinical sample was 57.8%.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Measures</title>
        <sec id="s0002-s2002-s3001">
          <title>Glasgow Sleep Effort Scale (GSES)</title>
          <p>The GSES consists of seven items and was developed by Broomfield and Espie<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>. This scale assesses a present state of sleep effort. Responses are recorded on a 3-point Likert scale including not at all (0), to some extent (1), and very much (2). Higher scores indicate greater effort to sleep over the past week. Psychometric properties of this scale have been examined in insomniac patients and good sleepers.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Results showed that the GSES had adequate internal consistency (Cronbach’s Alpha = 0.77) and it can differentiate good sleepers from insomniac patients appropriately.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2002-s3002">
          <title>Dysfunctional Beliefs and Attitudes About Sleep Scale-10 (DBAS-10)</title>
          <p>The DBAS-10 scale assesses dysfunctional cognitions and beliefs about sleep and it was developed by Espie, Inglis, Harvey, and Tessier.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> Each item is rated from 0 to 10, with higher scores indicating stronger agreement with dysfunctional beliefs. Internal consistency of DBAS-10 in terms of Cronbach’s Alpha is 0.69 and it can differentiate insomniac patients from good sleepers. Factor analysis of DBAS-10 demonstrated three factors including: Beliefs about the immediate negative consequences of insomnia (5 items), beliefs about the long-term negative consequences of insomnia (3 items), and beliefs about the need for control over insomnia (2 items).<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> In an Iranian clinical sample (n =120), the test-retest reliability of DBAS-10 for 2-weeks’ interval was 0.83% and its internal consistency was 0.82.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2002-s3003">
          <title>Depression Anxiety Stress Scale (DASS-21)</title>
          <p>The DASS-21<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> is a short form of DASS-42<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> designed to measure symptoms of depression, anxiety and stress in adults. Respondents are asked to indicate the extent to which each of the statements is applied to them on a 4-point Likert scale ranging from never (1) to always (4).<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> This scale has demonstrated appropriate convergent, discriminant and construct validity.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> Additionally, a study conducted on an Iranian sample of college students (n = 638) reported a test-retest reliability of 0.81, 0.78 and 0.80 and Cronbach’s Alphas of 0.85, 0.75 and 0.87 for depression, anxiety and stress components of this scale, respectively.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2002-s3004">
          <title>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)</title>
          <p>The PSQI is a nineteen-item index consisting of seven components developed by Buysse et al.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> The components are subjective sleep quality, sleep latency, sleep duration, habitual sleep efficiency, sleep disturbances, use of sleep medication, and daytime dysfunction. Individuals rated each item on a 4-point scale from 0 to 3. Cronbach’s Alpha and test-retest reliability of this scale were reported as 0.83 and 0.85, respectively.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> This scale has been previously examined within an Iranian sample and the Cronbach’s Alpha was 0.52 for the patient group (n =125) and 0.78 for the control group (n = 133). Also, the sensitivity and specificity of the Persian version were reported 0.95 and 0.72, respectively.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2002-s3005">
          <title>Insomnia Severity Index (ISI)</title>
          <p>The ISI is a seven-item scale evaluating the nature, severity and impact of insomnia.<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> The items measure the severity of the following problems: falling sleep, staying asleep, waking up too early, satisfaction with sleep, noticeability of sleep problem, interference of sleep problems with daytime functioning, and distress caused by sleep problems. Total scores of this scale range from 0 to 28, with higher scores indicating a greater perception of insomnia. Cronbach’s Alpha of the scale in insomniac patients was 0.74. The scale consists of three components: Impact (3 items), severity (3 items), satisfaction (3 items).<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> Cronbach’s Alpha of this scale for a group of Iranian patients was 0.82 and its item-total correlation coefficient was reported from 0.56 to 0.91.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2002-s3006">
          <title>Pre-Sleep Arousal Scale (PSAS)</title>
          <p>The PSAS includes 16 items and it was developed by Nicassio, Mendlowitz, Fussell, and Petras<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> to assess both cognitive and somatic components of arousal. Participants are asked to rate each item from 1 (not at all) to 5 (extremely).<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> Test-retest reliability of the scale in a sample of college students (n = 30) has been reported as 0.72 and 0.76 for cognitive and somatic components, respectively. Also, Cronbach’s Alpha of the cognitive and somatic components were 0.67 and 0.84 for the normal sleepers and 0.76 and 0.81 for the insomniacs, respectively.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> Cronbach’s Alpha of the Persian version in a sample of college students was 0.72 for the somatic and 0.84 for the cognitive components. Test-retest reliability of the scale in a two week interval was 0.88.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0002-s2002-s3007">
          <title>Consensus Sleep Dairy (CSD)</title>
          <p>A sleep diary is a self-report scale about the pattern and quality of sleep over two weeks.<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> CSD has three versions known as core (includes a standard set of 9 items), expanded for the morning (includes optional morning completion items), and expanded for evening (includes optional morning and evening completion). It assesses the sleep onset latency (SOL), wakefulness after sleep onset (WASO), terminal WASO, total wake time, time in bed (TIB), and total sleep time (TST).<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> Validity, usability, and clinical utility of the scale have been previously studied.<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> The core version of the CSD was used in the current study.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Procedure</title>
        <p>The study was approved by the ethics committee at the Tehran University of Medical Sciences [Ethics code: IR.TUMS.REC.1396.2947]. All participants completed written informed consent before they took part in the study. They were informed that their participation in the study is completely voluntary. They could withdraw at any step without restriction. In addition, they were informed that only the research team will have access to the data for academic purposes and the data will be treated confidentially and anonymously.</p>
        <p>At first, the English version of the GSES was carefully translated into Persian by a group of specialists, including two psychiatrists, three sleep clinicians and two clinical psychologists. Then, the translated version was back-translated to English by two linguistics experts. Later a bilingual expert compared the back-translated and original versions of the scale and confirmed the back-translated version in Persian. In respect to wording, the Persian back-translated version was piloted with 30 Persian participants, who were asked to rate readability and clarity of the items on a response scale ranging from 0 (not understandable) to 5 (completely understandable). Over 95% of the participants chose the “completely understandable” which indicated no need for further item revision.</p>
        <p>The clinical sample included individuals who were seeking treatment at the sleep disorders clinic of the Baharloo Hospital in Tehran. The non-clinical sample were good sleepers who responded to the study announcements via e-mail. Regarding the clinical sample, those who volunteered were interviewed by a sleep medicine specialist to evaluate them based on the inclusion criteria. Then, the eligible participants were asked to complete a sleep diary for 2-weeks with the aim to evaluate if they have SOL or WASO for more than 30 minutes. After that, participants were referred to a clinical psychologist and were asked to complete the study measures. All participants were asked to respond to the following scales: CSD, DASS-21, DBAS-10, PSAS-C, PSQI and ISI.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>SPSS-21 IBM statistical package was used for statistical analysis. Cronbach’s Alpha and mean inter-item correlation coefficients were computed for GSES to assess the internal consistency. Given the number of correlations and comparisons, the p-values were adjusted based on Bonferroni procedure:<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> an initial α of 0.05 was divided by the number of measures. The factor structure of the GSES was evaluated by principal component analysis in the clinical sample.</p>
        <p>A confirmatory factor analysis was used to examine the one-factor structure of the GSES<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> in the non-clinical sample. We used LISREL version 8.8 <xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> to measure the extent to which data collected from the non-clinical sample was compatible with the aforementioned model in the literature.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Confirmatory factor analysis offers a variety of statistical tests and indices designed to assess the goodness-of-fit of identified models.<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>–<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> For this purpose, in the present study, the goodness-of-fit was evaluated using the following statistics: the goodness-of-fit index (GFI &gt;.9), the adjusted goodness-of-fit index (AGFI &gt;.90), the non-normal fit index (NNFI &gt; 0.90), the comparative fit index (CFI &gt; 0.90), the root mean square residual (RMSR &lt; 0.08), the normal chi-square (3 &gt; χ<sup>2</sup>/df &lt;2), the root mean square error of approximation (RMSEA) and its 90% confidence interval (&lt;0.05).<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>–<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> PRILIS software<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> was also applied to estimate the polychoric correlations and their Asymptotic Covariance Matrix (ACM) of the sample variance and covariance.</p>
        <p>To evaluate concurrent validity, the correlation coefficient between the GSES and DBAS-10, PSAS-C, DASS-21, ISI and PSQI were investigated. For the purpose of test-retest analysis, Pearson correlation coefficients were calculated using a subsample who were selected randomly from the clinical sample (n = 50) and completed the GSES twice in a 4-week interval.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>A number of steps composed of consistency, descriptive and graphical analysis checks (e.g., box plots, histograms, and scatter plots outlier detection) were conducted to screen the data. Data screening and the assumption of normality were examined which revealed a small skewness in items 3 and 6 of the GSES. Because of the non-normal sample distribution of some items, non-parametric statistics (Mann–Whitney <italic>U</italic>-test) were used at the item level, group mean (clinical vs non-clinical) and gender differences (male vs female). To make a decision regarding whether or not to keep outliers, the original mean and 5% trimmed mean (p &gt; 0.05) were compared. Excluding five cases as the outliers did not affect the major findings of the analysis; thus, the present results are reported including all of the data with the presence of the outliers. Data were analyzed with original data without removing outliers as along with powerful estimation of related statistical parameters.<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></p>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Factor Structure of GSES</title>
        <p>To evaluate the component structure of the GSES in the clinical sample, using principal components analysis,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> a single component model was extracted. Two criteria were considered regarding components extraction including the Kaiser criterion (eigenvalues &gt;1), and Cattell’s scree plot (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref>). Acceptable conditions for conducting principal component analysis, that are inter item correlation coefficients about or above 0.30; Kaiser–Meyer–Olkin measure of sampling adequacy = 0.90, above the recommended minimum value of 0.50; significant Bartlett’s test of sphericity; and χ<sup>2</sup>(21) = 941.63, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001 were found.<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref> Mainly, a single principal component was found (eigenvalue = 3.08), which explained 64.77% of total variance (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).<table-wrap id="t0001" orientation="landscape" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Factor Loadings, Means, Standard Deviations, Internal Consistency Coefficients of GSES in Clinical (n = 120) and Non-Clinical (n = 110) Samples</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Structure Coefficients</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Mean</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><italic>SD</italic></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Mean</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><italic>SD</italic></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Alpha Cronbach if Item Deleted</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Mann–Whitney <italic>U</italic></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Component I</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>H2</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-clinical</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-clinical</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-clinical</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Samples</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Item 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.79**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.72**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Item 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.24**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.35**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Item 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.95**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.836</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Item 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.74**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.68**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Item 5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.68**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.94**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Item 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.73**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.72</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Item 7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.15**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.91</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.89**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.26**</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes:</bold> *<italic>P</italic>&lt; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic>&lt; 0.01, H<sup>2</sup> = communality coefficient.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The scree plot of GSES displays the number of the factor versus its corresponding eigenvalue.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-12-843-g0001"/><attrib><bold>Note:</bold> When no rotation is done, the eigenvalues of the correlation matrix equal the variances of the factors.</attrib></fig></p>
        <p>Following the original scale<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, we constructed a one-factor model in which all 7 items were loaded on a single factor. Preliminary analysis of data showed that the normality was violated. As such, the generalized weighted least squares estimation method was used as the distribution of the data which was less sensitive to normality.<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></p>
        <p>We also tested the factorial structure of the scale using confirmatory factor analysis (CFA). The results of the fit estimates for the one-factor model meet the previously specified fit criteria and adequate fit to the data. The chi-square test results were significant for all models, but that is to be expected with models with large degrees of freedom and relatively large sample sizes.<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> An examination of the fit indices approved the parsimonious aspect of the model [S-B χ<sup>2</sup>/df = 1.80; CFI = 0.97; NNFI = 0.96; SRMR =0.086, GFI =0.94, AGFI =0.92 and RMSEA = 0.086 (CI) 90% = 0.025, 0.13].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Reliability, Concurrent and Discriminant Validity of GSES</title>
        <p>To measure the test-retest reliability, 50 participants (41% male, 34% single; mean age of 37.5 years old) were recruited randomly from the clinical sample. They completed the GSES twice within a 4-week interval. The correlation between the first and second administrations was statistically significant (r = 0.70, p &lt; 0.01) which indicates relatively temporal stability of the GSES.</p>
        <p>Cronbach’s Alpha of the scale was found 0.75 for the clinical sample and 0.77 for the non-clinical sample which indicates a good internal consistency.<xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref> The results in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> showed that the removal of any item did not increase the level of internal consistency. The minimum corrected item-total correlation was 0.22 in the clinical sample versus 0.35 in the non-clinical sample.<table-wrap id="t0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Correlation Matrix Between Research Variables in Clinical Sample (n = 120)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Items</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alpha</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSES</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DBAS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSAS-C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depression-DASS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anxiety-DASS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress-DASS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Note:</bold> **<italic>P</italic>&lt; 0.01.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
        <p>Mann–Whitney <italic>U</italic>-test as the non-parametric test was used to test the diagnostic validity of the GSES. The results in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> indicated statistically significant differences between the clinical and non-clinical samples in the GSES`s items, and the total score suggesting that the GSES significantly discriminated the clinical sample from the non-clinical sample.</p>
        <p><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> shows the correlation matrix between research variables, number of items of each scale and the Cronbach’s Alpha for the scales. As the table shows, the concurrent validity of the GSES was assessed by calculating Pearson’s correlations between all of the study’s measures. Statistically Significant correlations were found between total score of the GSES and DBAS-10 (r =0.45), PSAS-C (r = 0.48), depression-DASS (r = 0.30), anxiety-DASS (r = 0.31), stress-DASS (r = 0.34), ISI (r =0.46), and PSQI (r = 0.48) in clinical sample.</p>
        <p>Results of item-by-item Spearman correlation matrix of the GSES are also shown in <xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. This table includes the correlations between items for both clinical and non-clinical groups. As it can be seen in <xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, all correlation coefficients ranged from 0.13 to 0.51 in the clinical sample, and from 0.025 to 0.58 in the non-clinical sample.<table-wrap id="t0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Glasgow Sleep Effort Scale (GSES) Item-by-Item Spearman`s Rho Correlation Matrix in Clinical (n = 120) and Non-Clinical (n = 110) Samples</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSES<sub>1</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSES<sub>2</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSES<sub>3</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSES<sub>4</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSES<sub>5</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSES<sub>6</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSES<sub>7</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSES<sub>1</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSES<sub>2</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSES<sub>3</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSES<sub>4</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSES<sub>5</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSES<sub>6</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSES<sub>7</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes:</bold> *<italic>P</italic>&lt; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic>&lt; 0.01; correlations for the clinical sample are above and for the non-clinical sample are blow diagonal.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Sensitivity and Specificity of the GSES</title>
        <p>A ROC curve, indicating sensitivity (or true positive rate) and specificity (or true negative rate) of every possible cut-off score, was constructed.<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref> Youden’s index (0.79, CI=0.71-0.85, cut-off = 6, 95%, Confidence interval with bootstrap interval = 4–6) was applied to assess the optimal cut-off point (using this formula: sensitivity + specificity - 1.00).<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref> Sensitivity and specificity indices were computed for all the possible GSES cut-off scores. The GSES scores were analyzed to classify both clinical and non-clinical samples. GSES score ranges from 0 to 14. A GSES score of 6 or higher yielded a sensitivity of 85% and a specificity of 94.55%, highlighting that 5.45% of the non-clinical sample and 85.00% of the clinical sample exceeded the cut-off of 6. The area under the curve was 0.95 [(95% CI) = 0.91 to 0.97, p&lt;0.001]. <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=258471.docx">Appendix 1</ext-link></underline> illustrates the final version of the validated Persian items of the GSES.<table-wrap id="ut0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Appendix 1</label><caption><p>List of Original Items in English and Validated Items in Persian</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Original items of the GSES in English</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Validated items of the GSES in Persian</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I put too much effort into sleeping when it should come naturally</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">من هنگامی که باید به طور طبیعی به خواب روم، برای به خواب رفتن بسیار تلاش می‏کنم.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I feel I should be able to control my sleep</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">من احساس می‏کنم که باید توانایی کنترل خوابم را داشته باشم.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I put off going to bed at night for fear of not being able to sleep</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">از ترس ناتوانی برای به خواب رفتن، از رفتن به رختخواب طفره می‏روم.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I worry about not sleeping if I cannot sleep</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">هنگامی که در رختخواب باشم و نتوانم بخوابم، درباره به خواب نرفتن نگران می‏شوم.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I am no good at sleeping</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">من از نظر به خواب رفتن خوب نیستم.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I get anxious about sleeping before I go to bed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">من قبل از رفتن به رختخواب، درباره به خواب رفتن مضطرب می‏شوم.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I worry about the consequences of not sleeping</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">من درباره پیامدهای طولانی مدت به خواب نرفتن نگران هستم.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>This study translated, tested, and evaluated the psychometric properties of the Persian version of the GSES for both clinical and research purposes in Iran. The Persian validated version of the GSES provides a standard and reliable scale of sleep effort consistent with the recommendation of sleep experts in using more standardized assessments in sleep research.<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref> This validation contributes to the usability and the generalizability of this scale in both western and non-western countries. This is particularly important for non-western countries because it shows that regardless of the cultural differences between western and non-western countries, this scale is still useful for identifying relevant problems of sleep effort in eastern countries such as Iran. Moreover, it provides additional evidence for the adequate psychometric properties of this scale in non-western countries, which, can expand the generalizability of this scale for conducting joint research collaborations between Iran and other countries.</p>
      <p>To fulfill the first aim of this study, evaluating the factorial structure of the scale previously proposed by Broomfield and Espie,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> and Meia-Via et al,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Principal Component Analysis was used and it revealed a single component in the clinical sample matched with the original scale<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> and similar validation in a Portuguese sample.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Results of the confirmatory factor analysis using the non-clinical sample confirmed the unidimensional structure of the scale. This is consistent with two previous studies that found a single component accounting for 44.8%<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> and 62.6%<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> of the total variance, respectively. Thus, our results verified the same one-factor model proposed by two previous studies.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></p>
      <p>Additionally, the results suggested that the Persian version of the GSES has adequate internal consistency for the clinical (Cronbach’s Alpha =0.75) and non-clinical (Cronbach’s Alpha =0.77) samples. These findings are consistent with previous studies demonstrating good internal consistency of the GSES.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Notably, since no research has previously examined the test-retest reliability of the GSES, this study was the first attempt to report a high test-retest reliability (r = 0.70) of the GSES in a clinical sample. Totally, the Cronbach’s Alpha coefficients, and the test-retest coefficients both confirmed the reliability of the GSES Persian version.</p>
      <p>Concurrent validity of the Persian version of the GSES was supported by significant correlations between its total score and related measures, moving in expected directions that exist in the current literature.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Statistical analysis showed a significant but mild positive correlation between GSES and subscales of DASS-21, indicating that the GSES is not simply measuring depression, anxiety or stress. Moreover, a significant correlation was found between GSES and DBAS-10 and between GSES and PSAS-C, demonstrating the concurrent validity of the scale in relation to existing cognitive sleep measures. The significant observed correlations between GSES and two widely used sleep screening questionnaires (i.e., ISI and PSQI) revealed that sleep effort is related to the severity and quality of sleep. As the two previous studies<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> assessing the psychometric properties of GSES did not report the correlation between GSES and PSQI and ISI; no comparison can be made between these associations in the two previous studies and our study. However, in this study the results suggest that GSES and PSQI and ISI are statistically associated in the clinical sample. The current study also provided additional support for the ability of the GSES to discriminate individuals with insomnia disorder from individuals with normal sleep, verifying previous studies.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> A cut-off score of 6 correctly identified 85% of insomnia patients and 94.55% of good sleepers. We found a lower sensitivity and a higher specificity and cut-off point in our sample: This means that a higher level of sleep effort is needed to identify a person with significant sleep effort in an Iranian sample. These results make it possible to screen and identify patient groups according to their GSES scores and consequently target sleep effort in treatment protocols.</p>
      <p>The original study<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> showed that the GSES could discriminate between individuals with and without insomnia separated by DSM-IV criteria. Additionally, a Portuguese study<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> showed that the GSES was capable of distinguishing three subgroups (i.e., no sleep problems, insomnia symptoms, and other sleep problems) based on a self-report measure. As our participants were diagnosed according to the DSM-5 criteria, the results of the present study demonstrated that the GSES is able to discriminate individuals with and without insomnia according to the DSM-5 criteria, which can be considered as another achievement of this study.</p>
      <sec id="s0004-s2001">
        <title>Suggestions and Limitations</title>
        <p>Although the present sample included individuals with different ages, it did not evaluate the outcomes across the life span. Therefore, it is not specified if the results hold up in older or younger age groups. Thus, it is important to replicate the current study in different age groups, various settings and, especially with larger sample sizes. In addition, our clinical sample did not consist of the participants diagnosed based on structured diagnostic interviews of sleep disorders. This was due to no structured interview of sleep disorders having been validated in the Persian language. Future studies may design or validate versions of these interviews to fill this gap. The current study was conducted using self-report measures. This may distort the relations among research variables by shared method variance and the participants may be prone to under- or over-estimation of their symptoms. In addition, an examination of the relations between the GSES and common objective measures (e.g., polysomnography and actigraphy) is suggested for future psychometric studies.</p>
        <p>Despite several limitations, the present study provides evidence for intercultural validity of the GSES. One of the unique strengths of the current study is that both clinical and non-clinical samples were matched regarding age and gender. This has been ignored in previous insomnia studies. Also, to increase the generalizability to real-world clinical samples, the participants were not excluded from the study if they were taking a stable dose of medication. Lastly, since the GSES can be used for the clinical assessment and change,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> the Persian version of the scale provides Iranian clinicians with a standardized and validated tool for screening insomniac patients and providing suggestions for suitable psychological treatments.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>The current study makes the first attempt to evaluate the psychometric properties of the GSES in a non-western country, using both clinical and non-clinical samples. This study revealed that the Persian version of the GSES is a valid and reliable instrument for application in Persian speaking populations. The cost-effective aspect of this scale reduces the burden on examiners to measure sleep effort of the participants in research activities. GSES can be used as a valid scale to assess one of the most important maintaining factors of insomnia. It is hoped that the validation of the Persian version will encourage Persian-speaking clinicians and researchers to use it during assessment and treatment of their patients with insomnia.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>The authors would like to sincerely thank all the individuals who participated in this study. Also, we would like to thank all the personnel of the Baharloo Hospitals who assisted us in conducting this study. Besides, we would like to sincerely thank our Canadian colleague, Laura Seidel, at the University of Ottawa who kindly edited the final version of this article.</p>
      <p>This study was partially supported by the Occupational Sleep Research Center of the Baharloo Hospital at Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran by grant number 27164. The funder had no role in the study design and collection, analysis, and interpretation of data and preparation of the manuscript.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Ethical Approval</title>
      <p>All procedures performed in studies involving human participants were in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007" sec-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>Mojtaba Habibi's researcher ID is: <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://publons.com/researcher/1908876/mojtaba-habibi-asgarabad/">L-1485-2018</ext-link></underline>. The authors declare no other conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><source>American Psychiatric Association. Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders: DSM-5</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Psychiatric Association</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Morphy</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dunn</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lewis</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boardman</surname>
<given-names>HF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Croft</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Epidemiology of insomnia: a longitudinal study in a UK population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>274</fpage>–<lpage>280</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17425223</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>KF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yeung</surname>
<given-names>WF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ho</surname>
<given-names>FY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yung</surname>
<given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>YM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kwok</surname>
<given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cross-cultural and comparative epidemiology of insomnia: the diagnostic and statistical manual (DSM), international classification of diseases (ICD) and international classification of sleep disorders (ICSD)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>477</fpage>–<lpage>482</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2014.10.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25761665</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bramoweth</surname>
<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grieser</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tatum</surname>
<given-names>JI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roane</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Epidemiology of insomnia in college students: relationship with mental health, quality of life, and substance use difficulties</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Ther</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>339</fpage>–<lpage>348</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.beth.2012.12.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23768662</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Appleton</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gill</surname>
<given-names>TK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lang</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence and comorbidity of sleep conditions in Australian adults: 2016 Sleep Health Foundation national survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Health</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleh.2017.10.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29332673</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gureje</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oladeji</surname>
<given-names>BD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abiona</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Makanjuola</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Esan</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The natural history of insomnia in the Ibadan study of ageing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>965</fpage>–<lpage>973</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/SLEEP.1138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21731147</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y-M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>H-G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence of insomnia and its risk factors in older individuals: a community-based study in four cities of Hebei Province, China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>116</fpage>–<lpage>122</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2015.10.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27198956</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Asghari</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Farhadi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kamrava</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghalehbaghi</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nojomi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Subjective sleep quality in urban population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Iran Med</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22292580</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Malakouti</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Foroughan</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nojomi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghalebandi</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zandi</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep patterns, sleep disturbances and sleepiness in retired Iranian elders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Geriatr Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1201</fpage>–<lpage>1208</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/gps.2246</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19343736</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ahmadvand</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sepehrmanesh</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghoreishi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mousavi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalence of insomnia among 18 years old people and over in Kashan city, Iran in 2008. <italic>Feyz, Journal of Kashan University of Medical Science</italic></article-title>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>320</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ohayon</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia: a ticking clock for depression?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychiatr Res</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>893</fpage>–<lpage>894</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2007.07.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17709046</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ohayon</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Observation of the natural evolution of insomnia in the american general population cohort</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Clin</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsmc.2008.12.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20161295</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jansson-Frojmark</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lindblom</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A bidirectional relationship between anxiety and depression, and insomnia? A prospective study in the general population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychosom Res</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>443</fpage>–<lpage>449</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychores.2007.10.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18374745</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sivertsen</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krokstad</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Overland</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mykletun</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The epidemiology of insomnia: associations with physical and mental health. The HUNT-2 study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychosom Res</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychores.2009.05.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19616137</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McCall</surname>
<given-names>WV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blocker</surname>
<given-names>JN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>D’Agostino</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia severity is an indicator of suicidal ideation during a depression clinical trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>822</fpage>–<lpage>827</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2010.04.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20478741</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Léger</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guilleminault</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bader</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lévy</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paillard</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Medical and socio-professional impact of insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>621</fpage>–<lpage>625</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/25.6.621</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Katz</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McHorney</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The relationship between insomnia and health-related quality of life in patients with chronic illness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Family Practice</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>235</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dewald</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meijer</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oort</surname>
<given-names>FJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kerkhof</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bögels</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The influence of sleep quality, sleep duration and sleepiness on school performance in children and adolescents: a meta-analytic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>189</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2009.10.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20093054</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rezaie</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khazaie</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yazdani</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Exploration of the experience of living with chronic insomnia: a qualitative study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Sci</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>185</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28123657</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rasekhi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pour Ashouri</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pirouzan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of sleep quality on the academic performance of undergraduate medical students</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Health Scope</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e31641</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17795/jhealthscope-31641</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Broomfield</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Espie</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Towards a valid, reliable measure of sleep effort</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>401</fpage>–<lpage>407</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.2005.00481.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16364141</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Meia-Via</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marques</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Espie</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>da Silva</surname>
<given-names>CF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allen Gomes</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Psychometric properties of Glasgow Sleep Effort Scale in Portuguese language</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychological Assessment</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e12</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/pas0000178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26121385</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jansson</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Linton</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Psychological mechanisms in the maintenance of insomnia: arousal, distress, and sleep-related beliefs</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Res Ther</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>511</fpage>–<lpage>521</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brat.2006.04.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16759637</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Espie</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Broomfield</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>MacMahon</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macphee</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The attention-intention-effort pathway in the development of psychophysiologic insomnia: a theoretical review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>245</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2006.03.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16809056</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fairholme</surname>
<given-names>CP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Manber</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Safety behaviors and sleep effort predict sleep disturbance and fatigue in an outpatient sample with anxiety and depressive disorders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychosom Res</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>76</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>236</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychores.2014.01.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24529043</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hertenstein</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nissen</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Riemann</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feige</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baglioni</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spiegelhalder</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The exploratory power of sleep effort, dysfunctional beliefs and arousal for insomnia severity and polysomnography‐determined sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>399</fpage>–<lpage>406</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.12293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25773981</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Broomfield</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Espie</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Initial insomnia and paradoxical intention: an experimental investigation of putative mechanisms using subjective and actigraphic measurement of sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Cogn Psychother</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>324</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1352465803003060</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kohn</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Espie</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sensitivity and specificity of measures of the insomnia experience: a comparative study of psychophysiologic insomnia, insomnia associated with mental disorder and good sleepers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>104</fpage>–<lpage>112</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/28.1.104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15700726</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Edinger</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bonnet</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bootzin</surname>
<given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Derivation of research diagnostic criteria for insomnia: report of an American Academy of Sleep Medicine Work Group</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1567</fpage>–<lpage>1596</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/27.8.1567</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15683149</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Espie</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Inglis</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harvey</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tessier</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomniacs’ attributions. psychometric properties of the dysfunctional beliefs and attitudes about sleep scale and the sleep disturbance questionnaire</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychosom Res</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>148</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-3999(99)00090-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10719130</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Doos Ali Vand</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ahmadian Vargahan</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Birashk</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Habibi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sadeghniiat Haghighi</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fereidooni</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Validity and reliability of the dysfunctional beliefs and attitudes about sleep scale-10 in Iranian clinical population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Iran J Psychiatry Behav Sci</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e12288</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5812/ijpbs.12288</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Henry</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crawford</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The short-form version of the Depression Anxiety Stress Scales (DASS-21): construct validity and normative data in a large non-clinical sample</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">British J Clin Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>Pt 2</issue>):<fpage>227</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1348/014466505X29657</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lovibond</surname>
<given-names>PF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lovibond</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The structure of negative emotional states: comparison of the Depression Anxiety Stress Scales (DASS) with the beck depression and anxiety inventories</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Res Ther</italic></source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>343</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0005-7967(94)00075-U</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7726811</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Samani</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jokar</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Validity and reliability of short version of anxiety, depression, and stress scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Social Sci Humanities Shiraz University</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>CF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monk</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berman</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kupfer</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0165-1781(89)90047-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2748771</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Farrahi Moghaddam</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nakhaee</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sheibani</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garrusi</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amirkafi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Reliability and validity of the Persian version of the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI-P)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breathing</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-010-0478-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21614577</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Morin</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Insomnia, Psychological Assessment and Management</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>; <year>1993</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bastien</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vallieres</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morin</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Validation of the Insomnia Severity Index as an outcome measure for insomnia research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>307</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1389-9457(00)00065-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11438246</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yazdi</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sadeghniiat-Haghighi</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zohal</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elmizadeh</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Validity and reliability of the Iranian version of the insomnia severity index</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Malaysian J Med Sci</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nicassio</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mendlowitz</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fussell</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petras</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The phenomenology of the pre-sleep state: the development of the pre-sleep arousal scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Res Ther</italic></source>. <year>1985</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>271</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0005-7967(85)90004-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4004706</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Doos Ali Vand</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gharraee</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Asgharnejad</surname>
<given-names>FAA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghaleh</surname>
<given-names>BMF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prediction of insomnia severity based on cognitive, metacognitive, and emotional variables in college students</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Explore</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>240</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.explore.2014.04.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25037666</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Morin</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Espie</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Insomnia: A Clinical Guide to Assessment and Treatment</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>; <year>2004</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Carney</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ancoli-Israel</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The consensus sleep diary: standardizing prospective sleep self-monitoring</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>302</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.1642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22294820</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Maich</surname>
<given-names>KHG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lachowski</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carney</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Psychometric properties of the consensus sleep diary in those with insomnia disorder</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Tabachnick</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fidell</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Multivariate Analysis of Variance and Covariance In: Using Multivariate Statistics</italic></source>. <edition>(6th Edition)</edition>
<publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pearson</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year>:<fpage>272</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Jöreskog, K.G. &amp; Sörbom, D. (<year>2006</year>). LISREL 8.80 for Windows [Computer Software]. Lincolnwood, IL: Scientific Software International, Inc.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mulaik</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>James</surname>
<given-names>LR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Alstine</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bennett</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lind</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stilwell</surname>
<given-names>CD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Evaluation of goodness-of-fit indices for structural equation models</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Bull</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>105</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>430</fpage>–<lpage>445</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0033-2909.105.3.430</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cole</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Utility of confirmatory factor analysis in test validation research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Consulting Clin Psychology</italic></source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>584</fpage>–<lpage>594</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0022-006X.55.4.584</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Breckler</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Applications of covariance structure modeling in psychology: cause for concern?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Bull</italic></source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>107</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>260</fpage>–<lpage>273</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0033-2909.107.2.260</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2320704</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Pallant</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">SPSS Survival Manual: A Step by Step Guide to Data Analysis Using SPSS for Windows (Version 12)</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Australia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Allen &amp; Unwin</publisher-name>; <year>2005</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Field</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Discovering Statistics Using SPSS</italic></source>. <edition>(2nd edition)</edition>
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>; <year>2005</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Pallant</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">SPSS Survival Manual: A Step by Step Guide to Data Analysis Using SPSS for Windows</italic></source>. <edition>(3rd ed.)</edition>
<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Open University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2007</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bentler</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bonett</surname>
<given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Significance tests and goodness of fit in the analysis of covariance structures</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Bull</italic></source>. <year>1980</year>;<volume>88</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>588</fpage>–<lpage>606</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0033-2909.88.3.588</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Shi D, DiStefano C, McDaniel HL, Jiang Z. Examining chi-square test statistics under conditions of large model size and ordinal data. <italic>Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal</italic>
<year>2018</year>; 25:924–945.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0055">
        <label>55.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Nunnally</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychometric Theory</italic></source>. <edition>2nd</edition> ed. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name>; <year>1978</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0056">
        <label>56.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fawcett</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>An introduction to ROC analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pattern Recognit Lett</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>861</fpage>–<lpage>874</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.patrec.2005.10.010</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0057">
        <label>57.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ancoli-Israel</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Edinger</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lichstein</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morin</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Recommendations for a standard research assessment of insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1155</fpage>–<lpage>1173</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/29.9.1155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17040003</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
