<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34234598</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">8253893</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">312037</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S312037</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Review</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Burden of Sleep Disturbance During COVID-19 Pandemic: A Systematic Review</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Lin et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Lin et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>Ying Ni</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="ft0001">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6679-4136</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Zhuo Ran</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0003">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="ft0001">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7172-5725</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Shi Qi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="ft0001">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Chuan Xiang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0004">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3721-0071</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Liu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Ning</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>Xian Wen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Hong Peng</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhou</surname>
            <given-names>Jian Ping</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Qing Yun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine, Ruijin Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <addr-line>200025</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Institute of Respiratory Disease, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <addr-line>200025</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Thyroid and Vascular Surgery, Ruijin Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <addr-line>200025</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Wuhan No.3 Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Wuhan</addr-line>, <addr-line>430000</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Qing Yun Li <institution>Department of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine, Ruijin Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <addr-line>200025</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country><phone>Tel +81-21-64370045</phone> Email liqingyun68@hotmail.com</corresp>
        <fn id="ft0001">
          <label>*</label>
          <p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>13</volume>
      <fpage>933</fpage>
      <lpage>966</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>30</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2021 Lin et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Lin et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <p>Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic may exert adverse impacts on sleep among populations, which may raise awareness of the burden of sleep disturbance, and the demand of intervention strategies for different populations. We aimed to summarize the current evidence for the impacts of COVID-19 on sleep in patients with COVID-19, healthcare workers (HWs), and the general population. We searched PubMed and Embase for studies on the prevalence of sleep disturbance. Totally, 86 studies were included in the review, including 16 studies for COVID-19 patients, 34 studies for HWs, and 36 studies for the general population. The prevalence of sleep disturbance was 33.3%–84.7%, and 29.5–40% in hospitalized COVID-19 patients and discharged COVID-19 survivors, respectively. Physiologic and psychological traumatic effects of the infection may interact with environmental factors to increase the risk of sleep disturbance in COVID-19 patients. The prevalence of sleep disturbance was 18.4–84.7% in HWs, and the contributors mainly included high workloads and shift work, occupation-related factors, and psychological factors. The prevalence of sleep disturbance was 17.65–81% in the general population. Physiologic and social-psychological factors contributed to sleep disturbance of the general population during COVID-19 pandemic. In summary, the sleep disturbance was highly prevalent during COVID-19 pandemic. Specific health strategies should be implemented to tackle sleep disturbance.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>sleep disturbance</kwd>
        <kwd>COVID-19 pandemic</kwd>
        <kwd>SARS-CoV2</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="1"/>
        <table-count count="10"/>
        <ref-count count="125"/>
        <page-count count="34"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) is an infectious disease caused by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). COVID-19 outbreak, declared as a global pandemic by the World Health Organization (WHO) on March 11th 2020, has presented an unprecedented challenge to public health systems and caused global economic crises. The uncertainties and fears towards COVID-19, along with the societal consequences of mass lockdown, may lead to sleep disturbance and psychological burdens on a large number of individuals, including patients with COVID-19, healthcare workers (HWs), and the general public.</p>
      <p>Sleep plays an essential role on regulation of psychological and physical processes.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Poor sleep and sleep disturbance could interact with psychological and physical disorders to worsen health consequences among populations. Several studies have reported impacts of COVID-19 on sleep in specific populations.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2–4</xref> Sleep disorders may exert negative impacts on the process, prognosis, and rehabilitation of patients with COVID-19. Sleep disorders also affect the working ability of HWs. COVID-19-associated societal responses including home confinement, school suspension, and social isolation also increase the likelihood of sleep disturbance in the general public. However, risk factors for sleep disturbance and its associated health consequences still need to be addressed. Thus, we summarized the current evidence on the prevalence and associated factors of sleep disturbance in patients with COVID-19, HWs, and the general public. The increasing evidence addresses the necessity of awareness and interventions of sleep disturbance during and after COVID-19 pandemic.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Search Strategy</title>
        <p>Electronic searches were performed in PubMed and Embase, and were updated on Dec 10th, 2020. The following terms were used for the searches, ie (sleep) OR (sleep disturbance) OR (sleep disorders) OR (sleep problems) OR (insomnia) OR (sleep apnea) OR (sleep breathing disorders) AND (COVID-19) OR (SARS-CoV2). The reference lists of full articles were also searched for relevant publications. The searches were conducted, and the full-text articles were reviewed and analyzed by 2 independent researchers (Lin YN and Li SQ). In case of disagreement between the two reviewers, a third reviewer (Liu ZR) reviewed the articles and consensus among the three reviewers was reached.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Study Selection</title>
        <p>Studies were included if (1) the studies were cross-sectional, longitudinal, prospective, retrospective, or case-series in design; (2) the studies targeted populations including HWs, the general public, and COVID-19 patients; (3) the studies provided data of prevalence and/or risk factors of sleep disturbance; (4) the studies were written in English. Studies were excluded if (1) the full-text were unavailable; (2) studies were not written in English; (3) they were reviews, meta-analysis, conference abstracts, and protocols.</p>
        <p>We initially identified 1430 studies. After removing 498 duplicates, we screened the remaining 932 studies by reviewing the titles and abstracts. Totally 136 studies were assessed for eligibility, and finally 86 studies were included in the review (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref>).<fig id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Flowchart of literature selection.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-933-g0001"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Assessment of Study Quality</title>
        <p>Study quality was assessed using the Loney criteria through eight items including study design and sampling method, unbias sampling frame, sample size, appropriate measurement, unbiased measurement, response rate, estimates of prevalence, and description of study subjects.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Scores range from 0 to 8 points. A total score of 7–8 is considered as high quality, 4–6 as moderate quality, and 0–3 as low quality. The detailed quality assessment of the studies was shown in <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=312037.docx">Table S1</ext-link></underline>. Study quality was assessed independently by two researchers (Lin YN and Li SQ). In case of disagreement, a third reviewer (Liu ZR) reassessed the studies and consensus among the three reviewers was reached.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results and Discussion</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Sleep Disturbance in Patients with COVID-19</title>
        <sec id="s0003-s2001-s3001">
          <title>Hospitalized Patients</title>
          <p>The prevalence of sleep disturbance (ranging from 33.3% to 84.7%) in hospitalized COVID-19 patients was reported in 6 studies<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6–11</xref> (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). A retrospective study reviewed the psychiatric medical records of 329 COVID-19 patients, and showed 25.5% received psychiatric consultations, 33% of whom were diagnosed with sleep disorders (insomnia, early awakening, difficulty falling asleep), and 22.6% and 54.8% were prescribed benzodiazepines and non-benzodiazepine sedative-hypnotics (zolpidem), respectively.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> In an Italian university hospital, 49.51% of 103 hospitalized COVID-19 patients complained of sleep disturbance without any sex difference. It should be noticed that symptoms of sleep disturbance appeared immediately after the admission, and the frequency increased from 36.36% on the first 2 days to 69.23% after 7-day hospitalization,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> indicating that sleep disturbance in hospitalized COVID-19 patients cannot be simply explained by acute psychological response to the disease. Sleep disturbance was also found in mild patients even in mobile cabin hospitals, of whom more than two-thirds experienced insomnia on entry, but the overall insomnia levels (based on Insomnia Severity Index, ISI scores) were improved before discharge.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><table-wrap id="t0001" orientation="landscape" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of Studies Reporting the Prevalence of Sleep Disturbance in COVID-19 Patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Author</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study Period</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Design</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Participants</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (Mean, yrs)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male/Female (n)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Response Rate (%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Screening Tools</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cut-off Values</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prevalence</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk Factors</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quality Assessment Score</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zhang et al<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 5, to Mar 6, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">COVID-19 patients in mobile cabin hospitals (n = 30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15/15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI, a semi-structured interview</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.3% (22 in 30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hao et al<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 18, to Mar 26, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospitalized COVID-19 patients (n=10), psychiatric patients (n=10), healthy controls (n=10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI, a semi-structured interview</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dai et al<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 23, to Feb 26, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">COVID-19 patients in Fangcang shelter hospital (n=307)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">174/133</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI (Online)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liguori et al<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 30, to April 24 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A prospective study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospitalized COVID-19 patients (n = 103)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59/44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anamnestic interview</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.51%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yue et al<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jan 20, to Mar 8, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A retrospective study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospitalized COVID-19 patients (n = 329)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">171/158</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Review of electronic medical records</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.5% of all patients received psychiatric consultations, 33.3% of whom were diagnosed with sleep disorders</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iqbal et al<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qatar</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A retrospective study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">COVID-19 patients (n=50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48/2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Review of electronic medical records</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70% complained of sleep disturbance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: ISI, Insomnia Severity Index; PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
          <p>Sleep disturbance may be associated with the adverse health consequences of COVID-19 patients. Compared to those without sleep disturbance, COVID-19 patients who suffered from sleep disturbance for at least 2 weeks during hospitalization presented with a slower recovery from lymphopenia, an increase in the deterioration of neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio. They also had a higher incidence of hospital-acquired infection, longer hospitalization, and an increased need for ICU care than those without sleep disturbance.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> The findings indicated the negative impacts of a sustained period of sleep disturbance on the delay in recovery of immune dysfunction in COVID-19 patients.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2001-s3002">
          <title>Discharged Patients</title>
          <p>Sleep disturbance continued to bother 29.5–40% of COVID-19 survivors during the early post-discharge period, as reported in 4 studies<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13–15</xref> (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Up to 29.5% of 370 Chinese survivors complained of sleep disturbance during a median time of 22 days after discharge.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> A comparable proportion of 734 COVID-19 survivors (30.6%) from Bangali reported insomnia, disturbance in sound sleep, and nightmares,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> while the prevalence (40%) was higher in an Italian study.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> A French study showed that 30.8% of COVID-19 survivors still suffered from sleep disturbance even 110 days after being discharged, with no difference between ward- and ICU patients,<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> highlighting the need for a long-term follow-up for sleep and rehabilitation consultants.<table-wrap id="t0002" orientation="landscape" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Characteristics of Studies Reporting the Prevalence of Sleep Disturbance in Post-Discharged COVID-19 Patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Author</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study Period</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Design</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Participants</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-Discharge Period (Median or Mean, d)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (Mean, yrs)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male/Female (n)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Loss to Follow-up (%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Screening Tools</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cut-off Values</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prevalence</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk Factors</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quality Assessment Score</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wu et al<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A case series</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-discharged COVID-19 patients (n=370)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">203/167</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Loss to follow up (25.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHQ-9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mazza et al<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apr 6 to June 9, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-discharged COVID-19 patients (n=402)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.80 </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">265/137</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHIIRS, an unstructured clinical interview</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥ 9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Akter et al<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apr1 to June 30, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bangladesh</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-discharged COVID-19 patients (n=734)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">558/176</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A phone questionnaire</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cannot sleep: 8.9%;<break/>Disturbance in sound sleep: 19.8%;<break/>Nightmare: 1.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Garrigues et al<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-discharged COVID-19 patients (n=120)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75/45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Loss to follow up (24.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A phone questionnaire</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: PHQ-9, Patient Health Questionnaire-9; WHIIRS, Women’s Health Initiative Insomnia Rating Scale.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2001-s3003">
          <title>Patients with Preexisting Sleep Disturbance</title>
          <p>Preexisting sleep disturbance might increase the susceptibility of COVID-19.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> A recent cross-sectional study showed that up to 60% of the patients reported sleep problems and had been taking sleeping pills over the past 12 months,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> indicating a high rate of preexisting sleep problems in COVID-19 patients and a possible role of poor sleep on the susceptibility of COVID-19. Cruz and colleagues have proposed a hypothesis that dysregulation of circadian rhythm and sleep may be associated with increased risk of SARS-CoV-2 infection and the severity of its clinical manifestations.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></p>
          <p>The preexisting obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) and obesity hypoventilation syndrome are common co-morbid diseases in COVID-19 patients. The prevalence of OSA in COVID-19 patients was reported in 6 studies<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19–24</xref> (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). In severe COVID-19 patients, the prevalence of OSA reached 21–28.6%.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> More recently, Perger and colleague conducted sleep tests in 44 COVID-19 patients, and identified 34% with OSA and 41% with central sleep apnea (CSA). Multivariate analysis revealed that higher BMI and higher obstructive AHI were associated with the need of ventilation support.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> COVID-19 patients with OSA are 1.58 times more likely to develop critical illness.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> The CORONADO study, which included 1317 hospitalized diabetic patients with COVID-19, also demonstrated that treated OSA prior to admission was associated with the increased risk of death on day 7 (adjusted OR 2.65).<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Thus, it is possible that OSA is not simply a co-morbidity, but could be a risk factor for poor outcomes in COVID-19 patients.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> The plausible mechanistic pathways by which OSA may have adverse effects on OSA COVID-19 patients have been summarized in a previous review.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><table-wrap id="t0003" orientation="landscape" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Characteristics of Studies Reporting the Prevalence of Sleep Apnea in COVID-19 Patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study Period</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Design</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Participants</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (Mean/Median, yrs)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male/Female (n)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prevalence of Sleep Apnea</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk Factors</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quality Assessment Score</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kragholm et al<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The end of Feb, to May 16, 2020.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Denmark</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A follow-up study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">COVID-19 patients (n=4842)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 for male, 52 for female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2281/2561</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4% in male, 1.2% in female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bhatraju et al<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 24 to Mar 9, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A case series study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Critically ill COVID-19 Patients (n=24)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15/9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arentz et al<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 20, to Mar 5, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A case series study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Critically ill COVID-19 Patients (n=21)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perger et al<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">April 8 to May 8th, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A case series study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">COVID-19 Patients (n=44)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI&lt;5: 51, 5≤AHI&lt;15: 62, 15≤AHI&lt;30: 70; AHI≥30: 72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29/15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34% with OSA, 41% with central sleep apnea (CSA)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Higher obstructive AHI were associated with the need of ventilation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gottlieb et al<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 4, to June 21, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A retrospective cohort study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">COVID‐19 patients (n=8673)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4045/4625 (Not specified 2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3% in all patients; 1.9% in non-hospitalized patients, 10.4% in hospitalized patients</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSA (OR = 1.58) was associated with the risk of critical illness.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cariou et al<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 10, to Mar 31, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A follow-up study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospitalized COVID-19 patients with diabetes (n = 1317)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">855/462</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1% of patients with treated OSA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treated OSA (adjusted OR = 2.8) was associated with the risk of death on day 7.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: AHI, Apnea Hypopnea Index; CSA, Central sleep apnea.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Factors Associated with Sleep Disturbance in COVID-19 Patients</title>
        <sec id="s0003-s2002-s3001">
          <title>Physiologic Factors</title>
          <sec id="s0003-s2002-s3001-s4001">
            <title>Neuronal System Injury</title>
            <p>The neuronal injury directly and indirectly caused by SARS-CoV-2 infection contributes to sleep disturbance in COVID-19 patients. SARS-CoV-2 could invade to the brain, possibly via the olfactory nerves or retrograde trans-synaptic dissemination from the lung to the medullary cardiorespiratory center.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> SARS-CoV-2 then rapidly spread to specific brain areas including thalamus and brain stem, which play essential roles in sleep control and respiratory regulation, respectively, and thereby increase the risks of abnormal sleep-wake behaviors and SDB. SARS-CoV-2 is also capable of causing secondary neuronal injury due to aberrant innate immune response, leading to chronic neurological sequelae that adversely affect sleep, emotion regulation, pain sensitivity, and energy.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> This indicates a possible long-lasting impact of COVID-19 on sleep. Additionally, the binding of SARS-CoV-2 to the ACE2-expressing endothelial cells together with hypercoagulation status may contribute to the increased risk of cerebrovascular events, which contribute to sleep disturbance including inversed sleep-wake cycle, sleep-disordered breathing (SDB), and increased paradoxical sleep.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="s0003-s2002-s3001-s4002">
            <title>Symptoms, Severity of COVID-19, and Medication</title>
            <p>Except for the neuronal pathology caused by the virus, the physical discomforts including cough, fever, pain, and dyspnea may also destroy sleep. Relief of symptoms help to improve sleep in COVID-19 patients. Jiang and colleagues showed that Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) scores were associated with subjective perception of the disease severity in COVID-19 patients.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> Yang and colleagues recently found that scores of PSQI were positively associated with severity of pneumonia, and improvement of PSQI scores were positively related to improvement from COVID-19.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> To be noted, adverse effects of medication, eg the use of corticosteroids, sedatives, beta-blocker, and nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAID) also create and exacerbate sleep problems in COVID-19 patients. Appropriate timing of medication, also called chronotherapy, should be taken into consideration to better fit patients’ circadian rhythms and to minimize the side effects of medication on sleep eg. the use of corticosteroids, sedatives, beta-blocker, and nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAID) also create and exacerbate sleep problems in COVID-19 patients. Appropriate timing of medication, also called chronotherapy, should be taken into consideration to better fit patients’ circadian rhythms and to minimize the side effects of medication on sleep.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2002-s3002">
          <title>Psychological Factors</title>
          <p>Sleep disturbance could also occur as the result of the psychologically traumatic effects of COVID-19. Two-week psychological intervention was able to improve PSQI scores, indicating a relationship between sleep disturbance and mental health in COVID-19 patients.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Studies have demonstrated a high prevalence of mental health disorders in hospitalized and discharged patients with COVID-19 due to the fear of the new fatal virus infection, uncertainty about disease progression, worries about physical disability, loneliness and social isolation.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Sleep is usually reciprocally associated with mental health. Sleep disturbance, and mental health disorders like depression, anxiety, and PTSD not only share symptoms, but also form a vicious cycle to deteriorate the prognosis in patients with COVID-19.Post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) not only share symptoms, but also form a vicious cycle to deteriorate the prognosis in patients with COVID-19.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0003-s2002-s3003">
          <title>Environmental Factors</title>
          <p>Environmental factors including noise, abnormal light exposure, patient care activities, diagnostic and treatment procedures contribute to the ICU-related sleep disturbance. A previous study has indicated an innegligible role of environmental factors on sleep disturbance in hospitalized patients with COVID-19,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> particularly for those critically ill patients. Sleep disturbance occurs frequently in ICU patients, presenting with decreased sleep efficiency, a shift toward light stages of sleep, increased arousals, and abnormal circadian rhythmicity.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></p>
          <p>Taken together, physiologic and psychological traumatic effects of the infection may interact with environmental factors to increase the risk of sleep disturbance in COVID-19 patients. However, several questions remain to be solved. How does sleep change during the acute infection of COVID-19 and what is the patho-physiological mechanism? What is the relationship between sleep disturbance and occurrence and prognosis of COVID-19? Does sleep interference improve the prognosis of COVID-19? Moreover, yet little is known about long-term impacts of COVID-19 on sleep. A recent meta-analysis demonstrated a decrease in the frequency of insomnia from 41.9% (95% CI, 22.5–50.5) during the acute illness to 12.1% (95% CI, 8.6–16.3) after a follow-up duration varying from 60 days to 12 years in patients admitted to hospital for SARS or MERS.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> In the case of COVID-19, further studies are warranted to illustrate how long sleep disturbance would last after rehabilitation, and to what extent sleep disturbance could be improved over time.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Sleep Disturbance in Healthcare Workers</title>
        <p>A total of 34 studies were included, with the subjective sleep quality being assessed by using self-reported questionnaires<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37–69</xref> (<xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). The prevalence of poor sleep quality in HWs during COVID-19 pandemic ranged from 18.4% to 84.7% based on scores of PSQI,<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37–47</xref> which were comparable to that before the pandemic.<xref rid="cit0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref> A longitudinal study showed worsened sleep quality in 116 doctors and 99 nurses after one-month during the early COVID-19 outbreak, with a percentage of HWs with PSQI &gt; 5 increasing from 61.9% to 69.3%.<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> The prevalence of sleep disturbance in HWs was generally higher than that in non-HWs or general population.<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53–55</xref> Insomnia is the most prominent symptom with a prevalence ranging from 23.6% to 68.3% based on ISI scores.<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48–55</xref>,<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,<xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59–62</xref> Moderate-to-severe insomnia with ISI≥15 presented in 6.78%-15%.<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50–52</xref>,<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,<xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,<xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,<xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,<xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref> Another two studies used AIS at a cut-off value of 6 showed 52.8% of nurses,<xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref> and 68.3% of physicians<xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref> suffered from insomnia.<table-wrap id="t0004" orientation="landscape" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Characteristics of Studies Reporting the Prevalence of Sleep Disturbance in HWs</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Author</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study Period</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Design</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Participants</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (Mean, yrs)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male/Female (n)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Response Rate (%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Screening Tools</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cut-off Values</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prevalence</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Factors Linked to Sleep Disturbance</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quality Assessment Score</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wang et al<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jan 30, to Feb 7, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HWs (n=123)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22/111</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Being an only child (OR = 3.4), exposure to COVID-19 patients (OR = 2.97), and depression (OR = 2.83)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tu et al<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 7, to 25, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frontline nurse (n=100)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depression symptoms (OR = 3.16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cheng et al<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 9 to 13, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pediatric HWs (n=534)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94/440</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI scores positively correlated with the anxiety.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qi et al<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FHWs (n=801), NFHWs (n=505)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256/1050</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI; AIS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.7%<break/>(78.4% for FHWs and 61.0% for NFHWs)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zhou et al<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 21 to 23, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FHWs (n= 1931)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88/1843</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Older age (OR=1.043), being nurse (OR=3.132), being working in outer emergency medical team (OR=1.755), being familiar with crisis response knowledge (OR=0.70)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wu et al<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HWs at the designated hospital (n=60), HWs at the non-designated hospital (n=60)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31/89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% in HWs at the designated hospital</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Herrero San Martin et al<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 1 to Apr 30, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HWs (n=100), non-HWs (n=70)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70/100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI, ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI:≥7;<break/>ISI:&gt;8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64% in HWs with PSQI ≥7; 44% with ISI&gt;8; 58% with parasomnias</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Being a shift worker (OR = 3.48).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zhao et al<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">First survey: Jan 18, 2020; Second survey: Feb 18, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A longitudinal study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Doctors (n=116), Nurses (n=99)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Doctors: 37.39; nurses: 34.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Doctors: 47/69; nurses: 4/95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.83%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increasing from 61.9% to 69.3% after one-month follow-up</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longer work times handling febrile patients, more years of work experience, and the use of online CBT were associated with lower PSQI scores.<break/>Subjective psychological stress related to COVID-19 was positively correlated with changes in total PSQI scores.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wang et al<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 4 to 9, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HWs (n=1514), non-HWs (n=487)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HWs:31; non-HWs:33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HWs: 193/294; non-HWs: 517/997</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Being NFHWs (OR = 2.07), being FHWs (OR = 2.33), burden of caring for the elderly or children (OR = 1.47), COVID-related bereavement (OR = 1.91), anxiety (OR = 2.98), and depression (OR = 2.96).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alnofaiey et al<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">May to Aug 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saudi Arabia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physicians (n=462)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">227/235</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Doctors aged 31–40 yrs, associate consultants and residents had higher prevalence of sleep disorders.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jahrami et al<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apr 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kingdom of Bahrain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FHWs (n=129), NFHWs (n=128)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77/180</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk factors for combined poor sleep quality and moderate-severe stress:<break/>Being female sex (OR = 2.03).<break/>Protective factors for combined poor sleep quality and moderate-severe stress: professional background (OR = 0.7).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Giardinoet al<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">June 5 to 25, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Argentina</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HWs (n=1059)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">287/770 (Non Binary: 2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI; ISI; SWIFT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI:≥5; ISI: ≥8; SWIFT (&gt; 12 for young adults; &gt; 9 for middle-aged adults)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.7% with PSQI≥5, and 73.7% with ISI≥8; 21.7% with fatigue/wakefulness problems.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living with adults &gt;10 (OR=1.63 for ISI), working in private sector (OR=1.56 for ISI), being physician (OR=4.87), contact with COVID-19 patients (OR=3.11 for ISI), sleep medication before lockdown (OR=92.0 for PSQI, OR=5.67 for ISI), sleep medication during lockdown (OR=67.0 for PSQI, OR=7.8 for ISI), gender (OR=6.4 for PSQI, OR=4.31 for ISI),</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cai et al<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">First survey (Peak period): Jan 29 to Feb 2, 2020; Second survey (Stable period): Feb 26 to Feb 28, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A longitudinal study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nurses (First survey, n=709; second survey, n=621)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peak period:25/684; Stable period:16/605</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.5% during outbreak, and 39.9% during stable period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fangcang shelter hospitals (OR=3.520), physical condition change worse (OR=1.445)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zhang et al<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 Jan to Feb 3, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional survey</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HWs (n=1563)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">492/1071</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">An education level of high school or below (OR = 2.69), currently working in an isolation unit (OR = 1.71), being worried about being infected (OR = 2.30), perceived lack of psychological support from news or social media (OR = 2.10), and being uncertain about effective disease control (OR = 3.30), being a doctor (OR = 0.44)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wang et al<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 2 to 3, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High-risk HWs (n=401), low-risk HWs (n=644)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">148/897</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.1% from the fever clinic, emergency department, ICU, and infectious disease departments, and 70.3% from the wards/auxiliary departments</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High-risk HW (OR = 1.6), less work experience (OR = 1.88).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lai et al<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jan 29 to Feb 3, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HWs (n=1257)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">293/964</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Working in the frontline (OR=2.97)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Que et al<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 16 to 23, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HWs (n=2285)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">707/1578</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.75%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drinking (OR=2.43), attention to negative information about the pandemic (OR=3.34), receiving negative feedback from families or friends who joined front-line work (OR=3.47), joining front-line work (OR=1.90) and unwilling to join front-line work if given a free choice (OR=3.39).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zhou et al<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 14 to Mar 29, 2020.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FHWs (n=606), general population (n=1099)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FHW: 35.77; general population:29.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FHWs: 114/492; general population:336/763</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daily working hours (OR=1.60), BMI (OR=1.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zhang et al<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 19 to Mar 6, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HWs (n = 927), non-HWs (n = 1255)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HWs: 249/678; non-HWs:532/723</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living in rural areas (OR= 2.18), being at risk of contact with COVID-19 patients in hospitals (OR, 2.53), having organic diseases (OR, 3.39)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liang et al<xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 14 to Mar 29, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FHWs (n=899), general population (n=1104)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FHWs: 168/731; general population:337/767</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.97% for FHWs in Hubei Province; 40.34% for FHW in other regions</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zhang et al<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">June 6 to 13, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HWs (n=642)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96/546</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.52% for HWs with probable PTSD, 40.16% for the non-PTSD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Florin et al<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apr 10 to 19, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Radiologists (n=1515)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">844/671</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The lack of sufficient protective equipment (OR= 1.7), increase of teleradiology activity (R=1.5), negative impact on education (OR=2.5), living with another HWs (OR=0.6), working in a public hospital (OR= 0.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jain et al<xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">May 12 to 22, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">India</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anaesthesiologists (n = 512)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">285/227</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Being 41–45 yrs (OR=2.641), unmarried (OR=1.184), being stress to COVID-19 (OR=2.014), increasing working hours (OR=3.157), GAD score ≥5 (OR=10.499), being 45–50 yrs (OR=0.506), being &gt;50 yrs (OR=0.797), being male (OR=0.758), being consultant (OR=0.504)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Almater et al<xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 28 to Apr 4, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saudi Arabia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ophthalmology physicians (n=107)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60/47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cai et al<xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 11 to 26, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A case-control study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FHWs (n=1173), NFHWs (n=1173)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FHWs:30.6; NFHWs:30.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FHWs:354/819; NFHWs:348/825</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.8% for FHWs, 29.1% for NFHWs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Working in the frontline (OR=1.96)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Khanal et al<xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apr 26 to May 12, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nepal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HWs (n=475)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">225/250</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stigma experience (OR=2.37), history of medication for mental health problems (OR=3.82), Janajati ethnic group (OR=1.74), less than 5 years’ work experience (OR=0.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Şahin et al<xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apr 23 to May 23, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Turkey</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HWs (n=939)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">319/620</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female (OR=1.48), a history of psychiatric illness (OR=2.37), taking the COVID-19 test (OR=1.45)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alshekaili et al<xref rid="cit0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apr 8 to 17, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oman</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FHWs (n=574), NFHWs (n=565)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FHWs:35.8; NFHWs:36.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FHWs:102/472; NFHWs:126/439</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FHWs was 1.5 times more likely to have insomnia than NFHWs.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rossi et al<xref rid="cit0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 27 to 31, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HWs (n=1379)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">315/1064</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.27%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Being nurses (OR=2.03) and health care assistants (OR=2.34), having a colleague deceased (OR=2.94)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zhan et al<xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 3 to 10, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nurse (n=1794)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54/1740</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AIS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Being female (<italic>β</italic>=0.04), more working experience (<italic>β</italic>=0.113), chronic diseases (<italic>β</italic>=−0.046), midday nap duration (<italic>β</italic>=−0.082), frequency of night shifts (<italic>β</italic>=−0.049), direct participation in the rescue of patients with COVID-19 (<italic>β</italic>=−0.112), negative experiences (<italic>β</italic>=−0.061), the degree of fear of COVID-19 (<italic>β</italic>=0.179), perceived stress (<italic>β</italic>=0.16), fatigue (<italic>β</italic>=0.379), professional psychological assistance (β=0.063).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abdulah et al<xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apr 9 to 24, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iraqi</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physicians (n=268)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">188/80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AIS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AIS score was positively associated with stress, and the duration of dealing with suspected/confirmed cases of COVID-19, and was negatively associated with age and experience.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mosheva et al<xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 19 to 22, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Israel</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physician (n=1106)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">564/542</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">An inventory of pandemic related stress factors</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep difficulties was associated with anxiety.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sharif et al<xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 countries</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neurosurgeons (n=357)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-Reporting Questionnaire-20 Items</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.8% reported “slept badly”.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bhargava et al<xref rid="cit0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apr 1 to 20, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 countries</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dermatologists (n=733)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-designed questionnaires</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30% with insomnia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: HWs, healthcare workers; FHWs, frontline healthcare workers; NFHWs, non-frontline healthcare workers; PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index; ISI, Insomnia Severity Index; AIS, Athens Insomnia Scale; ESS, Epworth Sleepiness Scale.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
        <p>Except for insomnia, symptoms of parasomnias including nightmares, sleepwalking, sleep terrors are more frequently reported in HWs than non-HWs.<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> Notably, Zhuo and colleagues carried out a study to investigate overnight sleep in 26 HW with insomnia using medical ring-shaped pulse oximeters, and showed that the incidence of comorbid moderate to severe sleep apnea in insomnia HW reached 38.5%, indicating a high comorbidity rate of sleep apnea and insomnia attributable to stress.HWs with insomnia using medical ring-shaped pulse oximeters, and showed that the incidence of comorbid moderate to severe sleep apnea in insomnia HWs reached 38.5%, indicating a high comorbidity rate of sleep apnea and insomnia attributable to stress.<xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></p>
        <sec id="s0003-s2003-s3001">
          <title>Factors Linked to Sleep Disturbance of HWs</title>
          <sec id="s0003-s2003-s3001-s4001">
            <title>High Workloads</title>
            <p>High daily workloads contribute to poor sleep in HWs. Increased working hours were associated higher risk of sleep disturbance.<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,<xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref> The intensity of physical activity during daily work was negatively associated with sleep duration, and was positively associated with the feeling of tiredness during the wake-up in the morning.<xref rid="cit0072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></p>
            <p>Being a shift worker has been reported to have 3.48 times likelihood to experience insomnia in the battle against COVID-19.<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> Irregular and prolonged work shifts disrupt homeostatic and circadian rhythms and cause disturbance of several hormones, including melatonin and cortisol, leading to insufficient or inadequate sleep. Shift work not only impairs daytime function, and increases the risk of critical errors in HWs at work,<xref rid="cit0073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref> but may also make HWs themselves more prone to COVID-19 infection.<xref rid="cit0074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,<xref rid="cit0075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref> A recent single-center, retrospective study showed that implementation of new night shift schedule, changing from a four-day cycle to only daytime work for doctors with emergency techniques and extensive first aid experience and a six-day cycle in other doctors and nurses, significantly decreased the mortality of critically ill patients with COVID-19.<xref rid="cit0076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref> Thus, more reasonable shift working schedules that allow for adequate rest for HWs and at the same time, ensure the continuity of treatments for patients, should be highly recommended during COVID-19 emergency status.<xref rid="cit0076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>,<xref rid="cit0077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref></p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="s0003-s2003-s3001-s4002">
            <title>Occupation-Related Factors</title>
            <p>Several occupation-related factors contribute to the increased risk of sleep disturbance in HWs. The frontline HWs who are engaged in direct diagnosis, treatment, and care of COVID-19 patients,<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48–52</xref>,<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,<xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,<xref rid="cit0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,<xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,<xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref> were more likely to experience sleep disturbance. Being a nurse is a risk factor for sleep disturbance (OR:1.48 to 3.132),<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref> while being a doctor was 0.44 times less likely to develop insomnia.<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> The results were consistent with a previous study showing lower scores on posttraumatic stress in doctors than in nurse during SARS outbreak.<xref rid="cit0078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref> However, being consultants and physicians, who took more responsibility on treating COVID-19 patients, were associated with sleep disturbance.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> The differences may be due to the fact that nurses are more likely to have more intense workloads, more frequent shift works, and more direct contacts with COVID-19 patients than doctors.<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> Education and working experience are also closely associated with sleep problems in HWs. HWs with lower education level,<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> less work experience,<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref> and poorer knowledge of crisis response,<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> and who were lack of sufficient protective equipment<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref> had higher probability of experiencing sleep problems.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="s0003-s2003-s3001-s4003">
            <title>Psychological Factors</title>
            <p>Psychological factors were associated with sleep disturbance in HWs, including psychological symptoms (ie depression and anxiety),<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37–39</xref>,<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,<xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref> COVID-19-related bereavement,<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="cit0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref> worries about the COVID-19 outbreak,<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref> being worried about being infected,<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> perceived lack of psychological support,<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> and preexisting psychological diseases or sleep medication.<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,<xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref> The relationship between sleep disturbance and COVID-19-related stress may be bidirectional. On one hand, the stress associated with high risk of the virus infection and high patient mortality, perceived physical isolation, the necessity for constant vigilance regarding infection control procedures, and concern about family members could cause anxiety, and depression,<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> and impair sleep quality. On the other hand, poor sleep may result in daytime fatigue, loss of interest, impairment of the daytime function, and increase the risk of critical errors at work,<xref rid="cit0073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref> which in turn, worsens psychological condition in HWs.</p>
            <p>Moreover, other factors including being female,<xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,<xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref> being aged 41–45 yrs,<xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref> being the only child,<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> having burden of caring for the elderly or children,<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> physical condition and medication history,<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,<xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref> being unmarried,<xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref> also contribute to sleep disturbance in HWs.</p>
            <p>Taken together, high workloads may interact with COVID-19-related stress to increase the risk of sleep disturbance in HWs. The majority of the included studies were cross-sectional surveys showing the prevalence of sleep disturbance in HWs during the pandemic. Only one longitudinal study reported a slight increase in the prevalence of sleep disturbance.<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> Further studies should be conducted to determine the prevalence of new-onset or worsened sleep disturbance during the pandemic. Additionally, the impacts of sleep disturbance on health being, life quality and working performance in HWs during and after the pandemic also need further investigation.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Sleep Disturbance in the General Public</title>
        <p>The prevalence of sleep disturbance in the general population during COVID-19 pandemic was reported in 36 studies,<xref rid="cit0079" ref-type="bibr">79–114</xref> ranging from 17.65% to 81%,<xref rid="cit0079" ref-type="bibr">79–86</xref> 24.66% to 86%,<xref rid="cit0087" ref-type="bibr">87–89</xref>–<xref rid="cit0093" ref-type="bibr">93–95</xref>–<xref rid="cit0096" ref-type="bibr">96</xref> and 30% to 56%,<xref rid="cit0100" ref-type="bibr">100–103</xref> based on scores of PSQI, ISI and AIS, respectively (<xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>), which were generally higher than that before the pandemic.<xref rid="cit0083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>,<xref rid="cit0115" ref-type="bibr">115</xref> However, the effects of COVID-19-related lockdown on the public sleep quality remain controversial. Data from Italian and Australian studies reported that approximately half of the participants experienced worsened sleep quality during the lockdown.<xref rid="cit0084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>,<xref rid="cit0085" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>,<xref rid="cit0107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>,<xref rid="cit0108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref> Similarly, a study in China showed more than one-third of the participants had increased impaired sleep quality.<xref rid="cit0091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref> Symptoms of sleep disturbance commonly overlapped with those of depression, anxiety and PTSD in the general public.<xref rid="cit0083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref> On the contrary, a longitudinal study in the United State showed that 47% had improved sleep with longer sleep duration, and only 29% had worsened sleep from baseline to lockdown.<xref rid="cit0116" ref-type="bibr">116</xref> Another multicenter study from 11 countries also showed a reduced prevalence of insomnia after 2-month lockdown.<xref rid="cit0110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref> The results may indicate societal resilience to the chronic threat of viral infection and the changes of daily life. The varied proportions of sleep disturbance and its changes among the countries may be, at least partially, explained by the difference in epidemic control policy and the public attitude towards COVID-19 crisis. Interestingly, Kocevska and colleagues found that 20% of pre-pandemic good sleepers experienced worsened sleep, while a quarter of participants with pre-pandemic clinical insomnia experienced an amelioration of insomnia during COVID-19 pandemic.<xref rid="cit0117" ref-type="bibr">117</xref> They argued that the effects of lockdown on sleep quality is not uniform, and emphasized the individual difference in response to COVID-19 crisis.<table-wrap id="t0005" orientation="landscape" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Characteristics of Studies Reporting the Prevalence of Sleep Disturbance in the General Public</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Author</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study Period</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Design</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Participants</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (Mean, yrs)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male/Female (n)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Response Rate (%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Screening Tools</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cut-off Values</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prevalence</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Factors Linked to Sleep Disturbance</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quality Assessment Score</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wang et al<xref rid="cit0079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 4 to 8, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 6437</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2824/3613</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.65%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">being older (OR = 1.42), being female (OR = 1.35), poor self-reported health status (OR = 5.59), believing COVID-19 had caused a high number of deaths (OR = 1.73), believing COVID-19 was not easy to cure (OR = 1.34), and regular exercise (OR = 0.77)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Huang et al<xref rid="cit0080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 3 to 17, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 7236</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3284/3952</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">being healthcare workers (OR = 1.32)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guo et al<xref rid="cit0081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 1 to 10, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 2441</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1162/1279</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Direct exposure to COVID-19 (OR = 1.70), perceived impact on livelihood (Relatively large, OR = 1.32; very large, OR = 1.25), emotion-focused coping (OR = 1.12).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zhao et al<xref rid="cit0082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">February 18 to 25, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 1630</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.38%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anxiety mediated the relationship between perceived stress and sleep quality.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Casagrande et al<xref rid="cit0083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 18 to Apr 2, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 2291</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">580/1708;<break/>Other:3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Being female (OR= 1.75), being unemployed (OR= 1.34), living in North Italy (OR= 1.24), being uncertain regarding COVID-19 exposure (OR= 1.21), knowing people that died because of COVID-19 (OR= 1.62).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellini et al<xref rid="cit0084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 24 to 28, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 1310</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">430/880</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased from 40.5% pre-lockdown to 52.4% post-lockdown</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor sleep quality was associated with subjective elongation of time (<italic>r</italic> = 0.33), and the increased use of digital media (<italic>r</italic> = 0.15).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Barrea et al<xref rid="cit0085" ref-type="bibr">85</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jan to Apr 30, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A retrospective study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 121</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43/78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased from 50.4% pre-quarantine to 81% post-quarantine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bigalke et al.<xref rid="cit0086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apr 25 to May 18, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 103</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42/61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI;<break/>ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSQI: &gt;5;<break/>ISI: &gt;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66% with a PSQI score &gt;5;<break/>47.6% with ISI &gt; 7;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Higher COVID-19 related anxiety was associated with higher ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Killgore et al<xref rid="cit0087" ref-type="bibr">87</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apr 9 to 10, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 1013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">466/567</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Worries over COVID-19 were correlated with insomnia (<italic>r</italic> = 0.37);<break/>Insomnia severity was associated with elevated suicidal ideation (<italic>r</italic> = 0.31).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wang et al<xref rid="cit0088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 10 to 17, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 19,372</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9307/10,065</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living in Hubei Province (OR = 2.376), no outside activity for 2 weeks (OR = 1.927), and age 35–49 years (OR = 1.262)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yu et al<xref rid="cit0089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apr 6 to 20, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 1138</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">391/747</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI; Questions on sleep quality, sleep initiation, and sleep duration; Brief Insomnia Questionnaire (BIQ)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insufficient store of masks (OR = 1.96), perceived high level of stress (OR=2.10), daily life interfered by COVID-19 (OR=1.55), tertiary education (OR=0.66)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shi et al<xref rid="cit0090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 28 to Mar 11, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 56,679</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27,149/29,530</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Being with confirmed or suspected COVID-19 (OR = 3.06), family members or friends of patients with COVID-19 (OR=1.62), potential occupational exposure risks to COVID-19 (OR = 1.60), being a close contact of a COVID-19 patient (OR=1.55), centralized quarantine or home quarantine experience (OR=1.63), Hubei resident (OR=1.2), being frontline workers (OR=1.06), being male (OR = 1.13), younger than 40 yrs (OR = 1.07), lower income (OR =1.10), history of chronic diseases (OR=1.53), history of psychiatric diseases (OR 1.70), being at work (OR = 0.87), being married (OR=0.76)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Li et al<xref rid="cit0091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 5 to 19, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 3637</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1346/2291</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased from 26.2% before COVID-19 outbreak to 33.7% during COVID-19 outbreak;<break/>13.6% developed new-onset insomnia; 12.5% had worsened insomnia symptoms</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Being female (OR = 1.52), mental illness (OR = 1.63), COVID-19–related stress (OR = 1.40), increased severity of anxiety (OR = 1.15), and depressive symptoms (OR = 1.28) and prolonged time in bed (&gt;60 minutes, OR = 1.30) during the outbreak.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Huang et al<xref rid="cit0093" ref-type="bibr">93</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 14 to Mar 29, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n=1172</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">360/812</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.66%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ren et al.<xref rid="cit0094" ref-type="bibr">94</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 14 to Mar 29, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 1172</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">360/812</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gualano et al<xref rid="cit0092" ref-type="bibr">92</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apr 19 to May 3, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 1515</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">511/973</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Being females (OR = 1.70), being with chronic conditions (OR = 1.67)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bartoszek et al<xref rid="cit0095" ref-type="bibr">95</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Two weeks after Apr 3 2020)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poland</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 471</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68/403</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marroquín et al<xref rid="cit0096" ref-type="bibr">96</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 26 to 28, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 435</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">230/202; Other:3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Being under a stay-at-home order was associated with higher depression, GAD symptoms, insomnia.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kokou-Kpolou et al<xref rid="cit0097" ref-type="bibr">97</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">May 3 to 16, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 556</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">136/420</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Being with undergraduate levels (OR = 2.59), those attending college (OR = 2.41), worries about the COVID-19 (OR = 1.39), pre-existing mental health illness (OR = 1.22).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rossi et al<xref rid="cit0098" ref-type="bibr">98</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 27 to Apr 6, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 18,147</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3653/14,207</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Being female (OR = 1.50), living in South Italy (OR = 1.41), having experienced a stressful life event due to COVID-19 (OR = 1.58), discontinued working activity (OR = 1.22), loved one being deceased (OR = 1.74), lower education (OR = 1.76), being homemakers (OR = 1.39), being unemployed (OR = 1.33), childhood trauma (OR =1.50), prior psychiatric disorders (OR = 1.76)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Salfi et al<xref rid="cit0099" ref-type="bibr">99</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">First survey: Mar 25 to 31, 2020; second survey: Apr 21 to 27, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A longitudinal study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">First survey: n =7107; second survey: n=2701</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">First survey: 32.37; second survey: 32.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">First survey: 1616/5491; second survey: 491/2210</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">For females: decreased from 13.12% pre-lockdown to 11.63% post-lockdown;<break/>For males: increased from 9.37% pre-lockdown to 12.02% post-lockdown</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fu et al<xref rid="cit0100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 18 to 28, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 1242</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">376/866</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AIS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Being female (OR = 1.36), bachelor’s degree and above (OR = 1.40), having high monthly income (CYN) (1000–5000, OR = 2.61; &gt;5000, OR = 2.14), with no physical exercise (OR = 1.85)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Voitsidis et al<xref rid="cit0101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apr 10 to 13, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greece</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 2363</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">563/1800</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AIS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">predicted insomnia was equal to 3.232 + 0.398 (JGLS) + 1.338 (PHQ-2) + 0.63 (IUS) + 0.178 (COVID-19 worry)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parlapani et al<xref rid="cit0103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greece</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 103</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40/63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AIS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Janati Idrissi et al<xref rid="cit0102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apr 1, to May 1, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Morocco</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 827</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">395/432</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AIS, ESS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AIS≥6, ESS≥11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.0% with insomnia and 9.9% with daytime sleepiness</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living in urban areas (OR = 2.09), having chronic diseases (OR = 2.14)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Li et al<sup>104</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apr 10 to 23, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 1970</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">650/1305; transgender: 15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5-point Likert scale questionnaire</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Worry about COVID-19 (OR = 1.04), academic/occupational interference by COVID-19 (OR = 1.12), impact of COVID-19 on social interaction (OR = 1.07), perceived social support (OR = 0.91), specific support against COVID-19 (OR = 0.92), self-reported physical health (OR = 0.80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Léger et al<sup>105</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apr 15 to 17, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 1005</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">items of the French Health Barometer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk factors for sleep problems with daytime impairment and/or sleeping drug use: being female (OR = 1.66), being unemployed before the lockdown (OR = 1.50), having financial difficulties due to the lockdown (OR = 1.85), exposure to media and screens (OR = 1.39).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ara et al<xref rid="cit0106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">May 12, 18, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bangladesh</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 1128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">622/506</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A self-reporting questionnaire</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.24%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aged 31–40 years (OR = 4.04), being female (OR = 1.56), working from home or taking online classes (OR = 1.34), losing a job (OR = 2.41), perception regarding the risk of getting infected (OR = 1.45), anxiety (OR = 1.42), and sleeping more at daytime (OR = 1.86).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stanton et al<xref rid="cit0107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apr 9 to 19, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 1491</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">484/999</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A self-reporting questionnaire</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.7% with negative changes, 8.6% with positive changes, and 50.7% with no changes in sleep quality</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk factors for negative changes in sleep: depression (OR = 1.19), anxiety (OR = 1.25), and stress (OR = 1.30).</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancello et al<xref rid="cit0108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apr 15 to May 4, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 490</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80/410</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A self-reporting questionnaire</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43% reported worsen sleep quality, 4% with a new-onset persistent insomnia, 43% unchanged, and 13% improved.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Goularte et al<sup>109</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">May 20 to July 14, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brazil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 1996</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">320/1676</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSM-5 Self-Rated Level 1 Cross-Cutting Symptom Measure</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Roitblat et al<xref rid="cit0110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">May 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 countries</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A prospective study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 14,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A sleep-wake patterns questionnaire; the simplified daily log, the expanded daily log, and phone/Skype/Zoom interviews</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decreased from 1.8% during the first 14-day period, to 0.5% after two months of stay-at-home</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ustun<xref rid="cit0111" ref-type="bibr">111</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 23 to Apr 3, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Turkey</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 1115</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">316/799</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A Personal Information Form</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.4% with sleep problems</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chakraborty et al<xref rid="cit0112" ref-type="bibr">112</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 29 to 31, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">India</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 507</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">382/125</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A 38-item self-designed questionnaire</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.1% with disturbed sleep-wake cycle</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hetkamp et al<xref rid="cit0113" ref-type="bibr">113</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 10 to Apr 30, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 16,245</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4695/11,500; other: 50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Item of PHQ-9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5% reported severe reduced sleep quality</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Roy et al<xref rid="cit0114" ref-type="bibr">114</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mar 22 to 24, 2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">India</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A cross-sectional study</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 662</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">323/339</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A self-reported questionnaire</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12% of had sleeping difficulty</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index; ISI, Insomnia Severity Index; AIS, Athens Insomnia Scale; ESS, Epworth Sleepiness Scale; JGLS, De Jong Gierveld Loneliness Scale; PHQ-2, Brief Patient Health Questionnaire 2; IUS, Intolerance to Uncertainty scale.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
        <sec id="s0003-s2004-s3001">
          <title>Factors Linked to Sleep Disturbance of General Public</title>
          <sec id="s0003-s2004-s3001-s4001">
            <title>Physiologic Factors</title>
            <p>The circadian rhythm may be altered due to reduced exposure to sunlight, reduced physical activity and changes in working schedule during COVID-19 lockdown. However, the impacts of circadian rhythm alteration on sleep and other health consequences are controversial. On one hand, reduced social jetlag (driven by delayed mid-sleep on weekdays), reduced social sleep restriction (driven by increased sleep duration on weekdays) and decreased sleep debt may harmonize sleep schedules throughout the week, and thereby may limit the decline in sleep quality during the lockdown.<xref rid="cit0118" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>,<xref rid="cit0119" ref-type="bibr">119</xref> On the other hand, later chronotype, manifested as delayed mid-sleep on weekdays, may be associated with increased risk of mood symptoms including depression,<xref rid="cit0120" ref-type="bibr">120</xref> which in turn, may worsen sleep quality.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="s0003-s2004-s3001-s4002">
            <title>Social-Psychological Factors</title>
            <p>The impacts of age on sleep during COVID-19 pandemic seem controversial. Two studies revealed that people aged more than 30 yrs are more likely to develop sleep disturbance during COVID-19 pandemic,<xref rid="cit0088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>,<xref rid="cit0106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref> consistent with previous studies showing that the prevalence increased with age.<xref rid="cit0121" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>,<xref rid="cit0122" ref-type="bibr">122</xref> The age-related deterioration in sleep may be attributable to not only the effects of aging on circadian pacemaker and sleep structure but also the increased working and social stress that older people may have during COVID-19 lockdown. On the contrary, data from The Coconel Group showed an increase in the prevalence of sleep disturbance in young people aged 18–34 yrs when compared with older ones.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Consistently, three cross-sectional studies reported an increase of sleep problems in college students from baseline to lockdown.<xref rid="cit0123" ref-type="bibr">123–125</xref> It could be explained by the increased sleep vulnerability to stress caused by dramatic changes in their daily life and studies due to home confinement, school suspension, and reduced outdoor activity during the COVID-19 lockdown. Therefore, it could be speculated that the effects of age on sleep during COVID-19 pandemic are complicated and inconclusive, and could be interfered by other social-psychological factors.</p>
            <p>Sex difference has been reported in the prevalence of sleep problems. Females seemed to be more prone to have sleep problems than males when facing COVID-19 crisis.<xref rid="cit0079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>,<xref rid="cit0083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>,<xref rid="cit0091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>,<xref rid="cit0092" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>,<xref rid="cit0098" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>,<xref rid="cit0100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>,<xref rid="cit0105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>,<xref rid="cit0106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref> However, a longitudinal study showed that although females generally scored higher in PSQI and ISI scores within the 4-week home confinement period, they reported a reduction in insomnia and other accompanied psychological symptoms, while males had an increase in PSQI and ISI scores, indicating a narrowed sex gap in sleep quality after a prolonged lockdown.<xref rid="cit0099" ref-type="bibr">99</xref></p>
            <p>Perceived COVID-19-related stress is another major contributor for sleep disturbance, possibly through a change in emotional state (eg, stress, depression and anxiety).<xref rid="cit0082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>,<xref rid="cit0086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>,<xref rid="cit0089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>,<xref rid="cit0091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>,<xref rid="cit0101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>,<xref rid="cit0107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref> Firstly, people who had direct or potential exposure to COVID-19<xref rid="cit0084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>,<xref rid="cit0086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>,<xref rid="cit0093" ref-type="bibr">93</xref> may be afraid of being infected and worry about being isolated and quarantined, all of which may exacerbate psychological distress and the accompanied symptoms of sleep disturbance. Secondly, post-traumatic stress due to the high mortality of COVID-19 and the unexpected death of someone close,<xref rid="cit0083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref> along with the loneliness due to social distancing or quarantine<xref rid="cit0090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>,<xref rid="cit0098" ref-type="bibr">98</xref> increased psychological burden, making people prone to PTSD and sleep disturbance. Thirdly, negative attitude towards COVID-19, such as worries about COVID-19, perceived high death risk, perceived difficulty in treatment of COVID-19, being negative about COVID-19 control and emotion-focused coping style, may provoke cognitive arousal and disturb poor sleep quality.<xref rid="cit0079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>,<xref rid="cit0081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>,<xref rid="cit0087" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>,<xref rid="cit0097" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>,<xref rid="cit0101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>,<xref rid="cit0104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>,<xref rid="cit0106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref> Fourthly, the more negative impacts do COVID-19 have on livelihood, the more likely do people develop sleep disturbance.<xref rid="cit0081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>,<xref rid="cit0083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>,<xref rid="cit0089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>,<xref rid="cit0098" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>,<xref rid="cit0104" ref-type="bibr">104–106</xref></p>
            <p>Additionally, geographical factors (eg, living in epicenters or in urban areas),<xref rid="cit0083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>,<xref rid="cit0088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>,<xref rid="cit0090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>,<xref rid="cit0102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref> education experience,<xref rid="cit0089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>,<xref rid="cit0097" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>,<xref rid="cit0098" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>,<xref rid="cit0100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref> marital status,<xref rid="cit0090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref> a history of chronic diseases or mental illnesses,<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,<xref rid="cit0079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>,<xref rid="cit0090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>,<xref rid="cit0092" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>,<xref rid="cit0097" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>,<xref rid="cit0098" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>,<xref rid="cit0102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref> and changes in daily life<xref rid="cit0084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>,<xref rid="cit0091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>,<xref rid="cit0100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>,<xref rid="cit0101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>,<xref rid="cit0105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>,<xref rid="cit0106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref> were also associated with sleep disturbance during COVID-19 pandemic.</p>
            <p>Taken together, sleep disturbance in the general public, which is greatly influenced by social-psychological factors, could be compromised by reduced social jetlag and social sleep restriction during the pandemic. However, sleep disturbance-associated health consequences in the general public still need further investigation.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Limitation</title>
      <p>There were several limitations in the review. Firstly, the majority of the included studies were cross-sectional design. More longitudinal studies are encouraged to determine the temporal changes of sleep disturbance during and after the pandemic. Secondly, the adoption of online surveys in most of the included studies limits the diagnosis of patterns of sleep disturbance and accurate assessment of disease severity. Thirdly, most of the included studies were descriptive. There is a lack of research to address the efficacy of targeted interventions including relaxation techniques, behavioral interventions, sleep medications by population on sleep disturbance and its associated health consequences. Fourthly, inclusion of studies in English only in the review may cause language bias.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>In summary, COVID-19 exerts adverse impacts on sleep and brings great burden among various groups of populations. Sleep disturbance, mental illnesses, and physiologic illnesses form a vicious cycle to worsen the prognosis in COVID-19 patients. High workforce, shift work and COVID-19-related stress could increase the risk of sleep disturbance of HWs. For the general public, sleep quality seems more sensitive to social-psychological factors. Therefore, specific health strategies by population should be implemented to tackle sleep disturbance.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgment</title>
      <p>This work was funded by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (founding no. 81700084, 81770084, 81570082, 81700085), National Key R&amp;D Program of China (2018YFC1311900), and Shanghai Key Discipline for Respiratory Disease (2017ZZ02014). Ying Ni Lin, Zhuo Ran Liu and Shi Qi Li are co-first authors.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006" sec-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zielinski</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McKenna</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCarley</surname>
<given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Functions and mechanisms of sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">AIMS Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3934/Neuroscience.2016.1.67</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28413828</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cappuccio</surname>
<given-names>FP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A systematic review of COVID-19 and obstructive sleep apnoea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>101382</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2020.101382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32980614</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Salazar de Pablo</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vaquerizo-Serrano</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Catalan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impact of coronavirus syndromes on physical and mental health of health care workers: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Affect Disord</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>275</volume>:<fpage>48</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2020.06.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32658823</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Alnofaiey</surname>
<given-names>YH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alshehri</surname>
<given-names>HA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alosaimi</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep disturbances among physicians during COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Res Notes</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>493</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13104-020-05341-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33087166</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Loney</surname>
<given-names>PL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chambers</surname>
<given-names>LW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bennett</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roberts</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stratford</surname>
<given-names>PW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Critical appraisal of the health research literature: prevalence or incidence of a health problem</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chronic Dis Can</italic></source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>170</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10029513</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Qin</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fan</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A psychological investigation of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) patients in mobile cabin hospitals in Wuhan</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Transl Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>941</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/atm-20-4907</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32953741</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dai</surname>
<given-names>LL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Anxiety and depressive symptoms among COVID-19 patients in Jianghan Fangcang Shelter Hospital in Wuhan, China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e0238416</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0238416</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32857826</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hao</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tam</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A quantitative and qualitative study on the neuropsychiatric sequelae of acutely ill COVID-19 inpatients in isolation facilities</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Transl Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>355</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41398-020-01039-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33077738</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liguori</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pierantozzi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spanetta</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Subjective neurological symptoms frequently occur in patients with SARS-CoV2 infection</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Behav Immun</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>88</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2020.05.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32416289</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yue</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ju</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>How psychiatrists coordinate treatment for COVID-19: a retrospective study and experience from China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Gen Psychiatr</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e100272</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gpsych-2020-100272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34192234</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Iqbal</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Al Abdulla</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Albrahim</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Latoo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haddad</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Psychiatric presentation of patients with acute SARS-CoV-2 infection: a retrospective review of 50 consecutive patients seen by a consultation-liaison psychiatry team</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BJPsych Open</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e109</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/bjo.2020.85</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32907692</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Poor-sleep is associated with slow recovery from lymphopenia and an increased need for ICU care in hospitalized patients with COVID-19: a retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Behav Immun</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>88</volume>:<fpage>50</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2020.05.075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32512133</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Mental health status and related influencing factors of COVID-19 survivors in Wuhan, China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Transl Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e52</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ctm2.52</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32508037</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mazza</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Lorenzo</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Conte</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Anxiety and depression in COVID-19 survivors: role of inflammatory and clinical predictors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Behav Immun</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>594</fpage>–<lpage>600</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2020.07.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32738287</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Garrigues</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Janvier</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kherabi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Post-discharge persistent symptoms and health-related quality of life after hospitalization for COVID-19</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Infect</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>81</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e4</fpage>–<lpage>e6</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2020.08.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32853602</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Akter</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mannan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mehedi</surname>
<given-names>HMH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Clinical characteristics and short term outcomes after recovery from COVID-19 in patients with and without diabetes in Bangladesh</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes Metab Syndr</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2031</fpage>–<lpage>2038</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dsx.2020.10.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33113469</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Meira</surname>
<given-names>ECM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miyazawa</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gozal</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Putative contributions of circadian clock and sleep in the context of SARS-CoV-2 infection</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Respir J</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Beck</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Léger</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fressard</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peretti-Watel</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Verger</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Covid-19 health crisis and lockdown associated with high level of sleep complaints and hypnotic uptake at the population level</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e13119</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.13119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32596936</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kragholm</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Andersen</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gerds</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, et al.. <article-title>Association between male sex and outcomes of Coronavirus disease 2019 (Covid-19) - a Danish nationwide, register-based study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cid/ciaa924</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bhatraju</surname>
<given-names>PK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghassemieh</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nichols</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Covid-19 in critically ill patients in the Seattle Region - Case Series</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>382</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):<fpage>2012</fpage>–<lpage>2022</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2004500</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32227758</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Arentz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yim</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Klaff</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Characteristics and outcomes of 21 critically ill patients with cOVID-19 in Washington State</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>323</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>1612</fpage>–<lpage>1614</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.4326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32191259</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Perger</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Soranna</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pengo</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meriggi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lombardi</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parati</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disordered breathing among hospitalized patients due to COVID-19</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gottlieb</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sansom</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frankenberger</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ward</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hota</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Clinical course and factors associated with hospitalization and critical illness among COVID-19 patients in Chicago, Illinois</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acad Emerg Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>963</fpage>–<lpage>973</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/acem.14104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32762106</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cariou</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hadjadj</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wargny</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Phenotypic characteristics and prognosis of inpatients with COVID-19 and diabetes: the CORONADO study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetologia</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1500</fpage>–<lpage>1515</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00125-020-05180-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32472191</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McSharry</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lam</surname>
<given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malhotra</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>OSA as a probable risk factor for severe COVID-19</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1649</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.8708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32713422</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McSharry</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malhotra</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Potential influences of obstructive sleep apnea and obesity on COVID-19 severity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1645</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.8538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32356516</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>YC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bai</surname>
<given-names>WZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hashikawa</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The neuroinvasive potential of SARS-CoV2 may play a role in the respiratory failure of COVID-19 patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Med Virol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>92</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>552</fpage>–<lpage>555</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmv.25728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32104915</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Najjar</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Najjar</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chong</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Central nervous system complications associated with SARS-CoV-2 infection: integrative concepts of pathophysiology and case reports</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neuroinflammation</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>231</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12974-020-01896-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32758257</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Moldofsky</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patcai</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Chronic widespread musculoskeletal pain, fatigue, depression and disordered sleep in chronic post-SARS syndrome; a case-controlled study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>37</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2377-11-37</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21435231</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vitti-Ruela</surname>
<given-names>BV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dokkedal-Silva</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosa</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tufik</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Andersen</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Possible sequelae in post-SARS-CoV-2 patients: effects on sleep and general health condition</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>2</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Culebras</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cerebrovascular disease and sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Neurol Neurosci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>164</fpage>–<lpage>169</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11910-004-0032-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14984690</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Psychological distress and sleep quality of COVID-19 patients in Wuhan, a lockdown city as the epicenter of COVID-19</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychiatr Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>136</volume>:<fpage>595</fpage>–<lpage>602</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2020.10.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33153759</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cao</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Social support and clinical improvement in COVID-19 positive patients in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nurs Outlook</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>830</fpage>–<lpage>837</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.outlook.2020.08.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32980152</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tan</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van Egmond</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Partinen</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lange</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benedict</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A narrative review of interventions for improving sleep and reducing circadian disruption in medical inpatients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>42</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2018.08.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30415906</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pisani</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Friese</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gehlbach</surname>
<given-names>BK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schwab</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weinhouse</surname>
<given-names>GL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep in the intensive care unit</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>191</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>731</fpage>–<lpage>738</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201411-2099CI</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25594808</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rogers</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chesney</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oliver</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Psychiatric and neuropsychiatric presentations associated with severe coronavirus infections: a systematic review and meta-analysis with comparison to the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>611</fpage>–<lpage>627</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2215-0366(20)30203-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32437679</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yao</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xiang</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disturbances among medical workers during the outbreak of COVID-2019</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Occup Med (Lond)</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>70</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>364</fpage>–<lpage>369</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/occmed/kqaa074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32372077</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tu</surname>
<given-names>ZH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep quality and mood symptoms in conscripted frontline nurse in Wuhan, China during COVID-19 outbreak: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Medicine (Baltimore)</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>26</issue>):<fpage>e20769</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000020769</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32590755</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>FF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhan</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Anxiety in Chinese pediatric medical staff during the outbreak of Coronavirus disease 2019: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Transl Pediatr</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>236</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/tp.2020.04.02</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32775241</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Qi</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>BZ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The evaluation of sleep disturbances for Chinese frontline medical workers under the outbreak of COVID-19</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.05.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32502844</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence and demographic correlates of poor sleep quality among frontline health professionals in Liaoning Province, China During the COVID-19 outbreak</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>520</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2020.00520</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32595534</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Analysis of psychological and sleep status and exercise rehabilitation of front-line clinical staff in the fight against COVID-19 in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Med Sci Monit Basic Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>e924085</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12659/MSMBR.924085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32389999</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Herrero San Martin</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parra Serrano</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Diaz Cambriles</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep characteristics in health workers exposed to the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>75</volume>:<fpage>388</fpage>–<lpage>394</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.08.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32950884</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Job-related factors associated with changes in sleep quality among healthcare workers screening for 2019 novel coronavirus infection: a longitudinal study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>75</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.07.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32853914</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xia</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep disturbance and psychological profiles of medical staff and non-medical staff during the early outbreak of COVID-19 in Hubei Province, China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>733</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2020.00733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32793014</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jahrami</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>BaHammam</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>AlGahtani</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The examination of sleep quality for frontline healthcare workers during the outbreak of COVID-19</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Giardino</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huck-Iriart</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Riddick</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garay</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The endless quarantine: the impact of the COVID-19 outbreak on healthcare workers after three months of mandatory social isolation in Argentina</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>16</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.09.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33059247</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cai</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cui</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Nurses endured high risks of psychological problems under the epidemic of COVID-19 in a longitudinal study in Wuhan China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychiatr Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>131</volume>:<fpage>132</fpage>–<lpage>137</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2020.09.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32971356</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Survey of insomnia and related social psychological factors among medical staff involved in the 2019 novel coronavirus disease outbreak</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>306</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2020.00306</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32346373</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The psychological impact of COVID-19 pandemic on medical staff in Guangdong, China: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lai</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Factors associated with mental health outcomes among health care workers exposed to Coronavirus disease 2019</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Netw Open</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e203976</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.3976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32202646</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Que</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deng</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Psychological impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on healthcare workers: a cross-sectional study in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Gen Psychiatr</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e100259</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gpsych-2020-100259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32596640</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The prevalence and risk factors of psychological disturbances of frontline medical staff in china under the COVID-19 epidemic: workload should be concerned</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Affect Disord</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>277</volume>:<fpage>510</fpage>–<lpage>514</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2020.08.059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32882508</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>WR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yin</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Mental health and psychosocial problems of medical health workers during the COVID-19 epidemic in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychother Psychosom</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>89</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>242</fpage>–<lpage>250</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000507639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32272480</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0055">
        <label>55.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mental health in frontline medical workers during the 2019 novel coronavirus disease epidemic in China: a comparison with the general population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<fpage>18</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph17186550</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0056">
        <label>56.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jing</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhan</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Posttraumatic stress disorder symptoms in healthcare workers after the peak of the COVID-19 outbreak: a survey of a large tertiary care hospital in Wuhan</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>294</volume>:<fpage>113541</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33128999</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0057">
        <label>57.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Florin</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pinar</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chavigny</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Socio-economic and psychological impact of the COVID-19 outbreak on private practice and public hospital radiologists</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Radiol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>132</volume>:<fpage>109285</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejrad.2020.109285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32957001</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0058">
        <label>58.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jain</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Singariya</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kamal</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jain</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Solanki</surname>
<given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>COVID-19 pandemic: psychological impact on anaesthesiologists</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Indian J Anaesth</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>774</fpage>–<lpage>783</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/ija.IJA_697_20</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33162572</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0059">
        <label>59.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Almater</surname>
<given-names>AI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tobaigy</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Younis</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alaqeel</surname>
<given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abouammoh</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effect of 2019 coronavirus pandemic on ophthalmologists practicing in Saudi Arabia: a psychological health assessment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Middle East Afr J Ophthalmol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/meajo.MEAJO_220_20</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32874039</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0060">
        <label>60.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cai</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The mental health of frontline and non-frontline medical workers during the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) outbreak in China: a case-control study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Affect Disord</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>275</volume>:<fpage>210</fpage>–<lpage>215</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2020.06.031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32734910</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0061">
        <label>61.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Khanal</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Devkota</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dahal</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paudel</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Joshi</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mental health impacts among health workers during COVID-19 in a low resource setting: a cross-sectional survey from Nepal</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Global Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>89</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12992-020-00621-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32977818</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0062">
        <label>62.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Şahin</surname>
<given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aker</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Şahin</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Karabekiroğlu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalence of depression, anxiety, distress and insomnia and related factors in healthcare workers during COVID-19 pandemic in Turkey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Community Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1168</fpage>–<lpage>1177</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10900-020-00921-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32915381</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0063">
        <label>63.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Alshekaili</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hassan</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Al Said</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Factors associated with mental health outcomes across healthcare settings in Oman during COVID-19: frontline versus non-frontline healthcare workers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ Open</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e042030</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2020-042030</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0064">
        <label>64.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rossi</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Socci</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pacitti</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Mental health outcomes among frontline and second-line health care workers during the Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic in Italy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Netw Open</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e2010185</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.10185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32463467</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0065">
        <label>65.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhan</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Factors associated with insomnia among Chinese front-line nurses fighting against COVID-19 in Wuhan: a cross-sectional survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Nurs Manag</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1525</fpage>–<lpage>1535</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jonm.13094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32657449</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0066">
        <label>66.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Abdulah</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Musa</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia and stress of physicians during COVID-19 outbreak</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Medicine: X</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>100017</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleepx.2020.100017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33860222</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0067">
        <label>67.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mosheva</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hertz-Palmor</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dorman Ilan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Anxiety, pandemic-related stress and resilience among physicians during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Depress Anxiety</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>965</fpage>–<lpage>971</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/da.23085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32789945</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0068">
        <label>68.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sharif</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amin</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hafiz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>COVID 19–depression and neurosurgeons</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">World Neurosurg</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>140</volume>:<fpage>e401</fpage>–<lpage>e410</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.wneu.2020.06.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32512242</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0069">
        <label>69.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bhargava</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sarkar</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kroumpouzos</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mental distress in dermatologists during COVID-19 pandemic: assessment and risk factors in a global, cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Dermatol Ther</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e14161</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32770716</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0070">
        <label>70.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Qiu</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>RQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>YL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xiao</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalence of sleep disturbances in Chinese healthcare professionals: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>258</fpage>–<lpage>266</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2019.01.047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31040078</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0071">
        <label>71.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhuo</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Stress and sleep: a survey based on wearable sleep trackers among medical and nursing staff in Wuhan during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Gen Psychiatr</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e100260</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32596641</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0072">
        <label>72.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Diomidous</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and motion disorders of physicians and nurses working in hospitals facing the pandemic of COVID 19</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Med Arch</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>74</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>210</fpage>–<lpage>215</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5455/medarh.2020.74.210-215</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32801438</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0073">
        <label>73.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ballesio</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lombardo</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lucidi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Violani</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Caring for the carers: advice for dealing with sleep problems of hospital staff during the COVID-19 outbreak</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e13096</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.13096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32515084</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0074">
        <label>74.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lim</surname>
<given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wambier</surname>
<given-names>CG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goren</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Are night shift workers at an increased risk for COVID-19?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Med Hypotheses</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>144</volume>:<fpage>110147</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mehy.2020.110147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32758906</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0075">
        <label>75.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rizza</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coppeta</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grelli</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>High body mass index and night shift work are associated with COVID-19 in health care workers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Endocrinol Invest</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0076">
        <label>76.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Improved night shift schedule related to the mortality of critically ill patients with Corona Virus disease 2019</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>75</volume>:<fpage>354</fpage>–<lpage>360</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.08.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32950880</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0077">
        <label>77.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep problems of healthcare workers in tertiary hospital and influencing factors identified through a multilevel analysis: a cross-sectional study in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ Open</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>e032239</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2019-032239</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0078">
        <label>78.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Phua</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>HK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tham</surname>
<given-names>KY</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Coping responses of emergency physicians and nurses to the 2003 severe acute respiratory syndrome outbreak</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acad Emerg Med</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>322</fpage>–<lpage>328</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1197/j.aem.2004.11.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15805323</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0079">
        <label>79.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gong</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep disturbances among Chinese residents during the Coronavirus disease 2019 outbreak and associated factors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.08.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32861011</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0080">
        <label>80.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Generalized anxiety disorder, depressive symptoms and sleep quality during COVID-19 outbreak in China: a web-based cross-sectional survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>288</volume>:<fpage>112954</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2020.112954</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32325383</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0081">
        <label>81.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>XL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>XH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van IJzendoorn</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Coping with COVID-19: exposure to COVID-19 and negative impact on livelihood predict elevated mental health problems in Chinese adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>11</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph17113857</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0082">
        <label>82.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lan</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Perceived stress and sleep quality among the non-diseased general public in China during the 2019 coronavirus disease: a moderated mediation model</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0083">
        <label>83.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Casagrande</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Favieri</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tambelli</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Forte</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The enemy who sealed the world: effects quarantine due to the COVID-19 on sleep quality, anxiety, and psychological distress in the Italian population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>75</volume>:<fpage>12</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.05.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32853913</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0084">
        <label>84.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cellini</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Canale</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mioni</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Costa</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Changes in sleep pattern, sense of time and digital media use during COVID-19 lockdown in Italy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e13074</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsr.13074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32410272</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0085">
        <label>85.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Barrea</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pugliese</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Framondi</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Does Sars-Cov-2 threaten our dreams? Effect of quarantine on sleep quality and body mass index</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Transl Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>318</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12967-020-02465-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32811530</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0086">
        <label>86.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bigalke</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Greenlund</surname>
<given-names>IM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carter</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sex differences in self-report anxiety and sleep quality during COVID-19 stay-at-home orders</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biol Sex Differ</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>56</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13293-020-00333-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33050941</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0087">
        <label>87.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Killgore</surname>
<given-names>WDS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cloonan</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fernandez</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grandner</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dailey</surname>
<given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Suicidal ideation during the COVID-19 pandemic: the role of insomnia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>290</volume>:<fpage>113134</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32505030</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0088">
        <label>88.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ding</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Psychological distress and sleep problems when people are under interpersonal isolation during an epidemic: a nationwide multicenter cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e77</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/j.eurpsy.2020.78</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32854786</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0089">
        <label>89.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>BY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yeung</surname>
<given-names>WF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lam</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence of sleep disturbances during COVID-19 outbreak in an urban Chinese population: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>18</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.07.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32836181</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0090">
        <label>90.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>ZA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Que</surname>
<given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence of and risk factors associated with mental health symptoms among the general population in china during the Coronavirus disease 2019 pandemic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Netw Open</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>e2014053</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.14053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32609353</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0091">
        <label>91.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Qin</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sanford</surname>
<given-names>LD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vgontzas</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia and psychological reactions during the COVID-19 outbreak in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1417</fpage>–<lpage>1418</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32351206</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0092">
        <label>92.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gualano</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lo Moro</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Voglino</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bert</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Siliquini</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of Covid-19 lockdown on mental health and sleep disturbances in Italy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>13</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph17134779</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0093">
        <label>93.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zeng</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence and correlation of anxiety, insomnia and somatic symptoms in a Chinese population during the COVID-19 epidemic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>568329</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2020.568329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33005165</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0094">
        <label>94.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ren</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Qian</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Public mental health under the long-term influence of COVID-19 in China: geographical and temporal distribution</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Affect Disord</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>277</volume>:<fpage>893</fpage>–<lpage>900</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2020.08.045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33065831</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0095">
        <label>95.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bartoszek</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Walkowiak</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bartoszek</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kardas</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mental well-being (Depression, Loneliness, Insomnia, Daily Life Fatigue) during COVID-19 related home-confinement-A Study from Poland</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>20</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph17207417</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0096">
        <label>96.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Marroquín</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vine</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morgan</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mental health during the COVID-19 pandemic: effects of stay-at-home policies, social distancing behavior, and social resources</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>293</volume>:<fpage>113419</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113419</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32861098</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0097">
        <label>97.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kokou-Kpolou</surname>
<given-names>CK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Megalakaki</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laimou</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kousouri</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Insomnia during COVID-19 pandemic and lockdown: prevalence, severity, and associated risk factors in French population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>290</volume>:<fpage>113128</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32563951</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0098">
        <label>98.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rossi</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Socci</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Talevi</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>COVID-19 pandemic and lockdown measures impact on mental health among the general population in Italy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>790</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2020.00790</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32848952</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0099">
        <label>99.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Salfi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lauriola</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amicucci</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Gender-related time course of sleep disturbances and psychological symptoms during the COVID-19 lockdown: a longitudinal study on the Italian population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurobiol Stress</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>100259</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ynstr.2020.100259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33102641</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0100">
        <label>100.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fu</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zou</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Psychological health, sleep quality, and coping styles to stress facing the COVID-19 in Wuhan, China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Transl Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>225</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41398-020-00913-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32647160</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0101">
        <label>101.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Voitsidis</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gliatas</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bairachtari</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Insomnia during the COVID-19 pandemic in a Greek population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>289</volume>:<fpage>113076</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113076</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0102">
        <label>102.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Janati Idrissi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lamkaddem</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benouajjit</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep quality and mental health in the context of COVID-19 pandemic and lockdown in Morocco</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>248</fpage>–<lpage>253</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.07.045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32862008</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0103">
        <label>103.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Parlapani</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holeva</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nikopoulou</surname>
<given-names>VA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Intolerance of uncertainty and loneliness in older adults during the COVID-19 Pandemic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>842</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2020.00842</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32973584</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0104">
        <label>104.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ko</surname>
<given-names>NY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>YL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>COVID-19-related factors associated with sleep disturbance and suicidal thoughts among the Taiwanese public: a Facebook Survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>12</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0105">
        <label>105.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Léger</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beck</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fressard</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Verger</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peretti-Watel</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Poor sleep associated with overuse of media during the COVID-19 lockdown</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>10</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsaa125</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0106">
        <label>106.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ara</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rahman</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hossain</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ahmed</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Identifying the associated risk factors of sleep disturbance during the COVID-19 lockdown in Bangladesh: a web-based survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>580268</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2020.580268</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33093839</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0107">
        <label>107.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stanton</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>To</surname>
<given-names>QG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khalesi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Depression, anxiety and stress during COVID-19: associations with changes in physical activity, sleep, tobacco and alcohol use in Australian adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>11</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph17114065</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0108">
        <label>108.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cancello</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Soranna</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zambra</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zambon</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Invitti</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Determinants of the lifestyle changes during COVID-19 pandemic in the residents of Northern Italy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>17</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph17176287</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0109">
        <label>109.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Goularte</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Serafim</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Colombo</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hogg</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caldieraro</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosa</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>COVID-19 and mental health in Brazil: psychiatric symptoms in the general population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychiatr Res</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>132</volume>:<fpage>32</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2020.09.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33038563</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0110">
        <label>110.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Roitblat</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burger</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leit</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Stay-at-home circumstances do not produce sleep disorders: an international survey during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychosom Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>139</volume>:<fpage>110282</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychores.2020.110282</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33130483</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0111">
        <label>111.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ustun</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Determining depression and related factors in a society affected by COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Soc Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<fpage>20764020938807</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0020764020938807</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0112">
        <label>112.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chakraborty</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chatterjee</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Psychological impact of COVID-19 pandemic on general population in West Bengal: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Indian J Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>62</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>266</fpage>–<lpage>272</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/psychiatry.IndianJPsychiatry_276_20</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32773869</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0113">
        <label>113.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hetkamp</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schweda</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bäuerle</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep disturbances, fear, and generalized anxiety during the COVID-19 shut down phase in Germany: relation to infection rates, deaths, and German stock index DAX</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>75</volume>:<fpage>350</fpage>–<lpage>353</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.08.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32950879</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0114">
        <label>114.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Roy</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tripathy</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kar</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sharma</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Verma</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaushal</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Study of knowledge, attitude, anxiety &amp; perceived mental healthcare need in Indian population during COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Asian J Psychiatr</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>102083</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajp.2020.102083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32283510</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0115">
        <label>115.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cao</surname>
<given-names>XL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhong</surname>
<given-names>BL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The prevalence of insomnia in the general population in China: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e0170772</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0170772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28234940</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0116">
        <label>116.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scullin</surname>
<given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep health early in the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) outbreak in the United States: integrating longitudinal, cross-sectional, and retrospective recall data</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.06.032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32745719</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0117">
        <label>117.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kocevska</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blanken</surname>
<given-names>TF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Someren</surname>
<given-names>EJW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rösler</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep quality during the COVID-19 pandemic: not one size fits all</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>86</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.09.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33126035</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0118">
        <label>118.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Blume</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schmidt</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cajochen</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of the COVID-19 lockdown on human sleep and rest-activity rhythms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Biol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>R795</fpage>–<lpage>r797</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2020.06.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32693067</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0119">
        <label>119.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Leone</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sigman</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Golombek</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of lockdown on human sleep and chronotype during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Biol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>R930</fpage>–<lpage>r931</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2020.07.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32810450</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0120">
        <label>120.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Au</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reece</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The relationship between chronotype and depressive symptoms: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Affect Disord</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>218</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2017.04.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28463712</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0121">
        <label>121.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Czeisler</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dumont</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duffy</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of sleep-wake habits in older people with changes in output of circadian pacemaker</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>340</volume>(<issue>8825</issue>):<fpage>933</fpage>–<lpage>936</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0140-6736(92)92817-Y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1357348</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0122">
        <label>122.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>REY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sex differences in deterioration of sleep properties associated with aging: a 12-year longitudinal cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>964</fpage>–<lpage>972</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.9072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33432918</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0123">
        <label>123.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Marelli</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Castelnuovo</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Somma</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impact of COVID-19 lockdown on sleep quality in university students and administration staff</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>268</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>8</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00415-020-10056-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32654065</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0124">
        <label>124.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Romero-Blanco</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rodríguez-Almagro</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Onieva-Zafra</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parra-Fernández</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Prado-Laguna</surname>
<given-names>MDC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hernández-Martínez</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep pattern changes in nursing students during the COVID-19 lockdown</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>14</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph17145222</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0125">
        <label>125.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kaparounaki</surname>
<given-names>CK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patsali</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mousa</surname>
<given-names>DV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Papadopoulou</surname>
<given-names>EVK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Papadopoulou</surname>
<given-names>KKK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fountoulakis</surname>
<given-names>KN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>University students’ mental health amidst the COVID-19 quarantine in Greece</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>290</volume>:<fpage>113111</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32450416</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
