<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34466047</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">8403018</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">313891</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S313891</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Objectively Measured Sleep Characteristics and Incidence of Ischemic Stroke: The Sleep Heart Health Study</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Zhao et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Zhao et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
            <given-names>Binbin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="ft0001">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>Yanhua</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="ft0001">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jin</surname>
            <given-names>Xiaoying</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Lihong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Jian</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ma</surname>
            <given-names>Xiancang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5607-3012</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Yan</surname>
            <given-names>Bin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Psychiatry, The First Affiliated Hospital of Xi’an Jiaotong University</institution>, <addr-line>Xi’an</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Clinical Research Center, The First Affiliated Hospital of Xi’an Jiaotong University</institution>, <addr-line>Xi’an</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Bin Yan <institution>Department of Clinical Research Center, The First Affiliated Hospital of Xi’an Jiaotong University</institution>, <addr-line>Xi’an</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country><phone>Tel +86 2985323614</phone> Email yanbin.1987@hotmail.com</corresp>
        <fn id="ft0001">
          <label>*</label>
          <p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>24</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>13</volume>
      <fpage>1485</fpage>
      <lpage>1494</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>07</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2021 Zhao et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Zhao et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Objective</title>
          <p>Sleep disorders are associated with the prevalence of stroke. However, there is limited evidence regarding the association between objectively measured sleep characteristics and ischemic stroke.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>Ischemic stroke was assessed during the mean follow-up period of 11 years in the Sleep Heart Health Study. Sleep parameters such as wake after sleep onset (WASO) and sleep efficiency (SE) were objectively measured based on in-home polysomnography records. Multivariable Cox regression analysis was utilized to examine the relationship between objective sleep characteristics and ischemic stroke incidence.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>This study involved 4204 participants (1978 males and 2226 females, 63.8±11.1 years). The incidence of ischemic stroke increased in individuals with long WASO, poor SE, and short sleep duration. Multivariable Cox regression analysis showed that WASO within the fourth quartile (hazard ratio [HR] 3.771, 95% confidence interval [CI] 1.805–7.877, P&lt;0.001), third quartile (HR 3.009, 95% CI 1.433–6.317, P=0.004), and second quartile (HR 3.108, 95% CI 1.470–6.568, P=0.003) had a higher incidence of ischemic stroke than WASO within the first quartile. Poor SE (&lt;80.0%) was also found to be a predictor for ischemic stroke (HR 2.220, 95% CI 1.244–3.960, P=0.007). Additionally, a short sleep duration (&lt;6 h) was associated with an increased risk of ischemic stroke (HR 1.725, 95% CI 1.026–2.899, P=0.040).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>Our results revealed a relationship between WASO, SE, and sleep duration and ischemic stroke. Therefore, these sleep characteristics may be adequate predictors for the incidence of ischemic stroke.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>sleep characteristics</kwd>
        <kwd>ischemic stroke</kwd>
        <kwd>polysomnography</kwd>
        <kwd>Sleep Heart Health Study</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
            <institution-wrap>
              <institution>the Clinical Research Award of the First Affiliated Hospital of Xi’an Jiaotong University</institution>
            </institution-wrap>
          </funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>This study was supported by the Clinical Research Award of the First Affiliated Hospital of Xi’an Jiaotong University, China (No. XJTU1AF-CRF-2019-022).</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="2"/>
        <table-count count="9"/>
        <ref-count count="41"/>
        <page-count count="10"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Stroke is one of the most common causes of severe disability and death in the world.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> The stroke burden is expected to rise from approximately 38 million disability-adjusted life-years globally in 1990 to 61 million disability-adjusted life-years in 2020.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Ischemic stroke is the most prevalent type of stroke, accounting for nearly 88% of all types.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> There are many common risk factors for ischemic stroke, including aging, smoking, tobacco use, and high blood pressure.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4–6</xref> Moreover, studies have revealed that sleep habits such as daytime napping and caloric intake before bedtime increase the risk of ischemic stroke and the prevalence of its risk factors.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7–10</xref></p>
      <p>A growing number of studies investigated the role of objective sleep characteristics on cardiovascular disease and its risk factors based on polysomnography (PSG) and actigraphy.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11–13</xref> Objective sleep characteristics such as sleep efficiency (SE), arousal index (ArI), the sleep fragmentation index, the percentage of rapid eye movement (REM sleep %), and the percentage of slow-wave sleep (SWS %) were found to be associated with cardiovascular disease and related risk factors, including hypertension, diabetes mellitus, and metabolic syndrome.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13–17</xref> Von Kanel et al also showed that long wake after sleep onset (WASO) was associated with an increased risk of coronary artery disease.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> However, there is limited evidence regarding the association between objectively measured sleep characteristics and ischemic stroke based on PSG records.</p>
      <p>In this study, we aimed to explore the role of objective sleep characteristics, including SE, WASO, sleep architecture (REM sleep % and SWS%), sleep fragmentation (SFI and ArI), sleep latency, and sleep duration, on the incidence of ischemic stroke based on a large community-based population from the database of the Sleep Heart Health Study (SHHS).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Study Population</title>
        <p>The SHHS is a community-based multicenter prospective cohort study that investigated the incidence of cardiovascular disease and the consequences of sleep-disordered breathing (ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier: NCT00005275). The design and quality control procedures have been previously reported.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> The study population was selected from multicenter prospective cohort studies, including the Framingham Offspring and Omni Study, the Strong Heart Study, the Cardiovascular Health Study, the Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities Study, and the cohort studies of respiratory diseases in Tucson. All the participants provided written informed consent, and the study was approved by the Institutional Review Board of each participating institution, including Boston University, Case Western Reserve University, Johns Hopkins University, Missouri Breaks Research Inc., New York University Medical Center, University of Arizona, University of California at Davis, University of Minnesota-Clinical and Translational Science Institute, and the University of Washington. We had access to the SHHS database through a signed agreement with Brigham and Women’s Hospital.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Inclusion and Exclusion Criteria</title>
        <p>We obtained data on 5804 participants from SHHS datasets. We included individuals with complete PSG records. Participants were excluded in the present study if they (1) had a history of stroke, (2) had no follow-up data, and (3) reported that their sleep during the nighttime was affected by PSG and was significantly different than usual (based on responses to questions such as “Compared to your usual night’s sleep, how well did you sleep last night?” collected in the morning survey questionnaires) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref>). Finally, a total of 4204 participants were included in the present study.<fig id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Inclusion and exclusion criteria for the study population. This figure depicts the inclusion of patients into the current investigation as a flowchart. The arrows that branch off represent patients that did not meet the criteria and were excluded.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-1485-g0001"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Sleep Characteristics</title>
        <p>All participants in the current investigation underwent overnight electroencephalography-based PSG (P-Series; Compumedics, Abbotsville, Australia) in their homes by trained and certified technicians. Details regarding the specific technical aspects of the PSG measurement are shown in the <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=313891.docx">Supplement Methods</ext-link></underline>. WASO is defined as the total amount of arousal time between the beginning of sleep and the ultimate wake time. In the present study, WASO was also categorized into a first quartile (&lt;30.0 min), second quartile (30.0 min–48.5 min), third quartile (49.0 min–80 min), and fourth quartile (&gt;80 min). SE, defined as the ratio of time spent asleep to the total time in bed multiplied by 100, was divided into a first quartile (&lt;80%), second quartile (80–84.9%), third quartile (85–89.9%), and fourth quartile (≥90%). Sleep duration in the present study was defined as the total time in bed, calculated as the time between lights off and lights on (rounded to the nearest minute). In addition, sleep duration was also split into three groups, including short sleep duration (&lt;6 h per night), normal sleep duration (6–8 h per night), and long sleep duration (&gt;8 h per night). Sleep latency was determined as the time from lights off to sleeping. ArI was calculated as the ratio of number of arousals to the total sleep time. REM sleep % was defined as the percentage of REM sleep captured by PSG. Slow-wave sleep was presented as the third stage of non-REM sleep. The sleep fragmentation index is determined by dividing the total number of awakenings and sleep stage shifts by the total sleep time multiplied by 100. Apnea is defined as a complete or almost complete cessation of airflow, lasting at least 10 seconds, and is usually associated with desaturation or an arousal. Hypopnea is a reduction in airflow (&lt;70% of a “baseline” level), associated with desaturation or arousal. The apnea-hypopnea index (AHI) was calculated as all apnea and hypopnea episodes per hour of sleep accompanied by at least a 4% drop in oxygen saturation. Sleep disorder breathing is a condition characterized by repeated episodes of hypopnea and apnea, defined as AHI ≥5 events/h in the present study.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Outcomes</title>
        <p>The incidence of ischemic stroke was evaluated according to the patient cohorts based on exhaustive protocols.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> Ischemic stroke was defined as the first occurrence between the baseline PSG and the end of follow-up. The medical records were extracted when potential ischemic stroke was identified. Ischemic stroke was further investigated and confirmed by symptoms, physical findings, the presence of a non-carotid embolic source, the results of computed tomography and magnetic resonance imaging examinations, cerebral angiograms and lumbar punctures, and pathology reports.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Covariates</title>
        <p>The participants’ age, gender, body mass index (BMI), race, smoking status, history of diabetes mellitus and hypertension, benzodiazepine use, alcohol use, and PSG data were obtained from the baseline examination of the SHHS.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2006">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>Analysis of variance (ANOVA) was performed to compare differences between continuous variables, while the chi-square test was used for categorical variables. Continuous variables were expressed as mean ± standard deviation, and categorical variables were identified as percentages. Unadjusted Kaplan-Meier plots were used to evaluate the association of WASO, SE, and sleep duration with ischemic stroke. Univariable and multivariable Cox regression analyses were performed to estimate the association between each individual’s sleep characteristics and the incidence of ischemic stroke. Covariates, including age, gender, smoking status, race, BMI, prevalent hypertension and diabetes mellitus, apnea-hypopnea index, benzodiazepine use, alcohol use, and sleep duration, were included in the final Cox regression model. The hazard ratio (HR) and 95% confidence intervals (CI) were utilized to examine the relationship between objectively measured sleep characteristics and the incidence of ischemic stroke. The analysis of interaction terms was also constructed between objective sleep characteristics and other covariates on the incidence of ischemic stroke. All statistical analyses were performed using Statistical Package for Social Sciences (SPSS) statistics software (v. 24.0, SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL), and <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Participant Characteristics</title>
        <p>In the present study, 4204 participants (1978 males and 2226 females, 63.8±11.1 years) were enrolled. During the mean follow-up period of 10.7±3.0 years, 129 cases of ischemic stroke were observed. Participants with long WASO were older and more likely to be male. Participants within the fourth quartile of WASO had the highest proportion of smokers, diabetes mellitus, and hypertension compared to the third, second, and first quartiles. In addition, long WASO was associated with a high level of AHI (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=313891.docx">Supplement Table 1</ext-link></underline> also provides the sleep characteristics in participants with (n=129) or without ischemic stroke (n=4075). Individuals with ischemic stroke were prone to short sleep durations, long WASO, poor SE, and high levels of AHI. Baseline characteristics data classified by sleep efficiency and sleep duration are provided in <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=313891.docx">Supplement Tables 2 and 3</ext-link></underline>.<table-wrap id="t0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Descriptive Characteristics by WASO Quartile (Quartile I: &lt;30.0min; Quartile II: 30.0min–48.5min; Quartile III:49.0min-80.0min; Quartile IV: &gt;80.0min)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (n=4204)</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">WASO (Min)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">First Quartile (n=1048)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Second Quartile (n=1063)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Third Quartile (n=1047)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fourth Quartile (n=1046)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.8±11.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.2±11.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.7±10.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.5±10.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.7±10.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1978 (47.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">405 (38.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">470 (44.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">537 (51.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">566 (54.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2226 (52.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">643 (61.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">593 (55.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">510 (48.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">480 (45.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body mass index, kg/m<sup>2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.2±5.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.2±5.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.0±4.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.4±4.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.4±5.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.122</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.076</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> White</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3668 (87.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">907 (86.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">919 (86.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">938 (89.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">904 (86.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">536 (12.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">141 (13.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">144 (13.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109 (10.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">142 (13.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking status, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.044</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Smoker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2260 (53.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">546 (52.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">549 (51.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">568 (54.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">597 (57.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Never smoker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1938 (46.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">502 (47.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">512 (48.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">478 (45.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">446 (42.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol use, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.170</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> At least 1 drink per day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1708 (43.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">419 (42.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">457 (45.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">399 (41.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">433 (43.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2238 (56.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">557 (57.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">538 (54.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">575 (59.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">568 (56.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benzodiazepine use, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">246 (5.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (4.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (6.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 (5.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 (7.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.105</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes mellitus, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">295 (7.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (5.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (5.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93 (8.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94 (9.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1681 (40.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">309 (29.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">382 (35.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">447 (42.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">543 (51.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI, events/h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9±13.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8±11.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9±12.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3±12.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5±15.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration, h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3±0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0±1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2±0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4±0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7±0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.4±10.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.6±5.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.0±4.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.7±4.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.1±9.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.7±6.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.3±6.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.3±6.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.3±6.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8±7.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SWS, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.5±11.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.9±12.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.3±11.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.9±11.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.0±12.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL, min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8±19.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0±21.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4±18.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7±18.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2±19.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.177</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total ArI, events/h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.0±10.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4±8.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.0±8.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.1±10.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.7±12.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ArI-REM, events/h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.2±10.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.7±10.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0±10.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.3±10.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.7±12.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ArI-NREM, events/h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.9±11.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8±9.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.7±9.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.2±11.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.0±13.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SFI, events/h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9±3.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4±2.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5±2.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0±3.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5±4.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow-up time, year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7±3.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2±2.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0±2.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7±2.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0±3.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Results are presented as mean ± standard deviation or n (%). The P values represent the difference among four groups.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: AHI, apnea hypopnea index; ArI, arousal index; NREM, non-rapid eye movement; REM, rapid eye movement; SFI, sleep fragmentation index; SL, sleep latency; SWS, slow wave sleep; WASO, wake after sleep onset.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Ischemic Stroke and WASO, SE, and Sleep Duration</title>
        <p>There were significant differences in the distribution of incident ischemic stroke in the fourth WASO quartile (P&lt;0.001). Unadjusted Kaplan-Meier analysis showed an increased incidence of ischemic stroke among participants who had long WASO (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2A</xref>). After adjusting for age, gender, smoking status, race, BMI, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, AHI, benzodiazepine use, alcohol use, and sleep duration, WASO (per min) (HR 1.004, 95% CI 1.000–1.008, P=0.028) was found to be a predictor for the incidence of ischemic stroke (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). HRs for WASO (continuous) associated with ischemic stroke were relatively small. We further explored the role of WASO classified by quartiles on the incidence of ischemic stroke. The results showed that the WASO of the fourth quartile (HR 3.771, 95% CI 1.805–7.877, P=0.001), third quartile (HR 3.009, 95% CI 1.433–6.317, P=0.004), and second quartile (HR 3.108, 95% CI 1.470–6.568, P=0.003) increased the risk of ischemic stroke incidence compared with that of the first quartile (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<table-wrap id="t0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>HRs and 95% CIs for Sleep Characteristics Associated with Ischemic Stroke</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Univariable Models</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multivariable Adjusted<sup>†</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multivariable Adjusted<sup>‡</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WASO</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.008 (1.005–1.011)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.003 (1.000–1.007)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.049</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.004 (1.000–1.008)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.964 (0.951–0.977)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.980 (0.966–0.995)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.981 (0.966–0.996)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REM, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.971 (0.947–0.995)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.993 (0.969–1.019)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.598</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.994 (0.970–1.020)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.665</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SWS, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.993 (0.978–1.008)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.361</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.992 (0.977–1.008)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.346</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.992 (0.976–1.007)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.300</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.003 (0.994–1.011)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.551</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.002 (0.993–1.011)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.639</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.002 (0.993–1.010)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.693</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SFI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.036 (0.987–1.087)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.149</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.007 (0.959–1.057)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.780</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.006 (0.958–1.056)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.815</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total ArI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.002 (0.985–1.019)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.798</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.992 (0.972–1.013)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.462</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.992 (0.972–1.013)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.450</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ArI-REM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.986 (0.968–1.004)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.986 (0.967–1.005)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.149</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.987 (0.968–1.005)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.162</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ArI-NREM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.005 (0.990–1.020)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.539</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.995 (0.978–1.014)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.623</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.995 (0.977–1.013)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.607</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;6h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.943 (1.173–3.220)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.725 (1.026–2.899)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;8h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.326 (0.893–1.970)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.162</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.223 (0.816–1.833)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.330</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6h–8h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>†</sup>Each individual sleep characteristics was adjusted by age, gender, smoking status, race, body mass index, prevalent hypertension and diabetes mellitus, apnea-hypopnea index, benzodiazepine use, alcohol use. <sup>‡</sup>Adjusted by <sup>†</sup>plus sleep duration.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: ArI, arousal index; 95% CI, 95% confidence interval; HR, hazard ratio; NREM, non-rapid eye movement; REM, rapid eye movement; SFI, sleep fragmentation index; SL, sleep latency; SWS, slow wave sleep.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="t0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>HRs and 95% CIs for Quartiles of WASO and SE Associated with Ischemic Stroke</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Univariable Models</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multivariable Adjusted<sup>†</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multivariable Adjusted<sup>‡</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">All Subjects</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WASO</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Fourth quartile (&gt;80 min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.996 (2.600–9.597)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.298 (1.608–6.768)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.771 (1.805–7.877)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Third quartile (49.0min–80min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.299 (1.675–6.496)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.749 (1.317–5.738)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.009 (1.433–6.317)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Second quartile (30.0min–48.5min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.005 (1.519–5.945)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.933 (1.392–6.183)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.108 (1.470–6.568)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> First quartile (&lt;30.0 min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep efficiency</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> First quartile (&lt;80.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.726 (2.174–6.386)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.210 (1.241–3.936)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.220 (1.244–3.960)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Second quartile (80.0–84.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.467 (1.332–4.569)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.859 (0.970–3.564)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.062</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.829 (0.952–3.514)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Third quartile (85.0–89.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.866 (1.017–3.423)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.044</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.443 (0.762–2.732)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.261</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.457 (0.769–2.760)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.248</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Fourth quartile (≥90%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(Ref)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>†</sup>Adjusted by age, gender, smoking status, race, body mass index, prevalent hypertension and diabetes mellitus, apnea-hypopnea index, benzodiazepine use, alcohol use. <sup>‡</sup>Adjusted by <sup>†</sup>plus sleep duration.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0006"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: 95% CI, 95% confidence interval; HR, hazard ratio; WASO, wake after sleep onset.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Kaplan-Meier plots of cumulative risk for ischemic stroke stratified by WASO quartiles ((<bold>A</bold>); quartile I &lt;30.0 min; quartile II: 30.0 min-48.5 min; quartile III: 49.0 min-80.0 min; quartile IV: &gt;80.0 min) and SE ((<bold>B</bold>); quartile I &lt;80%, quartile II: 80%-84.9%, quartile III: 85%-89.9%, and quartile IV: ≥90%).</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="NSS-13-1485-g0002"/></fig></p>
        <p>Moreover, the occurrence of ischemic stroke increased in individuals with poor SE according to the unadjusted Kaplan-Meier analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2B</xref>). Multivariable Cox regression analysis showed that SE (per 1% increase) (HR 0.981, 95% CI 0.966–0.996, P=0.012) was associated with a reduced risk of ischemic stroke (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Moreover, compared with SE≥90%, poor SE (&lt;80.0%) increased the risk of ischemic stroke (HR 2.220, 95% CI 1.244–3.960, P=0.007) (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Furthermore, a short sleep duration (&lt;6 h) was also a risk factor for the incidence of ischemic stroke (HR 1.725, 95% CI 1.026–1.833, P=0.040).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Ischemic Stroke and Other Sleep Characteristics</title>
        <p>We also investigated the association between ischemic stroke and REM sleep %, SWS %, sleep latency, sleep fragmentation index, and ArI. However, no significant difference was found in the multivariable Cox regression analysis (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). An analysis of the association between AHI and ischemic stroke was also performed. AHI levels of 5.0–14.9 events/hour are associated with a higher risk of ischemic stroke compared with controls (AHI &lt;5 events/hour) (<underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=313891.docx">Supplement Table 4</ext-link></underline>). No significant association of AHI levels ≥30.0 events/hour and 15.0–29.9 events/hour with ischemic stroke was found.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Interaction Analysis</title>
        <p>We further investigated the possible interaction effects between sleep characteristics and sleep disorder breathing (&lt;15 events/hour vs ≥15 events/hour) on the incidence of ischemic stroke. No significant interaction was found (<underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=313891.docx">Supplement Table 5</ext-link></underline>). We also investigated the association of sleep characteristics with the incidence of ischemic stroke stratified by gender. The results showed that WASO, SE, and short sleep duration were associated with the female but male sex. However, no significant interaction was found in these analyses (<underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=313891.docx">Supplement Table 6</ext-link></underline>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Increasing evidence shows that sleep disorders are closely related to stroke.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> In the present study, we investigated the association between ischemic stroke and objectively measured sleep characteristics based on PSG in a middle-age- and older community-based population. Our findings demonstrated that long WASO, poor SE, and short sleep duration were associated with an increased risk of ischemic stroke in middle aged and older adults.</p>
      <p>PSG and wrist actigraphy are important ways to measure objective sleep characteristics.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Sleep parameters such as WASO and SE could be obtained from PSG records. WASO is an important sleep parameter measured by the periods of wakefulness after defined sleep onset.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Von Kanel et al demonstrated that WASO was a predictor for morning fasting plasma levels of von Willebrand Factor antigen and soluble tissue factor antigen, which are closely related to the risk of coronary artery disease.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> SE refers to the percentage of total time in bed actually spent in sleep, which could reflect the general estimation of the overall quality of sleep.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Studies showed that SE was associated with risk factors of ischemic stroke, including BMI, hypertension, and insulin sensitivity in adults.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> These studies suggested that WASO and SE are closely related to ischemic stroke risk factors. However, little is known about the role of WASO and SE in the occurrence of ischemic stroke. In our analysis of SHHS data, individuals with long WASO and poor SE had an increased risk of ischemic stroke incidence. To provide more useful information about the role of WASO and SE on the incidence of ischemic stroke, we classified WASO and SE by quartiles. Our findings showed that WASO &gt; 80 min and SE &lt; 80% significantly contributes to the incidence of ischemic stroke. Our findings indicate that WASO and SE based on PSG records may be predictors for the incidence of ischemic stroke.</p>
      <p>Many studies have shown that sleep duration is closely related to quality of life and physical health. Sleep duration may be influenced by age, race, work status, education level, lifestyles, and environmental and medical conditions.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Sleep duration usually obtained from sleep questionnaires could also be measured by PSG and actigraphy. Studies showed that under- and over-reporting of sleep is common in middle-age and older population when compared with objectively measured sleep duration.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25–28</xref> Subjective reports of habitual sleep are correlated with objective measured sleep, but the true association between self-reported sleep duration and human health may be different.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> Many studies have explored the relationship between self-reported sleep duration and stroke. A systematic review showed that a self-reported sleep duration &gt;9 h or even &gt;10 h significantly increased the risk of ischemic stroke.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> Leng et al also demonstrated that a self-reported sleep duration &gt;8 h per night is related to a higher risk of stroke.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> A case-control study also showed that a self-reported sleep duration of &gt;8 h per night was associated with a high risk of ischemic stroke in Chinese populations.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> However, no significant association was found between a long sleep duration (defined as &gt;8 h per night) and ischemic stroke in our analysis. It may be caused by different definitions of long sleep duration or different study populations. In addition, Eguchi et al found that a self-reported sleep duration &lt;7.5 h was independently associated with the risk of ischemic stroke.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> Furthermore, a self-reported sleep duration &lt;6 h was also associated with ischemic stroke in postmenopausal women.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> In this study, we also found that a short sleep duration (defined as &lt;6 h per night) significantly increased the risk of ischemic stroke.</p>
      <p>A previous study found that REM sleep % &gt;25% was correlated with angina pectoris.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Sleep fragmentation index and SWS % were also demonstrated to be closely related to hypertension.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> Additionally, total ArI, ArI-REM, and ArI-NREM were significantly associated with a high coronary artery calcification burden.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> The effects of REM sleep %, SWS %, sleep fragmentation index, total ArI, ArI-REM, ArI-NREM, and sleep latency on the incidence of ischemic stroke were also explored in this study. However, no significant relationship between these sleep characteristics and ischemic stroke was found in these analyses.</p>
      <p>Sleep disorder breathing seriously affects the body’s homeostasis and circadian rhythm, which can then cause various cardiovascular and cerebrovascular diseases.<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> Redline et al showed that there was a significant association between sleep disorder breathing and ischemic stroke in middle-age and older men based on SHHS datasets.<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> In the present study, participants with a high level of AHI had a higher incidence of ischemic stroke than did the controls. However, the associations were attenuated after multivariable adjustment. It may be due to the relatively small sample size of high level of AHI, especially in AHI levels ≥30.0 events/hour and 15.0–29.9 events/hour. The participants with sleep disorder breathing may have micro-arousals during the night, which could affect SE and WASO. We therefore adjusted for AHI in our multivariable Cox regression analysis to explore the association between sleep characteristics and ischemic stroke. We also performed the subgroup analysis stratified by AHI (&lt;15 events/hour vs ≥15 events/hour). No significant interaction was found between SE/WASO and AHI.</p>
      <p>The potential mechanisms between objective sleep characteristics and ischemic stroke remain unclear. Poor sleep was correlated with cardiovascular risk factors such as hypertension, obesity, and type 2 diabetes.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> Individuals with poor SE and longer WASO were also more likely to have poor sleep quality, which could easily activate the sympathetic nervous system and lead to increased heart rate and blood pressure at nighttime.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> A recent study also found that mice with sleep fragmentation produce more Ly-6C monocytes, causing larger atherosclerotic lesions and the production of less hypocretin.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></p>
      <p>Because SHHS data is based on a community population, our results are suitable for the general population. However, this study had a few limitations. Participants consisted of middle-age and older adults (63.8±11.1 years), and most were Caucasian (87.3%). We observed that individuals with long WASO, low SE, and short sleep duration were more likely to be older. Therefore, our results should not be extended to all ethnic groups or young populations. Additionally, the participants whose sleep was obviously affected by in-home PSG were excluded from this study. However, we must note that the PSG effect on sleep, such as first night effect for PSG and sleep duration, cannot be avoided. Furthermore, single night PSG monitoring may not fully reflect sleep parameters. Multiple in-home PSGs over a long-period of time may provide additional details and decrease measurement error. Additionally, records regarding non-apnea sleep disorders such as restless legs’ syndrome, hypersomnia, clinical insomnia, and REM behavior disorders were not included in SHHS datasets at baseline. Therefore we were unable to enroll this information in our analysis.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>The current study found that longer WASO, poor SE, and short sleep duration were associated with the incidence of ischemic stroke. This significant difference still exists after the adjustment for potential risk factors. Sleep hygiene education, which could help people decrease sleep disruption, improve SE, and obtain suitable sleep duration, may be a helpful way to prevent the incidence of ischemic stroke.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We appreciate the Brigham and Women’s Hospital for sharing the Datasets of Sleep Heart Health Study (SHHS). Moreover, SHHS acknowledges the Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities Study, the Cardiovascular Health Study, the Framingham Offspring and Omni Study, the Strong Heart Study, the Tucson Epidemiological Study of Obstructive Lung Disease, the cohort studies of respiratory disease in Tucson, and cohort studies of hypertension in New York. The Sleep Heart Health Study (SHHS) was supported by National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute cooperative agreements U01HL53916 (University of California, Davis), U01HL53931 (New York University), U01HL53934 (University of Minnesota), U01HL53937 and U01HL64360 (Johns Hopkins University), U01HL53938 (University of Arizona), U01HL53940 (University of Washington), U01HL53941 (Boston University), and U01HL63463 (Case Western Reserve University). The National Sleep Research Resource was supported by the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (R24HL114473, 75N92019R002).” SHHS is particularly grateful to the members of these cohorts who agreed to participate in SHHS as well. SHHS further recognizes all the investigators and staff who have contributed to its success. A list of SHHS investigators, staff and their participating institutions is available on the SHHS website, <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.25822/ghy8-ks59">https://doi.org/10.25822/ghy8-ks59</ext-link></underline>.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Highlights</title>
      <p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>The relationship between objective sleep characteristics and the incidence ischemic stroke was investigated.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Increased WASO, low SE, and short sleep duration were associated with the incidence of ischemic stroke.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Objective sleep characteristics may be used as predictors to prevent the incidence of ischemic stroke.</p></list-item></list>
</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>B.Y., and B.Z. raised the idea for the study. B.Y., B.Z., Y.W., X.J., L.Y., and J.Y. contributed to the study design, writing and review of the report. B.Y. and X.M. acquired the data in SHHS and B.Y. participated in further data analysis. B.Y. handled supervision in this study. All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation, or in all these areas; took part in drafting, revising or critically reviewing the article; gave final approval of the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0008" sec-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mendis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mathers</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Global variation in stroke burden and mortality: estimates from monitoring, surveillance, and modelling</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>345</fpage>–<lpage>354</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(09)70023-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19233730</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="web"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/cardiovascular_diseases/resources/atlas/en/">www.who.int/cardiovascular_diseases/resources/atlas/en/</ext-link>Xu W, Lin J, Gao M, et al. Rapid computer-aided diagnosis of stroke by serum metabolic fingerprint based multi-modal recognition. <italic>Adv Sci (Weinh)</italic>. 2020;7(21):2002021. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/advs.202002021</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bogiatzi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hackam</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McLeod</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Secular trends in ischemic stroke subtypes and stroke risk factors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Stroke</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>3208</fpage>–<lpage>3213</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/STROKEAHA.114.006536</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25213343</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Combined effects of family history of CVD and heart rate on ischemic stroke incidence among Inner Mongolians in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurol Res</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>441</fpage>–<lpage>447</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01616412.2016.1155816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27101478</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Slomski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Rapid blood pressure reduction safe for ischemic stroke</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>321</volume>:<fpage>1558</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Deijle</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Schaik</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Wegen</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kwakkel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van den Berg-vos</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Lifestyle interventions to prevent cardiovascular events after stroke and transient ischemic attack: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Stroke</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>174</fpage>–<lpage>179</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/STROKEAHA.116.013794</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27924055</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Correlation analysis of sleep quality and youth ischemic stroke</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>2014</volume>:<fpage>246841</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2014/246841</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25161340</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ifergane</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ovanyan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Toledano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea in acute stroke: a role for systemic inflammation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Stroke</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1207</fpage>–<lpage>1212</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/STROKEAHA.115.011749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27073238</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration, midday napping, and sleep quality and incident stroke: the Dongfeng-Tongji cohort</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>94</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e345</fpage>–<lpage>e356</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000008739</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31827003</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Punjabi</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of sleep time with diabetes mellitus and impaired glucose tolerance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>165</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>863</fpage>–<lpage>867</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.165.8.863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15851636</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Associations between objective sleep and ambulatory blood pressure in a community sample</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychosom Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>81</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>545</fpage>–<lpage>556</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PSY.0000000000000711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31083055</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duggan</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brindle</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prospective associations among objectively and subjectively assessed sleep and the metabolic syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2019.02.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31028926</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rosique-Esteban</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Papandreou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Romaguera</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cross-sectional associations of objectively-measured sleep characteristics with obesity and type 2 diabetes in the PREDIMED-plus trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>zsy190</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsy190</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Massar</surname><given-names>SAA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JCJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mohammad</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chee</surname><given-names>MWL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Poor habitual sleep efficiency is associated with increased cardiovascular and cortisol stress reactivity in men</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychoneuroendocrinology</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>156</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psyneuen.2017.04.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28482312</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep patterns and hypertension using actigraphy in the Hispanic Community Health Study/Study of Latinos</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>153</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chest.2017.09.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28970105</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of incident angina pectoris and rapid eye movement sleep in a large community-based study: the Sleep Heart Health Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2018.10.040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31150947</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Javaheri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Punjabi</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Redline</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Slow-wave sleep is associated with incident hypertension: the Sleep Heart Health Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>zsx179</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>von Kanel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Loredo</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ancoli-Israel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Natarajan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dimsdale</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between polysomnographic measures of disrupted sleep and prothrombotic factors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>131</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>733</fpage>–<lpage>739</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.06-2006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17356087</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>BV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Iber</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The Sleep Heart Health Study: design, rationale, and methods</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1077</fpage>–<lpage>1085</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9493915</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burch</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wirth</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Persistence of social jetlag and sleep disruption in healthy young adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chronobiol Int</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>312</fpage>–<lpage>328</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07420528.2017.1405014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29231745</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bangdiwala</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rangarajan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of estimated sleep duration and naps with mortality and cardiovascular events: a study of 116 632 people from 21 countries</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Heart J</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>1620</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shrivastava</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saadat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sirohi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crewson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>How to interpret the results of a sleep study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Community Hosp Intern Med Perspect</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>24983</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3402/jchimp.v4.24983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25432643</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Centers for Disease C and Prevention</collab>. <article-title>Effect of short sleep duration on daily activities–United States, 2005–2008</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>242</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21368739</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Medic</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wille</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hemels</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Short- and long-term health consequences of sleep disruption</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Sci Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>161</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S134864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28579842</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Van Den Berg</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Rooij</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vos</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Disagreement between subjective and actigraphic measures of sleep duration in a population-based study of elderly persons</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Sleep Res</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>295</fpage>–<lpage>302</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2869.2008.00638.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18321246</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sherrill</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Relationship between reported and measured sleep times: the sleep heart health study (SHHS)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clini Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>622</fpage>–<lpage>630</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Miner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zeitzer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Self-reported and actigraphic short sleep duration in older adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clini Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>:<fpage>jcsm</fpage>–<lpage>9584</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tsuchiyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nagayama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kudo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Discrepancy between subjective and objective sleep in patients with depression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>264</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1440-1819.2003.01114.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12753564</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lauderdale</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knutson</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rathouz</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Self-reported and measured sleep duration: how similar are they?</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Epidemiology</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>838</fpage>–<lpage>845</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/EDE.0b013e318187a7b0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18854708</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Girschik</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fritschi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heyworth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Validation of self-reported sleep against actigraphy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>462</fpage>–<lpage>468</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2188/jea.JE20120012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22850546</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Landau</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baxter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Werden</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brodtmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The bidirectional impact of sleep and circadian rhythm dysfunction in human ischaemic stroke: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>54</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2019.03.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30954762</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cappuccio</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wainwright</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration and risk of fatal and nonfatal stroke: a Prospective Study and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>84</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1072</fpage>–<lpage>1079</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000001371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25716357</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Interaction between methylenetetrahydrofolate reductase C677T gene polymorphism and sleep duration on risk of stroke pathogenesis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Beijing Da Xue Xue Bao Yi Xue Ban</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>262</fpage>–<lpage>269</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18560453</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Eguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoshide</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kario</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Short sleep duration is an independent predictor of stroke events in elderly hypertensive patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Soc Hypertens</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jash.2010.09.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20940066</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brunner</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration and risk of ischemic stroke in postmenopausal women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Stroke</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>3185</fpage>–<lpage>3192</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/STROKEAHA.108.521773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18635832</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lutsey</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McClelland</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duprez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Objectively measured sleep characteristics and prevalence of coronary artery calcification: the Multi-Ethnic Study of Atherosclerosis Sleep Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Thorax</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>70</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>880</fpage>–<lpage>887</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2015-206871</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26156526</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Campos-Rodriguez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martinez-Garcia</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reyes-Nunez</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caballero-Martinez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Catalan-Serra</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Almeida-Gonzalez</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Role of sleep apnea and continuous positive airway pressure therapy in the incidence of stroke or coronary heart disease in women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>189</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1544</fpage>–<lpage>1550</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201311-2012OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24673616</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Redline</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yenokyan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Obstructive sleep apnea-hypopnea and incident stroke: the Sleep Heart Health Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>182</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>269</fpage>–<lpage>277</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.200911-1746OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20339144</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>St-Onge</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grandner</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration and quality: impact on lifestyle behaviors and cardiometabolic health: a scientific statement from the American heart association</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circulation</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>134</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<fpage>e367</fpage>–<lpage>e386</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIR.0000000000000444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27647451</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Castro-Diehl</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Diez Roux</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Redline</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration and quality in relation to autonomic nervous system measures: the Multi-Ethnic Study of Atherosclerosis (MESA)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1927</fpage>–<lpage>1940</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.6218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27568797</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McAlpine</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kiss</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rattik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep modulates haematopoiesis and protects against atherosclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nature</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>566</volume>(<issue>7744</issue>):<fpage>383</fpage>–<lpage>387</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-019-0948-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30760925</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
