<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34703345</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">8526947</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">331880</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S331880</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Idiopathic Sudden Sensorineural Hearing Loss in Patients with Obstructive Sleep Apnea</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Chen et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Chen et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Chin-Kuo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shen</surname>
            <given-names>Shih Chieh</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8414-595X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Li-Ang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>Ming-Hui</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8387-9318</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Ning-Hung</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5466-8995</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Chuang</surname>
            <given-names>Li-Pang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9016-8098</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Hsueh-Yu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Sleep Center, Chang Gung Memorial Hospital (Linkou)</institution>, <addr-line>Taoyuan City</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>College of Medicine, Chang Gung University</institution>, <addr-line>Taoyuan City</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, New Taipei Municipal Tucheng Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>New Taipei City</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Ophthalmology, Chang Gung Memorial Hospital (Linkou)</institution>, <addr-line>Taoyuan City</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label><institution>Department of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, Sleep Center, Chang Gung Memorial Hospital (Linkou)</institution>, <addr-line>Taoyuan City</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Hsueh-Yu Li; Shih Chieh Shen <institution>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Sleep Center, Chang Gung Memorial Hospital (Linkou)</institution>, <addr-line>33, No. 5, Fushing Street, Gueishan Shiang</addr-line>, <addr-line>Taoyuan City</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan</country>
<phone>Tel +886-3-3281200 ext.3966</phone>
<fax>Fax +886-3-3979361</fax> Email hyli38@cgmh.org.tw; b9102083@cgmh.org.tw</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>13</volume>
      <fpage>1877</fpage>
      <lpage>1885</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>30</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2021 Chen et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Chen et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p>Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) is characterized by recurring hypoxic-apneic events during sleep, and labyrinthine vascular compromise is a pathophysiologic hallmark of idiopathic sudden sensorineural hearing loss (ISSNHL). Some reports have discussed the relationship between OSA and hearing impairment; however, few have examined hearing prognosis in OSA and patients without OSA with ISSNHL. We aimed to investigate clinical manifestations of ISSNHL in patients with OSA, including severity of hearing loss and response to treatment.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Patients and Methods</title>
          <p>A case-control study was conducted by extracting data from the sleep center and cochlea center databases of the Chang Gung Memorial Hospital. A retrospective chart review was performed to include confirmed adult OSA patients diagnosed with unilateral ISSNHL. Age and sex-matched patients without OSA with ISSNHL were enrolled as controls. Pure-tone average (PTA) thresholds were measured at specific frequencies. Changes in PTA before and after standard treatment with oral prednisolone (1mg/kg/day for 5 days, then tapered) and between participants with OSA and without OSA were compared. Standard treatment was given to all ISSNHL patients.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>Twenty-eight out of 8500 (0.33%) OSA patients experienced subsequent ISSNHL in 9 years. Patients with OSA (n=28) had poorer high-frequency perception in the unaffected ear than the patients without OSA (n=120), although the difference was not significant. Hearing in the affected ear among patients with OSA was comparable to that patients without OSA at individual frequencies and average, suggesting no difference in hearing loss in the affected ear between the two groups. In terms of high-frequencies (4000 and 8000 Hz) perception, patients with OSA had significantly poorer responses to steroid treatment than patients without OSA.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>ISSNHL may be one of the auditory complications associated with OSA. Patients with OSA had poorer prednisolone related hearing improvement in high frequencies than patients without OSA. Despite study limitations, OSA-related hypoxia and snoring noise is hazardous to hearing and standard treatments with CPAP is suggested in OSA patients for both holistic and auditory health.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>obstructive sleep apnea</kwd>
        <kwd>idiopathic sudden sensorineural hearing loss</kwd>
        <kwd>high-frequency</kwd>
        <kwd>hypoxemia</kwd>
        <kwd>pure-tone average</kwd>
        <kwd>frequencies</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="3"/>
        <table-count count="9"/>
        <ref-count count="33"/>
        <page-count count="9"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA), characterized by recurring events of upper airway collapse during sleep, affects nearly 1 billion people worldwide.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Apnea and hypopnea are the hallmarks of OSA contributing to physiological instabilities, which include excessive fluctuations in intrathoracic and intracranial pressure, changes in the heart rate, and eventually, tissue desaturation.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> The pathogenesis of recurrent hypoxia/hypercapnia and chronic inflammatory status in OSA is associated with cardiovascular diseases and neurocognitive deficits.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3–6</xref> Moreover, recurrent hypoxia and noise exposure to the cochlea causes marked hearing dysfunction.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7–9</xref></p>
      <p>Organs without communication branch vesicles, such as the inner ear system, are easily influenced by recurrent hypoxia and inflammation. However, idiopathic sudden sensorineural hearing loss (ISSNHL) is an acute condition that presents with sudden deafness of ≥30 dB in at least three contiguous frequencies in &lt;3 days. ISSNHL has an incidence of 5–27 cases per 100,000 per year.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Although uncertain causes need to be excluded and the origin remains unclear, the main pathophysiological points linked to ISSNHL include labyrinthine vascular compromise, labyrinthine viral infection, intracochlear membrane rupture, and immune-mediated inner ear disease.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></p>
      <p>Prolonged hypoxia can elicit a chronic inflammatory status and excessive oxidative stress, potentially compromising the integrity of the inner ear’s microvasculature in patients with OSA.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Moreover, patients with OSA may have worsening hearing status and impaired high-frequency sound perception.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> Furthermore, a population-based case-control study has indicated that male patients with ISSNHL often have a history of OSA.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Nonetheless, there remains a paucity of information on the clinical manifestations of ISSNHL in patients with OSA.</p>
      <p>In this study, we aimed to investigate the clinical manifestations of ISSNHL in patients with OSA, including severity of hearing loss and response to treatment.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Data Sources and Study Population</title>
        <p>A retrospective chart review was conducted by extracting data from the sleep center and cochlear center at Chang Gung Memorial Hospital from 2009 to 2017. The Joint Institutional Review Board of Chang Gung Memorial Hospital approved (No. 201601393B0C601) the study, which was performed according to the principles outlined in the Declaration of Helsinki. Participants’ informed consent was waived due to retrospective chart review in this study. Adult patients diagnosed with unilateral ISSNHL were included, and the exclusion criteria comprised insomnia, simple snoring, preexisting otologic or neurologic disorders, prior otologic procedures, and comorbidities of the liver and the endocrine system. Also, all ISSNHL patients were diagnosed in the cochlear center after a thorough protocol including history taking, physical examination, otoscopy, audiometric tests, stapedius reflex, vestibular examination, tympanometry, bloody tests, ABR, MRI and/or CT scan to exclude its cause from infection, barotrauma, ototoxic drug, sickle cell disease, acoustic neuroma, etc. At the sleep center, 8500 OSA patients were recruited, and 28 of those who consequently developed ISSNHL were enrolled in this study. On the other hand, patients with ISSNHL were acquired from the cochlear center. Since sleep disorders were associated with inner ear disease, patients with ISSNHL were excluded if they had sleep-related symptoms/conditions including insomnia, sleep-deprivation, shift work, snoring, witnessed sleep apnea, or daytime sleepiness/fatigue based on the structured chart review. Furthermore, stratified sampling was applied to select patients without OSA group according to the average age of the OSA group (44–64 years), and the ratio of male to female (3:1); simple random sampling was used to select 85 men and 35 women, with a total of 120 patients. Overall, we enrolled 28 patients with OSA and 120 patients without OSA, matched by age and sex.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Study Outcome and Measurements</title>
        <p>All ISSNHL patients were administered oral prednisolone (1 mg/kg/day) for 5 days, followed by tapering within 5 days. Patients who failed systemic steroid therapy within 14 days were given intratympanic injection of 0.4 mL dexamethasone and/or HBO therapy. Audiometric tests were performed at specific frequencies of 250, 500, 1000, 2000, 4000, and 8000 Hz before and after the oral prednisolone treatment. Pure-tone average (PTA), the average of hearing thresholds at 500, 1000, 2000, and 4000 Hz, was calculated. Hearing loss was defined as the threshold difference between the affected and unaffected ears, and hearing improvement was defined as the threshold difference before and after the treatment. OSA was diagnosed based on polysomnography. The apnea‐hypopnea index (AHI) was defined as the average number of episodes of apneas and hypopneas per hour of sleep. The participants were categorized into two groups: OSA and without OSA groups. Patients with AHI &gt;5 were categorized as the OSA group.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Polysomnography</title>
        <p>All patients with OSA underwent full-night polysomnography at the sleep center of the Chang Gung Memorial Hospital. The patients avoided daytime naps and consumption of strong tea, coffee, alcohol, or sedative drugs. The sleep monitor assay was performed on the night of admission to analyze sleep for approximately 6–8 h.</p>
        <p>Rechtschaffen and Kales have rated sleep stages according to the guidelines.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> Standard polysomnography was performed to document sleep parameters. Arousals were defined according to the American Sleep Disorders Association criteria.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> In adults, apnea is defined as &gt;90% reduction of flow for &gt;10 s and classified as obstructive in the presence of rib cage and abdominal wall movements, or central with a lack of respiratory effort. Hypopneas are defined as &gt;50% reduction in flow for at least two breaths with subsequent oxygen desaturation of at least 3% or arousal.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Sample Size</title>
        <p>The sample size was determined using G*power version 3.1<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> and the results of a previous analysis with this effect size revealed that we needed a sample size, N=20, to achieve 95% power at α=0.05.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>Statistical analysis was performed using the Statistical Package for Social Science software (version 22.0; IBM Corp., Armonk, IBM Company, USA). Continuous variables are expressed as means and standard deviations (SD), and categorical variables are expressed as counts and frequencies. Effect sizes with 95% confidence intervals (CIs) were calculated for the variables. Independent samples t-tests were used to compare age, sex, and pure-tone audiometry between the OSA and without OSA groups. A paired sample <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test was used to compare the preoperative and postoperative data. The Wilcoxon signed-rank test was used to compare the preoperative and postoperative data of a small sample. Statistical significance was set at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Incidence of ISSNHL in OSA</title>
        <p>According to our data, 28 of 8500 (0.33%) patients with OSA experienced subsequent ISSNHL.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Patient Characteristics</title>
        <p>Twenty-eight OSA patients (21 men) and 120 patients without OSA (85 men) were enrolled in the study. There were no significant differences in demographic variables, such as age, sex, presence or absence of vertigo, type of audiogram, initial treatment days after onset of hearing loss, baseline hearing of the unaffected ear, and comorbidities (diabetes mellitus, hypertension, renal disease, and coronary artery diseases) between the OSA and without OSA groups. (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographics and Clinical Characteristics of ISSNHL in patients with OSA and without OSA</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Without OSA (n=120)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSA (n=28)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effect Size/OR (95% CI)<sup>a</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, mean (SD), y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.9 (8.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.9 (9.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11 (−4.57–2.59)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.587</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.817</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (70.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (75.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 (0.74–1.20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (29.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (25.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 (0.58–2.35)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comorbidity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> DM, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (25.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (32.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80 (0.43–1.49)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.637</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HTN, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (26.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (42.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62 (0.37–1.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.110</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> CAD, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (5.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (7.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70 (0.15–3.29)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Average=(500+1k+2k+4k)/4. <sup>a</sup>For continuous variables, effect size is the median of the difference of medians between the groups, and the 95% CI around that difference was calculated using the method of Cohen’s d for <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test. For categorical variables, effect size is the difference between proportions of the groups with relative 95% CIs calculated around that difference.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: OSA, obstructive sleep apnea; OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence intervals; SD, standard deviation; dB, decibel; DM, diabetes mellitus; HTN, hypertension; CAD, coronary artery disease.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Hearing Presentation of Unaffected Ears in the OSA and Without OSA Groups</title>
        <p>The baseline PTA of the unaffected ear in the OSA and without OSA groups were 24.6 ± 12.9 dB and 23.9 ± 16.0 dB (Cohen’s d, 0.05; 95% CI [−6.50, −5.27]; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.83), respectively (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The Hearing Thresholds of the Idiopathic Sudden Sensorineural Hearing Loss Ear in Patients with Obstructive Sleep Apnea (OSA) and Patients Without OSA, Before Treatment</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Without OSA (n=120)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSA (n=28)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effect Size (95% CI)<sup>a</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Baseline hearing of the unaffected ear (in Decibels), mean (SD)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.5 (12.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.6 (10.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 (−4.47, −5.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.709</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.0 (14.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.0 (9.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13 (−3.96, −6.97)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.500</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1k</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.3 (16.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.2 (12.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 (−5.10, −6.99)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.744</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2k</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.0 (18.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.7 (16.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 (−7.59, −5.98)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.865</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4k</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.1 (21.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.3 (21.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19 (−12.91, −4.68)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8k</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.4 (25.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.6 (23.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21 (−14.90, −5.01)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.326</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.9 (16.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.6 (12.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 (−6.50, −5.27)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.833</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Hearing of the affected ear (in Decibels), mean (SD)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.3 (20.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.1 (20.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 (2.51, −18.70)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.145</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.3 (21.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.0 (19.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 (−5.54, −11.19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.885</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1k</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.2 (22.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.4 (21.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 (−9.82, −7.88)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.362</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2k</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.4 (23.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.0 (24.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 (−8.04, −11.04)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.600</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4k</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.3 (23.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.8 (23.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18 (−5.66, −14.27)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.755</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8k</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.1 (23.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.1 (28.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 (−4.30, −16.26)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.855</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.2 (20.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.5 (18.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10 (−6.33, −10.15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.594</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Hearing loss of the affected ear (in Decibels), mean (SD)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.8 (20.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.6 (20.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51 (1.97, −18.22)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.215</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.3 (22.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.9 (21.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 (−7.73, −10.37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.578</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1k</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.9 (24.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.3 (21.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09 (−11.53, −7.69)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.292</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2k</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.3 (25.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.3 (25.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09 (−8.03, −12.64)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.712</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4k</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2 (25.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.5 (24.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33 (−2.21, −19.04)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.495</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8k</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.7 (26.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.6 (25.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42 (−0.19, −22.04)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.276</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.4 (22.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.9 (19.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12 (−6.32, −11.48)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.744</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Average=(500+1k+2k+4k)/4. <sup>a</sup> For continuous variables, the effect size is the median of the difference of medians between the groups, and the 95% CI around that difference was calculated using Cohen’s d for the <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: CI, confidence intervals; SD, standard deviation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Hearing Presentation of the Affected Ears in the OSA and Without OSA Groups</title>
        <p>The initial PTA of the affected ears in the OSA and without OSA groups were 63.5 ± 18.9 dB and 61.2 ± 20.4 dB (Cohen’s d, 0.10; 95% CI [−6.33, −10.15]; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.59), respectively (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The affected ears in both groups had comparable hearing presentations.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2005">
        <title>Initial Hearing Loss of the Affected Ear in the OSA and Without OSA Groups</title>
        <p>Before treatment, the hearing loss of PTA in the OSA and without OSA groups were 38.9 ± 19.5 dB and 37.4 ± 22.3 dB (Cohen’s d, 0.12; 95% CI [−6.32, −11.48]; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.74), respectively (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2006">
        <title>Hearing Presentation of the Affected Ears After Treatments in the OSA and Without OSA Groups</title>
        <p>After treatment, the OSA group had less hearing improvement at all frequencies than the without OSA group. The without OSA group had significant threshold improvements in frequencies at 2000, 4000 and 8000 Hz than the OSA group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05; <xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>The Hearing Thresholds of the Idiopathic Sudden Sensorineural Hearing Loss Ear in Patients with Obstructive Sleep Apnea (OSA) and Patients Without OSA, After Treatment</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Without OSA (n=120)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSA (n=28)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effect Size (95% CI)<sup>a</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Hearing of the affected ear (in Decibels), mean (SD)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.2 (19.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.9 (21.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26 (−3.79, −15.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.684</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.9 (21.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.0 (22.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 (−8.31, −11.15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.182</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1k</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.8 (22.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.4 (22.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 (−11.33, −9.28)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2k</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.9 (23.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.9 (20.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13 (−13.26, −6.98)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4k</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.4 (24.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.6 (23.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13 (−14.28, −7.63)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8k</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.8 (26.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.1 (26.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25 (−18.17, −4.72)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.0 (20.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.2 (17.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07 (−9.35, −6.31)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028*</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Hearing loss of the affected ear (in Decibels), mean (SD)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7 (21.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4 (20.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 (−4.66, −14.95)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.553</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.9 (22.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.0 (19.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (−8.70, −8.52)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.077</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1k</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5 (24.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.2 (19.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09 (−10.73, −6.79)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2k</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.9 (26.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.3 (19.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10 (−11.19, −6.53)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.055</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4k</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.3 (26.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.3 (22.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 (−10.40, −11.98)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.275</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8k</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4 (29.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.6 (24.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07 (−13.44, −9.88)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.169</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.2 (23.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.8 (15.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 (−8.08, −6.30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018*</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Average=(500+1k+2k+4k)/4. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05, statistically significant differences between the groups. <sup>a</sup>For continuous variables, the effect size is the median of the difference of medians between the groups, and the 95% CI around that difference was calculated using Cohen’s d for the <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0006"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: OSA, obstructive sleep apnea; ISSNHL, idiopathic sudden sensorineural hearing loss; PTA, pure-tone average; AHI, apnea-hypopnea index; SD, standard deviations; CI, confidence interval.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2007">
        <title>Hearing Loss of the Affected Ears After Treatments in Both Groups</title>
        <p>Both groups had comparable hearing loss after treatment (P&gt;0.05); however, the OSA group had a tendency toward more hearing loss than the without OSA group. Moreover, the OSA group had more hearing loss of PTA after treatment than the without OSA group (Cohen’s d, 0.04; 95% CI [−8.08, −6.30]; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.018; <xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2008">
        <title>Hearing Presentation Response to Treatments of ISSNHL in the OSA and Without OSA Groups</title>
        <p>The without OSA group showed significant hearing improvements at all frequencies (250–8000 Hz; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05; <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>). In the OSA group, the hearing sensitivity significantly improved after treatment at all frequencies, except at 8000 Hz (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>). Both groups also showed a significant improvement in PTA after treatment.<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The hearing thresholds of the idiopathic sudden sensorineural hearing loss ear in patients with obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) (<bold>B</bold>) and patients without OSA (<bold>A</bold>) before and after treatment. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05; a statistically significant Wilcoxon signed-rank test; b statistically significant paired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-1877-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2009">
        <title>Comparison of the Extent of Hearing Improvement in Response to Treatments in OSA and Without OSA Groups</title>
        <p>Both groups showed improvements at all hearing frequencies. Notably, the OSA group had significantly less hearing improvement at frequencies of 4000 and 8000 Hz than those in the without OSA group (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The magnitude of hearing improvements in patients with obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) and patients without OSA with idiopathic sudden sensorineural hearing loss. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05, statistically significant independent <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-1877-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>This study is the first to investigate the clinical manifestations of ISSNHL in patients with OSA before and after treatment, and compare them with patients without OSA as controls. This study benefited from data acquisition based on a single institutional setting, ensuring that all enrolled patients followed standardized diagnostics and therapeutics for ISSNHL. The clinical presentation of ISSNHL in patients with OSA and the linkage of OSA to ISSNHL were addressed from different perspectives: 1) the pathophysiological plausibility and experimental evidence, and 2) coherence to observational studies and biological gradients.</p>
      <p>OSA with neuro-otologic disease risk has been reported on by several studies;<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21–25</xref> however, the causal relationship between OSA and ISSNHL remains unclear. A population-based case-control study reported that patients with ISSNHL have an association with OSA.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> In a cross-sectional study, patients with ISSNHL (n=27) had OSA more frequently than those with normal hearing (n=33).<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Our study showed that 28 out of 8500 (0.33%) patients with OSA (aged 20 to 65 years old) experienced ISSNHL over 9 years. In two epidemiological studies,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> the prevalence of ISSNHL in the general population aged 18 to 64 years old was 9.8 (Taiwanese, Asian) and 27 (American, Caucasian) per 100,000 population. Although studies were not entirely comparable and the causal inference relationship could not be established, our study revealed a potentially high incidence of ISSNHL in OSA patients. Therefore, the risk of ISSNHL should be taken into account for OSA patients, and the comorbid OSA in ISSNHL patients should be evaluated, vice versa.</p>
      <p>OSA has a detrimental effect on the cochlea, which is particularly sensitive to circulatory alterations since it is supplied by a single terminal artery and lacks adequate collateral blood supply.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> OSA is characterized by repeated upper airway obstruction and related hypoxia during sleep, directly resulting in decreased cerebral blood flow, elevated sympathetic nerve activity, and oscillations of blood pressure, which cause adverse cerebrovascular events and in turn, ischemic injury to the cochlea.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Previous studies have emphasized that due to high metabolic demand, the inner ear is vulnerable to periodic hypoxia.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> Long-term exposure to the noisy snoring sound in OSA patients could damage the inner ear and incur hearing impairment. Clinical studies have revealed a decreased perception of high-frequency sounds (4000 and 8000 Hz) in patients with moderate-to-severe OSA.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> This study showed similar findings, and although not statistically significant, patients with OSA had a poorer high-frequency perception in the unaffected ear than patients without OSA. This suggests that OSA could be a risk factor for auditory dysfunction.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></p>
      <p>Hearing of the affected ears in the OSA and patients without OSA were comparable at individual frequencies and the average of the frequencies, and did not indicate hearing loss differences in the affected ear between the two study groups. We presume that patients with OSA experience chronic repeated hypoxia, which becomes more resistant to hemodynamic changes from ISSNHL, and consequently, compensates for its hearing loss.</p>
      <p>ISSNHL with OSA had a poorer response to treatment at a high-frequency. The hearing threshold of the affected ear improved after treatment (steroid therapy) at all individual frequencies in both groups, except at 8000 Hz in the OSA group (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref> and <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">B</xref>). Research has revealed that OSA and ISSNHL are inflammation-related, and inflammatory cytokines are higher in patients with OSA.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Since steroids are potent inflammatory inhibitors, it was not surprising to observe effective improvement in the hearing threshold of the affected ear after treatment. Notably, the improvement in hearing declined after 2000 Hz, with no change at 8000 Hz in the patients with OSA (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>). Furthermore, a significantly poorer improvement in hearing was noted at 4000 and 8000 Hz in the OSA group than in the without OSA group (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). We speculated that noise exposure from snoring sounds may have played a role in the treatment outcome in patients with OSA. The repeated loud snoring sound transmits through the velopharyngeal channel (Eustachian tube) and conductive mechanism into the hum that causes acoustic trauma to the auditory organ, particularly the exterior part, which corresponds to high-frequency hearing (<xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). The persistent acoustic trauma from snoring may explain the poor response to treatment at a high-frequency in patients with OSA. In addition to acoustic trauma, chronic inflammation, and intermittent hypoxia could contribute to rendering OSA patients refractory to treatment during the insult of ISSNHL. The poorer hearing recovery in patients with OSA also suggested that treatment of OSA is needed for both general and specific (auditory) health.<fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Different parts of the cochlea corresponding to different frequencies. High-frequency hearing in the cochlear basal turn is exposed and vulnerable to the snoring noise.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-1877-g0003" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
      <p>Our study has several limitations. This research could be biased by its limited sample size, lack of confounder stratification, selection of the study population, and the suboptimal method adopted in the matching process. The matching process in this study did not adopt some of the advanced matching procedures, such as propensity score matching. Reasons for utilizing a more traditional matching method was to ensure that bias would not be further introduced during the construction of regression models necessary for propensity score matching, while there were few potential confounders of sufficient evidence. On the other hand, due to the small sample size, it was less feasible to stratify within the OSA group based on the severity of OSA or the type of OSA treatment. Also, due to the disadvantages of the retrospective chart review, this study lacked detailed information regarding the efficiency of OSA treatment, compliance and adherence of continuous positive airway pressure, and the precise chronological relationship between the treatment and the onset of ISSNHL. As a result, it was less likely to evaluate the effects of OSA treatment on clinical manifestations of ISSNHL. Nevertheless, we aimed to present the preliminary findings for the relationship between OSA and ISSNHL. Studies of larger sample sizes and a robust study design will be needed to better understand the relationship between OSA and ISSNHL.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>OSA may be associated with ISSNHL. The hearing thresholds of both unaffected and ISSNHL ears did not differ between the OSA and without OSA groups. Patients in the OSA group had poorer hearing improvement after treatment, especially at high frequencies (4000 and 8000 Hz). Also, from the perspective of preventive medicine, it is crucial to timely intervene OSA patients with standard treatment of CPAP and sufficient support for both general and specific (auditory) health, and screening ISSNHL patients for the comorbid OSA should be considered.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>The authors would like to thank Ms. Yen-Ting Chiang, Ms. Ling-Hsuan Chuang, and Ms. Shin-Fei Chi for their assistance in data collection and statistical analyses.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0006">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. The authors disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. This research project was supported by the Chang Gung Memorial Hospital (Linkou, Taiwan) under Grant Number CORPG3F0851 and CMRPG3J0701-3.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Benjafield</surname>
<given-names>AV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ayas</surname>
<given-names>NT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eastwood</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Estimation of the global prevalence and burden of obstructive sleep apnoea: a literature-based analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Respir Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>687</fpage>–<lpage>698</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(19)30198-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31300334</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">The International Classification of Sleep Disorders: Diagnostic and Coding Manual</italic></source>. <edition>2nd</edition> ed. <publisher-loc>Westchester, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</publisher-name>; <year>2005</year>:<fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dewan</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nieto</surname>
<given-names>FJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Somers</surname>
<given-names>VK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Intermittent hypoxemia and OSA: implications for comorbidities</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>147</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>266</fpage>–<lpage>274</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.14-0500</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25560865</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dempsey</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Veasey</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morgan</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Donnell</surname>
<given-names>CP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pathophysiology of sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiol Rev</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>90</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>112</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physrev.00043.2008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20086074</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Deniz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Çiftçi</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ersözlü</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gültekin</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alp</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The evaluation of auditory system in obstructive sleep apnea syndrome (OSAS) patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Otolaryngol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>299</fpage>–<lpage>303</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjoto.2016.03.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27105973</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yoon</surname>
<given-names>IY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The association of nocturnal hypoxemia with arterial stiffness and endothelial dysfunction in male patients with obstructive sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Respiration</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>79</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>369</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000228905</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19602870</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>el-Kady</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Durrant</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tawfik</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abdel-Ghany</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moussa</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Study of auditory function in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary diseases</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hear Re</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>212</volume>(<issue>1–2</issue>):<fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heares.2005.05.018</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chopra</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jung</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaplan</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep apnea is associated with hearing impairment: the Hispanic community health study/study of latinos</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>719</fpage>–<lpage>726</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.5804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26951413</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sardesai</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tan</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Noise-induced hearing loss in snorers and their bed partners</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Otolaryngol</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2310/7070.2003.40256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12921130</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chandrasekhar</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsai Do</surname>
<given-names>BS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schwartz</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Clinical Practice Guideline: sudden Hearing Loss (Update)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>161</volume>(<issue>1_suppl</issue>):<fpage>S1</fpage>–<lpage>S45</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0194599819859885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31369359</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chao</surname>
<given-names>PZ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sudden sensorineural hearing loss: evidence from Taiwan</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Audiol Neurootol</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>156</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000091198</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16449805</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lionello</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Staffieri</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Breda</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Uni- and multivariate models for investigating potential prognostic factors in idiopathic sudden sensorineural hearing loss</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>272</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1899</fpage>–<lpage>1906</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00405-014-2992-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24664295</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gozal</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kheirandish-Gozal</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cardiovascular morbidity in obstructive sleep apnea: oxidative stress, inflammation, and much more</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>177</volume>:<fpage>369</fpage>–<lpage>375</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.200608-1190PP</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17975198</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hwang</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hsu</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association of obstructive sleep apnea and auditory dysfunctions in older subjects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>144</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>114</fpage>–<lpage>119</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0194599810390859</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21493399</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vorlová</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dlouhá</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kemlink</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Šonka</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Decreased perception of high frequency sound in severe obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiol Res</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>959</fpage>–<lpage>967</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.33549/physiolres.933167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27539102</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sheu</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between obstructive sleep apnea and sudden sensorineural hearing loss: a population-based case-control study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>138</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archoto.2011.227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22249630</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Kales</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rechtschaffen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">A Manual of Standardized Terminology, Techniques and Scoring System for Sleep Stages of Human Subjects</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Washington DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Public Health Service, United States Government Printing Office</publisher-name>; <year>1968</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Scoring</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>EEG arousals: scoring rules and examples: a preliminary report from the sleep disorders atlas task Force of the American Sleep Disorders Association</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>184</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/15.2.173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11032543</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Iber</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ancoli-Israel</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chesson</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">The AASM Manual for the Scoring of Sleep and Associated Events: Rules, Terminology and Technical Specifications</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Westchester, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Academy of Sleep Medicine</publisher-name>; <year>2007</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Faul</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Erdfelder</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buchner</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lang</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Statistical power analyses using G*Power 3.1: tests for correlation and regression analyses</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Res Methods</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1149</fpage>–<lpage>1160</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3758/BRM.41.4.1149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19897823</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ko</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cho</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>DK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association of obstructive sleep apnea with the risk of Ménière’s disease and sudden sensorineural hearing loss: a study using data from the Korean national health insurance service</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1293</fpage>–<lpage>1301</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.7922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31538600</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nakayama</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Masuda</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ando</surname>
<given-names>KB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A pilot study on the efficacy of continuous positive airway pressure on the manifestations of Ménière’s disease in patients with concomitant obstructive sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1101</fpage>–<lpage>1107</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.5080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26094927</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jeon</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hong</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Relationship between sleep quality and dizziness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e0192705</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0192705</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29513688</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tsai</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsai</surname>
<given-names>YT</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep apnea and risk of vertigo: a nationwide population-based cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Laryngoscope</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>128</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>763</fpage>–<lpage>768</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lary.26789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28771753</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fanfulla</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grassi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taurino</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>D’Artavilla Lupo</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trentin</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The relationship of daytime hypoxemia and nocturnal hypoxia in obstructive sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>255</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/31.2.249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18274273</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fischer</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yakinthou</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mann</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalence of obstructive sleep apnea syndrome (OSA) in patients with sudden hearing loss. a pilot study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">HNO</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>462</fpage>–<lpage>466</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00106-002-0712-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12835844</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lazarini</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Camargo</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Idiopathic sudden sensorineural hearing loss: etiopathogenic aspects. Braz</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Otorhinolaryngol</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>554</fpage>–<lpage>561</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>XY</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Inner ear function in patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-019-01891-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31309465</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Seo</surname>
<given-names>YJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Lowest oxyhemoglobin saturation may be an independent factor influencing auditory function in severe obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>653</fpage>–<lpage>658</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.5786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26857050</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kayabasi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hizli</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yildirim</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The association between obstructive sleep apnea and hearing loss: a cross-sectional analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>276</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>2215</fpage>–<lpage>2221</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00405-019-05468-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31098873</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Capaccio</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pignataro</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gaini</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Unbalanced oxidative status in idiopathic sudden sensorineural hearing loss</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>269</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>449</fpage>–<lpage>453</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00405-011-1671-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21706323</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Casale</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vesperini</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Potena</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Is obstructive sleep apnea syndrome a risk factor for auditory pathway?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>413</fpage>–<lpage>417</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-011-0517-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21479758</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>YS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chin</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guilleminault</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chu</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>HY</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Inflammatory factors: nonobese pediatric obstructive sleep apnea and adenotonsillectomy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1028</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm9041028</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
