<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35002347</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">8721018</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">337932</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S337932</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Fragmented Sleep and the Prevalence of Hypertension in Middle-Aged and Older Individuals</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Zhao et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Zhao et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
            <given-names>Juan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Wenjuan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wei</surname>
            <given-names>Suhua</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Lihong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>Yanhua</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5607-3012</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Yan</surname>
            <given-names>Bin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Haematology, the First Affiliated Hospital of Xi’an Jiaotong University</institution>, <addr-line>Xi’an</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Clinical Research Center, the First Affiliated Hospital of Xi’an Jiaotong University</institution>, <addr-line>Xi’an</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Psychiatry, the First Affiliated Hospital of Xi’an Jiaotong University</institution>, <addr-line>Xi’an</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Bin Yan <institution>Department of Clinical Research Center, the First Affiliated Hospital of Xi’an Jiaotong University</institution>, <addr-line>Xi’an</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>
<phone>Tel +86 02985323614</phone> Email yanbin.1987@hotmail.com</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>29</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2021</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>13</volume>
      <fpage>2273</fpage>
      <lpage>2280</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>08</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2021 Zhao et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Zhao et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Objective</title>
          <p>We aimed to investigate the association between fragmented sleep and the prevalence of hypertension in middle-aged and older individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>This study included 5804 participants with an average age of 63.1±11.2 years from the Sleep Heart Health Study. Fragmented sleep parameters including arousal index in total sleep (ArI-Total), rapid eye movement sleep (ArI-REM), non-rapid eye movement sleep (ArI-NREM), fragmented sleep index (SFI), sleep efficiency (SE) and wake after sleep onset (WASO) were monitored using polysomnography. The information on hypertension, defined as systolic blood pressure (SBP) ≥140 mmHg and/or diastolic blood pressure (DBP) ≥90 mmHg or under antihypertensive treatment, was collected at baseline. We conducted multivariable logistic regression to explore the cross-sectional association between fragmented sleep and the prevalence of hypertension.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>After adjusting for potential confounders, fragmented sleep parameters (per 5-unit change) including SE (odds ratio [OR] 0.904; 95% confidence interval [CI] 0.877–0.932; P &lt; 0.001), WASO (OR 1.019; 95% CI 1.012–1.027; P &lt; 0.001), ArI-Total (OR, 1.036; 95% CI, 1.005–1.068; P = 0.024), and ArI-NREM (OR 1.032; 95% CI 1.004–1.062; P = 0.027) were significantly associated with the prevalence of hypertension. In addition, ArI-Total, ArI-NREM, and ArI-REM were positively correlated with both systolic blood pressure and diastolic blood pressure.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>We found a high prevalence of hypertension among middle-aged and older individuals with fragmented sleep. The causal association between fragmented sleep and hypertension warrants further investigation.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>blood pressure</kwd>
        <kwd>polysomnography</kwd>
        <kwd>fragmented sleep</kwd>
        <kwd>Sleep Heart Health Study</kwd>
        <kwd>cross-sectional study</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Key Research and Development Program of Shaanxi</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Natural Science Basic Research Program of Shaanxi</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>This research was supported by Key Research and Development Program of Shaanxi (No. 2020SF-169) and Natural Science Basic Research Program of Shaanxi (No. 2021JQ-395).</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="1"/>
        <table-count count="9"/>
        <ref-count count="30"/>
        <page-count count="8"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Hypertension, also known as elevated blood pressure, is a global public health issue. Approximately 1.28 billion people age 30–79 years have hypertension worldwide, and the number of people with systolic blood pressure (SBP) of 140 mmHg or higher increased from 17,307 to 20,526 per 100,000 between 1990 and 2015.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Individuals with hypertension have an increased risk of heart, brain, and kidney disease.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Hypertension is the most common preventable risk factor for cardiovascular disease; the prevention of hypertension would decrease the social burden associated with the condition and improve the quality of life.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4–6</xref></p>
      <p>Previous studies have found a close relationship between sleep and hypertension.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Individuals with poor sleep quality have higher average SBP and diastolic blood pressure (DBP).<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Short sleep duration is a risk factor for hypertension,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> and sleep-disordered breathing may lead to an increased risk of the condition.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Fragmented sleep is another sleep condition that can be monitored using wrist actigraphy.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> A previous study based on wrist actigraphy reported that individuals with low sleep efficiency (SE) had high daytime SBP but not DBP.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></p>
      <p>Polysomnography (PSG) can record more fragmented sleep parameters than wrist actigraphy, including arousal index (ArI) in total sleep (ArI-Total), sleep fragmentation index (SFI), SE, and wake after sleep onset (WASO). Furthermore, PSG can be used to monitor the ArI in rapid eye movement sleep (ArI-REM) and non-rapid eye movement sleep (ArI-NREM). There is little evidence regarding the association between fragmented sleep and hypertension in NREM and REM sleep based on PSG records. In this study, we aimed to explore the relationship between fragmented sleep and the prevalence of hypertension using data from the Sleep Heart Health Study (SHHS).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Study Population</title>
        <p>This study included individuals from community-based populations examined in the SHHS study. The SHHS (ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier: NCT00005275) recruited participants who met the inclusion criteria (age 40 years or older; no history of treatment of sleep apnea; no tracheostomy; no current home oxygen therapy) from nine existing epidemiological studies, including the Framingham Offspring Cohort, the Hagerstown and Minneapolis/St. Paul sites of the Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities (ARIC) study, the Hagerstown, Sacramento and Pittsburgh sites of the Cardiovascular Health Study (CHS), the Strong Heart Study sites in South Dakota, Oklahoma and Arizona, and Studies of respiratory disease in Tucson and of hypertension in New York. But the Strong Heart Study participants were excluded due to sovereignty issues. Several parent cohorts oversampled snorers to increase the study-wide prevalence of sleep-disordered breathing. There was a clear and rigorous Data Quality Assurance and Control system in each parent study. For the existing data collected by the parent studies, the Comparability Committee was charged with comparing data collected by the various parent studies to determine the data to be used. All participants provided written informed consent, and the study was approved by the institutional review board of each institution. The study design and quality control procedures were previously reported.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> We also provided details about the PSG monitor in <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=337932.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplement Methods</ext-link></underline>. We had access to the SHHS database through a signed agreement with the Brigham and Women’s Hospital. This research was approved by the Ethical Review Board of the First Affiliated Hospital of Xi’an Jiaotong University.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Fragmented Sleep Parameters</title>
        <p>All the participants underwent overnight unattended PSG at home using a portable monitor (P-Series; Compumedics, Abbotsville, Australia) between November 1995 and January 1998. ArI-total was calculated as the total number of sleep arousals divided by the total sleep time. ArI-NREM and ArI-REM were measured based on the number of arousals per hour during NREM and REM sleep, respectively. SFI was defined as the number of awakenings and sleep-stage shifts per hour. SE was calculated as the total sleep time divided by the total time in bed and multiplied by 100%. WASO was defined as the total awake time from the first time the participant fell asleep to the time the participant was fully awake. Fragmented sleep parameters were also divided into four groups based on quartiles to observe the prevalence of hypertension in different group.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Outcomes and Covariates</title>
        <p>All of the initial blood pressure measurements were performed in the subject’s home, prior to setting up the PSG equipment. Blood Pressure was taken by the sleep technician with the subject in a seated position after 5 minutes’ rest at baseline of SHHS, using a standard mercury sphygmomanometer and a choice of four cuff sizes. The observer listened with the bell of a Littman stethoscope and recorded the pressures. The average of the two readings taken with at least 30 second intervals was used to describe the blood pressure. Hypertension status was based on blood pressure measurements (SBP ≥140 mmHg and/or DBP ≥90 mmHg) or antihypertensive treatment (mainly included angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors, Beta-blockers, calcium-channel blocker, diuretic and vasodilators). Covariates including age, gender, race, smoking status, alcohol use, body mass index (BMI), benzodiazepine use and history of diabetes mellitus were collected from the SHHS baseline investigations. Sleep duration was based on the total sleep time according to the PSG records. The apnea-hypopnea index (AHI) was defined as the number of apnea and hypopnea episodes (at least 4% decrease in oxygen saturation) divided by the total sleep time. In the present study, sleep disordered breathing (SDB) was defined as an AHI of ≥5 events/h.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Statistical Analyses</title>
        <p>Differences in baseline characteristics between hypertensive and non-hypertensive patients were assessed using chi-square tests for categorical variables and independent-sample <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-tests for continuous variables. Univariable and multivariable logistic regression analyses were employed to explore the cross-sectional associations between fragmented sleep parameters and the prevalence of hypertension. We also investigated the correlations between fragmented sleep parameters and SBP/DBP using linear regression analysis. Multicollinearity among the different fragmented sleep parameters was examined using multivariable regression analysis. Interaction analysis stratified by SDB (AHI &lt;5 events/h vs AHI ≥5 events/h), age (≥60 vs &lt;60), gender (males vs females) and alcohol use (yes vs no) were also conducted. All analyses were performed using SPSS software (v.24.0, SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL). Two-sided P-values &lt;0.05 indicated statistical significance.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Participant Characteristics</title>
        <p>A total of 5804 middle-aged and older adults (2765 men and 3039 women with an average age of 63.1±11.2 years) were included in our study. Characteristics of the hypertensive and non-hypertensive participants are shown in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Hypertension was more prevalent among participants who were older, with a high BMI, and with diabetes mellitus. In addition, when compared to controls, participants with hypertension had significantly elevated ArI-Total, ArI-REM, ArI-NREM, SFI, WASO, and AHI and reduced SE.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Subject Characteristics in Participants with or Without Hypertension</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (n=5804)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension (n=2948)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Controls (n=2856)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.1±11.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.4±10.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.8±10.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2765 (47.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1440 (48.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1325 (46.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">―</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3039 (52.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1508 (51.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1531 (53.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">―</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> White</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4907 (84.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2483 (84.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2424 (84.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">―</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Black</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">515 (8.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">327 (11.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">188 (6.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">―</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">380 (6.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">137 (4.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">243 (8.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">―</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, kg/m<sup>2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.2±5.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.8±5.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.5±4.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking status, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Current smoker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">560 (9.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">224 (7.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">336 (11.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">―</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Former smoker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2495 (43.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1305 (45.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1190 (42.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">―</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Never smoker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2708 (47.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1399 (47.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1309 (46.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">―</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol use, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> At least 1 drink per day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2412 (44.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1160 (42.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1252 (47.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2977 (55.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1590 (57.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1387 (52.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benzodiazepine use, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">308 (5.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">201 (6.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107 (3.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes mellitus, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">405 (7.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">311 (10.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94 (3.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;6 hours</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">624 (10.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">366 (12.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">258 (9.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">―</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6–8 hours</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3784 (65.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1881 (63.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1903 (66.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">―</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;8 hours</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1396 (24.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">701 (23.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">695 (24.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">―</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep fragmentation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> SE, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.8±10.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.0±11.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.6±9.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> WASO, min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.4±44.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.4±46.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.3±40.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> SFI, events/h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0±3.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2±3.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8±3.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ArI-Total, events/h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.2±10.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.2±11.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.1±9.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ArI-REM, events/h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5±10.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.9±11.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0±9.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ArI-NREM, events/h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.0±11.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.2±12.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.1±10.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AHI, events/h</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2±13.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1±15.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2±11.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBP, mmHg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">127.4±19.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">137.7±19.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">116.6±11.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DBP, mmHg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.7±11.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.8±13.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.4±8.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triglycerides, mg/dl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">150.1±101.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">159.7±98.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">140.0±102.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cholesterol, mg/dl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">207.6±38.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">209.4±38.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">205.7±38.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Results are presented as mean ± standard deviation or n (%). The P values represent the difference between two groups.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: AHI, apnea hypopnea index; ArI, arousal index; BMI, body mass index; DBP, diastolic blood pressure; NREM, non-rapid eye movement; REM, rapid eye movement; SBP, systolic blood pressure; SE, sleep efficiency; SFI, sleep fragmentation index; WASO, wake after sleep onset.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Fragmented Sleep Parameters and Hypertension</title>
        <p>The distributions of hypertension differed significantly in the different fragmented sleep quartiles (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Participants with elevated ArI-Total (P&lt;0.001), ArI-NREM (P&lt;0.001) and WASO (P&lt;0.001) tended to have an increased prevalence of hypertension; individuals with high SE had a lower prevalence of hypertension than those with low SE (P&lt;0.001).<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The distribution of prevalent hypertension in different fragmented sleep quartiles. (<bold>A</bold>) ArI-Total (quartile 1: &lt;12.0 events/h, quartile 2: 12.0–16.7 events/h, quartile 3: 16.8–23.5 events/h, and quartile 4: ≥23.6 events/h); (<bold>B</bold>) ArI-NREM (quartile 1: &lt;12.1 events/h, quartile 2: 12.1–17.2 events/h, quartile 3: 17.3–24.8 events/h, and quartile 4: ≥24.9 events/h); (<bold>C</bold>) ArI-REM (quartile 1: &lt;7.8 events/h, quartile 2: 7.8–12.9 events/h, quartile 3: 13.0–20.2 events/h, and quartile 4: ≥20.3 events/h); (<bold>D</bold>) SFI (quartile 1: &lt;6.7 events/h, quartile 2: 6.7–8.5 events/h, quartile 3: 8.6–10.6 events/h, and quartile 4: ≥10.7 events/h); (<bold>E</bold>) SE (quartile 1: &lt;77.7%, quartile 2: 77.7%-85.0%, quartile 3: 85.1%-90.4%, and quartile 4: ≥90.5%); (<bold>F</bold>) WASO (quartile 1: &lt;29.6min; quartile 2: 29.6–49.4 min; quartile 3: 49.5–81.9 min; quartile 4: &gt;82.0min).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-13-2273-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/></fig></p>
        <p>Univariable and multivariable logistic regression analyses were further used to investigate the relationships between fragmented sleep parameters and hypertension. Multicollinearity was found among the different fragmented sleep parameters. Therefore, we explored the role of each individual fragmented sleep variable on hypertension risk after adjusting for age, gender, race, BMI, smoking status, alcohol use, diabetes mellitus, sleep duration, benzodiazepine use, triglyceride level, total cholesterol, and AHI. Our results (per 5-unit increased) showed that SE (odds ratio [OR] 0.904; confidence interval [CI] 0.877–0.932; P&lt;0.001), WASO (OR 1.019; 95% CI 1.012–1.027; P&lt;0.001), ArI-Total (OR, 1.036; 95% CI, 1.005–1.068; P=0.024), and ArI-NREM (OR 1.032; 95% CI 1.004–1.062; P=0.027) were significantly associated with the prevalence of hypertension (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). No significant association of SFI and ArI-REM with the prevalence of hypertension was found.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>ORs and 95% CIs for Sleep Fragmentation Associated with Hypertension</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sleep Fragmentation*</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Unadjusted</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Multivariable Adjusted<sup>a</sup></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Multivariable Adjusted<sup>b</sup></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.845 (0.823 to 0.867)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.901 (0.874 to 0.929)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.904 (0.877 to 0.932)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WASO</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.033 (1.027 to 1.039)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.020 (1.013 to 1.028)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.019 (1.012 to 1.027)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SFI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.176 (1.091 to 1.267)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.092 (1.000 to 1.192)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.050</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.078 (0.987 to 1.177)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ArI-Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.097 (1.069 to 1.125)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.048 (1.017 to 1.079)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.036 (1.005 to 1.068)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ArI-REM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.038 (1.014 to 1.064)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.031 (1.002 to 1.061)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.021 (0.991 to 1.051)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.174</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ArI-NREM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.090 (1.065 to 1.116)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.042 (1.014 to 1.071)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.032 (1.004 to 1.062)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: *Per 5-unit increased. The results between SE, WASO, SFI and hypertension were based on 5804 individuals. The results between ArI-Total, ArI-REM, ArI-NREM and hypertension was based on 5642 individuals. <sup>a</sup>Each individual sleep fragmentation variables including ArI-Total, ArI-REM, ArI-NREM, SFI, SE and WASO was adjusted for age, gender, race, BMI, smoking status, alcohol use, diabetes mellitus, sleep duration, benzodiazepine use, triglyceride and total cholesterol. <sup>b</sup>Adjusted for a+ AHI.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: AHI, apnea hypopnea index; ArI, arousal index; BMI, body mass index; 95% CI, 95% confidence interval; NREM, non-rapid eye movement; OR, odds ratio; REM, rapid eye movement; SE, sleep efficiency; SFI, sleep fragmentation index; WASO, wake after sleep onset.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Fragmented Sleep Parameters and SBP/DBP</title>
        <p>The correlations between each individual fragmented sleep parameter and SBP/DBP were also determined using multivariable linear regression analysis. ArI-Total (β 0.094; 95% CI 0.041–0.146; P&lt;0.001), ArI-NREM (β 0.080; 95% CI 0.032–0.128; P=0.001), ArI-REM (β 0.061; 95% CI 0.010–0.112; P=0.018), and WASO (β 0.014; 95% CI 0.002–0.026; P=0.022) were positively correlated with SBP, while SE (β −0.126; 95% CI −0.178 to −0.075; P&lt;0.001) was negatively associated with SBP. In addition, ArI-Total (β 0.033; 95% CI 0.002–0.064; P=0.034), ArI-NREM (β 0.029; 95% CI 0.001–0.057; P=0.041) and ArI-REM (β 0.047; 95% CI 0.018–0.077; P=0.002) were significantly correlated with DBP (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Univariable and Multivariable Linear Regression Analysis for Sleep Fragmentation Associated with SBP and DBP</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variables</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Unadjusted</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Multivariable Adjusted<sup>a</sup></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Multivariable Adjusted<sup>b</sup></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">β (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">β (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">β (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> SE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.243 (−0.290 to −0.196)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.131 (−0.182 to −0.080)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.126 (−0.178 to −0.075)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> WASO</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041 (0.029 to 0.052)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015 (0.003 to 0.028)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014 (0.002 to 0.026)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> SFI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.103 (−0.039 to 0.245)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.155</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.058 (−0.209 to 0.093)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.449</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.079 (−0.230 to 0.073)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.307</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ArI-Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.181 (0.134 to 0.229)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.107 (0.056 to 0.158)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.094 (0.041 to 0.146)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ArI-REM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.090 (0.043 to 0.136)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.074 (0.025 to 0.124)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061 (0.010 to 0.112)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ArI-NREM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.164 (0.121 to 0.208)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.092 (0.045 to 0.139)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.080 (0.032 to 0.128)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DBP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> SE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013 (−0.016 to 0.041)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.392</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.015 (−0.045 to 0.014)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.312</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.014 (−0.044 to 0.016)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.368</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> WASO</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.013 (−0.020 to −0.006)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.003 (−0.010 to 0.004)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.444</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.003 (−0.010 to 0.004)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.379</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> SFI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.070 (−0.155 to 0.015)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.106</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.054 (−0.141 to 0.034)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.231</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.061 (−0.149 to 0.027)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.174</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ArI-Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.059 (0.031 to 0.088)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039 (0.009 to 0.069)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033 (0.002 to 0.064)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ArI-REM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.099 (0.071 to 0.127)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.052 (0.023 to 0.081)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047 (0.018 to 0.077)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ArI-NREM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041 (0.014 to 0.067)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030 (0.003 to 0.058)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029 (0.001 to 0.057)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: The results between SE, WASO, SFI and SBP/DBP were based on 5691 individuals. The results between ArI-Total, ArI-REM, ArI-NREM and SBP/DBP was based on 5536 individuals. <sup>a</sup>Each individual sleep fragmentation variables including ArI-Total, ArI-REM, ArI-NREM, SFI, SE and WASO was adjusted for age, gender, race, BMI, smoking status, alcohol use, diabetes mellitus, sleep duration, benzodiazepine use, triglyceride and total cholesterol. <sup>b</sup>Adjusted for a+ AHI.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0006"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: AHI, apnea hypopnea index; ArI, arousal index; BMI, body mass index; 95% CI, 95% confidence interval; DBP, diastolic blood pressure; NREM, non-rapid eye movement; REM, rapid eye movement; SBP, systolic blood pressure; SE, sleep efficiency; SFI, sleep fragmentation index; WASO, wake after sleep onset.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2004">
        <title>Interaction Analysis</title>
        <p>Individuals with SDB may experience micro-arousal. Therefore, we investigated the association between fragmented sleep parameters and hypertension stratified by SDB (AHI ≥5 events/h vs AHI &lt;5 events/h). We further explored the relationship between fragmented sleep parameters and hypertension stratified by age (≥60 vs &lt;60), gender (males vs females) and alcohol use (yes vs no). No significant interaction was found in these analyses (P<sub>interaction</sub> &gt; 0.05) (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=337932.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplement Tables 1</ext-link></underline>–<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=337932.docx" ext-link-type="uri">4</ext-link></underline>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In this large community-based study, we investigated the cross-sectional associations between fragmented sleep parameters and hypertension prevalence. Fragmented sleep variables, including ArI-Total, ArI-NREM, SE, and WASO, were significantly associated with the prevalence of hypertension. Moreover, ArI-Total, ArI-NREM and ArI-REM were positively correlated with both SBP and DBP, and increased SE was associated with a lower SBP.</p>
      <p>Fragmented sleep usually refers to arousals over the course of the entire sleep period. Physical and mental diseases as well as lifestyle habits such as exercising before bedtime, long naps during the day, alcohol use, caffeine consumption and a poor sleep environment may lead to fragmented sleep.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> SDB accompanied by micro-arousal also contributes to fragmented sleep.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Previous studies have shown that fragmented sleep promotes obesity in mice,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> and this association has also been found in humans.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Several studies have explored the relationship between fragmented sleep and blood pressure. Morrell et al found that SFI was associated with a high level of awake SBP, but they found no significant association between the SFI and awake SBP after adjusting for AHI.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> Doyle et al found that SE was positively associated with average daytime SBP, but not DBP, using wrist actigraphy.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> In the present study, we also investigated the correlations between fragmented sleep parameters and SBP and DBP. Our results showed that SE and WASO were associated with SBP, but not with DBP, based on PSG records. In addition, no significant associations were found between SFI and SBP and DBP. Ramos et al revealed that a 10% reduction in SE was associated with a 7.5% increase in hypertension prevalence based on wrist actigraphy.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> In our study, SE and WASO were significantly associated with the prevalence of hypertension. Our results also indicated that elevated ArI-Total and ArI-NREM increased the risk of hypertension. Furthermore, we found that ArI was positively correlated with both SBP and DBP in total sleep time, NREM sleep, and REM sleep. Our findings showed that individuals with fragmented sleep had a higher level of SBP/DBP and a higher prevalence of hypertension. Improving fragmented sleep may aid in controlling human blood pressure and decreasing the risk of hypertension.</p>
      <p>The relationship between hypertension and sleep disturbances is complex. Some conditions such as age, gender, SDB and alcohol use may contribute to both sleep disorder and hypertension which may be the mediate or confounders.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Previous studies have shown that SDB is a risk factor for hypertension.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> SDB may be accompanied by micro-arousal, which may further lead to fragmented sleep. AHI is usually used to assess the severity of SDB.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Our multicollinearity analysis revealed that AHI had some effect on ArI. Fragmented sleep parameters, including ArI-Total, ArI-NREM, ArI-REM, SE, and WASO, remained significantly associated with the prevalence of hypertension whether we adjusted for AHI in the multivariable analysis. Interaction analysis stratified by SDB and non-SDB showed no significant interaction when exploring the associations between each fragmented sleep variable and hypertension. Furthermore, no significant interaction was found when performed the subgroup analysis stratified by age, gender and alcohol use.</p>
      <p>The mechanisms underlying the association between fragmented sleep and hypertension are not fully understood. It is possible that fragmented sleep increases the activity of the sympathetic nervous system, which then further contributes to elevated blood pressure.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> Fragmented sleep is also associated with decreased physical activity, insulin resistance, obesity, and increased inflammation.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23–26</xref> In addition, fragmented sleep may increase the body’s stress response and lead to short sleep, poor sleep quality, and more daytime naps, all of which may contribute to high blood pressure.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27–29</xref></p>
      <p>The present study has several strengths. Our analysis was based on a large community population from the SHHS datasets, and all fragmented sleep parameters were objectively monitored using PSG. We investigated the association between fragmented sleep and hypertension in total sleep time, NREM sleep, and REM sleep. However, there are several potential limitations to the study that should be noted. First, we found a cross-sectional association between fragmented sleep and hypertension, but the causal relationship requires further study. Second, a single-night PSG may not fully represent an individual’s sleep characteristics. Wrist actigraphy has an advantage as it allows for multiple sleep monitoring. Thirdly, the definition of hypertension in our study was based on the blood pressure measurement and information about antihypertensive treatment. It is difficult to identify the masked hypertension in our study. Ambulatory blood pressure monitoring may be a useful measurement method.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> In SHHS, scorers reviewed the record, on an epoch by epoch basis (on screen), marking each sleep stage, each arousal, and each respiratory event. All the sleep technicians and investigators were trained and the portable monitor were corrected in SHHS study, but the information bias could not be completely avoided. Finally, as our findings were based on middle-aged and older individuals, they may not extrapolate to the entire population.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>In conclusion, our study provides evidence that middle-aged and older individuals with fragmented sleep have an increased risk of hypertension. Elevated ArI-Total, ArI-NREM, and ArI-REM were positively correlated with high SBP and DBP. Our results indicate that ArI-Total, ArI-NREM, SE, and WASO were significantly associated with the prevalence of hypertension. Improving fragmented sleep may help control high blood pressure. The causal relationship between fragmented sleep and hypertension also deserves further investigation.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We appreciate the Brigham and Women’s Hospital for sharing the Datasets of Sleep Heart Health Study (SHHS). The Sleep Heart Health Study (SHHS) was supported by National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute cooperative agreements U01HL53916 (University of California, Davis), U01HL53931 (New York University), U01HL53934 (University of Minnesota), U01HL53937 and U01HL64360 (Johns Hopkins University), U01HL53938 (University of Arizona), U01HL53940 (University of Washington), U01HL53941 (Boston University), and U01HL63463 (Case Western Reserve University). The National Sleep Research Resource was supported by the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (R24 HL114473, 75N92019R002). SHHS is particularly grateful to the members of these cohorts who agreed to participate in SHHS as well. SHHS further recognizes all the investigators and staff who have contributed to its success. A list of SHHS investigators, staff and their participating institutions is available on the SHHS website, <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.25822/ghy8-ks59" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.25822/ghy8-ks59</ext-link></underline>.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Author Responsibility Information</title>
      <p>All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation, or in all these areas; took part in drafting, revising or critically reviewing the article; gave final approval of the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0007">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>All the authors declare no conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Forouzanfar</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roth</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Global burden of hypertension and systolic blood pressure of at least 110 to 115 mm Hg, 1990–2015</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>317</volume>:<fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>182</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2016.19043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28097354</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>WHO</collab>. <article-title>Hypertension</article-title>; <year>2021</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xlink:href="https://wwwwhoint/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/hypertension" ext-link-type="uri">https://wwwwhoint/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/hypertension</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>December</month>
<day>24</day>, 2021</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Oparil</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Acelajado</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bakris</surname>
<given-names>GL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Dis Primers</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>18014</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrdp.2018.14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29565029</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Valenzuela</surname>
<given-names>PL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carrera-Bastos</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Galvez</surname>
<given-names>BG</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Lifestyle interventions for the prevention and treatment of hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>275</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41569-020-00437-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33037326</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Carey</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Muntner</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bosworth</surname>
<given-names>HB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whelton</surname>
<given-names>PK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevention and control of hypertension: JACC health promotion series</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>1278</fpage>–<lpage>1293</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2018.07.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30190007</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yan</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dong</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Reverse-dipper pattern of blood pressure may predict lacunar infarction in patients with essential hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1022</fpage>–<lpage>1025</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ene.12659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25614275</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>WZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>YC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zeng</surname>
<given-names>ZQ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and hypertension</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Breath</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>351</fpage>–<lpage>356</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11325-019-01907-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31402441</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Palagini</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bruno</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gemignani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baglioni</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghiadoni</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Riemann</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep loss and hypertension: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Pharm Des</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>2409</fpage>–<lpage>2419</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1381612811319130009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23173590</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lo</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Woo</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tam</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Subjective sleep quality, blood pressure, and hypertension: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Hypertens</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>592</fpage>–<lpage>605</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jch.13220</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zeng</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The association between sleep duration and hypertension: a meta and study sequential analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Hum Hypertens</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>621</fpage>–<lpage>626</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32587332</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sotres-Alvarez</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gallo</surname>
<given-names>LC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Associations of sleep-disordered breathing and insomnia with incident hypertension and diabetes. The Hispanic community health study/study of latinos</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>203</volume>:<fpage>356</fpage>–<lpage>365</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201912-2330OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32758008</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sadeh</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The role and validity of actigraphy in sleep medicine: an update</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>267</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2010.10.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21237680</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Doyle</surname>
<given-names>CY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruiz</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Associations between objective sleep and ambulatory blood pressure in a community sample</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychosom Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>545</fpage>–<lpage>556</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PSY.0000000000000711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31083055</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Quan</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Howard</surname>
<given-names>BV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Iber</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The sleep heart health study: design, rationale, and methods</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1077</fpage>–<lpage>1085</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9493915</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Abad</surname>
<given-names>VC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guilleminault</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Diagnosis and treatment of sleep disorders: a brief review for clinicians</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Dialogues Clin Neurosci</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>371</fpage>–<lpage>388</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22033666</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Smurra</surname>
<given-names>MV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dury</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aubert</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rodenstein</surname>
<given-names>DO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liistro</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep fragmentation: comparison of two definitions of short arousals during sleep in OSAS patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Respir J</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>723</fpage>–<lpage>727</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.01.17407230</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11401070</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carreras</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Chronic sleep fragmentation promotes obesity in young adult mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Obesity (Silver Spring)</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>758</fpage>–<lpage>762</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/oby.20616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24039209</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Koolhaas</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kocevska</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Te Lindert</surname>
<given-names>BHW</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Objectively measured sleep and body mass index: a prospective bidirectional study in middle-aged and older adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2019.01.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30897455</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Morrell</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Finn</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peppard</surname>
<given-names>PE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Badr</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Young</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep fragmentation, awake blood pressure, and sleep-disordered breathing in a population-based study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>162</volume>:<fpage>2091</fpage>–<lpage>2096</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/ajrccm.162.6.9904008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11112120</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ramos</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weng</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wallace</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep patterns and hypertension using actigraphy in the Hispanic community health study/study of latinos</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>153</volume>:<fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chest.2017.09.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28970105</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Haas</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Foster</surname>
<given-names>GL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nieto</surname>
<given-names>FJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Age-dependent associations between sleep-disordered breathing and hypertension: importance of discriminating between systolic/diastolic hypertension and isolated systolic hypertension in the Sleep Heart Health Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Circulation</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>111</volume>:<fpage>614</fpage>–<lpage>621</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.CIR.0000154540.62381.CF</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15699282</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sanders</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Newman</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haggerty</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep and sleep-disordered breathing in adults with predominantly mild obstructive airway disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>167</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.2203046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12502472</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cox</surname>
<given-names>NS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pepin</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holland</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Greater sleep fragmentation is associated with less physical activity in adults with cystic fibrosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cardiopulm Rehabil Prev</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>E11</fpage>–<lpage>E14</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/HCR.0000000000000363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30252784</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hursel</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rutters</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gonnissen</surname>
<given-names>HK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martens</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Westerterp-Plantenga</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of sleep fragmentation in healthy men on energy expenditure, substrate oxidation, physical activity, and exhaustion measured over 48 h in a respiratory chamber</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Clin Nutr</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>94</volume>:<fpage>804</fpage>–<lpage>808</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3945/ajcn.111.017632</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21795436</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>van den Berg</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knvistingh Neven</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tulen</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Actigraphic sleep duration and fragmentation are related to obesity in the elderly: the Rotterdam study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Obes (Lond)</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>1083</fpage>–<lpage>1090</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ijo.2008.57</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18414418</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yan</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fan</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The association between sleep efficiency and diabetes mellitus in community-dwelling individuals with or without sleep-disordered breathing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Diabetes</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>223</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1753-0407.12987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31503406</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Castro-Diehl</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Diez Roux</surname>
<given-names>AV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Redline</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration and quality in relation to autonomic nervous system measures: the multi-ethnic study of atherosclerosis (Mesa)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>1927</fpage>–<lpage>1940</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.6218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27568797</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ross</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Larson</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carter</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep efficiency and nocturnal hemodynamic dipping in young, normotensive adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>307</volume>:<fpage>R888</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpregu.00211.2014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25031228</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cao</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shen</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The effects of midday nap duration on the risk of hypertension in a middle-aged and older Chinese population: a preliminary evidence from the Tongji-Dongfeng Cohort Study, China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Hypertens</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<page-range>1993–8; discussion 1998</page-range>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/HJH.0000000000000291</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Peacock</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Diaz</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Viera</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schwartz</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shimbo</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Unmasking masked hypertension: prevalence, clinical implications, diagnosis, correlates and future directions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Hum Hypertens</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>521</fpage>–<lpage>528</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jhh.2014.9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24573133</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
