<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35250321</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">8893155</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">346851</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S346851</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Mediating Effect of Sleep Quality on the Relationship Between Electronic Screen Media Use and Academic Performance Among College Students</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Mao et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Mao et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mao</surname>
            <given-names>Yajun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xie</surname>
            <given-names>Biyao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1884-4960</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Baixin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6572-3969</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Cai</surname>
            <given-names>Yilin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>Jiahan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Jiansheng</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shao</surname>
            <given-names>Ruifan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6276-9104</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Yun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Sleep Medicine, Shantou University Mental Health Center, Shantou University Medical College</institution>, <addr-line>Shantou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Guangdong Province</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Sleep Medicine Center, Shantou University Medical College</institution>, <addr-line>Shantou</addr-line>, <addr-line>Guangdong Province</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Yun Li, Email s_liyun@stu.edu.cn</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>27</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <fpage>323</fpage>
      <lpage>334</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>07</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>01</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2022 Mao et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Mao et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Objective</title>
          <p>We aimed to examine the effects of sleep quality on the association between pre-bedtime electronic screen media use for entertainment and academic performance among college students. We hypothesized that sleep quality mediates the association between pre-bedtime electronic screen media entertainment use and academic performance among college students.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>This was a cross-sectional survey with 1385 participants (age 19.99 ± 1.4 years [range, 17–24 years] and 36.82% males) conducted at Shantou University. The levels of academic performance were based on self-reported academic class ranking from average grades of their last final major examinations. Poor sleep quality was defined as a total score of the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index &gt;7. The pre-bedtime prolonged electronic screen media use for entertainment (PESM-E) was defined as the use of electronic screen media for entertainment longer than 60 minutes/night after 10:00 p.m. during the past 6 months.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>College students with pre-bedtime PESM-E were 1.28-fold more likely to have a poor academic performance than those who used electronic screen media less than 60 minutes (95% confidence interval [CI]: 1.04–1.57, P=0.020). Furthermore, pre-bedtime PESM-E was significantly associated with poor sleep quality (adjusted odds ratio [AOR]=1.87, 95% CI: 1.27–2.74, P=0.001) after controlling for confounders. Mediation model showed that poor sleep quality accounted for 53.08% of the effect of pre-bedtime PESM-E on lower levels of academic performance (Sobel Z=2.04, P=0.041).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>Pre-bedtime PESM-E is associated with poor academic performance in college students, and this association is mediated by poor sleep quality. Our findings highlight the importance of limiting the use of electronic screen media before bedtime in college students.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>poor sleep quality</kwd>
        <kwd>sleep</kwd>
        <kwd>academic performance</kwd>
        <kwd>electronic screen use</kwd>
        <kwd>college students</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Guangdong University Students Innovation and Entrepreneurship Training Program</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>This study was supported by the Guangdong University Students Innovation and Entrepreneurship Training Program (201910560138 and 202010560040), National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 81970087) and Guangdong Province Science and Technology Special Fund Project (200115165870512).</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="1"/>
        <table-count count="6"/>
        <ref-count count="65"/>
        <page-count count="12"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Electronic screen media use has become one of the dominant forms of entertainment around the world, especially among college students.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Electronic screen media includes computers, mobile phones, game consoles, Kindle, and televisions. A study in 2017 showed that 85% of 18- to 29-year-old adolescents are smartphone subscribers,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> and 40–80% of adolescents use electronic screen media for periods that exceed the recommended usage duration of 2 hours/day.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Prolonged electronic screen media use (PESM) especially before bedtime has been found to be associated with a wide range of adverse physical and psychological health outcomes, such as depression,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> anxiety,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> obesity,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> poor sleep quality<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> and poor academic performance.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10−14</xref></p>
      <p>Recent studies have shown that the PESM affects cognitive function<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> and academic performance,<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> and may ultimately lead to poor work accomplishment and career achievement in adulthood.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> For example, adolescents who use electronic screen media for over 7 hours per day have 1.4-fold odds of achieving poor academic performance.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> A meta-analysis also showed that watching television and playing video games are the most detrimental activities for affecting academic performance, especially among adolescents.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Furthermore, a recent study focusing on children and adolescents demonstrates that PESM is associated with poor academic performance, and this association is mediated by bedtime,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> suggesting a potential complex association among sleep, PESM, and academic performance.</p>
      <p>PESM is associated with various sleep problems, such as insufficient sleep,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> poor sleep quality,<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19–21</xref> eveningness chronotype<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> and excessive daytime sleepiness.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Not only does PESM have a negative impact on sleep throughout the day,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> PESM before bedtime also negatively affects sleep.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> It has been reported that electronic screen media use for one hour or more before bedtime is associated with both difficulty falling asleep and unrefreshing sleep.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Furthermore, findings of a meta-analysis showed that pre-bedtime PESM increases risk of short sleep duration 2.17-fold compared to non-users,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> and previous studies have shown that electronic screen media use is associated with poor academic performance.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></p>
      <p>Poor sleep quality is common among college students.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> A few studies have shown that poor sleep quality leads to lower levels of academic performance<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26–28</xref> by impairing memory and concentration.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29–32</xref> However, only a limited number of studies have examined the associations between sleep quality, electronic screen media use and academic performance among college students. Furthermore, most studies have focused on the use of electronic screen media throughout the whole day,<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> while few have focused on the use of electronic screen media before bedtime, which may have a greater impact on sleep.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></p>
      <p>Given the associations between sleep quality and academic performance, electronic screen media use and academic performance, as well as academic performance and sleep quality, we therefore conducted this cross-sectional study to examine the effects of sleep quality on the association between pre-bedtime PESM and academic performance among college students. As PESM for the purposes of studying and entertainment may have different effects on sleep and academic performance, we focused on pre-bedtime PESM for entertainment (PESM-E) in this study. We hypothesized that sleep quality mediates the association between pre-bedtime electronic screen media use for entertainment and academic performance among college students.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Study Design</title>
        <p>The Shantou College Students Sleep Cohort (STCSSC) is a study designed to investigate sleep problems (ie, poor sleep quality, insomnia symptoms, chronotype and excessive daytime sleepiness) as risk factors for depression, anxiety and poor academic performance. In this study, a voluntary response sample of Shantou University students were selected to complete a series of online questionnaires related to sleep, mood, living habits and academic performance by using the WeChat-based survey program, Questionnaire Star, in early May and late October of 2019. As college students usually have their final major examinations for spring and fall semesters from the end of June to early July and end of December to early January, respectively, and in order to reduce academic stress-related sleep and mood problems, we chose early May and early October (ie, 2 months before the final examinations) to conduct this survey. This study was registered in the Chinese Clinical Trial Registry (ChiCTR2100051755). The study was approved by the Institutional Review Board of the Shantou University Mental Health Center (SUMHC20190510). All participants signed informed consents online and were informed that their personal information would be confidential. This study complied with the Declaration of Helsinki.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p>According to the cross-sectional survey sample size calculation formula, taking the average prevalence of poor sleep quality among college students from previous studies (22.31%)<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> to be the expected proportion of poor sleep quality among college students, and using α set at 0.05 and the allowable error (δ) set as 0.025, a sample size of 1065 students was calculated for this study. Estimating 10% of the questionnaires to be invalid, we needed at least 1183 students to be surveyed.</p>
        <p>In this online survey, a total of 2098 students were initially approached. Among those, 1517 subjects completed the questionnaires (total response rate: 72.31%). In order to improve the reliability of this survey, we excluded 132 participants whose amount of time to complete the survey was shorter than 8.33 minutes, which was the average completion time of the overall sample minus 2 standard deviations. Finally, a total of 1385 participants were included in this study, and the average completed time was 17.82 ± 8.89 minutes.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Sleep Assessments</title>
        <p>The Chinese version of the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) questionnaire was used to assess the subjects’ habitual sleep quality.<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> A higher PSQI score indicates worse sleep quality.<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> In this study, we used a PSQI &gt;7 to define poor sleep quality.<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> The Cronbach’s alpha was 0.74 in the present study. The habitual bedtime and total sleep time were extracted from the PSQI. According to the National Sleep Foundation, a sleep duration between 7 to 9 hours per day is the recommended sleep duration for young adults.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> Furthermore, based on previous studies, short sleep duration was defined as sleep for less than 7 hours per night.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> Thus, in this study short sleep duration was defined as a habitual total sleep time of less than 7 hours per night. Bedtime later than 0:00 a.m. was regarded as a meaningful clinical cut-off point for the general population.<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> However, late bedtime has not been well-defined in college students. Considering this situation, using a statistical approach, the median value as the cut-off point (00:00 a.m.) can be used as an alternative option.<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> We therefore defined late bedtime as a habitual bedtime later than 00:00 a.m. (the median bedtime in this survey).</p>
        <p>The Morningness-Eveningness Questionnaire (MEQ) was used to evaluate the morningness and eveningness chronotype of the participants.<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> An eveningness chronotype was defined as a score between 16 to 41, intermediate chronotype was defined as an MEQ score between 42 to 58, and morningness chronotype was defined as an MEQ score between 59 to 86.<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> The Cronbach’s alpha was 0.82 in the present study.</p>
        <p>The Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS) was used to assess daytime sleepiness.<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> A higher total ESS score indicates more daytime sleepiness. We used a total ESS score &gt;10 to define excessive daytime sleepiness.<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> The Cronbach’s alpha was 0.82 in the present study.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Academic Performance</title>
        <p>The levels of academic performance were based on self-reported academic class ranking from the average grades of their last final major examinations, and classified into 4 levels: 1) the 1<sup>st</sup> quartile (top 25%), 2) 2<sup>nd</sup> quartile (26–50%), 3) 3<sup>rd</sup> quartile (51–75%) and 4) 4<sup>th</sup> quartile (the worst 25%). If a student completed his/her online survey in May, his/her corresponding final major examinations should have been in December or January of the previous year; in other words, if a student completed his/her online survey in October, his/her corresponding final major examinations were in July of the same year.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2005">
        <title>Pre-Bedtime Electronic Screen Media Use</title>
        <p>Pre-bedtime electronic screen media use was based on a self-reported question: How long do you usually use electronic screen media for entertainment (i.e., read e-books, play video games, watch videos, do online shopping, read electronic news and use social networking sites/applications) after 10:00 p.m. in the past 6 months when you were at school? (≤15 minutes, 15-30 minutes, 30-60 minutes, &gt;60 minutes). After searching the relevant literature, a pre-bedtime PESM-E had not been well-defined in previous studies. Considering this situation, using a statistical approach, the median value (&gt;60 minutes) as the cut-off point can be an alternative option.<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> We therefore used longer than the median duration between 10:00 p.m. to the median bedtime (0:00 a.m.) of the overall subjects as the cut-off point (ie, &gt;60 minutes) to define pre-bedtime PESM-E in this study. Furthermore, all participants needed to answer the types (ie, read e-books, play video games, watch videos, do online shopping, read electronic news and use social networking sites/applications) and frequency (ranking from 1 [never] to 5 [5–7 days/week]) of screen-based activities before bedtime. In this study, a frequency of screen-based activity before bedtime ≥3 times throughout the whole week was defined as frequent use.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2006">
        <title>Psychological Assessments</title>
        <p>The Beck Depression Inventory (BDI) was used to assess depressive symptoms. Higher total BDI scores indicate more severe depressive symptoms.<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> In this study, we used a total score of BDI&gt; 13 to define depressive symptoms.<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> The Cronbach’s alpha was 0.89 in the present study.</p>
        <p>The Beck Anxiety Inventory (BAI) was used to assess somatic symptoms of anxiety.<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> Higher BAI scores indicate more severe anxiety symptoms. We used a total score of BAI&gt;9 to define anxiety symptoms.<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> The Cronbach’s alpha was 0.91 in the present study.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2007">
        <title>Other Measures</title>
        <p>Sociodemographic characteristics, ie, gender, age, major, self-reported height and weight, academic grade, financial situation satisfaction, and physical activity, were also collected. Body mass index (BMI) was calculated based on weight/ height (kg/m<sup>2</sup>). Physical activity was defined as exercise for more than 20 minutes twice a week during the past month. Smoking was defined as smoking at least once per day continuously for 6 months or more. Alcohol consumption was defined as drinking more than 50 mL of liquor or 200 mL of beer at least twice per week continuously for 6 months or more. Caffeine consumption was defined as drinking coffee, tea, cola and/or caffeinated energy drinks on most days.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2008">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>Data are presented as mean ± standard deviation for continuous variables, and percentage for categorical variables. Analysis of variance (ANOVA) for continuous variables and the χ<sup>2</sup> test for categorical variables were used to examine social-demographics, electronic screen media use, and sleep and psychological characteristics among students in different levels of academic performance. Cronbach’s alpha coefficients were used to assess the internal consistency of the scales/questionnaires.</p>
        <p>Multinomial ordinal/binary logistic regression was performed to assess the associations among sleep quality, pre-bedtime PESM-E and academic performance. In the regression models, age, gender, survey time and BMI were always entered in the models as covariates, while other relevant factors that may affect the academic performance were also entered as covariates (p-value of the comparison among students in different levels of academic performance was ≤ 0.100, <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Multicollinearity analysis was conducted to examine multicollinearity among the included covariates. A variance inflation factor (VIF) &gt;10 indicates multicollinearity. Based on multicollinearity analysis, values of VIF in all variables included in the regression model were &lt;10 (range from 1.07–1.24), which indicated that no multicollinearity was observed among these variables. Because total sleep time and bedtime were extracted from the PSQI, we did not adjust these two variables in regression models. Adjusted odds ratios (AORs) with 95% confidence intervals (95% CIs) are presented.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic, Electronic Screen Media Use, Sleep and Psychological Characteristics of the Included Subjects</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall<break/>(n=1385)</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Academic Performance Level</th><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">P</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1<sup>st</sup> Quartile (n=548)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2<sup>nd</sup> Quartile (n=437)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3<sup>rd</sup> Quartile (n=281)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4<sup>th</sup> Quartile (n=119)</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD/%</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Demographic characteristic</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Age, years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.99±1.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.92±1.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.97±1.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.04±1.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.23±1.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.149</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> BMI, kg/m<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.24± 2.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.14±2.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.11±2.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.37±2.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.84±2.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.024</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Gender (Male, n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">510, 36.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">173, 31.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">160, 36.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">117, 41.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60, 50.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt; 0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Grade</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Freshman (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">734, 53.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">288, 52.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">246, 56.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">146, 51.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54, 45.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.150</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sophomore (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">284, 20.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">124, 22.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75, 17.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64, 22.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21, 17.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Junior (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">270, 19.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103, 18.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83, 18.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52, 18.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32, 26.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Senior (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97, 7.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33, 6.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33, 7.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19, 6.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12, 10.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15, 1.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4, 0.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5, 1.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5, 1.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1, 0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.574</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol consumption (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20, 1.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6, 1.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10, 2.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3, 1.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1, 0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.356</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caffeine consumption (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">681, 49.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">261, 47.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">219, 50.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">138, 49.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63, 52.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.716</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major (Medicine, n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">708, 51.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">253, 46.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">223, 51.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">152, 54.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80, 67.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt; 0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Survey time (May, 2019, n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1025, 74.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">371, 67.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">339, 77.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">224, 79.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91, 76.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt; 0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Satisfaction for financial situation (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1088, 78.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">438,79.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">344, 78.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">222, 79.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84, 70.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.162</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical activity (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">704, 50.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">279, 50.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">226, 51.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">144, 51.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55, 46.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.760</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Pre-bedtime electronic screen media use</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Pre-bedtime PESM-E <sup>a</sup> (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">843, 60.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">310, 56.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">263, 60.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">188, 66.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82, 68.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.008</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Frequent user <sup>b</sup> of reading an e-book (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">408, 29.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">150, 27.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">132, 30.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87, 30.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39, 32.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.532</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Frequent user <sup>b</sup> of shopping online (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">299, 21.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">127, 23.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91, 20.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57, 20.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24, 20.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.708</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Frequent user <sup>b</sup> of reading electronic news (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">540, 38.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">215, 39.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">176, 40.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103, 36.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46, 38.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.809</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Frequent user <sup>b</sup> of playing video games (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">328, 23.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96, 17.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104, 23.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83, 29.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45, 37.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt; 0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Frequent user <sup>b</sup> of using social networking applications (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1210, 87.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">485, 88.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">372, 85.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">244, 86.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109, 91.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.201</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Frequent user <sup>b</sup> of watching video (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">670, 48.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">232, 42.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">230, 52.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">149, 53.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59, 49.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.003</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sleep characteristics</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Total sleep time, hour</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.77±0.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.81±0.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.75±0.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.79±0.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.54±0.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.045</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Short sleep duration <sup>c</sup> (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">609, 43.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">224, 40.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">196, 44.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">129, 45.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60, 50.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.195</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">00:02±62min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23:55±56min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">00:03±58min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">00:11±80min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">00:08±56min</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Late bedtime <sup>d</sup> (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">458, 33.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">168, 30.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">146, 33.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105, 37.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39, 32.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.282</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Poor sleep quality <sup>e</sup> (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">182, 13.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45, 8.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75, 17.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39, 13.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23, 19.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt; 0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> PSQI, scores</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.81±2.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.45±2.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.01±2.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.98±2.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.27±2.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt; 0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Excessive daytime sleepiness <sup>f</sup> (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">399, 28.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">138, 25.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">127, 29.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88, 31.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46, 38.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.018</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ESS, scores</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.33±4.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.03±3.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.42±3.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.54±3.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.90±4.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.096</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronotype</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Morningness <sup>g</sup> (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">160, 11.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81, 14.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42, 9.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25, 8.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12, 10.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.128</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Eveningness <sup>h</sup> (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">201, 14.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74, 13.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65, 14.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42, 14.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20, 16.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Intermediate <sup>i</sup> (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1024, 73.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">393, 71.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">330, 75.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">214, 76.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87, 73.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> MEQ, scores</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.52±7.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.18±7.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.35±7.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.76±7.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.89±7.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.041</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Psychological characteristics</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Anxiety symptoms <sup>j</sup> (n, %)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">260, 18.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98, 17.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86, 19.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50, 17.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26, 21.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.697</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  BAI, scores</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.47±5.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.17±5.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.59±6.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.64±6.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.02±7.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.403</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Depressive symptoms <sup>k</sup> (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">333, 24.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109, 19.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107,24.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77, 27.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40, 33.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.005</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  BDI, scores</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.94±7.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.21±7.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.88±7.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.56±7.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.03±9.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>a</sup>PESM-E before bedtime was defined as the use of electronic screen media for entertainment longer than 60 minutes/night after 10:00 p.m. during the past 6 months. <sup>b</sup>Frequency of screen-based activities before bedtime ≥3 days/week was defined as frequent use. <sup>c</sup>Short sleep duration was defined as habitual total sleep time extracted from PSQI &lt; 7 hours. <sup>d</sup>Late bedtime was defined as habitual bedtime extracted from PSQI later than 00:00 a.m. <sup>e</sup>Poor sleep quality was defined base on the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index &gt;7. <sup>f</sup>Excessive daytime sleepiness was defined based on the Epworth Sleepiness Scale score &gt;10. <sup>g</sup>Morningness chronotype was defined based on the Morningness-Eveningness Questionnaire scores between 59 to 86. <sup>h</sup>Eveningness chronotype was defined based on the Morningness-Eveningness Questionnaire scores between 16 to 41. <sup>i</sup>Intermediate chronotype was defined based on the Morningness-Eveningness Questionnaire scores between 42 to 58. <sup>j</sup> Anxiety symptoms were defined based on the Beck Anxiety Inventory scores &gt;9. <sup>k</sup>Depression symptoms were defined based on the Beck Depression Inventory scores &gt;13. P-values in bold indicate P&lt;0.100.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: BAI, Beck Anxiety Inventory; BDI, Beck Depression Inventory; BMI, body mass index; ESS, Epworth Sleepiness Scale; MEQ, Morningness-Eveningness Questionnaire; PESM-E, prolonged electronic screen media use for entertainment; PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index; SD, standard deviation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
        <p>A sequence of hierarchical logistic regression models, adjusting for age, gender, survey time, BMI and relevant factors, was used to determine the mediating effects of sleep quality on the relationship between pre-bedtime PESM-E and academic performance. Based on Baron and Kenny’s study,<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> the mediation model shows how the independent variable’s (ie, pre-bedtime PESM-E) causal effect can be apportioned into its indirect effect on a dependent variable (ie, academic performance) through the mediator (ie, poor sleep quality) and its direct effect on the dependent variable. As shown in <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>, path “a” represents the effect of the independent variable on the proposed mediator, whereas path “b” is the effect of the mediator on the dependent variable, adjusting for the independent variable. Path “c’” represents the direct effect of the independent variable on the dependent variable after controlling for the mediator. All of these paths would typically be quantified with unstandardized regression coefficients. The mediating effect through poor sleep quality can be quantified as <italic toggle="yes">ab/(ab + c’)</italic>.<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref> The Sobel Z test was used to assess the significance of the mediation effects.<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref> SPSS (version 22.0) was used for statistical analysis. A p-value ≤ 0.05 was used to determine statistical significance.<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Mediating effect of poor sleep quality on the association between pre-bedtime prolonged electronic screen media use for entertainment and academic performance. All models were adjusted for age, body mass index, gender, major, survey time, excessive daytime sleepiness, depressive symptoms and frequent user of playing video games and watching videos. <sup>d</sup>Pre-bedtime PESM-E was defined as an average use duration exceeding 60 min before 10:00 p.m. <sup>e</sup>poor sleep quality was defined based on a Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index &gt;7.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-323-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: β<italic toggle="yes"><sub>a</sub></italic>, effect of pre-bedtime PESM-E on poor sleep quality; β<italic toggle="yes"><sub>b</sub></italic>, effect of poor sleep quality on academic performance after adjusting for pre-bedtime PESM-E; β<italic toggle="yes"><sub>c’</sub></italic>, direct effect of pre-bedtime PESM-E on academic performance after controlling for poor sleep quality; β<italic toggle="yes"><sub>c</sub></italic>, effect of pre-bedtime PESM-E on academic performance; AOR, adjusted odds ratios; CI, confidence interval; PESM-E, prolonged electronic screen media use for entertainment; Path “a”, the effect of the independent variable on the proposed mediator; Path “b”, the effect of the mediator on the dependent variable; Path “<italic toggle="yes">c’”</italic>, the direct effect of the independent variable on the dependent variable after controlling for the mediator; Path “c”, the total effect of the independent variable on the dependent variable.</attrib></fig></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Sample Characteristics</title>
        <p>A summary of sample characteristics is presented in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Participants had a mean age of 19.99 ± 1.40 years (range, 17–24 years) and mean BMI of 20.24 ± 2.52 kg/m<sup>2</sup>, and 36.82% were males. The prevalence of poor sleep quality and PESM-E before bedtime were 13.14% and 60.87%, respectively. Among the 1385 students included, 548 (39.57%), 437 (31.55%), 281 (20.29%) and 119 (8.59%) students reported within the 1<sup>st</sup>, 2<sup>nd</sup>, 3<sup>rd</sup>, and 4<sup>th</sup> quartile of academic performance, respectively. Furthermore, 20 (1.44%), 165 (11.91%), 357 (25.78%) and 843 (60.87%) students reported using electronic screen for entertainment before bedtime for ≤15 minutes, 15–30 minutes, 30–60 minutes and &gt;60 minutes, respectively. Significant differences in BMI, gender, survey time, major, pre-bedtime PESM-E, pre-bedtime video gaming and pre-bedtime watching videos, poor sleep quality, excessive daytime sleepiness and depressive symptoms were observed among different academic performance levels (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). No significant differences were observed regarding social-demographic characteristics (all p&gt;0.300) between the overall students who completed the questionnaire (n=1517) and the sample included in the final analyses (n=1385).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Mediation Analysis</title>
        <p>As shown in <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, binary logistic regression showed that pre-bedtime PESM-E was significantly associated with poor sleep quality (AOR=1.87, 95% CI: 1.27–2.74, P=0.001, Model 1) after adjusting for age, BMI, gender, major, survey time, excessive daytime sleepiness, depressive symptoms and frequent playing of video games and watching videos. Furthermore, poor sleep quality was significantly associated with lower levels of academic performance (AOR=1.53, 95% CI: 1.14–2.06, P=0.005, Model 2) after adjusting for age, BMI, gender, major, survey time, excessive daytime sleepiness, depressive symptoms, frequent playing of video games and watching videos. Moreover, the multinomial ordinal logistic regression model showed that pre-bedtime PESM-E was significantly associated with lower levels of academic performance (AOR=1.28, 95% CI: 1.04–1.57, P=0.020, Model 3) after adjusting for age, BMI, gender, major, survey time, excessive daytime sleepiness, depressive symptoms, frequent playing of video games and watching videos. When sleep quality was added to Model 3, the AOR for pre-bedtime PESM-E on academic performance decreased from 1.28 to 1.25, which suggested that sleep quality mediated the association between pre-bedtime PESM-E and academic performance.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Associations Between PESM-E Before Bedtime, Poor Sleep Quality and Academic Performance</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Path</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dependent Variable</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Independent Variable</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AOR</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">a</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor sleep quality <sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-bedtime PESM-E <sup>b</sup><break/>(ref: Non pre-bedtime PESM-E)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27–2.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic performance level</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor sleep quality <sup>a</sup><break/>(ref: Non poor sleep quality)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14–2.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">c</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic performance level</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-bedtime PESM-E <sup>b</sup><break/>(ref: Non pre-bedtime PESM-E)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04–1.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">c ’</italic></td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Academic performance level</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-bedtime PESM-E<sup>b</sup><break/>(ref: Non pre-bedtime PESM-E)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01–1.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">b</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor sleep quality <sup>a</sup><break/>(ref: Non poor sleep quality)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11–2.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: All models were adjusted for age, body mass index, gender, major, survey time, excessive daytime sleepiness, depressive symptoms and frequent playing of video games and watching of videos. Path “a”, the effect of the independent variable on the proposed mediator. Path “b”, the effect of mediator on the dependent variable. Path “c’ ”, the direct effect of the independent variable on the dependent variable after controlling the mediator. Path “c”, the total effect of the independent variable on the dependent variable. <sup>a</sup>Poor sleep quality was defined base on the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index &gt;7. <sup>b</sup>PESM-E before bedtime was defined as the use of electronic screen media for entertainment longer than 60 minutes/night after 10:00 p.m. during the past 6 months.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: PESM-E, prolonged electronic screen media use for entertainment; AOR, adjusted odds ratios; CI, confidence interval.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
        <p>In order to further examine the potential mediating effect of sleep quality on the association between pre-bedtime PESM-E and academic performance, the Sobel Z test was conducted. As shown in <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>, the mediating effect size of poor sleep quality was 53.08% for the association between pre-bedtime PESM-E and academic performance (Sobel Z=2.04, P=0.041), which suggested that poor sleep quality accounted for 53.08% of the association between pre-bedtime PESM-E and academic performance. Considering the potential influence of smoking, alcohol and caffeine consumption on sleep quality and academic performance, we further adjusted the aforementioned factors in sensitivity analysis, resulting in similar and significant findings (Sobel Z=1.96, P=0.050, P<sub>M</sub>=51.64%).</p>
        <p>Furthermore, because depressive symptoms were more severe in students with poor academic performance, moderated mediation analyses were conducted to examine whether depressive symptoms moderated the associations between pre-bedtime PESM-E, poor sleep quality and poor academic performance. After controlling for potential confounding factors, results of the moderated mediation analyses for pre-bedtime PESM-E and academic performance showed that interaction terms in pre-bedtime PESM-E × depressive symptoms in path a (interaction-P=0.717), pre-bedtime PESM-E × depressive symptoms in path c’ (interaction-P=0.298) and poor sleep quality × depressive symptoms in path b (interaction-P=0.838) were not significant, indicating no moderating effect of depressive symptoms on the association between pre-bedtime PESM-E, poor sleep quality and poor academic performance. Moreover, students with pre-bedtime PESM-E had higher percentages of frequent playing of video games (29.54% vs 14.58%, P&lt;0.001) and frequent watching of videos (36.53% vs 55.99%, P&lt;0.001). However, interaction analyses showed that neither frequent playing of video games (pre-bedtime PESM-E × frequent playing of video games, interaction-P=0.182) nor frequent video watching (pre-bedtime PESM-E × frequent video watching, interaction-P=0.607) moderated the associations between pre-bedtime PESM-E and poor academic performance.</p>
        <p>Besides sleep quality, pre-bedtime PESM-E may also associate with insufficient sleep and late bedtimes. Therefore, we also used short sleep duration or late bedtime instead of sleep quality in the mediation model and found neither total sleep time nor bedtime mediated the association between pre-bedtime PESM-E and academic performance in college students (<underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=346851.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Supplement</ext-link></underline>). Regarding excessive daytime sleepiness, no significant association between PESM-E before bedtime and excessive daytime sleepiness was observed (AOR=1.21, 95% CI: 0.94–1.57, P=0.148), suggesting excessive daytime sleepiness did not mediate the association between pre-bedtime PESM-E and poor academic performance.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>To our knowledge, this is the first study examining the mediating effects of sleep quality on the association between pre-bedtime PESM-E and academic performance in college students. The findings of our study suggest that poor sleep quality mediates the association between pre-bedtime PESM-E and academic performance. Specifically, poor sleep quality accounts for 53.08% of the effect of pre-bedtime PESM-E on academic performance in college students.</p>
      <p>Our findings, showing that the pre-bedtime PESM-E is associated with poor sleep quality, are consistent with previous studies.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Poor sleep quality in people with pre-bedtime PESM-E could be associated with several factors,<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref> such as increased emotional and physiological arousal, which may induce poor sleep. Our findings also show that students with pre-bedtime PESM-E have more severe depressive symptoms. However, the depressive symptoms do not moderate the associations between pre-bedtime PESM-E, poor sleep quality and poor academic performance. Future studies should examine the association between pre-bedtime PESM-E and emotional arousal (eg, anger, fear, sadness, happiness and frustration). Many experimental studies have shown that pre-bedtime video game playing and communication via mobile phone increase emotional and/or cognitive arousal.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,<xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref> Furthermore, the light emitted from electronic screen media devices might influence sleep quality through dysregulation of the endogenous circadian melatonin phase.<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56–58</xref> An experimental study showed that, compared to reading a printed book, reading an eBook before bedtime decreased objective sleep quality and delayed their endogenous circadian melatonin phase by 1.5 hours.<xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref> In addition, screen media use before bedtime may increase the risk of insufficient sleep.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,<xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></p>
      <p>We also observed that college students with pre-bedtime PESM-E were 1.25 times more likely to have poor academic performance, which is consistent with previous studies showing that excessive use of electronic screen media is associated with poor academic performance.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8,10</xref>−<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> A recent study reported that compared to reading a printed book, screen time was related to lower functional connectivity between the seed area and regions related to language and cognitive control.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> Interestingly, the current study shows that the association between pre-bedtime PESM-E and academic performance is mediated by sleep quality: poor sleep quality accounts for 53.08% of the effect of pre-bedtime PESM-E on lower levels of academic performance. In other words, pre-bedtime PESM-E increases the risk of having poor sleep quality, which in turn has a negative impact on academic performance. It has been well established that sleep plays an essential role for memory consolidation,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29–32</xref> especially in slow wave sleep.<xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref> Thus, it is not hard to understand the mediating role of poor sleep quality of the association between pre-bedtime PESM-E and lower levels of academic performance.</p>
      <p>Our findings have several important clinical implications, suggesting that pre-bedtime PESM-E affects academic performance through poor sleep quality among college students. Thus, awareness of the reciprocal relationship between excessive use of screen media before bedtime and sleep quality, as well as academic performance among college students is needed and important. In order to improve academic performance and sleep quality, limiting pre-bedtime screen media use is important for college students. It might be helpful to have a text or voice reminders for those who have already used a screen for more than an hour after 10 p.m. Health education on sleep hygiene through schools and mass media is needed and would be a benefit for college students. Furthermore, reducing the brightness of the screen or wearing blue light blocking glasses when using an electronic screen before bedtime might be helpful.<xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref> Future longitudinal studies examining the long-term effect of PESM-E before bedtime on sleep and academic performance, as well as the effects of protective measures (eg, sleep hygiene education or wearing blue light blocking glasses) on sleep quality and academic performance are needed.</p>
      <p>The strengths of our study include the relatively large sample size and satisfactory response rate. Furthermore, several variables that may affect sleep quality and academic performance, such as depressive symptoms, anxiety symptoms and types and frequency of pre-bedtime screen-based activities, have also been collected and taken into consideration when examining the association between screen media use before bedtime, sleep quality and academic performance in college students. However, several limitations should be acknowledged. First, our findings are based on self-reported questionnaires, which may lead to recall bias and social desirability bias. However, it has been reported that the Chinese version of the PSQI is a valid and reliable questionnaire to assess sleep quality in the Chinese population.<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> Moreover, the internal consistency in our data was between 0.74–0.91, which suggests a high level of internal consistency. Second, this is a cross-sectional study, which cannot examine the causal relationship between screen media use before bedtime, poor sleep quality and lower levels of academic performance. Third, because this is an online-based survey and participants were not allowed to submit their questionnaires without completing all of the questions. Thus, we do not have information regarding the students who approached and refused to complete or provided incomplete information. Fourth, the information regarding some common waking substances was not collected in this survey (eg, taurine and medication use), and its effect on our findings should be examined in future studies. Finally, our findings are based on one university and mainly focused on electronic screen media use for entertainment rather than for studying, which may not be generalizable to other college students in other regions or relevant to the effects of electronic screen media use for studying on sleep quality and academic performance. However, in the middle of a semester, after 10 p.m. is usually leisure time for most students. Future multicenter longitudinal studies to examine the mediating effects of sleep quality on the association between pre-bedtime electronic screen media use for the purposes of entertainment, studying and academic performance should be conducted.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>Pre-bedtime PESM-E is associated with poor academic performance in college students. Importantly, this association is predominantly mediated by poor sleep quality. Our findings highlight the importance of limiting pre-bedtime use of electronic screen media by college students. It might be an achievable strategy for improving sleep quality and academic performance for college students.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>The authors thank Prof. Stanley Lin, a native English-speaking scientist who proof-read this manuscript before submission. The work was performed at the Shantou University Mental Health Center.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <p>ANOVA, analysis of variance; AOR, adjusted odds ratio; BMI, body mass index; BAI, Beck Anxiety Inventory; BDI, Beck Depression Inventory; ChiCTR, Chinese Clinical Trial Registry; CI, confidence interval; ESS, Epworth Sleepiness Scale; MEQ, Morningness-Eveningness Questionnaire; PESM, prolonged electronic screen media use; PESM-E, prolonged electronic screen media use for entertainment; PSQI, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index; STCSSC, Shantou College Students Sleep Cohort; SUMHC, Shantou University Mental Health Center; VIF, variance inflation factor.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0007">
      <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
      <p>Data and protocols are available upon reasonable request. Data and protocols are available on request from the corresponding author.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0008">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>All authors report no bioMedical financial interests or other potential conflicts of interest for this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Marshall</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gorely</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Biddle</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A descriptive epidemiology of screen-based media use in youth: a review and critique</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Adolesc</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>333</fpage>–<lpage>349</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16246411</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Carter</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rees</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hale</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bhattacharjee</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paradkar</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between portable screen-based media device access or use and sleep outcomes: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Pediatr</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>170</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1202</fpage>–<lpage>1208</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27802500</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Owens</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Christian</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Polivka</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep behaviors in traditional-age college students: a state of the science review with implications for practice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Assoc Nurse Pract</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>695</fpage>–<lpage>703</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28981991</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sisson</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Church</surname>
<given-names>TS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>CK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Profiles of sedentary behavior in children and adolescents: the US National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey, 2001-2006</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int j Ped Obesity</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>353</fpage>–<lpage>359</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gray</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Larouche</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barnes</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Are we driving our kids to unhealthy habits? Results of the active healthy kids Canada 2013 report card on physical activity for children and youth</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>6009</fpage>–<lpage>6020</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24905246</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Maras</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Flament</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Murray</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Screen time is associated with depression and anxiety in Canadian youth</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Prev Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>138</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25657166</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>QL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Du</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ye</surname>
<given-names>YL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>QQ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Associations of physical activity, screen time with depression, anxiety and sleep quality among Chinese college freshmen</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e100914</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24964250</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Morita</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nakajima</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Okita</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ishihara</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sagawa</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yamatsu</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Relationships among fitness, obesity, screen time and academic achievement in Japanese adolescents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiol Behav</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>163</volume>:<fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27150913</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Falbe</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosner</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Willett</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sonneville</surname>
<given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>FB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Field</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Adiposity and different types of screen time</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatrics</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>132</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e1497</fpage>–<lpage>1505</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24276840</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Adelantado-Renau</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moliner-Urdiales</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cavero-Redondo</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beltran-Valls</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martínez-Vizcaíno</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Álvarez-bueno</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between screen media use and academic performance among children and adolescents: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Pediatr</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>173</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1058</fpage>–<lpage>1067</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31545344</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yan</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oniffrey</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Associations among screen time and unhealthy behaviors, academic performance, and well-being in Chinese Adolescents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Azizi</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Soroush</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khatony</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The relationship between social networking addiction and academic performance in Iranian students of medical sciences: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>28</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31053171</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aguilar</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vergara</surname>
<given-names>FA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Velásquez</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marina</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>García-Hermoso</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Screen time impairs the relationship between physical fitness and academic attainment in children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Pediatr (Rio J)</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>91</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>339</fpage>–<lpage>345</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25645029</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Poulain</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peschel</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vogel</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jurkutat</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kiess</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cross-sectional and longitudinal associations of screen time and physical activity with school performance at different types of secondary school</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>563</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29703168</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Horowitz-Kraus</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hutton</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Brain connectivity in children is increased by the time they spend reading books and decreased by the length of exposure to screen-based media</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Paediatrica (Oslo, Norway: 1992)</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>107</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>685</fpage>–<lpage>693</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Faught</surname>
<given-names>EL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gleddie</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Storey</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davison</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Veugelers</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Healthy lifestyle behaviours are positively and independently associated with academic achievement: an analysis of self-reported data from a nationally representative sample of Canadian early adolescents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>e0181938</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28753617</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Syväoja</surname>
<given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kankaanpää</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kallio</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The relation of physical activity, sedentary behaviors, and academic achievement is mediated by fitness and bedtime</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Phys Act Health</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>143</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28872392</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wing</surname>
<given-names>YK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The associations of long-time mobile phone use with sleep disturbances and mental distress in technical college students: a prospective cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>2</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fossum</surname>
<given-names>IN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nordnes</surname>
<given-names>LT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Storemark</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bjorvatn</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pallesen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The association between use of electronic media in bed before going to sleep and insomnia symptoms, daytime sleepiness, morningness, and chronotype</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>343</fpage>–<lpage>357</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24156294</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Munezawa</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaneita</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Osaki</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The association between use of mobile phones after lights out and sleep disturbances among Japanese adolescents: a nationwide cross-sectional survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1013</fpage>–<lpage>1020</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21804663</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mak</surname>
<given-names>YW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hui</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association between screen viewing duration and sleep duration, sleep quality, and excessive daytime sleepiness among adolescents in Hong Kong</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>11201</fpage>–<lpage>11219</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25353062</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gradisar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wolfson</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harvey</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hale</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosenberg</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Czeisler</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The sleep and technology use of Americans: findings from the National Sleep Foundation’s 2011 Sleep in America poll</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1291</fpage>–<lpage>1299</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24340291</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jackson</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eye</surname>
<given-names>AV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fitzgerald</surname>
<given-names>HE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Witt</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yong</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Internet use, videogame playing and cell phone use as predictors of children’s body mass index (BMI), body weight, academic performance, and social and overall self-esteem</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Comp Human Behav</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>599</fpage>–<lpage>604</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kiatrungrit</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hongsanguansri</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cross-sectional study of use of electronic media by secondary school students in Bangkok, Thailand</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Shanghai Arch Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>216</fpage>–<lpage>226</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25317008</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bai</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence and correlates of poor sleep quality among college students: a cross-sectional survey</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Health Qual Life Outcomes</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>210</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32611434</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lemma</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berhane</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Worku</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gelaye</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Good quality sleep is associated with better academic performance among university students in Ethiopia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep &amp; Breathing = Schlaf &amp; Atmung</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>257</fpage>–<lpage>263</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23928956</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Okano</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaczmarzyk</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dave</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gabrieli</surname>
<given-names>JDE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grossman</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep quality, duration, and consistency are associated with better academic performance in college students</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">NPJ Sci Learning</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>16</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lau</surname>
<given-names>EY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wan</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheung</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hui</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mok</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The interplay between sleep and mood in predicting academic functioning, physical health and psychological health: a longitudinal study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychosom Res</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>74</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>277</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23497826</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fogel</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>CT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cote</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dissociable learning-dependent changes in REM and non-REM sleep in declarative and procedural memory systems</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Brain Res</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>180</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>48</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17400305</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lim</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dinges</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A meta-analysis of the impact of short-term sleep deprivation on cognitive variables</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychol Bull</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>136</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>375</fpage>–<lpage>389</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20438143</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Alapin</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fichten</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Libman</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Creti</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bailes</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wright</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>How is good and poor sleep in older adults and college students related to daytime sleepiness, fatigue, and ability to concentrate?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Psychosom Res</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>390</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11164064</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Walker</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stickgold</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep, memory, and plasticity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Rev Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16318592</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hale</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Screen time and sleep among school-aged children and adolescents: a systematic literature review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>50</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25193149</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Carter</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rees</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hale</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bhattacharjee</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paradkar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A meta-analysis of the effect of media devices on sleep outcomes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Ped</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>170</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1202</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meng</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Bedtime procrastination predicts the prevalence and severity of poor sleep quality of Chinese undergraduate students</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am College Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>2020</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Smartphone use and sleep quality in Chinese college students: a preliminary study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>352</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32435208</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Xiancheng</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maqin</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lei</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aizhen</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Reliability and validity of the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chinese J Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>. Chinese.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monk</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berman</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kupfer</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2748771</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hirshkowitz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whiton</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Albert</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>National Sleep Foundation’s sleep time duration recommendations: methodology and results summary</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Health</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29073412</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Steptoe</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peacey</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wardle</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep duration and health in young adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Intern Med</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>166</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>1689</fpage>–<lpage>1692</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16983045</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Grandner</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kripke</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Self-reported sleep complaints with long and short sleep: a nationally representative sample</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychosom Med</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>241</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15039509</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>[Relationship between bedtime and BMI, waist, blood pressure in college students: a one-year follow-up study]</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Wei sheng Yan Jiu = Journal of Hygiene Research</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>614</fpage>–<lpage>619</lpage>. <comment>Chinese</comment>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29903332</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yan</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fan</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association between late bedtime and diabetes mellitus: a large community-based study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1621</fpage>–<lpage>1627</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31739852</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Farrington</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Loeber</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Some benefits of dichotomization in psychiatric and criminological research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Criminal Behav Mental Health</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>100</fpage>–<lpage>122</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Horne</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ostberg</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A self-assessment questionnaire to determine morningness-eveningness in human circadian rhythms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Chronobiol</italic></source>. <year>1976</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>110</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1027738</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Johns</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A new method for measuring daytime sleepiness: the Epworth sleepiness scale</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>540</fpage>–<lpage>545</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1798888</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Richter</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Werner</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heerlein</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kraus</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sauer</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>On the validity of the Beck Depression Inventory. A review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychopathology</italic></source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>160</fpage>–<lpage>168</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9636945</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ambrosini</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Metz</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bianchi</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rabinovich</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Undie</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Concurrent validity and psychometric properties of the Beck Depression Inventory in outpatient adolescents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2005064</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0049">
        <label>49.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Beck</surname>
<given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Epstein</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Steer</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>An inventory for measuring clinical anxiety: psychometric properties</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Consult Clin Psychol</italic></source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>893</fpage>–<lpage>897</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3204199</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0050">
        <label>50.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Creamer</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Foran</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bell</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Beck Anxiety Inventory in a non-clinical sample</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Res Ther</italic></source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>477</fpage>–<lpage>485</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7755538</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0051">
        <label>51.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baron</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kenny</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The moderator-mediator variable distinction in social psychological research: conceptual, strategic, and statistical considerations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Pers Soc Psychol</italic></source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1173</fpage>–<lpage>1182</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3806354</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0052">
        <label>52.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>MacKinnon</surname>
<given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fairchild</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fritz</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mediation analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Rev Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>593</fpage>–<lpage>614</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16968208</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0053">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cain</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gradisar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Electronic media use and sleep in school-aged children and adolescents: a review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>735</fpage>–<lpage>742</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20673649</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0054">
        <label>54.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Weaver</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gradisar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dohnt</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lovato</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Douglas</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effect of presleep video-game playing on adolescent sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>184</fpage>–<lpage>189</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20411697</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0055">
        <label>55.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ivarsson</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Anderson</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Åkerstedt</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lindblad</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effect of violent and nonviolent video games on heart rate variability, sleep, and emotions in adolescents with different violent gaming habits</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychosom Med</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>390</fpage>–<lpage>396</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23645706</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0056">
        <label>56.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Grønli</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Byrkjedal</surname>
<given-names>IK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bjorvatn</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nødtvedt</surname>
<given-names>Ø</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hamre</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pallesen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Reading from an iPad or from a book in bed: the impact on human sleep. A randomized controlled crossover trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>86</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27448477</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0057">
        <label>57.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Studer</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brucker</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haag</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of blue- and red-enriched light on attention and sleep in typically developing adolescents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiol Behav</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>199</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30381244</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0058">
        <label>58.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aeschbach</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duffy</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Czeisler</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Evening use of light-emitting eReaders negatively affects sleep, circadian timing, and next-morning alertness</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>112</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1232</fpage>–<lpage>1237</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25535358</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0059">
        <label>59.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Van den Bulck</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Television viewing, computer game playing, and Internet use and self-reported time to bed and time out of bed in secondary-school children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>101</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14998244</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0060">
        <label>60.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lemola</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perkinson-Gloor</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brand</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dewald-Kaufmann</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grob</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Adolescents’ electronic media use at night, sleep disturbance, and depressive symptoms in the smartphone age</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Youth Adolesc</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>405</fpage>–<lpage>418</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25204836</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0061">
        <label>61.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gruber</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Can slow-wave sleep enhancement improve memory? A review of current approaches and cognitive outcomes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Yale J Biol Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>92</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30923474</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0062">
        <label>62.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lawrenson</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hull</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Downie</surname>
<given-names>LE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effect of blue-light blocking spectacle lenses on visual performance, macular health and the sleep-wake cycle: a systematic review of the literature</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ophthalmic Physiol Optics</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>644</fpage>–<lpage>654</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
