<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35401018</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">8985910</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">353131</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S353131</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Men’s Sleep Quality and Assisted Reproductive Technology Outcomes in Couples Referred to a Fertility Clinic: A Chinese Cohort Study</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Du et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Du et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9044-219X</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Du</surname>
            <given-names>Cong-Qi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Dong-Xue</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Jing</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1175-1913</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>He</surname>
            <given-names>Qiu-Fen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>Wen-Qin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Reproductive Medicine Center, the First Affiliated Hospital, College of Medicine, Zhejiang University</institution>, <addr-line>Hangzhou</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Embryo Laboratory, the First Affiliated Hospital, College of Medicine, Zhejiang University</institution>, <addr-line>Hangzhou</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Wen-Qin Lin, <phone>Tel +86-0571-87235031</phone>, Email wzlwq70@126.com</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>02</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <fpage>557</fpage>
      <lpage>566</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2022 Du et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Du et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Poor sleep quality has been linked to lower semen quality, but it is unclear whether this result in decreased fertility. To address this question, we retrospectively evaluated the relationship between men’s sleep quality and treatment outcomes in subfertile couples receiving assisted reproductive technology (ART).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Patient Enrollment and Methods</title>
          <p>From September 2017 to November 2019, 282 subfertile couples referred to a Chinese fertility clinic and eligible for ART procedures were enrolled in our study. Sociodemographic characteristics, life habits, and sleep habits in the year prior to ART were recorded. Sleep quality was measured using the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI). We first divided the patients into two groups based on sleep quality (good sleep: PSQI &lt; 5 and poor sleep: PSQI ≥ 5). Then, the ART outcomes (fertilization rate, good quality embryo rate, implantation rate, positive pregnancy rate, clinical pregnancy rate, live birth rate, miscarriage rate, and birth weight) of each group were analyzed. Finally, multivariate linear and logistic regression analysis were used to examine the relationship between sleep quality (discrete variable or dichotomous variable) and ART outcomes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>The participants in the poor sleep group showed a lower fertilization rate of 60.13% (543/903) when compared with 67.36% for the good sleep group (902/1339), <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001. The global PSQI score had a significant influence on birth weight (β, −63.81; 95% CI, −119.91- −8.52; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.047), and live birth rate (OR, 0.88; 95% CI, 0.78- 0.99; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.047) after adjusting for the interfering factors. Men’s sleep quality was unrelated to good quality embryos rate, implantation rate, positive pregnancy rate, clinical pregnancy rate, or miscarriage rate.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>Men’s sleep quality was positively associated with fertilization rate, birth weight, and live birth rate among couples undergoing ART.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>sleep quality</kwd>
        <kwd>PSQI</kwd>
        <kwd>fertility</kwd>
        <kwd>male reproduction</kwd>
        <kwd>in vitro fertilization</kwd>
        <kwd>intracytoplasmic sperm injection</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="2"/>
        <table-count count="9"/>
        <ref-count count="48"/>
        <page-count count="10"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>According to the World Health Organization (WHO), approximately 15% of the couples of childbearing age face fertility issues, and male factors contribute to 40%–50% of all infertility cases.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> The prevalence of infertility has increased significantly over the past decades, while the increasing prevalence of not optimal lifestyle factors such as obesity,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> tobacco<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> or alcohol consumption. Because these lifestyle factors are modifiable, they represent an improved way of infertility management. In addition to the widely studied unhealthy lifestyle parameters associated with infertility, the short sleep duration and poor sleep quality<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> were proved to be potential risk factors. Sleep is a naturally recurring state that is modulated by the circadian rhythm<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> and homeostatic system.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Inadequate sleep duration has been linked to adverse health outcomes, including all-cause mortality,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> cardiovascular diseases,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> hypertension,<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> and diabetes.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></p>
      <p>Therefore, the influence of sleep on reproduction and fertility has aroused widespread concern in recent years.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Goldstein et al<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> previously reported that women’s total sleep time was positively related to the oocytes retrieved during in vitro fertilization (IVF) treatment among 22 women presenting to an infertility clinic. Our previous studies in men confirmed those of other researchers, demonstrating that sleep quality<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> and sleep duration<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> are related to sperm concentration and sperm motility. However, other studies have not validated this relationship.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Therefore, it is unclear whether the recently described sleep-related variations in semen quality translate into diminished fertility. Moreover, one study to date has evaluated whether sleep impacts couple fecundity rather than semen quality. Wise<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> and colleagues found that fecundability ratios (FRs) were 0.62 (95% CI 0.42–0.87) in men who slept less than 6 hours per night compared to men who slept 8 hours per night. To further understand how sleep impacts male fertility, we evaluated the association of men’s sleep quality with infertility treatment outcomes of subfertile couples undergoing assisted reproductive technology (ART).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Study Population</title>
        <p>This retrospective study was conducted on 342 infertile couples undergoing their first ART cycle with in vitro fertilization/ intracytoplasmic sperm injection (IVF/ICSI) in a reproductive medicine center from September 2017 to November 2019. Among couples attending the infertility clinic, the female partners were 20–42 years old. Of these 342 couples, 60 were excluded: 45 male partners used sperm retrieval techniques (testicular sperm extraction or percutaneous epididymal sperm aspiration), 4 male partners did not join the study, and 11 treatment cycles were canceled due to ovarian hyporesponse or natural pregnancy.</p>
        <p>During the study period, the controlled ovarian stimulation protocols for women undergoing ART treatments included: long agonist protocol, antagonist protocol, ultra-long protocol. Only the first fresh embryo transfer cycle was analyzed in this study, and all the couples agreed to participate in this study with a signed informed consent form. This study was approved by the Research Ethics Committee of the First Affiliated Hospital, College of Medicine, Zhejiang University (No. 2017–708). The study was conducted in accordance with the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Questionnaire</title>
        <p>Patient demographics, including age, education, occupation and duration of infertility, and lifestyle habits such as smoking, alcohol, coffee consumption, and exercise, were collected. Any history of chronic illness, urinary or reproductive disease, neurological or psychiatric condition, and a recent fever (≥38°C within the past 3 months) were also disclosed, and the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) was used to measure the sleep quality.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> The self-survey included 19 items reflecting the sleep quality of respondents in the past month. These items reflect sleep quality through seven components, namely: subjective sleep quality, sleep latency, sleep duration, habitual sleep efficiency, sleep disturbances, use of sleeping medication, and daytime dysfunction. Each component was scored between 0–3, and the overall PSQI scores ranged from 0 to 21.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Ovarian Stimulation and Outcome Survey</title>
        <p>Women underwent one of three ovarian stimulation treatment protocols for ART: long agonist protocol, antagonist protocol, or ultra-long protocol. Briefly, gonadotropins were initiated on day 3 of induced menses or after 14 days of down-regulation, and the GnRH agonist or antagonist was continued or started according to the usual ovarian stimulation protocols.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> The HCG trigger injection was administered when a transvaginal ultrasound revealed at least three dominant follicles (≥16 mm), and oocyte retrieval was completed after 36 hours. Oocytes underwent either conventional IVF or ICSI as clinically specified. The percentage of normally fertilized oocytes (2PN) in the inseminated oocytes was calculated as fertilization rate. The good-quality embryo rate was defined as the percentage of optimal embryos among the total number of cleavage embryos. Consequently, clinical outcomes were measured following the transfer of one or two embryos. The positive pregnancy rate referred to the percentage of positive pregnancies in the total fresh embryo transfer cycles, defined by an elevation in plasma β-HCG levels above 10 IU/L, measured 12 days after embryo transfer. The clinical pregnancy rate was defined as the percentage of clinical pregnancies in total fresh embryo transfer (ET) cycles, characterized by the presence of an intrauterine pregnancy confirmed by ultrasound at 6 weeks of gestation. The miscarriage rate referred to the percentage of early miscarriages in the clinical pregnancies, indicating pregnancy termination before 12 gestational weeks. The live birth rate referred to the percentage of live births to fresh embryo transfer cycles, defined as the birth of a neonate on or after 24 weeks of gestation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2004">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>Data were presented as frequencies and percentages for categorical variables and mean standard deviation (SD) for continuous variables. The participants were divided into two groups according to a previously validated<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24–26</xref> cut-off point (PSQI= 5), namely the good sleep group and the poor sleep group. A total PSQI score of 5 or more points indicates poor sleep quality.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24–26</xref> The PSQI features a diagnostic sensitivity of 98% and a specificity of 55%.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></p>
        <p>We assessed the relationship between sleep quality and potential confounders using the Kruskal–Wallis test for continuous variables and the chi-square test for categorical variables. To study the association of sleep quality (continuous variable or dichotomous variable, independent variables) with fertilization rate, good quality embryos rate, and birth weight (dependent variables), multivariate linear regressions were conducted. In contrast, binary logistic regressions were performed to study the relationship between sleep quality (continuous variable or dichotomous variable, independent variables) and positive pregnancy, clinical pregnancy, live birth, and miscarriage (dependent variables). Both continuous variable methods (general PSQI scores) and dichotomous variable methods (PQSI&lt; 5 vs PQSI≥ 5) were both employed to analyze sleep quality. Two models were created: an unadjusted model with only the sleep quality (independent variables); and a second model with the main effects adjusted for potential confounders (independent variables) associated with ART outcomes (dependent variables), such as paternal age, BMI, smoking, alcohol drinking, and maternal age, BMI, duration of infertility, type of ovarian stimulation protocol, the number of retrieved oocytes, oocyte insemination technique (IVF/ICSI), global PSQI score, duration of sleep (categorical variable), endometrial thickness, number of embryos transferred, embryo transfer day.</p>
        <p>Throughout the study, to reduce the probability of obtaining false positive results, the <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value was adjusted using Benjamini-Hochberg False Discovery Rate (FDR).<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Differences were considered to be statistically significant if <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05. Statistical analyses were performed using the Statistical Package for the Social Sciences version 23.0 (SPSS, Inc., IBM) software.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>Oocyte retrieval was performed on all 282 participating females. A total of 274 cycles were successfully fertilized, while no oocyte was retrieved, or fertilization was failed in 8 cycles. In addition, embryo transfer was completed in 267 cycles but failed in 7 cycles (3 with no cleavage and 4 with poor embryo quality). Finally, 183 positive pregnancies were recorded, leading to 164 clinical pregnancies and 141 cycles with live birth (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>).<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>A cohort study population flowchart.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-557-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: TESE, testicular sperm extraction; PESA, percutaneous epididymal sperm aspiration; HCG, human chorionic gonadotropin.</attrib></fig></p>
      <p>The demographic characteristics are displayed in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The study population included 282 participants, with a mean age of 32.49 ±4.98 years and a BMI of 24.11 ±3.45 kg/m<sup>2</sup>. The median PSQI score was 4 (interquartile range, 3–6), and the mean PSQI score was 4.02 ±2.42, with an average sleep duration of 7.44 ±0.94 hours. A total of 110 participants (39%) were classified into the poor sleep group (general PSQI scores ≥5). Compared with the good sleep group, they experienced a shorter sleep duration (7.06 ±1.04 hrs), while their female partners had higher general PSQI scores (4.06 ±2.39). In <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=353131.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Table S1</ext-link></underline>, we re-grouped according to PSQI&gt;5 as cut-off, a total of 62 participants (21.99%) were classified into the poor sleep group (PSQI&gt;5). Compared with the good sleep group (PSQI≤5), they experienced a shorter sleep duration (6.69 ±1.00 hrs), while their female partners had higher general PSQI scores (4.44 ±2.31). Out of 282 female partners (mean age = 30.05 ±3.76 years; BMI = 22.28 ±3.46 kg/m<sup>2</sup>), 267 completed assisted reproductive technology- embryo transfer (ART-ET) cycles and retrieved 7.95 ±3.85 oocytes. Consequently, embryo transfer failed in 15 (5.32%) cases, and 18.79% (53/282) couples reported a primary diagnosis of male factor infertility.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic and Reproductive Characteristics of Study Populations</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (n= 282)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good Sleep (n= 172)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor Sleep (n= 110)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value<sup>a</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (year)<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.49 ±4.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.35 ±4.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.69 ±5.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.812</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.11 ±3.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.24 ±3.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.91 ±3.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.199</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of infertility (years)<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.30 ±2.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.08 ±1.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.65 ±2.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.152</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">College and higher, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">126 (44.68)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 (46.51)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (41.82)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.439</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Employed, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">263 (93.26)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">160 (93.02)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103 (93.64)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.841</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107 (37.94)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (38.37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (37.27)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.853</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drinking alcohol, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (19.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (21.51)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (16.36)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.287</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drinking coffee, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (9.57)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (9.30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (10.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.846</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physically activity, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (27.66)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (30.23)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (23.64)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.227</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (3.55)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (3.49)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (3.64)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Global PSQI score<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.02 ±2.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.49 ±1.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.42 ±1.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">&lt;</italic> 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of sleep (hours)<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.44 ±0.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.68 ±0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.06 ±1.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">&lt;</italic> 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary infertility diagnosis, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.315</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (18.79)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (16.28)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (22.73)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">206 (73.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128 (74.42)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (70.91)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Ovulation disorders</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (11.65)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (11.72)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (11.54)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Diminished ovarian reserve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (12.62)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (10.94)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (15.38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Tubal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">113 (54.85)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71 (55.47)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (53.85)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Endometriosis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (13.11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (12.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (14.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Uterine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (7.77)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (9.38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (5.13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unexplained</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (8.16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (9.30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (6.36)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of embryos transferred, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No embryos transferred</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (5.32)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (2.91)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (9.09)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1 embryo</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (19.86)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (16.86)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (24.55)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2 embryos</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">211 (74.82)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">138 (80.23)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (66.36)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Embryo transfer day, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.078</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No embryos transferred</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (5.32)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (2.91)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (9.09)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Day 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (13.12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (11.63)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (15.45)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Day 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">219 (77.66)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">141 (81.98)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (70.91)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Day 5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (3.90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (3.49)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (4.55)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICSI, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (16.37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (13.45)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (20.91)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.099</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Female partner characteristics</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (year)<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.05 ±3.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.98 ±3.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.16 ±3.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.772</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.28 ±3.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.28 ±3.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.28 ±3.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.732</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Endometrial thickness (mm)<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.45 ±1.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.34 ±1.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.62 ±1.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.116</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oocytes retrieved (n)<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.95 ±3.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.78 ±3.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.21 ±3.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.388</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Global PSQI score<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.62 ±2.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.34 ±2.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.06 ±2.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of sleep (hours)<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.55 ±1.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.64 ±1.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.40 ±1.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.478</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>a</sup>Comparison between each group: continuous variable (Kruskal–Wallis test), categorical variables (χ<sup>2</sup> or Fisher’s exact test). <sup>b</sup>Data were expressed as mean± standard deviation.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: BMI, body mass index; PSQI, Pittsburg Sleep Quality Index; ICSI, intracytoplasmic sperm injection.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      <p><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> shows the laboratory and clinical outcomes of ART for both groups. The comparison showed that the fertilization rate (60.13%) of the poor sleep group (PQSI≥ 5) participants was significantly lower than those in the good sleep group (PQSI&lt; 5) (67.36%) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.001). In <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=353131.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Table S2</ext-link></underline>, we re-grouped according to PSQI&gt;5 as cut-off, the poor sleep group (PSQI&gt; 5) had a significantly lower fertilization rate (55.01%) when compared with the good sleep group (PSQI≤ 5) (67.22%)(<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001). However, there was no statistically significant difference between the two groups in good quality embryos rate, implantation rate, positive pregnancy rate, clinical pregnancy rate, live birth rate, miscarriage rate, and birth weight.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Laboratory and Clinical Outcomes of ART in Each Group According to the Paternal Global PSQI Scores</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (n = 282)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good Sleep (n = 172)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor Sleep (n = 110)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value<sup>a</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fertilization rate % (n)<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.45 (1445/2242)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.36 (902/1339)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.13 (543/903)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good quality embryos rate % (n)<sup>d</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.05 (813/1425)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.77 (498/893)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.21 (315/532)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.255</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Implantation rate % (n)<sup>e</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.82 (219/478)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.89 (143/305)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.93 (76/173)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.533</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive pregnancy rate % (n)<sup>f</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.54 (183/267)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.26 (119/167)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.00 (64/100)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.259</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical pregnancy rate % (n)<sup>g</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.42 (164/267)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.07 (107/167)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.00 (57/100)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.293</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Live birth rate % (n)<sup>h</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.81 (141/267)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.29 (94/167)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.00 (47/100)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.188</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Miscarriage rate % (n)<sup>i</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.20 (20/164)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.28 (11/107)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.79 (9/57)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.349</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Birth weight (g)<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2926.84 ±596.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2990.74 ±604.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2799.02 ±565.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.089</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>a</sup>Comparison between each group: continuous variable (Kruskal–Wallis test), categorical variables (χ<sup>2</sup>-test). <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value was adjusted using Benjamini-Hochberg False Discovery Rate(FDR). <sup>b</sup>Data were expressed as mean± standard deviation. <sup>c</sup>Fertilization rate: normally fertilized oocytes/inseminated oocytes; <sup>d</sup> Good quality embryo rate: optimal embryos/cleavage embryos; <sup>e</sup>Implantation rate: number of gestational sac/ number of embryos transferred; <sup>f</sup>Positive pregnancy rate: positive β-HCG/fresh embryo transfer cycles; <sup>g</sup>Clinical pregnancy rate: clinical pregnancies/fresh embryo transfer cycles; <sup>h</sup>Live birth rate: live births/fresh embryo transfer cycles; <sup>i</sup>Miscarriage rate: miscarriages/clinical pregnancies.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: ART, assisted reproductive technology; PSQI, Pittsburg Sleep Quality Index.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      <p>Regression analysis is shown in <xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. In crude analyses, linear regression analysis illustrated that the global PSQI score had a negative influence on fertilization rate (β, −1.43; 95% CI, −2.67- −0.19; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.045), and birth weight (β, −55.08; 95% CI, −104.70- −5.46; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.045) (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref> and <xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">C</xref>). After adjustment for confounders, the global PSQI score had a negative influence on birth weight (β, −63.81; 95% CI, −119.91- −8.52; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.047). Moreover, binary logistic regression analysis demonstrated that the global PSQI score was negatively associated with the live birth (OR, 0.88; 95% CI, 0.78- 0.99; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.047) (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2D</xref>). In addition, we observed an inverse association between poor sleep group (PQSI≥ 5) and the fertilization rate, both before and after the adjustments. In <underline><ext-link xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=353131.docx" ext-link-type="uri">Table S3</ext-link></underline>, we also found the same conclusion, although we grouped according to PSQI&gt;5 as cut-off. In contrast, regression analysis found no relationship between sleep quality and good quality embryos rate, positive pregnancy, clinical pregnancy, and miscarriage.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Linear and Logistic Regression Analysis of the Association Between the Paternal Sleep Quality and Laboratory and Clinical Outcomes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">The Global PSQI Score</th><th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">Good Sleep vs Poor Sleep</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">u-β/ OR (95% CI)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value<sup>a</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a-β/ OR (95% CI)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value<sup>a</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">u-β/ OR (95% CI)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value<sup>a</sup></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a-β/ OR (95% CI)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value<sup>a</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fertilization rate (%)<sup>bf</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.43 (−2.67, -0.19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.045</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.33(−2.62, −0.04)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.059<sup>d</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.19 (−14.32, −2.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.06(−14.38, −1.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026<sup>d</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good quality embryos rate (%)<sup>bg</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56 (−0.98, 2.09)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.475</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57(−1.02, 2.17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.479<sup>d</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.55 (−8.21, 7.11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.888</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30(−7.60, 8.20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.940<sup>d</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Birth weight (g)<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−55.08 (−104.70, −5.46)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.045</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−63.81(−119.11, −8.52)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047<sup>e</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−191.72 (−400.76, 17.31)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.108</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−200.77(−429.48, 27.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.113<bold><sup>e</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive pregnancy<sup>ch</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.83, 1.03)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.166</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92(0.82, 1.03)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.188<sup>e</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 (0.42, 1.22)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.271</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71(0.40, 1.28)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.308<bold><sup>e</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical pregnancy<sup>ci</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.83, 1.02)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.153</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91(0.81, 1.02)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.135<sup>e</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 (0.45, 1.23)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.301</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73(0.41, 1.28)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.316<bold><sup>e</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Live birth<sup>cj</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.83, 1.01)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.109</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88(0.78, 0.99)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047<sup>e</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 (0.42, 1.13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.189</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57(0.33, 1.01)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.078<bold><sup>e</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Miscarriage<sup>ck</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 (0.92, 1.44)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.268</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24(0.90, 1.70)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.217<sup>e</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.64 (0.63, 4.22)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.359</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.31(0.64, 8.35)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.250<bold><sup>e</sup></bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>a</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value was adjusted using Benjamini-Hochberg False Discovery Rate(FDR). <sup>b</sup>Multiple linear regression analysis; <sup>c</sup>Binary logistic regression analysis; <sup>d</sup>Regression coefficients were adjusted for paternal age, BMI, smoking, alcohol drinking, and maternal age, BMI, duration of infertility, type of ovarian stimulation protocol, the number of retrieved oocytes, oocyte insemination technique (IVF/ICSI), global PSQI score, duration of sleep (categorical variable). <sup>e</sup>Regression coefficients were adjusted for paternal age, BMI, smoking, alcohol drinking, and maternal age, BMI, duration of infertility, type of ovarian stimulation protocol, the number of retrieved oocytes, oocyte insemination technique (IVF/ICSI), global PSQI score, duration of sleep (categorical variable), endometrial thickness, number of embryos transferred, embryo transfer day. <sup>f</sup>Fertilization rate (continuous variables): normally fertilized oocytes/inseminated oocytes; <sup>g</sup>Good quality embryo rate (continuous variables): optimal embryos/cleavage embryos; <sup>h</sup>Positive pregnancy (dichotomous variables): 12 days after embryo transfer, the level of plasma β-HCG above 10 IU/L; <sup>i</sup>Clinical pregnancy (dichotomous variables): at 6 weeks of gestation, the presence of intrauterine pregnancy by ultrasound; <sup>j</sup>Live birth (dichotomous variables): the birth of a neonate on or after 24 weeks of gestation; <sup>k</sup>Miscarriage (dichotomous variables): pregnancy termination before 12 gestational weeks.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0006"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: PSQI, Pittsburg Sleep Quality Index; u-β/ OR, unadjusted beta coefficient/odds ratio; a-β/ OR, adjusted beta coefficient/odds ratio; 95% CI, 95% confidence intervals.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The paternal total PSQI score and ART outcomes. (<bold>A-C)</bold> respectively illustrate the linear regression analysis result between the global PSQI score and fertilization rate (N= 281), good quality embryos rate (N= 272); and birth weight (N= 141). The black line indicates the linear regression result, and the shaded area represents the 95% confidence interval. (<bold>D)</bold> shows the logistic regression analysis results between the global PSQI score and positive pregnancy (N= 183), clinical pregnancy (N= 164), live birth (N= 141), and miscarriage (N= 20).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-557-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: PSQI, Pittsburg Sleep Quality Index; ART, assisted reproductive technology; OR, odds ratio; 95% CI, 95% confidence intervals.</attrib></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>We retrospectively assessed the relationship between men’s sleep quality and treatment outcomes in their partners who underwent ART. We found that a higher global PSQI score was related to lower fertilization rate, birth weight, and live birth rate. However, men’s subjective sleep quality was unrelated to good quality embryos rate, implantation rate, positive pregnancy rate, clinical pregnancy rate, or miscarriage rate.</p>
      <p>Previous studies mostly focused on the potential effect of sleep quality on male reproduction and its relation with semen quality. We found that men with poor sleep quality had fewer spermatozoa with lower motility and lower normal sperm morphology than men who slept well.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> However, sleep quality was unrelated to ejaculate volume in a cross-sectional analysis among men from the Reproductive Medicine Center in Zhejiang. Chen HG et al<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> studied the sperm samples from 842 healthy potential sperm donors and reported that poor sleep quality was associated with lower total sperm count, total motility, and progressive motility. Furthermore, Jensen et al<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> reported that sleep disturbance was negatively related to sperm concentration, total sperm count, and percentage of normal sperm morphology in a 953 Danish men’s case-control study. These three findings are in accordance with our analysis and infer strong associations between sleep quality and semen quality.</p>
      <p>This study illustrates an inverse relationship between the global PSQI score and outcomes in ART cycles and supports the previous reports of a negative association between the general PSQI scores and sperm morphology.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Such a relationship was expected since sperm morphology is associated with ART outcomes.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> However, whether sleep quality has an impact on semen quality has yet to be elucidated.</p>
      <p>Notably, few previous studies have evaluated the association between men’s sleep and infertility treatment outcomes. Interestingly, a study examined the association between male sleep and fecundability ratios (FRs) in a population-based cohort of 1176 couples who were attempting to conceive without using contraception or fertility treatment.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> In this study, multivariable-adjusted FRs for participants with &lt;6 hours of sleep per night were 0.62 (95% CI 0.42–0.87) when compared to peers with 8 hours of sleep per night. This study reached a similar conclusion as our findings, that is, compared with men who had no trouble sleeping, the FRs for men who had difficulty sleeping less than half the time was 1.06 (95% CI 0.85–1.31), and the FRs for men who had trouble sleeping more than half the time was 0.93 (95% CI 0.72–1.20).</p>
      <p>The mechanisms by which poor sleep quality can reduce male fertility remain unclear. Several studies support the testosterone hypothesis; Andersen ML et al, Leproult R et al, and Jankowski KS et al<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30–32</xref> found that poor sleep quality was associated with lower semen quality and/or lower testosterone levels. However, Jensen et al, Chen Q et al, Du CQ et al, and Morten Ruge et al<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> found little connection between sleep quality and testosterone in their studies. The discrepancy in the results from various studies may reflect the complexity of the involved mechanisms. The circadian rhythm system may partially account for our observations. This system, regulated by the solar light and dark cycle, controls vital aspects of our physiology, including body temperature, heart rate, hormone secretion and cellular metabolism.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> Therefore, the circadian rhythm plays an essential role in the mature sperm production process.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36–39</xref> Unhealthy sleep habits disrupt the expression of circadian rhythm genes and have adverse effects on the male reproductive system.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> Since melatonin regulates the sleep-wake cycle of the circadian rhythm, the inhibition of melatonin and cortisol production by endogenous circadian rhythm disorders may cause a disruption of the cycle.<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> Additional functions of melatonin include the regulation of gonadotropin and testosterone secretion, promotion of testicular maturation and free radical scavenging, thus preventing testicular injury.<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> Therefore, the potential impact of sleep on male fertility deserves further investigation.</p>
      <p>This study features a number of notable aspects. Our study was retrospectively designed and used a previously validated PSQI, and the participating couples were followed up during pregnancy until the babies were born. Furthermore, we examined multiple factors that could affect semen quality and ART outcomes, such as paternal age, paternal BMI, smoking, alcohol drinking, and maternal age, maternal BMI, global PSQI score, duration of sleep (categorical variable), duration of infertility, type of ovarian stimulation protocol, the number of retrieved oocytes, oocyte insemination technique (IVF/ICSI), endometrial thickness, number of embryos transferred, and embryo transfer day. Moreover, direct and objective measures of male fertility were selected, including fertilization rate, good quality embryos rate, implantation rate, live birth rate, and miscarriage rate. This is a novel approach that improves on the traditional semen quality parameters to assess male fertility. However, the present research also has some limitations. Firstly, sleep quality is a self-reported subjective indicator, and measurement errors cannot be completely excluded. Secondly, the participants were recruited from a single fertility clinic and were limited in number, raising the possibility of selection bias. Lastly, we only investigated the sleep quality before entering the ART cycle, without dynamically detecting the sleep quality, without considering the influences of anxiety and obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) on sleep quality, and only selected the data of the fresh embryo transfer cycle, which may cause some deviations in the results.</p>
      <p>Sleep is closely related to quality of life and mental health. Some researchers have proposed that psychological stress negatively affects sperm parameters.<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44–46</xref> Furthermore, psychological stress is associated with sleep disturbance and is more common in infertile couples than in fertile couples.<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> So, it should be emphasized that the relationship between sleep disturbances and male fertility may be bidirectional. Therefore, it will be interesting to include these confounding factors in future studies. Efforts to improve sleep can also be incorporated into global and individualized preconception care plans for infertile couples.<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>In this retrospective study, we present evidence that poor sleep quality is correlated with adverse pregnancy outcomes. This suggests a greater male reproductive potential with better sleep quality. Our study extends the current literature on the relationship between sleep quality and male fertility. In view of the growing global evidence that human semen quality is declining, and poor sleep quality is becoming more common, further research is needed to explore the underlying mechanisms and confirm our findings.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>The authors are grateful to colleagues from Reproductive Medicine Center of The First Affiliated Hospital, College of Medicine, Zhejiang University for providing direct assistance and constructive suggestions for this research.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>All authors made a significant contribution to the work reported, whether that is in the conception, study design, execution, acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation, or in all these areas; took part in drafting, revising or critically reviewing the article; gave final approval of the version to be published; have agreed on the journal to which the article has been submitted; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0007">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors declare no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship and publication of this article.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Brinster</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Male germline stem cells: from mice to men</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Science</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>316</volume>(<issue>5823</issue>):<fpage>404</fpage>–<lpage>405</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1137741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17446391</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Singh</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Trends of male factor infertility, an important cause of infertility: a review of literature</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Hum Reprod Sci</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0974-1208.170370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26752853</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sermondade</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huberlant</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bourhis-Lefebvre</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Female obesity is negatively associated with live birth rate following IVF: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hum Reprod Update</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>439</fpage>–<lpage>451</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/humupd/dmz011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30941397</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sermondade</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Faure</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fezeu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>BMI in relation to sperm count: an updated systematic review and collaborative meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hum Reprod Update</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>231</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/humupd/dms050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23242914</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Waylen</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Metwally</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>GL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilkinson</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ledger</surname>
<given-names>WL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of cigarette smoking upon clinical outcomes of assisted reproduction: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Hum Reprod Update</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/humupd/dmn046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18927070</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bin</surname>
<given-names>YS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Is Sleep Quality More Important Than Sleep Duration for Public Health?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1629</fpage>–<lpage>1630</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.6078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27568809</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gentry</surname>
<given-names>NW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ashbrook</surname>
<given-names>LH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fu</surname>
<given-names>YH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ptáček</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Human circadian variations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Invest</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>131</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>5347</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI148282</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lanza</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>DelRosso</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferri</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and homeostatic control of plasticity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Handb Clin Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>184</volume>:<fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35034758</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bangdiwala</surname>
<given-names>SI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rangarajan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of estimated sleep duration and naps with mortality and cardiovascular events: a study of 116 632 people from 21 countries</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Heart J</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>1620</fpage>–<lpage>1629</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehy695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30517670</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Domínguez</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fuster</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fernández-Alvira</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of Sleep Duration and Quality With Subclinical Atherosclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Cardiol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>73</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>134</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2018.10.060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30654884</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kang</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ryu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Changes in sleep duration and subsequent risk of hypertension in healthy adults</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>638</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsy159</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shan</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration and risk of type 2 diabetes: a meta-analysis of prospective studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes Care</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>529</fpage>–<lpage>537</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc14-2073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25715415</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Palnitkar</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Phillips</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoyos</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marren</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bowman</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yee</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Linking sleep disturbance to idiopathic male infertility</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med Rev</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>159</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2018.07.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30377037</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Caetano</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bozinovic</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dupont</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Léger</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lévy</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sermondade</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Impact of sleep on female and male reproductive functions: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Fertil Steril</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>115</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>715</fpage>–<lpage>731</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fertnstert.2020.08.1429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33054981</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Goldstein</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lanham</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>YR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O’Brien</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep in women undergoing in vitro fertilization: a pilot study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2016.12.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28366321</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Du</surname>
<given-names>CQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>YY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>WQ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association Between Sleep Quality and Semen Parameters and Reproductive Hormones: a Cross-Sectional Study in Zhejiang, China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Sci Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S235136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32021520</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>HG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>YJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep duration and quality in relation to semen quality in healthy men screened as potential sperm donors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Environ Int</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>135</volume>:<fpage>105368</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2019.105368</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31830732</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>CPS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Waters</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chi</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>DYL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Lifestyle and demographic factors associated with human semen quality and sperm function</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Syst Biol Reprod Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>358</fpage>–<lpage>367</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/19396368.2018.1491074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30033774</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wogatzky</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wirleitner</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stecher</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The combination matters–distinct impact of lifestyle factors on sperm quality: a study on semen analysis of 1683 patients according to MSOME criteria</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Reprod Biol Endocrinol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>115</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1477-7827-10-115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23265183</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pokhrel</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yihao</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wangcheng</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The impact of sociodemographic characteristics, lifestyle, work exposure and medical history on semen parameters in young Chinese men: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Andrologia</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e13324</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/and.13324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31134681</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wise</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rothman</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wesselink</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Male sleep duration and fecundability in a North American preconception cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Fertil Steril</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>109</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>453</fpage>–<lpage>459</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fertnstert.2017.11.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29566862</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Buysse</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>CF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monk</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berman</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kupfer</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychiatry Res</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0165-1781(89)90047-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2748771</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Colaci</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Afeiche</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gaskins</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Men’s body mass index in relation to embryo quality and clinical outcomes in couples undergoing in vitro fertilization</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Fertil Steril</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>98</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1193</fpage>–<lpage>1199.e1191</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fertnstert.2012.07.1102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22884013</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tsai</surname>
<given-names>PS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>MY</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Psychometric evaluation of the Chinese version of the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (CPSQI) in primary insomnia and control subjects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Qual Life Res</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1943</fpage>–<lpage>1952</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11136-005-4346-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16155782</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aloba</surname>
<given-names>OO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adewuya</surname>
<given-names>AO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ola</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mapayi</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Validity of the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) among Nigerian university students</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>266</fpage>–<lpage>270</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2006.08.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17368977</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Curcio</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tempesta</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scarlata</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Validity of the Italian version of the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>511</fpage>–<lpage>519</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10072-012-1085-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22526760</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Benjamini</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hochberg</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Controlling the False Discovery Rate: a Practical and Powerful Approach to Multiple Testing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Med</italic></source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jensen</surname>
<given-names>TK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Andersson</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Skakkebaek</surname>
<given-names>NE</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of sleep disturbances with reduced semen quality: a cross-sectional study among 953 healthy young Danish men</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>177</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1027</fpage>–<lpage>1037</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kws420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23568594</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fan</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gong</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>[Human normal sperm morphology rate and in vitro fertilization outcome]</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Zhong Nan Da Xue Xue Bao Yi Xue Ban</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>738</fpage>–<lpage>742</lpage>. <comment>Chinese</comment>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3969/j.issn.1672-7347.2010.07.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20693717</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Andersen</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alvarenga</surname>
<given-names>TF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mazaro-Costa</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hachul</surname>
<given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tufik</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The association of testosterone, sleep, and sexual function in men and women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Res</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>1416</volume>:<fpage>80</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainres.2011.07.060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21890115</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Leproult</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Cauter</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effect of 1 week of sleep restriction on testosterone levels in young healthy men</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>305</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):<fpage>2173</fpage>–<lpage>2174</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2011.710</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21632481</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jankowski</surname>
<given-names>KS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fajkowska</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Domaradzka</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wytykowska</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Chronotype, social jetlag and sleep loss in relation to sex steroids</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Psychoneuroendocrinology</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>108</volume>:<fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psyneuen.2019.05.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31238173</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Inverse U-shaped Association between Sleep Duration and Semen Quality: longitudinal Observational Study (MARHCS) in Chongqing, China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5665/sleep.5322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26350472</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ruge</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Skaaby</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Andersson</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Linneberg</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cross-sectional analysis of sleep hours and quality with sex hormones in men</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Endocrine Connections</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>149</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1530/EC-18-0548</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30668526</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Eckel-Mahan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sassone-Corsi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Metabolism and the circadian clock converge</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiol Rev</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>93</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physrev.00016.2012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23303907</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Alvarez</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hansen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ord</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The circadian clock protein BMAL1 is necessary for fertility and proper testosterone production in mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Biol Rhythms</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0748730407311254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18258755</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Beaver</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gvakharia</surname>
<given-names>BO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vollintine</surname>
<given-names>TS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hege</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stanewsky</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Giebultowicz</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Loss of circadian clock function decreases reproductive fitness in males of Drosophila melanogaster</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>2134</fpage>–<lpage>2139</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.032426699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11854509</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tobback</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boerjan</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vandersmissen</surname>
<given-names>HP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huybrechts</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Male reproduction is affected by RNA interference of period and timeless in the desert locust Schistocerca gregaria</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Insect Biochem Mol Biol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>115</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ibmb.2011.11.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22154754</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Peterlin</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kunej</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peterlin</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The role of circadian rhythm in male reproduction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Opin Endocrinol Diabetes Obes</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>316</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MED.0000000000000512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31633567</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Boden</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Varcoe</surname>
<given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kennaway</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Circadian regulation of reproduction: from gamete to offspring</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Prog Biophys Mol Biol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>113</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>387</fpage>–<lpage>397</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbiomolbio.2013.01.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23380455</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gamble</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Resuehr</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Shift work and circadian dysregulation of reproduction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Endocrinol (Lausanne)</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>92</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fendo.2013.00092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23966978</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Eckel-Mahan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sassone-Corsi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Metabolism and the Circadian Clock Converge</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiological Reviews</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>93</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23303907</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Melatonin and male reproduction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Chim Acta</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>446</volume>:<fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>180</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cca.2015.04.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25916694</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0044">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gollenberg</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brazil</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Semen quality in fertile men in relation to psychosocial stress</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Fertil Steril</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>93</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1104</fpage>–<lpage>1111</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fertnstert.2008.12.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19243749</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0045">
        <label>45.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nordkap</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jensen</surname>
<given-names>TK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hansen</surname>
<given-names>ÅM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Psychological stress and testicular function: a cross-sectional study of 1215 Danish men</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Fertil Steril</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>105</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<page-range>174–187.e171-172</page-range>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fertnstert.2015.09.016</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0046">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nordkap</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Priskorn</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bräuner</surname>
<given-names>EV</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impact of psychological stress measured in three different scales on testis function: a cross-sectional study of 1362 young men</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Andrology</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1674</fpage>–<lpage>1686</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/andr.12835</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32621382</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0047">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nargund</surname>
<given-names>VH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of psychological stress on male fertility</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Urol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>373</fpage>–<lpage>382</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrurol.2015.112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26057063</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0048">
        <label>48.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dupont</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aegerter</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Foucaut</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effectiveness of a therapeutic multiple-lifestyle intervention taking into account the periconceptional environment in the management of infertile couples: study design of a randomized controlled trial - The PEPCI study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Pregnancy Childbirth</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>322</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12884-020-2855-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32456614</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
