<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
    <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
  </processing-meta>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Sci Sleep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nss</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature and Science of Sleep</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1179-1608</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35814490</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">9258772</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">367900</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/NSS.S367900</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Sleep Disturbances in Chinese Children with Epilepsy: Associations with Behavioral Problems and Quality of Life</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Zhao et al</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Zhao et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
            <given-names>Fen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5797-2124</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>Xiaoning</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Yingyan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhou</surname>
            <given-names>Yunqing</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>He</surname>
            <given-names>Yingzhong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Cuijin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Han</surname>
            <given-names>Feng</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Jie</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tsai</surname>
            <given-names>Shao-Yu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Guanghai</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Jiwen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref rid="an0002" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Pediatric Neurology, Shanghai Children’s Medical Center, School of Medicine, Shanghai Jiao Tong University</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Paediatric Translational Medicine Institute, Department of Developmental and Behavioral Pediatrics, Shanghai Children’s Medical Center, School of Medicine, Shanghai Jiao Tong University</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>School of Nursing, College of Medicine, National Taiwan University</institution>, <addr-line>Taipei</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Guanghai Wang, <institution>Shanghai Children’s Medical Center, School of Medicine, Shanghai Jiao Tong University</institution>, <addr-line>1678 Dongfang Road</addr-line>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <addr-line>200127</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, Email wang-guanghai@163.com</corresp>
        <corresp id="an0002">Jiwen Wang, <institution>Shanghai Children’s Medical Center, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>1678 Dongfang Road</addr-line>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <addr-line>200127</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>, Email wangjiwen@scmc.com.cn</corresp>
        <fn id="ft0001">
          <label>*</label>
          <p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>02</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <fpage>1225</fpage>
      <lpage>1236</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2022 Zhao et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Zhao et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s2001">
          <title>Objective</title>
          <p>To investigate the association between sleep disturbances and behavioral problems as well as quality of life (QOL) in Chinese children with epilepsy.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2002">
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>Caregivers of 167 epileptic children aged 3 to 12 years completed the Child Sleep Habits Questionnaire (CSHQ), the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ), and the Pediatric Quality of Life Inventory (PedsQL™, 4.0 Core).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2003">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>The prevalence of sleep disturbances (CSHQ total score &gt;41) in epileptic children was 73.7% [95% CI (66.9%.80.4%)]. Epileptic children with sleep disturbances demonstrated more behavioral problems and lower QOL compared to those without sleep disturbances. Sleep disturbances such as sleep anxiety and daytime sleepiness were associated with more behavioral problems and lower QOL (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt;0.05). Linear regression analyses showed that higher disturbance in sleep duration domain were associated with more behavioral problems, while higher sleep disordered breathing domains was associated with lower QOL (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt;0.05). The interaction between sleep disturbances and behavioral problems in predicting QOL was not significant. The sensitivity analysis using 48 as an alternative cutoff for CSHQ total score obtained consistent results.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2004">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>Sleep disturbances occur frequently among Chinese children with epilepsy, and are associated with more behavioral problems and lower QOL. The sleep disturbance-QOL association is unlikely contingent on behavioral problems. This study highlights the necessity of evaluating and treating sleep disturbances multidimensionally among children with epilepsy to promote their whole health and wellbeing.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>sleep disturbances</kwd>
        <kwd>behavioral problems</kwd>
        <kwd>quality of life</kwd>
        <kwd>epilepsy</kwd>
        <kwd>children</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="open-funder-registry">10.13039/501100001809</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Shanghai Science and Technology Commission</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Shanghai Pudong District Technology Development Funds</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
        </award-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported by National Natural Science Foundation of China (82071493), Shanghai Science and Technology Commission (18JC1420305, 19QA1405800, 19411968800) and Shanghai Pudong District Technology Development Funds (PKJ2018-Y45).</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="2"/>
        <table-count count="12"/>
        <ref-count count="43"/>
        <page-count count="12"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Epilepsy is a common childhood neurological disease, affecting more than 10 million children worldwide.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Sleep disturbances are among the most prevalent comorbidities of epilepsy, with prevalence ranging 45–95% among children with epilepsy,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> as compared with 25–40% among typically developing children.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> The most common sleep disturbances in children with epilepsy include excessive daytime sleepiness (76%), sleep disordered breathing (65%), and parasomnia (53%).<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> The relationship between epilepsy and sleep disturbances is likely bidirectional and complex.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Sleep can modulate seizure occurrence or interictal epileptiform discharges, and sleep disturbances may worsen epileptic symptoms. Conversely, epileptic discharges have been shown to disrupt sleep-wake cycles.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Therefore, epilepsy with the added sleep disturbances likely exacerbates children’s health and functioning.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Previous studies have independently reported high prevalence of sleep disturbances,<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> behavioral problems,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> and poor QOL,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> in children with epilepsy. Yet, there lacks a systematic examination of the association among sleep disturbances, behavioral problems, and QOL.</p>
      <p>Emerging evidence suggested the association between sleep disturbances and behavioral problems in children with epilepsy. A study regarding the Rolandic epilepsy reported higher level of behavioral problems in epileptic children with sleep problems than those without.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Byars et al also found that in children with epilepsy, sleep disturbances were correlated with increased behavioral problems.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> However, existing studies focused predominantly on Western children with epilepsy, and thus the results may not be generalizable to Chinese children due to the social and cultural differences in sleep practice and behaviour.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> What’s more, for those having sleep disturbances or/and behavioral problems, impaired QOL may also be present. Yet, there are few studies on the relationship between sleep disturbance and QOL in children with epilepsy. A recent study showed that children with epilepsy and sleep disturbances had poorer QOL.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Given above evidence, it is possible that sleep disturbances may interact with behavioral problems in children with epilepsy to reduce QOL. However, such interaction has not been systematically investigated in empirical studies. Bridging such literature gap is crucial to furthering our understanding of the association among the three conditions and to inform clinical interventions.</p>
      <p>Therefore, the current study was to explore the association among sleep disturbances, behavioral problems, and QOL in Chinese children with epilepsy. We hypothesized: 1) children with sleep disturbances would demonstrate more behavioral problems and poor QOL, 2) sleep disturbances would be associated with more behavioral problems and lower QOL, and 3) the sleep disturbance-QOL association would be contingent on behavioral problems in Chinese children with epilepsy.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s0002-s2001">
        <title>Participants and Procedure</title>
        <p>The current study is a cross-sectional design. We recruited children with epilepsy and their caregivers from a paediatric neurological clinic and inpatient ward in a tertiary children’s hospital in Shanghai. Children aged 3 to 12 years who met the International League Against Epilepsy (ILAE) 2017 criteria<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> admitted for a diagnosis of epilepsy from July 2020 to October 2021. The exclusion criteria were: (1) children born at less than 37 weeks; (2) children with overt structural brain damage or cerebral palsy; (3) children with other confirmed physical and psychiatric diseases, such as haematologic tumours, congenital heart diseases, attention deficit hyperactivity disease (ADHD), autism spectrum disorder (ASD), and tic disorder (TD); or (4) parents unable to speak, read, and understand Chinese.</p>
        <p>According to previous studies, sleep disturbances occurred 25–40% in typically developing children<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> and 45–95% of children with epilepsy.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Using the two lowest rates (25% vs 45%) by PASS software, we estimated that a sample size of at least 115 would provide an effect size of 0.9. A total of 206 children with epilepsy were contacted, and caregivers of 183 agreed to participate and signed informed consent (response rate 88.8%). Investigators on site supervised the caregivers of children with epilepsy while completing the questionnaires in person and independently in a quiet hospital setting. Three participants with haematologic tumours, three with congenital heart diseases, and ten with other clearly diagnosed neurodevelopmental disorders (ie, ADHD, ASD or TD) were excluded; data from 167 participants ultimately were included in the analysis (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>).<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Flowchart of study participants with data on inclusion, exclusion and distribution according to CSHQ.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-1225-g0001" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: CSHQ, Children’s Sleep Habits Questionnaire; ADHD, Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disease; ASD, Autism Spectrum Disorder; TD, Tic Disorder.</attrib></fig></p>
        <p>The current study was approved by the Shanghai Children’s Medical Center Ethics Committee (SCMCIRB-K2020030-1) in accordance with the guidelines of the Declaration of Helsinki (1964).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2002">
        <title>Measures</title>
        <p>Children’s sleep disturbances were assessed by the Children’s Sleep Habit Questionnaire (CSHQ), a 33-item parent-reported questionnaire initially designed for children aged 4 to 10 years.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> More recent studies have extended its use to children aged 3–12 years.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Each item was rated on a 3-point scale ranging from “usually” to “rarely”, reflecting sleep habits of children in the past week. The CSHQ evaluated sleep disturbances on eight subscales: bedtime resistance, sleep onset delay, sleep duration, sleep anxiety, night awaking, parasomnias, sleep disordered breathing, and daytime sleepiness. Higher total and subscale scores indicated more sleep problems. A total score of &gt; 41 was suggested as the clinical cutoff for general sleep disturbance.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Considering the cutoff of 41 based on American children may overestimate sleep disturbances, especially for behavioral domains in Chinese children, a total score of 48 as an alternative cutoff point was utilized in the current study for a sensitivity analysis.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> The Chinese version of the CSHQ<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> has been used in children with epilepsy.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> The Cronbach’s α was 0.73 in the current study for the full questionnaire.</p>
        <p>Behavioral problems were assessed by Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ).<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> This 25-item questionnaire was designed for children aged 4 to 16 years, with later studies extending its use to children aged as young as 3 years.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Each response is rated on a 3-point Likert scale (0 for “not true”, 1 for “partly true”, or 2 for “very true”). The SDQ consists of five subscales: emotional symptoms, conduct problems, hyperactivity/inattention, peer relationship problems, and prosocial behaviors. Score ranged from 0 to 10 for each of the five subscales. The total difficulties score ranging from 0 to 40 was calculated by totalling all subscales except for prosocial behaviors. The internalizing score was a sum of emotional symptoms and peer relationship scales (ranges from 0 to 20) while the externalizing score was a sum of conduct problems and hyperactivity/inattention scales (ranges from 0 to 20). A higher score was indicative of more severe behavioral symptoms. Total score ≥ 14 was suggested as the clinical cutoff point for behavioral difficulties.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> The SDQ had been used in children with epilepsy<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> and prior to this was used within the Chinese population with good psychometrics.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> The Cronbach’s α for the total difficulties was 0.61 in current study.</p>
        <p>The Paediatric Quality of Life Inventory (PedsQL™, 4.0 Core) scale was used to assess the QOL in children.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> The PedsQL is a 23-item generic measure including four age-group scales specific to children aged 2–4, 5–7, 8–12, and 13–18 years. It assesses the following 4 domains: physical functioning (8 items), emotional functioning (5 items), social functioning (5 items), and school functioning (5 items). Emotional, school, and social functioning can be combined into a psychosocial health domain. Each item was rated on a 5-point Likert scale from 0 to 4, subsequently reverse scored and linearly transformed to a 0 to 100 points scale (0 = 100, 1 = 75, 2 = 50, 3 = 25, 4 = 0). Thus, a higher converted score was indicative of a better QOL. The reliability and validity of the Chinese translations of the PedsQL 4.0 scale have been reported for Chinese children.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> The Cronbach’s α for the full scale was 0.94 in the current study.</p>
        <p>In addition to the above assessments, caregivers also reported the sociodemographic characteristics including age, sex, the only-child status, caregivers’ education level, family structure, family living environment, and their children’s seizure history.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0002-s2003">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>Descriptive statistics were used to characterize sociodemographic variables, and sleep and epilepsy-related variables. Continuous data were presented as mean ± standard deviation (SD), and categorical data as frequencies (percentages). To test for sample distribution, we used a Shapiro–Wilk test. As most of data were not distributed normally, we used the Mann–Whitney test to compare continuous variables between groups. The categorical variables from the two groups were compared using chi-square test. Spearman correlation analyses were used to measure the association between sleep variables and behavioral problems as well as QOL. Stepwise linear regression analyses were performed to determine sleep and epileptic parameters predicting behavior problems or lower QOL. We conducted a two-way ANOVA to examine the interaction between sleep disturbance and behavioral problems in predicting QOL, including CSHQ total score (below or above cutoff) and SDQ total difficulties (below or above cutoff) as independent variables, and some sociodemographic variables (ie, sex, age, being the only child at home, family structure, education of caregiver, and family living environment) as covariates. We also used 48 as the alternative cutoff point of CSHQ total score for sensitivity analysis to examine the robustness of our findings. All analyses were performed using Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS<sup>®</sup>), version 26.0, with a significance level of 0.05.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0003">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0003-s2001">
        <title>Sample Characteristics</title>
        <p>Demographic and sleep characteristics of the samples are summarized in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Of the 167 children, 123 (73.7%) were rated as having sleep disturbances (CSHQ total score &gt; 41). There was a significant age difference between the group with sleep disturbances and the group without. As our preliminary analysis detected no difference in behavioral problems and QOL between children aged 3–6 years and 6–12 years, and thus we combined the age groups for all subsequent analyses. Children with epilepsy in the sleep disturbances group had significantly higher prevalence of bed-sharing and room-sharing than those without. Regarding epilepsy characteristics (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), seizure duration of children with sleep disturbances were significantly longer than those without, and children with sleep disturbances had significantly more epileptic status during the duration of epilepsy than those in the other group. And significant difference in specified diagnosis was observed between the two groups, with a higher proportion of Benign Epilepsy with Centrotemporal Spikes (BECTS) in the group without sleep disturbance.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic Characteristics of Children with Epilepsy</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">Value<sup>a</sup></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Samples (n = 167)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CSHQ &gt; 41 (n = 123)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CSHQ ≤ 41 (n = 44)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic><sup>b</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.56 ± 2.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.27 ± 2.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.38 ± 2.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (38.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (39.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (36.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n. s.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.31 ± 5.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.97 ± 5.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.27 ± 6.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n. s.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The education of caregiver</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">n. s.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> High school or less</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (50.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (51.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (50.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> College</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (43.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (43.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (43.2%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Graduate school</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (6.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (5.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (6.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> The only-child status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 (47.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (51.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (38.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n. s.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family structure</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">n. s.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Nuclear family</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (55.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (52.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (63.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Extended family</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (43.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (47.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (34.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Single parent or other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family living environment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">n. s.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Quiet</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105 (62.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (59.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (72.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Noisy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (37.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (40.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (27.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleeping arrangement pattern</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Child-adult bed-sharing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">117 (70.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96 (78.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (47.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Child-adult room-sharing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (16.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (12.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (25.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Others</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (13.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (8.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (27.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total sleep time per 24h (hours)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.06 ± 1.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.16 ± 1.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.78 ± 0.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n. s.</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Percentages may not total to 100% due to rounding, <sup>a</sup>Data are presented as mean ± standard deviation (SD) or n (%), <sup>b</sup>The Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test were used for continuous variables. Chi-square tests or Fisher’s exact tests for categorical data.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: CSHQ, Children’s Sleep Habits Questionnaire; BMI, body mass index; n. s., non-significant.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Epilepsy Related Characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">Value<sup>a</sup></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Samples (n = 167)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CSHQ&gt;41 (n = 123)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CSHQ ≤ 41 (n = 44)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic><sup>b</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age at seizure onset, years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.13± 2.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.03 ± 2.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.40 ± 2.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n. s.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of epilepsy, months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.70 ± 26.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.92± 23.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.48 ± 32.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n. s.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of epilepsy ≤ 1 month</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (30.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (30.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (29.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n. s.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seizure frequency (in last 6 months)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="6" colspan="1">n. s.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Daily</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (9.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (10.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (6.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Weekly</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (8.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (8.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (6.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Monthly</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (5.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (5.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (4.5%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Less than 1 per month</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (28.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (30.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (22.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81 (48.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (44.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (59.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seizure type</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">n. s.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Focal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 (49.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (49.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (50.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Generalized</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (38.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (35.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (47.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Both</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (6.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (7.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unclassified</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (6.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (8.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seizure diurnal pattern</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">n. s.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (28.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (30.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (52.5%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Night</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 (46.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (43.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (22.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Both</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (25.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (25.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (25.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epileptic discharge in EEG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">n. s.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Normal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (25.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (27.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (18.2%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unilateral discharge</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 (35.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (34.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (38.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Bilateral discharge</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (39.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (38.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (43.2%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seizure duration (min)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="6" colspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt; 5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110 (65.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (59.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (84.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 5–15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (15.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (15.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (13.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 16–30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (8.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (11.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (2.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (3.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time inconsistency</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (8.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (10.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The Status epilepticus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (28.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (35.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (9.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family history</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (13.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (14.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (11.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n. s.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specific diagnosis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="6" colspan="1">&lt; 0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> BECTS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 (35.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (28.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (54.5%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Childhood Absence epilepsy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (6.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (7.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (4.5%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Occipital epilepsy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (1.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ADNFLE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unclassified</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (55.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (61.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (38.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current AED</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="8" colspan="1">n. s.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Monotherapy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">132 (79.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95 (77.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (84.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> OXC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (39.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (40.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (40.5%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> LEV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (43.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (43.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (45.9%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> VPA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (14.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (14.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (13.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> TPM</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (2.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Polytherapy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (17.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (17.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (15.9%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (4.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (5.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Percentages may not total to 100% due to rounding; <sup>a</sup>Data are presented as mean ± standard deviation (SD) or n (%); <sup>b</sup>The Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test were used for continuous variables. Chi-square tests or Fisher’s exact tests for categorical data.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: CSHQ, Children’s Sleep Habits Questionnaire; AED, anti-epileptic drug; EEG, electroencephalogram; BECTS, Benign Epilepsy with Centrotemporal Spikes; ADNFLE, Autosomal Dominant Nocturnal Frontal Lobe Epilepsy; OXC, oxcarbazepine; LEV, levetiracetam; VPA, valproic acid; TPM, topiramate; n. s., non-significant.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2002">
        <title>Differences of Behavioral Problems and QOL Between CSHQ &gt; 41 Group and CSHQ ≤ 41 Group</title>
        <p>Compared with children without sleep disturbances, those with sleep disturbances had significantly higher score in SDQ total difficulty as well as the domains of emotional symptom, conduct problems, hyperactivity/inattention, and peer relationship (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>s &lt; 0.05). The domain of prosocial problems was not significantly different between the two groups (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>). Regarding QOL, children in the sleep disturbances group had significantly lower scores in emotional, social, and school functioning and psychosocial health domains (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Significant differences were not observed in physical functioning (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>).<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Differences of SDQ subscale (<bold>A</bold>) and QOL subscale scores (<bold>B</bold>) between CSHQ &gt; 41 group and CSHQ ≤ 41 group. Number of samples in each group are as follows: children with epilepsy in CSHQ ≤ 41 score group (n =44) and in CSHQ &gt; 41 score group (n =123). Each column shows SDQ subscale scores and QOL subscale scores and error bar represent 95% confidence interval. *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="NSS-14-1225-g0002" content-type="print-only" position="float"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: CSHQ, Children’s Sleep Habits Questionnaire; SDQ, the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire; QOL, quality of life.</attrib></fig></p>
        <p>In the sensitivity analysis, consistent results showed that epileptic children with CSHQ total score &gt; 48 had significantly higher SDQ total score and lower QOL total score.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0003-s2003">
        <title>Association Among Sleep Disturbances, Behavioral Problems, and QOL</title>
        <p>A series of significant correlations were detected between sleep disturbances and behavioral problems or QOL in children with epilepsy (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Bedtime resistance, sleep onset delay, sleep duration, sleep anxiety, night waking, parasomnias, and daytime sleepiness were significantly correlated with SDQ total score (all <italic toggle="yes">r<sub>s</sub></italic> &lt; 0.5, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Sleep anxiety, sleep disordered breathing, daytime sleepiness, and total sleep disturbance scores were correlated significantly with QOL total score (all |<italic toggle="yes">r<sub>s</sub></italic>| &lt; 0.3, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Sleep disordered breathing and daytime sleepiness were significantly correlated with both physical functioning and psychosocial health scores (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Spearman Correlation Between Sleep Subscales and Behavioral Problems as Well as QOL</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">CSHQ Domains</th><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Behavioral Problems</th><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Quality of Life</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Internalizing Problems</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Externalizing Problems</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SDQ Total Score</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychosocial Health</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical Functioning</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">QOL Total Score</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bedtime resistance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep onset delay</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep duration</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep anxiety</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.25**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.18*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Night waking</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parasomnias</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.16*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep disordered breathing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.19*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.16*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.20**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daytime sleepiness</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.19*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.18*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.16*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CSHQ total score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.30**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.19*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.25**</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: *p &lt;0.05; **p &lt;0.01.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0006"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: SDQ, Strengths and Difficulty Questionnaire; QOL, Quality of Life; CSHQ, Children’s Sleep Habits Questionnaire.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
        <p>In the regression analyses (<xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>), the multicollinearity test found that the tolerance of each variable was between 0.81 and 0.98, and the variance expansion factor ranged between 1.01 and 1.23, indicating no multicollinearity. The SDQ total score was significantly associated with the CSHQ subscale score on sleep duration (<italic toggle="yes">β</italic> = 0.43, <italic toggle="yes">p &lt;</italic> 0.001) and sleep anxiety (<italic toggle="yes">β</italic> = 0.16, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05), while QOL total score was significantly associated with the CSHQ subscale scores on sleep disordered breathing (<italic toggle="yes">β</italic> = −0.17, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). In epilepsy-related parameters, diagnosis of BECTS was significantly correlated both higher SDQ total score (<italic toggle="yes">β</italic> = −0.17, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) and lower QOL total scores (<italic toggle="yes">β</italic> = 0.24, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Duration of epilepsy ≤ 1 month (<italic toggle="yes">β</italic> = −0.18, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) was only significantly correlated with SDQ total score, while the ≥2 anti-epileptic drugs (AEDs) was only significantly correlated lower QOL total score (<italic toggle="yes">β</italic> = −0.20, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Linear Regression Models for Epileptic and Sleep Parameters on Behavioral Problems and QOL in Children with Epilepsy</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Behavioral Problems</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Quality of Life</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SDQ Total Scores</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Internalizing Problems</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Externalizing Problems</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">QOL Total Scores</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychosocial Health</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical Health</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">β</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">β</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">β</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">β</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">β</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">β</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.18**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The only-child status</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family structure</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of epilepsy≤ 1month</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.18*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.16*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.34***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seizure diurnal pattern</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.19*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seizure type</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BECTS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.17*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥ 2AEDs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.20**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.21**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.19*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CSHQ</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sleep anxiety</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.24**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Sleep duration</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29***</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Parasomnia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Daytime sleepiness</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.22**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep disordered breathing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.17*</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjust R<sup>2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>F</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0007"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt;0.05; **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt;0.01; ***<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt;0.001.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0008"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: SDQ, Strengths and Difficulty Questionnaire; QOL, Quality of Life; BECTS, Benign Epilepsy with Centrotemporal Spikes; CSHQ, Children’s Sleep Habits Questionnaire; AEDS, Anti-epileptic drugs.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
        <p>There was a strong correlation between sleep disturbances and behavioral problems, but the results of two-way ANOVA showed no significant interaction between CSHQ total score and SDQ total score (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>
<sub>(1,163)</sub> = 0.71, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Our study provided first evidence for the association among sleep disturbances, behavioral problems, and QOL among Chinese children with epilepsy. Sleep disturbances were highly prevalent in children with epilepsy (73.7%). Among children with epilepsy, sleep disturbances were significantly associated with more behavioral problems and lower QOL, and the sleep disturbance-QOL association was unlikely contingent on behavioral problems. The sensitivity analysis using an alternative cutoff of 48 for CSHQ total score obtained consistent results, ensuring the robustness of our findings. Results of the current study suggested that sleep disturbances, behavioral problems, and QOL should be integrated as part of a comprehensive assessment of overall life functioning for epileptic children to enhance clinicians’ awareness and promote children’s health.</p>
      <p>The current study showed that sleep disturbances were common and severe in epileptic children, with a prevalence of 73.7% and a mean CSHQ total score of 45.92. In Hong Kong, CSHQ total score was 48.89 from a sample of epileptic children aged 4 to 12 years old.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> A study among American children with epilepsy aged 2 to 10 years reported a CSHQ total score of 48.25.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> The relatively lower severity level of sleep disturbances in the current sample compared to earlier reports in Hong Kong and US may due to sample’s heterogeneity and cross-cultural differences. In our study, nearly half of epileptic children reported no seizures within the last six months, which was higher than 41% in the Hong Kong study.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> A prior study reported higher seizure frequency was related to higher scores for excessive sleepiness and disorders of sleep-wake transition.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Also, a polysomnographic study did not identify difference in sleep structures between epilepsy patients without seizures and healthy controls,<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> which may partially explain the lower prevalence of sleep disturbances in our sample. Additionally, the effect of antiepileptic drugs on sleep should be acknowledged. For example, benzodiazepines and barbiturates may reduce sleep latency, valproate may increase the stage 1 sleep, and lamotrigine may decrease slow wave sleep and insomnia.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> Further, children on polytherapy presented with worse sleep problems than children on monotherapy.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> In our study, 79% of the children with epilepsy took the monotherapy, which was higher than the American sample (50%)<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> and the Hong Kong sample (62%).<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Regarding cross-cultural difference, unique school schedules and sleep practices may contribute to the differences in the sleep disturbances of children from different regions.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> For example, previous studies showed that Chinese children had significantly later bedtimes, earlier morning wake time, and shorter sleep duration compared with those from the United States,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> and Hong Kong children had significant later bedtime and shorter sleep duration than Shanghai children.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> These factors may account for the lower prevalence of sleep disturbances in our study.</p>
      <p>Consistent with previous studies,<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> the current study showed that epileptic children with sleep disturbances presented with higher emotional symptoms, conduct problems, hyperactivity/attention, and peer relationship problems than those without.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> The mechanisms of this relationship may involve the prefrontal cortex and its associated neurocognitive and neurobehavioral processes.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> Additionally, our results revealed that epileptic children with sleep disturbances had lower scores on emotional, school, social functioning and psychosocial health of QOL, which corroborated with previous studies.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> It is worth noting that discrepancies in the specific domain of QOL also existed. For instance, as previous studies reported significant differences in physical functioning of QOL between epileptic children with and without sleep disturbances,<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> the current study did not. It may be possible that, as children in the current sample experienced shorter duration of illness, its deleterious influence on physical functioning has yet to manifest. Another conjectural reason may be that the low rate of seizure within the last six months may decrease the positive moderating role of active epileptic seizures on the relationship between sleep disturbances and physical functioning.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Also, patients with CHSQ &gt; 41 in our study had more status epilepticus in which the massive epileptic discharges releasing from brain might have a different impact on physical and psychosocial health of QOL.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></p>
      <p>More importantly, we found an independent association of sleep disturbances and behavioral problems with QOL in children with epilepsy, without detecting a significant interaction effect. This finding expands our understanding of the complex relationship among sleep disturbances, behavioral problems, and QOL in children with epilepsy, and underlines comprehensive management of these comorbidities.</p>
      <p>In analysing specific domains of sleep disturbances, we found sleep disordered breathing was significantly associated with QOL, but not with behavioral problems. However, previous studies have reported that children with sleep-disordered breathing displayed worse behavioral functioning and lower QOL.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> It is possible that sleep-disordered breathing symptoms can affect QOL initially, but behavioral functioning over time. A prior study showed that remission of sleep breathing symptoms after adenotonsillectomy frequently improved QOL in short time but did not improve behavioral outcomes.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> Hence, it is imperative to routinely screen for sleep disturbances and refer epileptic children for polysomnography (PSG) studies if necessary, particularly for those with sleep complaints and symptoms of sleep-disordered breathing.</p>
      <p>Finally, the current study found that the diagnosis of BECTS was associated with both behavioral functioning and QOL. As a benign epilepsy, BECTS had lower seizure frequency than other epilepsy and seizures usually disappeared after puberty, so it had subtle impact on sleep, behavior, and QOL.<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> When viewed in combination with the studies of BECTS, behavioral problems may be slighter but more persistent in children with BECTS than in children with epilepsy in general, though direct comparisons between epilepsy syndromes are not available.<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></p>
      <p>In our study, shorter duration of epilepsy was also correlated with more behavioral problems. Consistently, an Italian study suggested that the longer duration of the epilepsy was associated with behavioral problems and children with enduring epileptic manifestations were at higher risk for social failures.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> Furthermore, epileptogenic networks with enduring changes in brain function and structure, may have resulted in emotional and behavioral alterations.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> We also found the number of antiepileptic drugs was associated with lower QOL, which was similar with that being reported in previous studies.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> The reason may be that the treatment of epilepsy may cause significant side effects, such as drowsiness, irritability, nausea, and headache, which had particular risk for diminished QOL.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></p>
      <p>Our study was strengthened by using validated instruments, covering a wide range of relevant factors, and conducting a sensitivity analysis. Nevertheless, the findings should be interpreted with caution due to the following limitations. Firstly, with the current sample being recruited from the same site, nearly half reported no seizures within the last six months, and the majority being on monotherapy, our findings may lack generalizability. Future studies with larger samples from multiple sites are encouraged to confirm and expand our findings. Secondly, the study did not include objective sleep measurements such as actigraphy or polysomnography, and thus the findings may be subject to reporting bias. Nevertheless, the CSHQ is a well-validated tool for screening sleep problems in children with neurodevelopmental disorders,<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> providing measurements that correspond moderately well with objective measurement results.<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> Similarly, the study could be enhanced by including clinical evaluation of sleep disorders, psychopathology, and neurodevelopmental disorders by experienced psychiatrist or developmental and behavioral pediatricians, which would provide more accurate information such as detecting more children with ADHD and ASD. Thirdly, parents, teachers and children (particularly for old children) might have different perspectives in terms of sleep disturbances, emotional and behavioral problem, and QOL, and thus future studies would better consider multiple informants. Fourthly, the small sample size of the group without sleep disturbances could potentially produce the type 2 error when comparing to the group with sleep disturbances. However, our sensitivity analysis using an alternative cutoff of 48 for CSHQ total score increased the sample size of the group without sleep disturbances, but still demonstrated consistent results, which ensured the robustness of our findings. Finally, we could not establish a causal relationship due to the cross-sectional design. Thus, longitudinal and intervention studies are warranted to fully unveil the relationship among sleep disturbances, behavioral problems and QOL in children with epilepsy.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>In conclusion, sleep disturbances are prevalent in Chinese children with epilepsy. Among the epileptic children, sleep disturbances are significantly associated with worse behavioral functioning and lower QOL, and the sleep disturbance-QOL association is unlikely contingent on behavioral problems. Our study highlights the necessity of evaluating and treating sleep disturbances multidimensionally among children with epilepsy to promote their whole health and wellbeing. Future studies should investigate whether effective sleep interventions can improve behavioral functioning and QOL in children with epilepsy.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgment</title>
      <p>Special thanks to the children and families who participated in the study. This work was supported by National Natural Science Foundation of China (82071493), Shanghai Science and Technology Commission (18JC1420305, 19QA1405800, 19411968800) and Shanghai Pudong District Technology Development Funds (PKJ2018-Y45).</p>
    </ack>
    <sec id="s0006">
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <p>QOL, quality of life; CSHQ, Children’s Sleep Habits Questionnaire; SDQ, the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire; PedsQL™, the Pediatric Quality of Life Inventory; ILAE, the International League Against Epilepsy; ADHD, Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disease; ASD, Autism Spectrum Disorder; TD, Tic Disorder; AEDs, antiepileptic drugs; PSG, polysomnography; BECTS, Benign Epilepsy with Centrotemporal Spikes; ADNFLE, Autosomal Dominant Nocturnal Frontal Lobe Epilepsy.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0007">
      <title>Disclosure</title>
      <p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="cit0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Guerrini</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Epilepsy in children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>367</volume>:<fpage>499</fpage>–<lpage>524</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(06)68182-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16473127</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tsai</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>WT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jeng</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weng</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and behavior problems in children with epilepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Pediatr Health Care</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>138</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pedhc.2018.07.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30149961</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jain</surname>
<given-names>SV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dye</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kedia</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Value of combined video EEG and polysomnography in clinical management of children with epilepsy and daytime or nocturnal spells</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Seizure</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.seizure.2018.12.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30590283</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep patterns and sleep disturbances among Chinese school-aged children: prevalence and associated factors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2012.09.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23218539</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Maganti</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hausman</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koehn</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sandok</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Glurich</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mukesh</surname>
<given-names>BN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Excessive daytime sleepiness and sleep complaints among children with epilepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsy Behav</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>272</fpage>–<lpage>277</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yebeh.2005.11.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16352471</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gibbon</surname>
<given-names>FM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maccormac</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gringras</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and epilepsy: unfortunate bedfellows</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Dis Child</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>104</volume>:<fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/archdischild-2017-313421</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30266875</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Larson</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ryther</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jennesson</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impact of pediatric epilepsy on sleep patterns and behaviors in children and parents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsia</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>1162</fpage>–<lpage>1169</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1528-1167.2012.03515.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22594377</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheong</surname>
<given-names>EY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ng</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>YC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>QU</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>KY</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Evaluation of sleep disturbances in children with epilepsy: a questionnaire-based case-control study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsy Behav</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>437</fpage>–<lpage>440</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yebeh.2011.05.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21704566</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Graham</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gossell-Williams</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tapper</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Melbourne-Chambers</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disorders and behavioral disorders in Jamaican children with epilepsy: a case-control study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsy Behav</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>99</volume>:<fpage>106477</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yebeh.2019.106477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31425974</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yong</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chengye</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jiong</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Factors affecting the quality of life in childhood epilepsy in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Neurol Scand</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>113</volume>:<fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>173</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0404.2005.00567.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16441246</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Samaitienė</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Norkūnienė</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tumienė</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grikinienė</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and behavioral problems in rolandic epilepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatr Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>122</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pediatrneurol.2012.10.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23337004</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Byars</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Byars</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The relationship between sleep problems and neuropsychological functioning in children with first recognized seizures</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsy Behav</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>607</fpage>–<lpage>613</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yebeh.2008.07.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18687412</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mindell</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sadeh</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kwon</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goh</surname>
<given-names>DY</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cross-cultural differences in the sleep of preschool children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1283</fpage>–<lpage>1289</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2013.09.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24269649</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ekinci</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Isik</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gunes</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ekinci</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Understanding sleep problems in children with epilepsy: associations with quality of life, attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder and maternal emotional symptoms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Seizure</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>108</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.seizure.2016.06.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27394056</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fisher</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cross</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>French</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Operational classification of seizure types by the International League against epilepsy: position paper of the ILAE commission for classification and terminology</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsia</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>522</fpage>–<lpage>530</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/epi.13670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28276060</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Owens</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spirito</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McGuinn</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Children’s Sleep Habits Questionnaire (CSHQ): psychometric properties of a survey instrument for school-aged children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>1043</fpage>–<lpage>1051</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/23.8.1d</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11145319</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0017">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Beebe</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lewin</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zeller</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sleep in overweight adolescents: shorter sleep, poorer sleep quality, sleepiness, and sleep-disordered breathing</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Pediatr Psychol</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jpepsy/jsj104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16467311</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0018">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Goodlin-Jones</surname>
<given-names>BL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sitnick</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Anders</surname>
<given-names>TF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Children’s Sleep Habits Questionnaire in toddlers and preschool children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Dev Behav Pediatr</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>82</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/dbp.0b013e318163c39a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18478627</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0019">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Geng</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Owens</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep patterns, sleep disturbances, and associated factors among Chinese urban kindergarten children</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>100</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15402002.2014.963581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25396279</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0020">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tan</surname>
<given-names>TX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheah</surname>
<given-names>CSL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>GH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Reliability and construct validity of the children’s sleep habits questionnaire in Chinese kindergartners</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Health</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>104</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleh.2017.10.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29332670</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0021">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Goodman</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The strengths and difficulties questionnaire: a research note</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Child Psychol Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>581</fpage>–<lpage>586</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-1610.1997.tb01545.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9255702</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0022">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Du</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kou</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coghill</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The validity, reliability and normative scores of the parent, teacher and self report versions of the strengths and difficulties questionnaire in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Child Adolesc Psychiatry Ment Health</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1753-2000-2-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18445259</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0023">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Reilly</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Atkinson</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Memon</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Autism, ADHD and parent-reported behavioural difficulties in young children with epilepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Seizure</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.seizure.2019.08.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31425870</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0024">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chien</surname>
<given-names>YL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shang</surname>
<given-names>CY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>YC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gau</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Psychometric properties of the Chinese version of strength and difficulties questionnaire</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Compr Psychiatry</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>720</fpage>–<lpage>730</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.comppsych.2013.01.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23433222</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0025">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Varni</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seid</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kurtin</surname>
<given-names>PS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>PedsQL (TM) 4.0: reliability and validity of the pediatric quality of life Inventory (TM) Version 4.0 generic core scales in healthy and patient populations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Med Care</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>800</fpage>–<lpage>812</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005650-200108000-00006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11468499</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0026">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Duan</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xiao</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Reliability and validity of the PedsQL generic core scales 4.0 for Chinese children with epilepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsy Behav</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>431</fpage>–<lpage>436</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yebeh.2011.12.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22436443</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0027">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bazil</surname>
<given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep and Epilepsy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Semin Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>407</fpage>–<lpage>412</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0037-1604352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28837987</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0028">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Al-Biltagi</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Childhood epilepsy and sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">World J Clin Pediatr</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5409/wjcp.v3.i3.45</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25254184</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0029">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Owens</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaplan</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep patterns and sleep problems among schoolchildren in the United States and China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatrics</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>115</volume>:<fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>249</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2004-0815F</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15866858</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0030">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lam</surname>
<given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Ten-year secular trends in sleep/wake patterns in shanghai and hong kong school-aged children: a tale of two cities</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1495</fpage>–<lpage>1502</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.7984</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31596215</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0031">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Owens</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lewin</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Skora</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baylor</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between short sleep duration and risk behavior factors in middle school students</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>40</volume>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsw004</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0032">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gutter</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brouwer</surname>
<given-names>OF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Weerd</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Subjective sleep disturbances in children with partial epilepsy and their effects on quality of life</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsy Behav</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>481</fpage>–<lpage>488</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yebeh.2013.06.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23892578</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0033">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wirrell</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blackman</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barlow</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mah</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hamiwka</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sleep disturbances in children with epilepsy compared with their nearest-aged siblings</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Dev Med Child Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>754</fpage>–<lpage>759</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0012162205001581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16225739</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0034">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Szaflarski</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Choi</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A systematic review of seizure clusters: prevalence, risk factors, burden of disease and treatment patterns</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsy Res</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>177</volume>:<fpage>106748</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eplepsyres.2021.106748</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34521043</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0035">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hartmann</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bruni</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferri</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Redline</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baumert</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cyclic alternating pattern in children with obstructive sleep apnea and its relationship with adenotonsillectomy, behavior, cognition, and quality of life</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>44</volume>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sleep/zsaa145</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0036">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Constantin</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kermack</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nixon</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tidmarsh</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ducharme</surname>
<given-names>FM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brouillette</surname>
<given-names>RT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Adenotonsillectomy improves sleep, breathing, and quality of life but not behavior</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Pediatr</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>150</volume>:<fpage>540</fpage>–<lpage>6, 546 e1</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpeds.2007.01.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17452233</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0037">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Samaitienė</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Norkūnienė</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jurkevičienė</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grikinienė</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Behavioral problems in children with benign childhood epilepsy with centrotemporal spikes treated and untreated with antiepileptic drugs</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Medicina</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>338</fpage>–<lpage>344</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23032905</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0038">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tovia</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goldberg-Stern</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ben Zeev</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The prevalence of atypical presentations and comorbidities of benign childhood epilepsy with centrotemporal spikes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsia</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>1483</fpage>–<lpage>1488</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1528-1167.2011.03136.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21692792</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0039">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dal Canto</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pellacani</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Valvo</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Masi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferrari</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sicca</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Internalizing and externalizing symptoms in preschool and school-aged children with epilepsy: focus on clinical and EEG features</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsy Behav</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yebeh.2017.10.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29253677</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0040">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Holmes</surname>
<given-names>GL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of seizures on brain development: lessons from the laboratory</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatr Neurol</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pediatrneurol.2004.12.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15993318</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0041">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Palermo</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grewe</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Quality of life in pediatric epilepsy: demographic and disease-related predictors and comparison with healthy controls</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epilepsy Behav</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1525-5050(02)00601-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12609226</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0042">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gruber</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Somerville</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Santisteban</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Using parental report to identify children at risk for poor sleep and daytime problems</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Behav Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>460</fpage>–<lpage>476</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15402002.2019.1613236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31092006</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="cit0043">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Urfer-Maurer</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brand</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holsboer-Trachsler</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grob</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weber</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lemola</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Correspondence of maternal and paternal perception of school-aged children’s sleep with in-home sleep-electroencephalography and diary-reports of children’s sleep</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>180</fpage>–<lpage>186</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2018.05.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29960212</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
